December/DATE 201/NUMBER 6/NUMBER PREPARING/O FOR/O THE/DATE FUTURE/DATE OF/O ARTIFICIAL/ORGANIZATION INTELLIGENCE/ORGANIZATION National/ORGANIZATION Science/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION Council/ORGANIZATION Artificial/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION ,/O Automation/O ,/O and/O the/O Economy/ORGANIZATION Executive/ORGANIZATION Office/ORGANIZATION of/O the/O President/O Copyright/O Information/O This/O is/O a/O work/O of/O the/O U.S./ORGANIZATION Government/ORGANIZATION and/O is/O in/O the/O public/O domain/O ./O 
It/O may/O be/O freely/O distributed/O ,/O copied/O ,/O and/O translated/O ;/O acknowledgment/O of/O publication/O by/O the/O Executive/O Office/O of/O the/O President/O -LRB-/O EOP/O -RRB-/O is/O appreciated/O ./O 
Any/O translation/O should/O include/O a/O disclaime/O r/O that/O the/O accuracy/O of/O the/O translation/O is/O the/O responsibility/O of/O the/O translator/O and/O not/O EOP/ORGANIZATION ./O 
It/O is/O requested/O that/O a/O copy/O of/O any/O translation/O be/O sent/O to/O EOP/ORGANIZATION ./O 
This/O work/O is/O available/O for/O worldwide/O use/O and/O reuse/O and/O under/O the/O Creative/ORGANIZATION Commons/ORGANIZATION CC0/ORGANIZATION 1.0/ORGANIZATION Universal/ORGANIZATION l/O icense/O ./O 
EXECUTIVE/O OFFICE/O OF/O THE/O PRESIDENT/O WASHINGTON/LOCATION ,/O D.C./LOCATION 20502/NUMBER December/DATE 20/DATE ,/DATE 2016/DATE Advances/O in/O Artificial/O Intelligence/O -LRB-/O AI/O -RRB-/O technology/O and/O related/O fields/O have/O opened/O up/O new/O markets/O and/O new/O opportunities/O for/O progress/O in/O critical/O areas/O such/O as/O health/O ,/O edu/O cation/O ,/O energy/O ,/O economic/O inclusion/O ,/O social/O welfare/O ,/O and/O the/O environment/O ./O 
In/O recent/DURATION years/DURATION ,/O machines/O have/O surpassed/O humans/O in/O the/O performance/O of/O certain/O tasks/O related/O to/O intelligence/O ,/O such/O as/O aspects/O of/O image/O recognition/O ./O 
Experts/O forecast/O that/O rapid/O progress/O in/O the/O field/O of/O specialized/O artificial/O intelligence/O will/O continue/O ./O 
Although/O it/O is/O unlikely/O that/O machines/O will/O exhibit/O broadly/O -/O applicable/O intelligence/O comparable/O to/O or/O exceeding/O th/O at/O of/O humans/O in/O the/DURATION next/DURATION 20/DURATION years/DURATION ,/O it/O is/O to/O be/O expected/O that/O machines/O will/O continue/O to/O reach/O and/O exceed/O human/O performance/O on/O more/O and/O more/O tasks/O ./O 
AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O will/O continue/O to/O create/O wealth/O and/O expand/O the/O American/O economy/O in/O the/DATE coming/DATE years/DATE ,/O but/O ,/O while/O many/O will/O benefit/O ,/O that/O growth/O will/O not/O be/O costless/O and/O will/O be/O accompanied/O by/O changes/O in/O the/O skills/O that/O workers/O need/O to/O succeed/O in/O the/O economy/O ,/O and/O structural/O changes/O in/O the/O economy/O ./O 
Aggressive/O policy/O action/O will/O be/O needed/O to/O help/O Americans/O who/O are/O disadvantaged/O by/O these/O changes/O and/O to/O ensure/O that/O the/O enormous/O benefits/O of/O AI/O and/O automation/O are/O developed/O by/O and/O available/O to/O all/O ./O 
Following/O up/O on/O the/O Administration/ORGANIZATION 's/O previous/O report/O ,/O Preparing/O for/O the/DATE Future/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Artificial/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION ,/O which/O was/O published/O in/O October/DATE 2016/DATE ,/O this/O report/O further/O in/O vestigates/O the/O effects/O of/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O on/O the/O U.S./LOCATION job/O market/O and/O economy/O ,/O and/O outlines/O recommended/O policy/O responses/O ./O 
This/O report/O was/O produced/O by/O a/O team/O from/O the/O Executive/ORGANIZATION Office/ORGANIZATION of/O the/O President/O including/O staff/O from/O the/O Council/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Advisers/ORGANIZATION ,/O Domestic/ORGANIZATION Policy/ORGANIZATION Council/ORGANIZATION ,/O National/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Council/ORGANIZATION ,/O Office/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Management/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Budget/ORGANIZATION ,/O and/O Office/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Science/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION Policy/ORGANIZATION ./O 
The/O analysis/O and/O recommendations/O included/O herein/O draw/O on/O insights/O learned/O over/O the/O course/O of/O the/DATE Future/DATE of/O AI/O Initiative/O ,/O which/O was/O announced/O in/O May/DATE of/DATE 2016/DATE ,/O and/O included/O Federal/ORGANIZATION Government/ORGANIZATION coordination/O efforts/O and/O cross/O -/O sector/O and/O public/O outreach/O on/O AI/O and/O related/O policy/O matters/O ./O 
Beyond/O this/O report/O ,/O m/O ore/O work/O remains/O ,/O to/O further/O explore/O the/O policy/O implications/O of/O AI/O ./O 
Most/O notably/O ,/O AI/O creates/O important/O opportunities/O in/O cyberdefense/O ,/O and/O can/O improve/O systems/O to/O detect/O fraud/O ulent/O transactions/O and/O messages/O ./O 
Jason/PERSON Furman/PERSON John/PERSON P./PERSON Holdren/PERSON Chair/PERSON ,/O Council/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Advisers/ORGANIZATION Director/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION Office/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Science/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION Policy/ORGANIZATION Cecilia/ORGANIZATION Mu?oz/ORGANIZATION Megan/ORGANIZATION Smith/ORGANIZATION Director/ORGANIZATION ,/O Domestic/ORGANIZATION Policy/ORGANIZATION Council/ORGANIZATION U.S./ORGANIZATION Chief/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION Officer/ORGANIZATION Jeffrey/ORGANIZATION Zients/ORGANIZATION Director/ORGANIZATION ,/O National/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Council/ORGANIZATION ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O Contents/O Executive/O Summary/O .../O .../O .../O .../O .../O 1/NUMBER Economics/O of/O AI/O -/O Driven/O Automation/O .../O .../O .../O .../O 1/NUMBER Policy/O Responses/O .../O .../O .../O .../O .../O 3/NUMBER Conclusion/O .../O .../O .../O .../O .../O 4/NUMBER Outreach/O and/O Development/O of/O this/O Report/O .../O .../O .../O .../O 5/NUMBER Introduction/O .../O .../O .../O .../O .../O ./O 
6/NUMBER Economics/O of/O AI/O -/O Driven/O Automation/O .../O .../O .../O .../O 8/NUMBER AI/O and/O the/O Macroeconomy/O :/O Technology/O and/O Productivity/O Growth/O .../O .../O .../O 8/NUMBER AI/O and/O the/O Labor/O Market/O :/O Diverse/O Potential/O Effects/O .../O .../O .../O 10/NUMBER Historical/O Effects/O of/O Technical/O Change/O .../O .../O .../O .../O 11/NUMBER AI/O and/O the/O Labor/O Market/O :/O The/O Near/O Term/O .../O .../O .../O .../O 13/NUMBER What/O kind/O of/O jobs/O will/O AI/O create/O ?/O 
.../O .../O .../O .../O 18/NUMBER Technology/O is/O Not/O Destiny/O --/O Institutions/O and/O Policies/O Are/O Critical/O .../O .../O .../O 21/NUMBER Policy/O Responses/O .../O .../O .../O .../O .../O 26/NUMBER Strategy/O #/MONEY 1/MONEY :/O Invest/O In/O and/O Develop/O AI/O for/O its/O Many/O Benefits/O .../O .../O .../O 27/NUMBER Strategy/O #/MONEY 2/MONEY :/O Educate/O and/O Train/O Americans/O for/O Jobs/O of/O the/DATE Future/DATE .../O .../O .../O 30/NUMBER Strategy/O #/MONEY 3/MONEY :/O Aid/O Workers/O in/O the/O Transition/O and/O Empower/O Workers/O to/O Ensure/O Broadly/O Shared/O Growth/O .../O 34/NUMBER Conclusion/O .../O .../O .../O .../O .../O ./O 
./O 
43/NUMBER References/O .../O .../O .../O .../O .../O ./O 
./O 
44/NUMBER ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 1/NUMBER Executive/O Summary/O Accelerating/O artificial/O intelligence/O -LRB-/O AI/O -RRB-/O capabilities/O will/O enable/O automation/O of/O some/O tasks/O that/O have/O long/O required/O human/O labor/O ./O 
1/NUMBER These/O transformations/O will/O open/O up/O new/O opportunities/O for/O individuals/O ,/O the/O economy/O ,/O and/O society/O ,/O but/O they/O have/O the/O potential/O to/O disrupt/O the/O current/DATE livelihoods/O of/O millions/O of/O Americans/O ./O 
Whether/O AI/O leads/O to/O unemployment/O and/O increases/O in/O inequality/O over/O the/O long/O -/O run/O depends/O not/O only/O on/O the/O technology/O itself/O but/O also/O on/O the/O institutions/O and/O policies/O that/O are/O in/O place/O ./O 
This/O report/O examines/O the/O expected/O impact/O of/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O on/O the/O ec/O onomy/O ,/O and/O describes/O broad/O strategies/O that/O could/O increase/O the/O benefits/O of/O AI/O and/O mitigate/O its/O costs/O ./O 
Economics/O of/O AI/O -/O Driven/ORGANIZATION Automation/ORGANIZATION Technological/ORGANIZATION progress/O is/O the/O main/O driver/O of/O growth/O of/O GDP/O per/O capita/O ,/O allowing/O output/O to/O increase/O faster/O than/O labor/O and/O capital/O ./O 
One/NUMBER of/O the/O main/O ways/O that/O technology/O increases/O productivity/O is/O by/O decreasing/O the/O number/O of/O labor/O hours/DURATION needed/O to/O create/O a/O unit/O of/O output/O ./O 
Labor/O productivity/O increases/O generally/O translate/O into/O increases/O in/O average/O wage/O s/O ,/O giving/O workers/O the/O opportu/O nity/O to/O cut/O back/O on/O work/O hours/DURATION and/O to/O afford/O more/O goods/O and/O services/O ./O 
Living/O standards/O and/O leisure/O hours/DURATION could/O both/O increase/O ,/O although/O to/O the/O degree/O that/O inequality/O increases/O --/O as/O it/O has/O in/O recent/DURATION decades/DURATION --/O it/O offsets/O some/O of/O those/O gains/O ./O 
AI/O should/O be/O welcome/O d/O for/O its/O potential/O economic/O benefits/O ./O 
Those/O economic/O benefits/O ,/O however/O ,/O will/O not/O necessarily/O be/O evenly/O distributed/O across/O society/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O t/O he/O 19/NUMBER th/O century/DURATION was/O characterized/O by/O technological/O change/O that/O raised/O the/O productivity/O of/O lower/O -/O skilled/O workers/O relative/O to/O that/O of/O higher/O -/O skilled/O workers/O ./O 
Highly/O -/O skilled/O artisans/O who/O controlled/O and/O executed/O full/O production/O processes/O saw/O their/O livelihoods/O threate/O ned/O by/O the/O rise/O of/O mass/O production/O technologies/O ./O 
Ultimately/O ,/O many/O skilled/O crafts/O were/O replaced/O by/O the/O combination/O of/O machines/O and/O lower/O -/O skill/O ed/O labor/O ./O 
Output/O per/O hour/DURATION rose/O while/O inequality/O declined/O ,/O driving/O up/O average/O living/O standards/O ,/O but/O the/O labor/O of/O som/O e/O high/O -/O skill/O workers/O was/O no/O longer/O as/O valuable/O in/O the/O market/O ./O 
In/O contrast/O ,/O technological/O change/O tended/O to/O work/O in/O a/O different/O direction/O throughout/O the/O late/O 20/NUMBER th/O century/DURATION ./O 
The/O advent/O of/O computers/O and/O the/O Internet/O raised/O the/O relative/O productivity/O of/O higher/O -/O skilled/O workers/O ./O 
Routine/O -/O intensive/O occupations/O that/O focused/O on/O predictable/O ,/O easily/O -/O programmable/O tasks/O --/O such/O as/O switchboard/O operators/O ,/O filing/O clerks/O ,/O travel/O agents/O ,/O and/O assembly/O line/O workers/O --/O were/O particularly/O vulnerable/O to/O replacement/O by/O new/O technolog/O ies/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Some/O occupations/O were/O virtually/O eliminated/O and/O demand/O for/O others/O reduced/O ./O 
Research/O suggests/O that/O technological/O innovation/O over/O this/O period/O increased/O the/O productivity/O of/O those/O engaged/O in/O abstract/O thinking/O ,/O creative/O tasks/O ,/O and/O problem/O -/O solving/O and/O wa/O s/O therefore/O at/O least/O partially/O responsible/O for/O the/O substantial/O growth/O in/O jobs/O employing/O such/O traits/O ./O 
Shifting/O demand/O towards/O more/O skilled/O labor/O raised/O the/O relative/O pay/O of/O this/O group/O ,/O contributing/O to/O rising/O inequality/O ./O 
At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O a/O 1/NUMBER A/O more/O extensive/O introductory/O discussion/O of/O artificial/O intelligence/O ,/O machine/O learning/O ,/O and/O related/O policy/O topics/O can/O be/O found/O in/O the/O Administration/ORGANIZATION 's/O first/ORDINAL report/O on/O this/O subject/O ./O 
See/O The/ORGANIZATION White/ORGANIZATION House/ORGANIZATION ,/O ``/O Preparing/O for/O the/DATE Future/DATE of/O Artificial/O Intelligence/O ,/O ''/O October/DATE 2016/DATE -LRB-/O https://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/whitehouse_files/microsites/ostp/NSTC/preparing_for_the_future_o/O f_ai.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 2/NUMBER slowdown/O in/O the/O rate/O of/O improvement/O in/O education/O ,/O and/O institutional/O changes/O such/O as/O the/O reduction/O in/O unionization/O and/O decline/O in/O the/O minimum/O wage/O ,/O also/O contributed/O to/O inequality/O --/O underscoring/O that/O technological/O changes/O do/O not/O uniquely/O determine/O outcomes/O ./O 
Today/DATE ,/O it/O may/O be/O chall/O enging/O to/O predict/O e/O xactly/O which/O jobs/O will/O be/O most/O immediately/O affected/O by/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O ./O 
Because/O AI/O is/O not/O a/O single/O technology/O ,/O but/O rather/O a/O collection/O of/O technologies/O that/O are/O applied/O to/O specific/O tasks/O ,/O the/O effects/O of/O AI/O will/O be/O felt/O unevenly/O throu/O gh/O the/O economy/O ./O 
Some/O tasks/O will/O be/O more/O easily/O automated/O than/O others/O ,/O and/O some/O jobs/O will/O be/O affected/O more/O than/O others/O --/O both/O negatively/O and/O positively/O ./O 
Some/O jobs/O may/O be/O automated/O away/O ,/O while/O for/O others/O ,/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O will/O make/O many/O workers/O more/O produc/O tive/O and/O increase/O demand/O for/O certain/O skills/O ./O 
Finally/O ,/O new/O jobs/O are/O likely/O to/O be/O directly/O created/O in/O areas/O such/O as/O the/O development/O and/O supervision/O of/O AI/O as/O well/O as/O indirectly/O created/O in/O a/O range/O of/O areas/O throughout/O the/O economy/O as/O higher/O incomes/O lead/O to/O expan/O ded/O demand/O ./O 
Recent/O research/O suggests/O that/O the/O effects/O of/O AI/O on/O the/O labor/O market/O in/O the/O near/O term/O will/O continue/O the/O trend/O that/O computerization/O and/O communication/O innovations/O have/O driven/O in/O recent/DURATION decades/DURATION ./O 
Researchers/O '/O e/O stimates/O on/O the/O scale/O of/O threatened/O jobs/O over/O the/DATE next/DATE decade/DATE or/O two/NUMBER range/O from/O 9/NUMBER to/O 47/PERCENT percent/PERCENT ./O 
For/O context/O ,/O every/SET 3/SET months/SET about/O 6/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O jobs/O in/O the/O economy/O are/O destroyed/O by/O shrinking/O or/O closing/O businesses/O ,/O while/O a/O slightly/O larger/O percentage/O of/O jobs/O are/O added/O --/O resulting/O in/O rising/O employment/O and/O a/O roughly/O constant/O unemployment/O rate/O ./O 
The/O economy/O has/O repeatedly/O proven/O itself/O capable/O of/O handling/O this/O scale/O of/O change/O ,/O although/O it/O would/O depend/O on/O how/O rapidly/O the/O changes/O happen/O and/O how/O concentrated/O the/O losse/O s/O are/O in/O specific/O occupations/O that/O are/O hard/O to/O shift/O from/O ./O 
Research/O consistently/O finds/O that/O the/O jobs/O that/O are/O threatened/O by/O automation/O are/O highly/O concentrated/O among/O lower/O -/O paid/O ,/O lower/O -/O skilled/O ,/O and/O less/O -/O educated/O workers/O ./O 
This/O means/O that/O automation/O will/O conti/O nue/O to/O put/O downward/O pressure/O on/O demand/O for/O this/O group/O ,/O putting/O downward/O pressure/O on/O wages/O and/O upward/O pressure/O on/O inequality/O ./O 
In/O the/O longer/O -/O run/O ,/O there/O may/O be/O different/O or/O larger/O effects/O ./O 
One/NUMBER possibility/O is/O superstar/O -/O biased/O technological/O change/O ,/O where/O the/O be/O nefits/O of/O technology/O accrue/O to/O an/O even/O smaller/O portion/O of/O society/O than/O just/O highly/O -/O skilled/O workers/O ./O 
The/O winner/O -/O take/O -/O most/O nature/O of/O information/O technology/O markets/O means/O that/O only/O a/O few/O may/O come/O to/O dominate/O markets/O ./O 
If/O labor/O productivity/O increases/O do/O not/O tra/O nslate/O into/O wage/O increases/O ,/O then/O the/O large/O economic/O gains/O brough/O t/O ab/O out/O by/O AI/O could/O accrue/O to/O a/O select/O few/O ./O 
Instead/O of/O broadly/O shared/O prosperity/O for/O workers/O and/O consumers/O ,/O this/O might/O push/O towards/O reduced/O competition/O and/O increased/O wealth/O inequality/O ./O 
Historically/O and/O across/O countries/O ,/O however/O ,/O there/O has/O been/O a/O strong/O relationship/O between/O productivity/O and/O wages/O --/O and/O with/O more/O AI/O the/O most/O plausible/O outcome/O will/O be/O a/O combination/O of/O higher/O wages/O and/O more/O opportunities/O for/O leisure/O for/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O workers/O ./O 
But/O the/O degree/O that/O this/O materializes/O depends/O not/O just/O on/O the/O nature/O of/O technological/O change/O but/O importantly/O on/O the/O policy/O and/O institutional/O choices/O that/O are/O made/O about/O how/O to/O prepare/O workers/O for/O AI/O and/O to/O handle/O its/O impacts/O on/O the/O labor/O market/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 3/NUMBER Policy/O R/O esponses/O Technology/O is/O not/O destiny/O ;/O economic/O incentives/O and/O public/O policy/O can/O play/O a/O significant/O role/O in/O shaping/O the/O direction/O and/O effects/O of/O technological/O change/O ./O 
Given/O appropriate/O attention/O and/O the/O right/O policy/O and/O institutional/O responses/O ,/O advanced/O autom/O ation/O can/O be/O compatible/O with/O productivity/O ,/O high/O levels/O of/O employment/O ,/O and/O more/O broadly/O shared/O prosperity/O ./O 
In/O the/DATE past/DATE ,/O the/O U.S./LOCATION economy/O has/O adapted/O to/O new/O production/O patterns/O and/O maintained/O high/O levels/O of/O employment/O alongside/O rising/O productivity/O as/O more/O pr/O oductive/O workers/O have/O had/O more/O incentive/O to/O work/O and/O more/O highly/O paid/O workers/O have/O spent/O more/O ,/O supporting/O this/O work/O ./O 
But/O ,/O some/O shocks/O have/O left/O a/O growing/O share/O of/O workers/O out/O of/O the/O labor/O force/O ./O 
This/O report/O advocates/O strategies/O to/O educate/O and/O prepare/O new/O w/O orkers/O to/O enter/O the/O workforce/O ,/O cushion/O workers/O who/O lose/O jobs/O ,/O keep/O them/O attached/O to/O the/O labor/O force/O ,/O and/O combat/O inequality/O ./O 
Most/O of/O these/O strategies/O would/O be/O important/O regardless/O of/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O ,/O but/O all/O take/O on/O even/O greater/O importance/O to/O the/O degre/O e/O that/O AI/O is/O making/O major/O changes/O to/O the/O economy/O ./O 
Strategy/O #/MONEY 1/MONEY :/O Invest/O in/O and/O develop/O AI/O for/O its/O many/O benefits/O ./O 
If/O care/O is/O taken/O to/O responsibly/O maximize/O its/O development/O ,/O AI/O will/O make/O important/O ,/O positive/O contributions/O to/O aggregate/O productivity/O growth/O ,/O and/O ad/O vances/O in/O AI/O technology/O hold/O incredible/O potential/O to/O help/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION stay/O on/O the/O cutting/O edge/O of/O innovation/O ./O 
Government/O ha/O s/O an/O important/O role/O to/O play/O in/O advancing/O the/O AI/O field/O by/O investing/O in/O research/O and/O development/O ./O 
Among/O the/O areas/O for/O advancement/O in/O AI/O are/O cyberdefense/O and/O the/O detection/O of/O fraudulent/O transactions/O and/O messages/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O t/O he/O rapid/O growth/O of/O AI/O has/O also/O dramatically/O increased/O the/O need/O for/O people/O with/O relevant/O skills/O from/O all/O backgrounds/O to/O support/O and/O advance/O the/O field/O ./O 
Prioritizing/O diversity/O and/O inclusion/O in/O STEM/O fields/O and/O in/O the/O AI/O community/O specifically/O ,/O in/O addition/O to/O other/O possible/O policy/O responses/O ,/O is/O a/O key/O part/O in/O addressing/O potential/O barriers/O stemming/O from/O algorithmic/O bias/O ./O 
Competition/O from/O new/O and/O existing/O firms/O ,/O and/O the/O development/O of/O sound/O pro/O -/O competition/O policies/O ,/O will/O increasingly/O play/O an/O important/O role/O in/O the/O creation/O and/O adoption/O of/O new/O technologies/O and/O innovations/O related/O to/O AI/O ./O 
Strategy/O #/MONEY 2/MONEY :/O Educate/O and/O train/O Americans/O for/O jobs/O of/O the/DATE future/DATE ./O 
As/O AI/O changes/O the/O nature/O of/O work/O and/O the/O skills/O demanded/O by/O the/O labor/O market/O ,/O American/O workers/O will/O need/O to/O be/O prepared/O with/O the/O education/O and/O training/O that/O can/O help/O them/O continue/O to/O succeed/O ./O 
Delivering/O this/O education/O and/O training/O will/O require/O significant/O investments/O ./O 
This/O starts/O with/O providing/O all/O children/O with/O access/O to/O high/O -/O quality/O early/O education/O so/O that/O all/O families/O can/O prepare/O their/O students/O for/O continued/O education/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O investing/O in/O graduating/O all/O students/O from/O high/O school/O college/O -/O and/O career/O -/O ready/O ,/O and/O ens/O uring/O that/O all/O Americans/O have/O access/O to/O affordable/O post/O -/O secondary/O education/O ./O 
Assisting/O U.S./LOCATION workers/O in/O successfully/O navigating/O job/O transitions/O will/O also/O become/O increasingly/O important/O ;/O this/O includes/O expanding/O the/O availability/O of/O job/O -/O driven/O training/O and/O oppo/O rtunities/O for/O lifelong/O learning/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O providing/O workers/O with/O improved/O guidance/O to/O navigate/O job/O transitions/O ./O 
Strategy/O #/MONEY 3/MONEY :/O Aid/O workers/O in/O the/O transition/O and/O empower/O workers/O to/O ensure/O broadly/O shared/O growth/O ./O 
Policymakers/O should/O ensure/O that/O workers/O and/O j/O ob/O seekers/O are/O both/O able/O to/O pursue/O the/O job/O opportunities/O for/O which/O they/O are/O best/O qualified/O and/O best/O positioned/O to/O ensure/O they/O receive/O an/O appro/O priate/O return/O for/O their/O work/O in/O the/O form/O of/O rising/O wages/O ./O 
This/O includes/O steps/O to/O modernize/O the/O social/O safety/O net/O ,/O including/O exploring/O strengthening/O critical/O supports/O such/O as/O unemployment/O ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 4/NUMBER insurance/O ,/O Medicaid/O ,/O Supplemental/ORGANIZATION Nutrition/ORGANIZATION Assistance/ORGANIZATION Program/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O SNAP/O -RRB-/O ,/O and/O Temporary/ORGANIZATION Assistance/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Needy/ORGANIZATION Families/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O TANF/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O ,/O and/O putting/O in/O place/O new/O programs/O such/O as/O wage/O insurance/O and/O emergency/O aid/O for/O families/O in/O crisis/O ./O 
Worker/O empowerment/O also/O includes/O bolstering/O critical/O safeguards/O for/O workers/O and/O families/O in/O need/O ,/O building/O a/O 21/NUMBER st/O century/DURATION retirement/O system/O ,/O and/O expanding/O healthcare/O access/O ./O 
Increasing/O wages/O ,/O competition/O ,/O and/O worker/O b/O argaining/O power/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O modernizing/O tax/O policy/O and/O pursuing/O strategies/O to/O address/O differential/O geographic/O impact/O ,/O will/O be/O important/O aspects/O of/O supporting/O workers/O and/O addressing/O concerns/O related/O to/O displacement/O amid/O shifts/O in/O the/O labor/O market/O ./O 
Finally/O ,/O if/O a/O significant/O proportion/O of/O Americans/O are/O affected/O in/O the/O short/O -/O and/O medium/O -/O term/O by/O AI/O -/O driven/O job/O displacements/O ,/O policymakers/O will/O need/O to/O consider/O more/O robust/O interventions/O ,/O such/O as/O further/O strengthening/O the/O unemployment/O insurance/O system/O and/O counterva/O iling/O job/O creation/O strategies/O ,/O to/O smooth/O the/O transition/O ./O 
Conclusion/O Responding/O to/O the/O economic/O effects/O of/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O will/O be/O a/O significant/O policy/O challenge/O for/O the/O next/O Administration/ORGANIZATION and/O its/O successors/O ./O 
AI/O has/O already/O begun/O to/O transform/O the/O Amer/O ican/O workplace/O ,/O change/O the/O types/O of/O jobs/O available/O ,/O and/O reshape/O the/O skills/O that/O workers/O need/O in/O order/O to/O thrive/O ./O 
All/O Americans/O should/O have/O the/O opportunity/O to/O participate/O in/O addressing/O these/O challenges/O ,/O whether/O as/O students/O ,/O workers/O ,/O managers/O ,/O technical/O lead/O ers/O ,/O or/O simply/O as/O citizens/O with/O a/O voice/O in/O the/O policy/O debate/O ./O 
AI/O raises/O many/O new/O policy/O questions/O ,/O which/O should/O be/O continued/O topics/O for/O discussion/O and/O consideration/O by/O future/DATE Administrations/O ,/O Congress/ORGANIZATION ,/O the/O private/O sector/O ,/O academia/O ,/O and/O the/O public/O ./O 
Continued/O engagement/O among/O government/O ,/O industry/O ,/O technical/O and/O policy/O experts/O ,/O and/O the/O public/O should/O play/O an/O important/O role/O in/O moving/O the/O Nation/O toward/O policies/O that/O create/O broadly/O shared/O prosperity/O ,/O unlock/O the/O creative/O potential/O of/O America/LOCATION n/O companies/O and/O workers/O ,/O and/O ensure/O America/LOCATION 's/O continued/O leadership/O in/O the/O creation/O and/O use/O of/O AI/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 5/NUMBER Outreach/O and/O Development/O of/O this/O Report/O This/O report/O was/O developed/O by/O a/O team/O in/O the/O Executive/ORGANIZATION Office/ORGANIZATION of/O the/O President/O including/O staff/O from/O the/O White/ORGANIZATION House/ORGANIZATION Council/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Advisers/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O CEA/O -RRB-/O ,/O Domestic/O Policy/O Council/O -LRB-/O DPC/O -RRB-/O ,/O National/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Council/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O NEC/O -RRB-/O ,/O Office/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Management/ORGANIZATION and/O Budget/O -LRB-/O OMB/O -RRB-/O ,/O and/O Office/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Science/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION Policy/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O OSTP/O -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O report/O follows/O a/O previous/O report/O published/O in/O October/DATE 2016/DATE titled/O Preparing/O for/O the/DATE Future/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Artificial/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION and/O the/O accompanying/O National/ORGANIZATION Artificial/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Development/ORGANIZATION Strategic/ORGANIZATION Plan/ORGANIZATION ,/O developed/O by/O the/O National/ORGANIZATION Science/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION Council/ORGANIZATION 's/O -LRB-/O NSTC/O -RRB-/O Subcommittee/O on/O Machine/O Learning/O and/O Artificial/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION ./O 
This/O subcommittee/O was/O chartered/O in/O May/DATE 2016/DATE by/O OSTP/O to/O foster/O interagency/O coordination/O and/O provide/O technical/O and/O policy/O advice/O on/O topics/O related/O to/O AI/O ,/O and/O to/O monitor/O the/O development/O of/O AI/O technologies/O across/O industry/O ,/O the/O research/O community/O ,/O and/O the/O Federal/ORGANIZATION Government/ORGANIZATION ./O 
This/O report/O also/O follows/O a/O series/O of/O public/O -/O outreach/O activities/O as/O a/O part/O of/O the/O White/ORGANIZATION House/ORGANIZATION Future/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Artificial/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION Initiative/ORGANIZATION ,/O designed/O to/O allow/O government/O officials/O to/O learn/O from/O experts/O and/O from/O the/O public/O ,/O which/O included/O five/NUMBER co/O -/O hosted/O public/O workshops/O ,/O and/O a/O public/O Request/O for/O Information/O -LRB-/O RFI/O -RRB-/O ./O 
2/NUMBER This/O report/O more/O deeply/O examines/O the/O impact/O of/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O on/O the/O economy/O and/O policy/O responses/O to/O it/O ./O 
It/O considers/O the/O economic/O evidenc/O e/O to/O better/O understand/O the/O lessons/O from/O past/DATE waves/O of/O automation/O ,/O the/O impact/O already/O caused/O by/O the/O current/DATE wave/O of/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O and/O its/O prospects/O for/O the/DATE near/DATE future/DATE ,/O and/O how/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O may/O affect/O workers/O in/O the/DATE future/DATE ./O 
The/O report/O also/O co/O nsiders/O policy/O steps/O that/O are/O needed/O to/O address/O the/O economic/O dislocation/O caused/O by/O the/O arrival/O of/O these/O technologies/O and/O to/O prepare/O for/O longer/O -/O term/O trends/O in/O the/O economy/O caused/O by/O AI/O ,/O automation/O ,/O and/O other/O factors/O that/O are/O systemically/O disadvantaging/O certa/O in/O workers/O ./O 
The/O report/O lays/O out/O three/NUMBER broad/O strategies/O for/O policymakers/O to/O consider/O ./O 
2/NUMBER Ed/PERSON Felten/PERSON and/O Terah/PERSON Lyons/PERSON ,/O ``/O Public/O Input/O and/O Next/O Steps/O on/O the/DATE Future/DATE of/O Artificial/O Intelligence/O ,/O ''/O Medium/O ,/O September/DATE 6/DATE 2016/DATE -LRB-/O https://medium.com/@USCTO/public/O -/O input/O -/O and/O -/O next/O -/O steps/O -/O on/O -/O the/O -/O future/DATE -/O of/O -/O artificialintelligence/O -458/NUMBER b82059fc3/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Further/O details/O on/O the/O public/O workshop/O s/O and/O the/O RFI/ORGANIZATION can/O be/O found/O in/O the/O October/DATE 2016/DATE report/O ,/O Preparing/O for/O the/DATE Future/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Artificial/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 6/NUMBER Introduction/O Recent/O progress/O in/O Artificial/O Intelligence/O -LRB-/O AI/O -RRB-/O ha/O s/O brought/O renewed/O attention/O to/O questions/O about/O automation/O driven/O by/O these/O advances/O and/O their/O impact/O on/O the/O economy/O ./O 
The/O current/DATE wave/O of/O progress/O and/O enthusiasm/O for/O AI/O began/O around/O 2010/DATE ,/O driven/O by/O three/NUMBER mutually/O reinforcing/O factors/O :/O the/O availability/O of/O big/O data/O from/O sources/O including/O e/O -/O commerce/O ,/O businesses/O ,/O social/O media/O ,/O science/O ,/O and/O government/O ;/O 3/NUMBER which/O prov/O ided/O raw/O material/O for/O dramatically/O improved/O machine/O learning/O approaches/O and/O algorithms/O ;/O which/O in/O turn/O relied/O on/O the/O capabilities/O of/O more/O powerful/O computers/O ./O 
4/NUMBER During/O this/O period/O ,/O the/O pace/O of/O improvement/O surprised/O AI/O experts/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O on/O a/O popular/O image/O recognition/O challenge/O that/O has/O a/O 5/PERCENT percent/PERCENT human/O error/O rate/O according/O to/O one/NUMBER error/O measure/O ,/O 5/NUMBER the/O best/O AI/O result/O improved/O from/O a/O 26/PERCENT percent/PERCENT error/O rate/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2011/DATE to/O 3.5/PERCENT percent/PERCENT in/U_TEMPPRED 2015/DATE ./O 
This/O p/O rogress/O may/O enable/O a/O range/O of/O workplace/O tasks/O that/O require/O image/O un/O derstanding/O to/O be/O automated/O ,/O and/O will/O also/O enable/O new/O types/O of/O work/O and/O jobs/O ./O 
Progress/O on/O other/O AI/O challenges/O will/O drive/O similar/O economic/O changes/O ./O 
Technical/O innovation/O has/O been/O expand/O ing/O the/O American/O economy/O since/O the/O country/O 's/O founding/O ./O 
American/O ingenuity/O has/O always/O been/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O Nation/ORGANIZATION 's/O greatest/O resources/O ,/O a/O key/O driver/O of/O economic/O growth/O ,/O and/O a/O source/O of/O strategic/O advantage/O for/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ./O 
Remarkable/O homegrown/O innovations/O have/O improved/O quality/O of/O life/O ,/O created/O jobs/O ,/O broadened/O understanding/O of/O the/O world/O ,/O and/O helped/O Americans/O approach/O their/O full/O potential/O ./O 
At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O they/O have/O forced/O Americans/O to/O adapt/O to/O changes/O in/O the/O workplace/O and/O the/O job/O market/O ./O 
These/O transformations/O have/O not/O always/O been/O comfortable/O ,/O but/O in/O the/O long/O run/O --/O and/O supported/O by/O good/O public/O policy/O --/O they/O have/O provided/O great/O benefits/O ./O 
The/O current/DATE wave/O of/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O may/O not/O be/O so/O different/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O robots/O have/O made/O the/O economy/O more/O efficient/O ./O 
A/O 2015/DATE study/O of/O robots/O in/O 17/NUMBER countries/O found/O that/O they/O added/O an/O estimated/O 0.4/NUMBER percentage/O point/O on/O average/O to/O those/O countries/O '/O annual/SET GDP/O growth/O between/O 1993/DATE and/O 2007/DATE ,/O accounting/O for/O just/O over/O one/NUMBER -/O tenth/ORDINAL of/O those/O countries/O '/O overall/O GDP/O growth/O during/O that/O time/O ./O 
6/NUMBER Some/O of/O that/O growth/O has/O been/O achieved/O by/O U.S./LOCATION manufactur/O ers/O adopting/O robots/O ,/O allowing/O more/O goods/O to/O be/O produced/O while/O employing/O fewer/O workers/O at/O some/O facilities/O ./O 
AI/O in/O its/O many/O manifestations/O also/O holds/O promise/O to/O transform/O the/O basis/O of/O economic/O growth/O for/O countries/O across/O the/O world/O ;/O a/O recent/O analysis/O of/O 12/NUMBER dev/O eloped/O economies/O -LRB-/O including/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION -RRB-/O 3/NUMBER ``/O Big/O Data/O :/O Seizing/O Opportunities/O ,/O Preserving/O Values/O ,/O ''/O Executive/O Office/O of/O the/O President/O ,/O May/DATE 2014/DATE ,/O https://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files//O docs/big_data_privacy_report_may_1_2014.pdf/O ./O 
4/NUMBER For/O more/O information/O about/O AI/O and/O its/O policy/O implications/O ,/O see/O :/O The/O White/ORGANIZATION House/ORGANIZATION ,/O ``/O Preparing/O for/O the/DATE Future/DATE of/O Artificial/O Intelligence/O ,/O ''/O October/DATE 2016/DATE ./O 
-LRB-/O https://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/whitehouse_files/microsites/ostp/NSTC/preparing_for_the_fut/O ure_of_ai.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
5/NUMBER The/O ImageNet/ORGANIZATION Large/ORGANIZATION Scale/ORGANIZATION Visual/ORGANIZATION Recognition/ORGANIZATION Challenge/ORGANIZATION provides/O a/O set/O of/O photographic/O ima/O ges/O and/O asks/O for/O an/O accurate/O description/O of/O what/O is/O depicted/O in/O each/O image/O ./O 
Statistics/O in/O the/O text/O refer/O to/O the/O ``/O classification/O error/O ''/O metric/O in/O the/O ``/O classification/O +/O localization/O with/O provided/O training/O data/O ''/O task/O ./O 
See/O http://image/O -net.org/challenges/LSVRC//O ./O 
6/NUMBER Georg/PERSON Graetz/PERSON and/O Guy/PERSON Michaels/PERSON ,/O ``/O Robots/O at/O Work/O ,/O ''/O CEPR/ORGANIZATION Discussion/O Paper/O No/O ./O 
DP10477/O ,/O March/DATE 2015/DATE -LRB-/O http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2575781/O -RRB-/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 7/NUMBER found/O that/O AI/O has/O the/O potential/O to/O double/O annual/SET economic/O growth/O rates/O in/O the/O countries/O analyzed/O by/U_TEMPPRED 2035/DATE ./O 
7/NUMBER Some/O experts/O have/O characterized/O the/O rise/O of/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O as/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O most/O important/O economic/O and/O social/O developments/O in/O history/O ./O 
The/O World/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Forum/ORGANIZATION has/O characterized/O it/O as/O the/O lynchpin/O of/O a/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION .8/NUMBER Furthermore/O ,/O the/O economist/O Andrew/PERSON McAfee/PERSON wrote/O ,/O ``/O Digital/O technologies/O are/O doing/O for/O human/O brainpower/O what/O the/O steam/O engine/O and/O related/O technologies/O did/O for/O human/O muscle/O power/O during/O the/O Industrial/O Revolution/O ./O 
They/O 're/O allowing/O us/O to/O overcome/O many/O limitations/O rapidly/O and/O to/O open/O up/O new/O frontiers/O with/O unprecedented/O speed/O ./O 
It/O 's/O a/O v/O ery/O big/O deal/O ./O 
But/O how/O exactly/O it/O will/O play/O out/O is/O uncertain/O ./O ''/O 
9/NUMBER At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O has/O yet/O to/O have/O a/O quantitatively/O major/O impact/O on/O productivity/O growth/O ./O 
In/O fact/O ,/O measured/O productivity/O growth/O over/O the/DATE last/DATE decade/DATE has/O slowed/O in/O almost/O every/O advanced/O economy/O ./O 
It/O is/O plausible/O ,/O however/O ,/O that/O the/O pace/O of/O measured/O productivity/O growth/O will/O pick/O up/O in/O the/DATE coming/DATE years/DATE ./O 
To/O the/O degree/O that/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O realizes/O its/O potential/O t/O o/O drive/O tremendous/O positive/O advancement/O in/O diverse/O fields/O ,/O it/O will/O make/O Americans/O better/O off/O on/O average/O ./O 
But/O ,/O there/O is/O no/O guarantee/O that/O everyone/O will/O benefit/O ./O 
AI/O -/O driven/O changes/O in/O the/O job/O market/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION will/O cause/O some/O workers/O to/O lose/O their/O j/O obs/O ,/O even/O while/O creating/O new/O jobs/O elsewhere/O ./O 
The/O economic/O pain/O this/O causes/O will/O fall/O more/O heavily/O up/O on/O some/O than/O on/O others/O ./O 
Policymakers/O must/O consider/O what/O can/O be/O done/O to/O help/O those/O families/O and/O communities/O get/O back/O on/O their/O feet/O and/O assemble/O the/O tools/O they/O need/O to/O thrive/O in/O the/O transformed/O economy/O and/O share/O in/O its/O benefits/O ./O 
7/NUMBER Paul/PERSON Daugherty/PERSON and/O Mark/PERSON Purdy/PERSON ,/O ``/O Why/O AI/O is/O the/DATE Future/DATE of/O Growth/O ,/O ''/O 2016/DATE -LRB-/O https://www.accenture.com/t20161031T154852__w__/us/O -/O en/O //O _/O acnmedia/PDF/O -33/NUMBER //O Accenture/ORGANIZATION -/O Why/O -/O AI/O -/O is-the/O -/O Future/DATE -/O of-Growth/O ./O 
PDF/O #zoom/O =/O 50/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
8/NUMBER Klaus/PERSON Schwab/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O Fourth/ORDINAL Industrial/O Revolution/O :/O what/O it/O means/O ,/O how/O to/O respond/O ,/O ''/O World/O Economic/O Forum/O ,/O January/DATE 2016/DATE -LRB-/O https://ww/O w.weforum.org/agenda/2016/01/the/O -/O fourth/ORDINAL -/O industrial/O -/O revolution/O -/O what/O -/O it-means/O -/O and/O -/O how/O -/O to-respond/O //O -RRB-/O ./O 
-LRB-/O The/O first/ORDINAL three/NUMBER industrial/O revolutions/O are/O listed/O as/O those/O driven/O by/O steam/O power/O ,/O electricity/O ,/O and/O electronics/O ./O -RRB-/O 
9/NUMBER Amy/PERSON Bernstein/PERSON and/O Anand/PERSON Raman/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O Great/O Decoupling/O :/O An/O Interview/O with/O Erik/PERSON Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O Andrew/PERSON McAfee/PERSON ,/O ''/O Harvard/ORGANIZATION Business/ORGANIZATION Review/ORGANIZATION ,/O June/DATE 2015/DATE -LRB-/O https://hbr.org/2015/06/the/O -/O great/O -/O decoupling/O -RRB-/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 8/NUMBER Econom/O ic/O s/O of/O AI/O -/O Driven/O Automation/O Accelerating/O AI/O capabilities/O will/O enable/O automation/O of/O some/O tasks/O that/O have/O long/O required/O human/O labor/O ./O 
Rather/O than/O relying/O on/O closely/O -/O tailored/O rule/O s/O explicitly/O crafted/O by/O programmers/O ,/O modern/O AI/O programs/O can/O learn/O from/O patterns/O in/O whatever/O data/O they/O encounter/O and/O develop/O their/O own/O rules/O for/O how/O to/O interpret/O new/O information/O ./O 
This/O means/O that/O AI/O can/O solve/O problems/O and/O learn/O with/O very/O little/O human/O input/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O advances/O in/O robotics/O are/O expanding/O machines/O '/O abilities/O to/O interact/O with/O and/O shape/O the/O physical/O world/O ./O 
Combined/O ,/O AI/O and/O robotics/O will/O give/O rise/O to/O smart/O er/O machines/O that/O can/O perform/O more/O sophisticated/O functions/O than/O ever/O before/O and/O erode/O some/O of/O the/O advantages/O that/O humans/O have/O exercised/O ./O 
This/O will/O permit/O automation/O of/O many/O tasks/O now/DATE performed/O by/O human/O workers/O and/O could/O change/O the/O shape/O of/O the/O labor/O market/O and/O human/O activity/O ./O 
These/O transformations/O may/O open/O up/O new/O opportunities/O for/O individuals/O ,/O th/O e/O economy/O ,/O and/O society/O ,/O but/O they/O may/O also/O foreclose/O opportunities/O that/O are/O currently/DATE essential/O to/O the/O livelihoods/O of/O many/O Americans/O ./O 
This/O chapter/O explores/O the/O important/O role/O that/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O is/O likely/O to/O have/O in/O growing/O the/O economy/O and/O potential/O effects/O on/O labor/O markets/O and/O communities/O ./O 
It/O draws/O on/O economic/O theory/O and/O empirical/O studies/O of/O past/DATE technological/O transformations/O and/O applies/O these/O lessons/O to/O the/O current/DATE context/O ./O 
While/O there/O are/O many/O reasons/O to/O think/O that/O changes/O in/O the/O labor/O market/O prompted/O by/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O will/O be/O similar/O to/O what/O has/O been/O observed/O in/O the/DATE past/DATE ,/O this/O chapter/O will/O also/O discuss/O arguments/O for/O how/O the/O current/DATE period/O could/O be/O different/O from/O previous/O technological/O revolutions/O ./O 
Critically/O ,/O technology/O alone/O will/O not/O determine/O the/O economic/O outcomes/O in/O terms/O of/O growth/O ,/O inequality/O or/O employment/O ./O 
The/O advanced/O economies/O all/O have/O had/O access/O to/O similar/O levels/O of/O technology/O but/O have/O had/O very/O different/O outcomes/O along/O all/O of/O these/O dimension/O s/O because/O they/O have/O ha/O d/O different/O institutions/O and/O policies/O ./O 
But/O understanding/O the/O technological/O forces/O is/O critical/O to/O shaping/O the/O continued/O evolution/O of/O these/O policies/O ./O 
AI/O and/O the/O Macroeconomy/O :/O Technology/O and/O Productivity/O Growth/O To/O the/O extent/O that/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O resembl/O es/O past/DATE forms/O of/O technological/O advance/O ment/O ,/O it/O will/O make/O important/O contributions/O to/O aggregate/O productivity/O growth/O ./O 
For/O centuries/DURATION ,/O the/O American/O economy/O has/O adjusted/O to/O and/O evolved/O with/O technology/O ./O 
Many/O jobs/O that/O existed/O 150/DATE years/DATE ago/DATE do/O not/O exist/O today/DATE ,/O an/O d/O jobs/O no/O one/NUMBER could/O have/O imagined/O then/O have/O taken/O their/O place/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1870/DATE ,/O almost/O 50/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O American/O employees/O worked/O in/O agriculture/O ,/O supplying/O the/O Nation/ORGANIZATION 's/O food/O ./O 
10/NUMBER Today/DATE ,/O thanks/O in/O large/O part/O to/O technological/O change/O ,/O agriculture/O employs/O less/O than/O 2/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O American/O workers/O and/O American/O food/O production/O exceeds/O domestic/O demand/O ./O 
11/NUMBER In/O this/O case/O ,/O technological/O innovations/O ,/O from/O McCormick/PERSON harvesters/O 10/NUMBER Patricia/PERSON A./PERSON Daly/PERSON ,/O ``/O Agricultural/O Employment/O :/O Has/O the/O Decline/O Ended/O ?/O ''/O 
Monthly/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Review/ORGANIZATION ,/O November/DATE 198/DATE 1/DATE -LRB-/O http://www.bls.gov/opub/mlr/1981/11/art2full.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
11/NUMBER Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION ,/O ``/O Employment/O Projections/O :/O Employment/O by/O major/O industry/O sector/O ,/O ''/O December/DATE 2015/DATE -LRB-/O http://www.bls.gov/emp/ep_table_201.htm/O -RRB-/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 9/NUMBER to/O today/DATE 's/O self/O -/O driving/O tractors/O ,/O increased/O the/O productivity/O of/O the/O agricultur/O al/O sector/O and/O contr/O ibuted/O to/O increases/O in/O standard/O of/O living/O ./O 
12/NUMBER One/NUMBER of/O the/O main/O ways/O that/O technology/O increases/O productivity/O is/O by/O decreasing/O the/O number/O of/O labor/O hours/DURATION needed/O to/O create/O a/O unit/O of/O output/O ./O 
Labor/O productivity/O increases/O generally/O translate/O into/O increases/O in/O average/O wage/O s/O ,/O giving/O workers/O the/O opportunity/O to/O cut/O back/O on/O work/O hours/DURATION and/O to/O afford/O more/O goods/O and/O services/O ./O 
Living/O standards/O and/O leisure/O hours/DURATION could/O both/O increase/O ,/O although/O to/O the/O degree/O that/O inequality/O increases/O --/O as/O it/O has/O in/O recent/DURATION decades/DURATION --/O it/O offsets/O some/O of/O t/O hose/O gains/O ./O 
Th/O e/O expectation/O that/O productivity/O increases/O would/O be/O accompanied/O by/O wage/O grow/O th/O is/O what/O led/O John/PERSON Maynard/PERSON Keynes/PERSON to/O predict/O in/O his/O 1930/DATE essay/O on/O ``/O Economic/O Possibilities/O for/O our/O Grandchildren/O ''/O that/O ,/O given/O the/O rates/O of/O technical/O progress/O ,/O we/O might/O have/O achieved/O a/O 15/DURATION -/DURATION hour/DURATION workweek/O by/O now/DATE ./O 
13/NUMBER While/O that/O prediction/O remains/O far/O off/O ,/O over/O the/DURATION last/DATE 65/DATE years/DATE ,/O most/O developed/O economies/O saw/O annual/SET hours/DURATION worked/O decline/O substantially/O -LRB-/O Figure/O 1/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O the/O U/O nited/O States/O uniquely/O ,/O however/O ,/O this/O decline/O stopped/O in/O the/DATE late/DATE 1970s/DATE ,/O and/O hours/DURATION per/O worker/O has/O remained/O flat/O since/O then/O ./O 
Technology/O has/O been/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O main/O drivers/O of/O this/O productivity/O growth/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O changes/O in/O technology/O help/O explain/O permanent/O productivity/O increases/O throughout/O the/DATE 1990s/DATE ./O 
14/NUMBER There/O is/O also/O 12/NUMBER USDA/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION Service/ORGANIZATION ,/O ``/O Table/O 1/NUMBER ./O 
Indices/O of/O farm/O output/O ,/O input/O ,/O and/O total/O factor/O productivity/O for/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O 1948/DATE -2013/DURATION ''/O -LRB-/O https://www.ers.usda.gov/data/O -/O products/agricultural/O -/O productivity/O -/O in-the/O -/O us/O //O -RRB-/O ./O 
13/NUMBER John/PERSON M./PERSON Keynes/PERSON ,/O ``/O Economic/O Possibilities/O for/O our/O Grandchildren/O ./O ''/O 
In/O Essays/O in/O Persuasion/O ,/O New/LOCATION York/LOCATION :/O W.W.Norton/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Co./ORGANIZATION ,/O pp/O ./O 
358/NUMBER -373/NUMBER ,/O 1930/DATE ./O 
-LRB-/O http://www.econ.yale.edu/smith/econ116a/keynes1.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
14/NUMBER Susanto/PERSON Basu/PERSON ,/O John/PERSON G./PERSON Fernald/PERSON ,/O and/O Matthew/PERSON D./PERSON Shapiro/PERSON ,/O ``/O Productivity/O growth/O in/O the/DATE 1990s/DATE :/O technology/O ,/O utilization/O ,/O or/O adjustment/O ?/O ''/O 
Carnegie/O -/O Rochester/ORGANIZATION Conference/ORGANIZATION Series/ORGANIZATION on/O Public/O Policy/O 55/NUMBER -LRB-/O 1/NUMBER -RRB-/O :/O 117/NUMBER -65/NUMBER ,/O 2001/DATE -LRB-/O https://ideas.repec.org/a/eee/crcspp/v55y2001i1p117/O -165/NUMBER ./O 
html/O -RRB-/O ./O 
1,000/NUMBER 1,200/NUMBER 1,400/NUMBER 1,600/NUMBER 1,800/NUMBER 2,000/NUMBER 2,200/NUMBER 2,400/NUMBER 1950/DATE 1960/DATE 1970/DATE 1980/DATE 1990/DATE 2000/DATE 2010/DATE United/ORGANIZATION States/ORGANIZATION United/ORGANIZATION Kingdom/ORGANIZATION Canada/ORGANIZATION France/ORGANIZATION Italy/ORGANIZATION Japan/ORGANIZATION Germany/ORGANIZATION Figure/ORGANIZATION 1/NUMBER :/O Average/O Annual/SET Hours/DURATION Worked/O per/O Worker/O ,/O G/O -7/NUMBER Countries/O ,/O 1950/DATE -2015/DURATION Average/O annual/SET hours/DURATION worked/O Source/O :/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Stat/O ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 10/NUMBER evidence/O that/O industrial/O robotic/O automation/O alone/O increased/O labor/O productivity/O growth/O by/O 0.36/PERCENT percentage/PERCENT points/PERCENT across/O 17/NUMBER countries/O between/O 1993/DATE and/O 2007/DATE .15/NUMBER The/O potential/O positive/O impact/O of/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O on/O productivity/O is/O particularly/O important/O given/O recent/O trends/O in/O productivity/O ./O 
In/O the/DATE last/DATE decade/DATE ,/O despite/O technology/O 's/O positive/O push/O ,/O measured/O productivity/O growth/O has/O slowed/O in/O 30/NUMBER of/O the/O 31/NUMBER advanced/O economies/O ,/O slowing/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION from/O an/O average/O annual/SET growth/O rate/O of/O 2.5/NUMBER perce/O nt/O in/O the/DATE decade/DATE after/DATE 1995/DATE to/O only/O 1.0/PERCENT percent/PERCENT growth/O in/O the/DATE decade/DATE after/O 2005/DATE -LRB-/O Figure/O 2/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
While/O a/O considerable/O amount/O of/O this/O slowdown/O in/O many/O countries/O --/O including/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION --/O is/O due/O to/O a/O slowdown/O in/O investment/O in/O capital/O stock/O ,/O the/O slowdown/O in/O tota/O l/O factor/O productivity/O growth/O -LRB-/O the/O component/O influenced/O by/O technological/O change/O -RRB-/O has/O also/O been/O important/O ./O 
16/NUMBER This/O has/O contributed/O to/O slower/O growth/O in/O real/O wages/O and/O if/O continued/O will/O slow/O improvements/O in/O living/O standards/O ./O 
AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O could/O help/O boost/O total/O factor/O productivity/O growth/O and/O create/O new/O potential/O to/O improve/O the/O lives/O of/O Americans/O broadly/O ./O 
The/O benefits/O of/O technological/O change/O and/O economic/O growth/O ,/O however/O ,/O are/O not/O necessarily/O shared/O equally/O ./O 
This/O can/O depen/O d/O on/O both/O the/O nature/O and/O speed/O of/O the/O technological/O change/O as/O well/O as/O the/O ability/O of/O workers/O to/O negotiate/O for/O the/O benefits/O of/O their/O increased/O productivity/O ,/O as/O discussed/O below/O ./O 
AI/O and/O the/O Labor/O Market/O :/O Diverse/O Potential/O Effects/O Few/O would/O dispute/O that/O the/O in/O dustrial/O revolution/O largely/O made/O society/O better/O off/O ,/O but/O the/O transition/O led/O to/O severe/O disruptions/O to/O the/O lives/O and/O communities/O of/O many/O agricultural/O workers/O ,/O with/O 15/NUMBER Georg/PERSON Graetz/PERSON and/O Guy/PERSON Michaels/PERSON ,/O ``/O Robots/O at/O Work/O ,/O ''/O Centre/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Policy/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O CEPR/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O Discussion/O Paper/O No/O ./O 
DP10477/O ,/O 2015/DATE -LRB-/O http://cep.lse.ac.uk/pubs/download/dp1335.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
16/NUMBER Jason/PERSON Furman/PERSON ,/O ``/O Productivity/O Growth/O in/O the/O Advanced/O Economies/O :/O The/DATE Past/DATE ,/O the/O Present/DATE ,/O and/O Lessons/O for/O the/DATE Future/DATE ,/O ''/O Speech/O at/O the/O Peterson/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION International/ORGANIZATION Economics/ORGANIZATION ,/O Washington/LOCATION ,/O July/DATE 9/DATE 20/DATE 15/DATE -LRB-/O https://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/docs/20150709_productivity_advanced_economies_piie.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
-0.5/NUMBER 0.0/NUMBER 0.5/NUMBER 1.0/NUMBER 1.5/NUMBER 2.0/NUMBER 2.5/NUMBER 3.0/NUMBER United/ORGANIZATION States/ORGANIZATION Canada/ORGANIZATION Japan/ORGANIZATION Germany/ORGANIZATION France/ORGANIZATION United/ORGANIZATION Kingdom/ORGANIZATION Italy/ORGANIZATION 1995-2005/ORGANIZATION 2005-2015/DURATION Figure/O 2/NUMBER :/O Labor/ORGANIZATION Productivity/ORGANIZATION Growth/ORGANIZATION ,/O G/O -7/NUMBER Countries/O Percent/O ,/O Annual/SET Rate/O Source/O :/O Conference/ORGANIZATION Board/ORGANIZATION ,/O Total/ORGANIZATION Economy/ORGANIZATION Database/ORGANIZATION ;/O CEA/ORGANIZATION calculations/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 11/NUMBER industrialization/O inducing/O many/O Americans/O to/O move/O to/O new/O communities/O where/O they/O could/O acquire/O new/O skills/O and/O put/O their/O time/O to/O new/O uses/O ./O 
Even/O during/O these/O periods/O of/O great/O technological/O change/O ,/O America/LOCATION has/O maintained/O high/O employment/O ./O 
Over/O long/O periods/O ,/O between/O 90/NUMBER and/O 95/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O the/O people/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION who/O want/O a/O job/O at/O a/O given/O point/O in/O t/O ime/O can/O find/O one/NUMBER ,/O and/O the/O unemployment/O rate/O is/O currently/DATE less/O than/O 5/PERCENT percent/PERCENT ./O 
17/NUMBER Historical/O Effects/O of/O Technical/O C/O hange/O Technological/O advances/O have/O historically/O had/O varied/O impacts/O on/O the/O labor/O market/O ./O 
New/O technologies/O may/O substitute/O for/O some/O skills/O while/O complementing/O others/O ,/O and/O these/O trends/O change/O over/O time/O .18/NUMBER At/O times/O ,/O new/O technologies/O have/O raised/O the/O productivity/O and/O increased/O employment/O opportunities/O for/O workers/O with/O little/O education/O ,/O and/O other/O times/O for/O workers/O with/O more/O ./O 
To/O illustrate/O the/O diversity/O o/O f/O potential/O impacts/O and/O provide/O a/O framework/O for/O understanding/O today/DATE ,/O this/O section/O discusses/O historical/O examples/O of/O how/O innovations/O affected/O workers/O in/O different/O ways/O ./O 
The/O 19/NUMBER th/O century/DURATION was/O characterized/O by/O technological/O change/O that/O raised/O the/O productivity/O o/O f/O lower/O -/O skilled/O workers/O and/O reduced/O the/O relative/O productivity/O of/O certain/O higher/O -/O skilled/O workers/O .19/NUMBER This/O kind/O of/O innovation/O has/O been/O called/O unskill/O -/O biased/O technical/O change/O ./O 
Highly/O -/O skilled/O artisans/O who/O controlled/O and/O executed/O full/O production/O processes/O saw/O their/O livelihoods/O threatened/O by/O the/O rise/O of/O mass/O production/O technologies/O that/O used/O assembly/O lines/O with/O interchangeable/O parts/O and/O lower/O -/O skilled/O workers/O ./O 
In/O reaction/O ,/O some/O En/O glish/O textile/O weavers/O participated/O in/O the/O Luddite/O Riots/O of/O the/DATE early/DATE 1800s/DATE by/O destroying/O looms/O and/O machinery/O that/O threatened/O to/O undercut/O their/O highly/O -/O skilled/O ,/O highly/O -/O paid/O jobs/O with/O lower/O -/O wage/O roles/O ./O 
Ultimately/O ,/O the/O protesters/O '/O fears/O came/O true/O ,/O and/O many/O ski/O lled/O crafts/O were/O replaced/O by/O the/O combination/O of/O machines/O and/O lower/O -/O skill/O labor/O ./O 
There/O were/O also/O new/O opportunities/O for/O less/O -/O skilled/O workers/O and/O o/O utput/O per/O hour/DURATION rose/O ./O 
As/O a/O result/O ,/O average/O living/O standards/O could/O rise/O ,/O but/O certain/O high/O -/O skill/O workers/O were/O no/O lo/O nger/O as/O valuable/O in/O the/O market/O ./O 
Technological/O change/O tended/O to/O work/O in/O a/O different/O direction/O throughout/O the/O late/O 20/NUMBER th/O century/DURATION ./O 
The/O advent/O of/O computers/O and/O the/O internet/O raised/O the/O relative/O productivity/O of/O higher/O -/O skilled/O workers/O ,/O an/O example/O of/O skill/O -/O biased/O t/O echnical/O change/O ./O 
Routine/O -/O intensive/O occupations/O that/O focused/O on/O predictable/O ,/O easily/O -/O programmable/O tasks/O --/O such/O as/O switchboard/O operators/O ,/O filing/O clerks/O ,/O travel/O agents/O ,/O and/O assembly/O line/O workers/O --/O have/O been/O particularly/O vulnerable/O to/O replacement/O by/O new/O technologie/O s./O 20/NUMBER Some/O entire/O occupations/O were/O virtually/O eliminated/O and/O demand/O for/O others/O reduced/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O Nir/PERSON Jaimovich/PERSON and/O Henry/PERSON Si/PERSON u/O argue/O that/O the/O decline/O in/O manufacturing/O and/O other/O 17/NUMBER Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statis/ORGANIZATION tics/O ,/O Civilian/O Unemployment/O Rate/O ,/O 1948/DATE -2016/DURATION ./O 
18/NUMBER Daron/PERSON Acemoglu/PERSON and/O David/PERSON Autor/PERSON ,/O ``/O Skills/O ,/O tasks/O and/O technologies/O :/O Implication/O s/O for/O employment/O and/O earnings/O ,/O ''/O 2011/DATE ,/O Handbook/O of/O labor/O economics/O 4/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O :/O 1043/DATE -171/NUMBER ,/O -LRB-/O http://economics.mit.edu/files/5571/O -RRB-/O ./O 
19/NUMBER Daron/PERSON Acemoglu/PERSON ,/O NBER/ORGANIZATION reporter/O article/O ,/O 2002/DATE ;/O David/PERSON Hounshell/PERSON ,/O From/O the/O American/O system/O to/O mass/O production/O ,/O 1800/DATE -1932/DURATION :/O The/O develop/O ment/O of/O manufacturing/O technology/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O Baltimore/LOCATION :/O JHU/O Press/O ,/O 1985/DATE ;/O John/PERSON A./PERSON James/PERSON and/O Jonathan/PERSON S./PERSON Skinner/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O Resolution/O of/O the/O Labor/O -/O Scarcity/O Paradox/O ,/O ''/O The/O Journal/O of/O Economic/O History/O ,/O 45/NUMBER -LRB-/O 3/NUMBER -RRB-/O :/O 513/NUMBER -40/NUMBER ,/O 1985/DATE -LRB-/O http://www.jstor.org/stable/2121/O 750/NUMBER ?/O 
seq/O =/O 1/NUMBER #page_scan_tab_contents/O -RRB-/O ;/O Joel/PERSON Mokyr/PERSON ,/O ``/O Technological/O inertia/O in/O Economic/O History/O ./O ''/O 
The/O Journal/O of/O Economic/O History/O ,/O 52/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2/NUMBER -RRB-/O :/O 325/NUMBER -38/NUMBER ,/O 1992/DATE -LRB-/O http://www.jstor.org/stable/2123111?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents/O -RRB-/O ./O 
20/NUMBER David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON ,/O Frank/PERSON Levy/PERSON ,/O and/O Richard/PERSON J./PERSON Murnane/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O Skill/O Content/O of/O Recent/O Technological/O Change/O :/O An/O Empirical/O Exploration/O ,/O ''/O Quarterly/SET Journal/O of/O Economics/O 118/NUMBER -LRB-/O 4/NUMBER -RRB-/O :/O 1279/DATE -1333/DATE ,/DATE 2003/DATE ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 12/NUMBER routine/O jobs/O is/O largely/O responsible/O for/O recent/O low/O labor/O demand/O for/O less/O educated/O wor/O kers/O ./O 
21/NUMBER Research/O suggests/O that/O technological/O innovation/O over/O this/O period/O increased/O the/O productivity/O of/O those/O engaged/O in/O abstract/O thinking/O ,/O creative/O ability/O ,/O and/O problem/O -/O solving/O skills/O and/O ,/O therefore/O ,/O is/O partially/O responsible/O for/O the/O substantial/O growth/O in/O jo/O bs/O employing/O such/O traits/O ./O 
22/NUMBER Autor/O ,/O Levy/PERSON ,/O and/O Murnane/PERSON find/O that/O about/O 60/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O the/O estimated/O relative/O demand/O shift/O favoring/O college/O -/O educated/O labor/O from/O 1970/DATE to/O 1998/DATE can/O be/O explained/O by/O the/O reduced/O labor/O input/O needed/O for/O routine/O manual/O tasks/O and/O the/O incr/O eased/O labor/O input/O for/O non/O -/O routine/O cognitive/O tasks/O ,/O which/O tended/O to/O be/O more/O concentrated/O in/O higher/O -/O skilled/O occupations/O ./O 
23/NUMBER Given/O that/O college/O -/O educated/O labor/O was/O already/O more/O highly/O compensated/O ,/O shifting/O demand/O towards/O college/O -/O educated/O labor/O and/O raising/O their/O relative/O pay/O contributed/O to/O rising/O income/O inequality/O ./O 
24/NUMBER Like/O these/O past/DATE waves/O of/O technological/O advancements/O ,/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O is/O setting/O off/O labor/O -/O market/O disruption/O and/O adjustment/O ./O 
Economic/O theory/O suggests/O that/O there/O must/O be/O gai/O ns/O from/O innovation/O s/O ,/O or/O they/O would/O not/O be/O adopted/O ./O 
M/O arket/O forces/O alone/O ,/O however/O ,/O will/O not/O ensure/O that/O the/O financial/O benefits/O from/O innovations/O are/O broadly/O shared/O ./O 
Market/O disruptions/O can/O be/O difficult/O to/O navigate/O for/O many/O ./O 
Recent/O empirical/O research/O highlights/O the/O costs/O of/O the/O adjustment/O process/O ./O 
In/O recent/DURATION decades/DURATION ,/O U.S./LOCATION workers/O who/O were/O displaced/O from/O their/O jobs/O --/O due/O to/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O a/O plant/O closing/O or/O a/O company/O moving/O --/O experienced/O substantial/O earnings/O declines/O ./O 
25/NUMBER Autor/O ,/O Dorn/PERSON ,/O and/O Hanson/PERSON find/O that/O negative/O shocks/O to/O local/O economies/O can/O have/O substantial/O negative/O and/O long/O -/O lasting/O effects/O on/O unemployment/O ,/O labor/O force/O participation/O ,/O and/O wages/O ./O 
26/NUMBER Perhaps/O more/O significantly/O ,/O over/O time/O ,/O displaced/O workers/O '/O earnings/O recover/O only/O slowly/O and/O incompletely/O ./O 
Even/O ten/NUMBER or/O more/O year/DURATION s/O later/O ,/O the/O earnings/O of/O these/O workers/O remain/O depressed/O by/O 10/PERCENT percent/PERCENT or/O more/O relative/O to/O their/O previous/O wages/O ./O 
27/NUMBER These/O results/O suggest/O that/O for/O many/O displaced/O workers/O there/O appears/O to/O be/O a/O deterioration/O in/O their/O ability/O either/O to/O match/O their/O current/DATE skills/O to/O ,/O or/O retrain/O for/O ,/O new/O ,/O in/O -/O demand/O jobs/O ./O 
AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O can/O act/O --/O and/O in/O some/O cases/O has/O already/O acted/O --/O as/O a/O shock/O to/O local/O labor/O markets/O that/O can/O initiate/O long/O -/O standing/O disruptions/O ./O 
Without/O some/O form/O of/O transfers/O and/O safety/O net/O ,/O the/O economic/O benefits/O o/O f/O AI/O -/O driven/O 21/NUMBER Nir/PERSON Jaimovich/PERSON and/O Henry/PERSON E./PERSON Siu/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O Trend/O is/O the/O Cycle/O :/O Job/O Polarization/O and/O Jobless/O Recoveries/O ./O ''/O 
NBER/ORGANIZATION Worki/O ng/O Paper/O No/O ./O 
18334/NUMBER ,/O 2012/DATE -LRB-/O http://www.nber.org/papers/w18334.pdf/O -RRB-/O ;/O Kerwin/PERSON Kofi/PERSON Charles/PERSON ,/O Erik/PERSON Hurst/PERSON ,/O and/O Matthew/PERSON J./PERSON Notowidigdo/PERSON ,/O ``/O Housing/O Booms/O ,/O Manufacturing/O Decline/O ,/O and/O Labor/O Ma/O rket/O Outcomes/O ,/O ''/O Working/O Paper/O ,/O 2016/DATE -LRB-/O http://faculty.wcas.northwestern.edu/noto/O //O research/CHN_manuf_decline_housing_booms_mar2016.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
22/NUMBER Lawrence/PERSON F./PERSON Katz/PERSON and/O Kevin/PERSON M./PERSON Murphy/PERSON ,/O ``/O Changes/O in/O Relative/O Wages/O ,/O 1963/DATE -1987/DURATION :/O Supply/O and/O Demand/O Factors/O ,/O ''/O Quarterly/SET Journal/O of/O Economics/O ,/O 107/NUMBER -LRB-/O Feb/DATE -RRB-/O :/O 35/NUMBER -78/NUMBER ,/O 1992/DATE ;/O Daron/PERSON Acemoglu/PERSON ,/O ``/O Technical/O change/O ,/O ine/O quality/O ,/O and/O the/O labor/O market/O ,/O ''/O Journal/O of/O economic/O literature/O 40/NUMBER -LRB-/O 1/NUMBER -RRB-/O :/O 7-72/O ,/O 2002/DATE ;/O Autor/O ,/O Levy/PERSON ,/O and/O Murnane/PERSON 2003/DATE ;/O Jaimovich/PERSON and/O Siu/O 2012/DATE ;/O David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON and/O David/PERSON Dorn/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O Growth/O of/O Low/O -/O Skill/ORGANIZATION Service/ORGANIZATION Jobs/O and/O the/O Polarization/O of/O the/O US/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Market/ORGANIZATION ,/O ''/O Amer/O ican/O Economic/O Review/O 103/NUMBER -LRB-/O 5/NUMBER -RRB-/O :/O 1553/DATE -97/NUMBER ,/O 2013/DATE -LRB-/O http://www.ddorn.net/papers/Autor/O -/O Dorn/PERSON -/O LowSkillServices/O -/O Polarization.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
23/NUMBER Autor/O ,/O Levy/PERSON ,/O and/O Murnane/PERSON ,/O 2003/DATE ./O 
24/NUMBER Katz/PERSON and/O Murphy/PERSON ,/O 1992/DATE ./O 
25/NUMBER Steven/PERSON J./PERSON Davis/PERSON and/O Till/PERSON Von/PERSON Wachter/PERSON ,/O ``/O Recessions/O and/O the/O Costs/O of/O Job/O Los/O s/O ,/O ''/O Brookings/ORGANIZATION Papers/ORGANIZATION on/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Activity/ORGANIZATION ,/O Economic/O Studies/O Program/O ,/O The/O Brookings/O Institution/O ,/O 43/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2/NUMBER -RRB-/O :/O 1-72/O ,/O 2011/DATE -LRB-/O http://www.econ.ucla.edu/workshops/papers/Monetary/Recessions%20and%20the%20Costs%20of%20Job%20Los/O s/PERCENT %/PERCENT 20with/PERCENT %/PERCENT 20Appendix.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
26/NUMBER David/PERSON H/PERSON Autor/PERSON ,/O David/PERSON Dorn/PERSON ,/O and/O Gordon/PERSON H./PERSON Hanson/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O China/LOCATION Syndrome/O :/O Local/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Market/ORGANIZATION Effects/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Import/ORGANIZATION Competition/ORGANIZATION in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O ''/O American/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Review/ORGANIZATION 103/NUMBER -LRB-/O 6/NUMBER -RRB-/O :/O 2121/DATE -68/NUMBER ,/O 2013/DATE -LRB-/O http://gps.ucsd.edu/_files/faculty/hanson/hanson_publication_it_china.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
27/NUMBER Davis/PERSON and/O Von/PERSON Wachter/PERSON ,/O 2011/DATE ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 13/NUMBER automation/O may/O not/O be/O shared/O by/O all/O ,/O and/O some/O workers/O ,/O families/O ,/O and/O communities/O may/O be/O persistently/O negatively/O affected/O ./O 
AI/O and/O the/O Labor/O Market/O :/O The/O N/O ear/O Term/O Today/DATE ,/O it/O may/O be/O challenging/O to/O predict/O exactly/O which/O jobs/O will/O be/O most/O immediately/O affected/O by/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O ./O 
Because/O AI/O is/O not/O a/O single/O technology/O ,/O but/O rather/O a/O collection/O of/O technologies/O that/O are/O applied/O to/O specific/O tasks/O ,/O the/O effects/O of/O AI/O will/O be/O felt/O unevenly/O through/O the/O economy/O ./O 
Some/O work/O tasks/O will/O be/O more/O easily/O automated/O than/O others/O ,/O and/O some/O jobs/O will/O be/O affected/O more/O than/O others/O ./O 
Some/O specific/O predictions/O are/O possible/O based/O on/O the/O current/DATE trajectory/O of/O AI/O technology/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O driving/O jobs/O and/O housecleaning/O jobs/O are/O both/O jobs/O that/O require/O relatively/O less/O education/O to/O perform/O ./O 
Advancements/O in/O computer/O vision/O and/O related/O technolog/O ies/O have/O made/O the/O feasibility/O of/O fully/O automated/O vehicles/O -LRB-/O AVs/O -RRB-/O ,/O which/O do/O not/O require/O a/O human/O driver/O ,/O appear/O more/O likely/O ,/O potentially/O displacing/O some/O workers/O in/O driving/O -/O dominant/O professions/O ./O 
AVs/O rely/O upon/O ,/O among/O other/O things/O ,/O capabilities/O of/O navigating/O complex/O environments/O ,/O analyzing/O dynamic/O surroundings/O ,/O and/O optimization/O ./O 
Seemingly/O similar/O capabilities/O are/O requi/O red/O of/O a/O household/O -/O cleaning/O robot/O ,/O for/O which/O the/O operational/O mandate/O is/O less/O specific/O -LRB-/O i.e./O ``/O clean/O the/O house/O ,/O ''/O as/O opposed/O to/O the/O objective/O of/O navigating/O to/O a/O specific/O destination/O while/O following/O a/O set/O of/O given/O rules/O and/O preserving/O safety/O -RRB-/O ./O 
And/O yet/O the/O tech/O nology/O that/O would/O enable/O a/O robot/O to/O navigate/O and/O clean/O a/O space/O as/O effectively/O as/O a/O human/O counterpart/O appears/O farther/O off/O ./O 
In/O the/O near/O to/O medium/O term/O ,/O at/O least/O ,/O drivers/O will/O probably/O be/O impacted/O more/O by/O automation/O than/O will/O housecleaners/O ./O 
Th/O e/O following/O sect/O ions/O lay/O out/O a/O framework/O for/O more/O general/O predictions/O of/O the/O effect/O of/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O on/O jobs/O ./O 
Continued/O skill/O -/O biased/O technical/O change/O ?/O 
Recent/O research/O suggests/O that/O the/O effects/O of/O AI/O on/O the/O labor/O market/O in/O the/DATE decade/DATE ahead/O will/O continue/O the/O trend/O toward/O skill/O -/O biased/O change/O that/O computerization/O and/O communication/O innovations/O have/O driven/O in/O recent/DURATION decades/DURATION ./O 
Researchers/O differ/O on/O the/O possible/O magnitude/O of/O this/O effect/O ./O 
Carl/PERSON Frey/PERSON and/O Michael/PERSON Osbourne/PERSON asked/O a/O panel/O of/O experts/O on/O AI/O to/O classify/O occupations/O by/O how/O likely/O it/O is/O that/O foreseeable/O AI/O technologies/O could/O feasibly/O replace/O them/O over/O roughly/O the/DATE next/DATE decade/DATE or/O two/NUMBER .28/NUMBER Based/O on/O this/O assessment/O of/O the/O technical/O properties/O of/O AI/O ,/O the/O relationship/O between/O those/O properties/O to/O existing/O occupations/O ,/O and/O employment/O levels/O across/O occupations/O ,/O they/O posit/O that/O 47/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O U.S./LOCATION jobs/O are/O at/O risk/O of/O being/O replaced/O by/O AI/O technologies/O and/O computerization/O in/O this/O period/O ./O 
29/NUMBER Many/O occupations/O are/O likely/O to/O change/O as/O some/O of/O their/O associated/O tasks/O become/O automatable/O ,/O so/O the/O OECD/ORGANIZATION analysis/O 28/NUMBER Carl/PERSON Frey/PERSON and/O Michael/PERSON Osborne/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Employment/O :/O How/O Susceptible/O are/O Jobs/O to/O Computerization/O ,/O ''/O Oxford/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2013/DATE -LRB-/O http://www.oxfordmartin.ox.ac.uk/downloads/academic/The_Future_of_Employment.pdf/O -RRB-/O ./O 
29/NUMBER Melanie/PERSON Ar/PERSON ntz/PERSON ,/O Terry/PERSON Gregory/PERSON ,/O and/O Ulrich/PERSON Zierahn/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O Risk/O of/O Automation/O for/O Jobs/O in/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Countries/O :/O A/O Comparative/O Analysis/O ,/O ''/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Social/O ,/O Employment/O and/O Migration/O Working/O Papers/O No/O ./O 
189/NUMBER ,/O 2016/DATE -LRB-/O http://www.oecd/O -ilibrary.org/docserver/download/5jlz9h56dvq7/O -/O en.pdf?exp/O ires/O =/O 1480994298/NUMBER &/O id/O =/O id/O &/O accname/O =/O guest/O &/O checksum/O =/O 6DC4B241A91EE860DC391585FF43C51C/O -RRB-/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 14/NUMBER concludes/O that/O relatively/O few/O will/O be/O entirely/O automated/O away/O ,/O estimating/O that/O only/O 9/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O jobs/O are/O at/O risk/O of/O being/O completely/O displaced/O ./O 
If/O these/O estimates/O of/O threatened/O jobs/O translate/O into/O job/O displacement/O ,/O millions/O of/O Americans/O will/O have/O their/O livelihoods/O significantly/O altered/O and/O potentially/O face/O considerable/O economic/O challenges/O in/O the/O short/O -/O and/O medium/O -/O term/O ./O 
In/O addition/O to/O understanding/O the/O magnitude/O of/O the/O overall/O employment/O effects/O ,/O it/O is/O also/O important/O to/O understand/O the/O distributional/O implications/O ./O 
CEA/ORGANIZATION ranked/O occupations/O by/O wages/O and/O found/O that/O ,/O according/O to/O the/O Frey/PERSON and/O Osbourne/PERSON analysis/O ,/O 83/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O jobs/O making/O less/O than/O $/MONEY 20/MONEY per/O hour/DURATION would/O come/O und/O er/O pressure/O from/O automation/O ,/O as/O compared/O to/O 31/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O jobs/O making/O between/O $/MONEY 20/MONEY and/O $/MONEY 40/MONEY per/O hour/DURATION and/O 4/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O jobs/O making/O above/O $/MONEY 40/MONEY per/O hour/DURATION -LRB-/O Figure/O 3a/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O the/O OECD/ORGANIZATION study/O estimates/O that/O less/O -/O educated/O workers/O are/O more/O likely/O to/O be/O replaced/O by/O automation/O than/O highly/O -/O educated/O ones/O -LRB-/O Figure/O 3b/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O the/O OECD/ORGANIZATION study/O 's/O authors/O estimate/O that/O 4/PERCENT 4/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O American/O workers/O with/O less/O than/O a/O high/O school/O degree/O hold/O jobs/O made/O up/O of/O highly/O -/O automatable/O tasks/O while/O 1/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O people/O with/O a/O bachelor/O 's/O degree/O or/O higher/O hold/O such/O a/O job/O ./O 
To/O the/O degree/O that/O education/O and/O wages/O are/O correlated/O with/O skills/O ,/O this/O implies/O a/O large/O decline/O in/O demand/O for/O lower/O -/O skilled/O workers/O and/O little/O decline/O in/O demand/O for/O higher/O -/O skilled/O workers/O ./O 
These/O estimates/O suggest/O a/O contin/O uation/O of/O skill/O -/O biased/O technical/O change/O in/O the/O near/O term/O ./O 
Nevertheless/O ,/O humans/O still/O maintain/O a/O comparative/O advantage/O over/O AI/O and/O robotics/O in/O many/O areas/O ./O 
While/O AI/O detects/O patterns/O and/O create/O s/O predictions/O ,/O it/O still/O can/O not/O replicate/O social/O or/O general/O intelli/O gence/O ,/O creativity/O ,/O or/O human/O judgment/O ./O 
Of/O course/O ,/O many/O of/O the/O occupations/O that/O use/O these/O types/O of/O skills/O are/O high/O -/O skilled/O occupations/O ,/O and/O likely/O require/O higher/O levels/O of/O education/O ./O 
Further/O ,/O given/O the/O current/DATE dexterity/O limits/O of/O the/O robotics/O that/O would/O be/O n/O eeded/O to/O implement/O mass/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O ,/O occupations/O that/O require/O manual/O dexterity/O will/O also/O likely/O remain/O in/O demand/O in/O the/O near/O term/O ./O 
83/NUMBER 31/NUMBER 4/DATE 0/DATE 10/DATE 20/DATE 30/DATE 40/DATE 50/DATE 60/DATE 70/DATE 80/DATE 90/DATE 100/NUMBER Less/O than/O 20/MONEY Dollars/MONEY 20/NUMBER to/O 40/MONEY Dollars/MONEY More/O than/O 40/MONEY Dollars/MONEY Figure/O 3a/O :/O Share/O of/O Jobs/O with/O High/ORGANIZATION Probability/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Automation/ORGANIZATION ,/O by/O Occupation/ORGANIZATION 's/ORGANIZATION Median/ORGANIZATION Hourly/ORGANIZATION Wage/ORGANIZATION Median/ORGANIZATION Probability/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Automation/ORGANIZATION ,/O Percent/ORGANIZATION Median/ORGANIZATION Hourly/ORGANIZATION Wage/ORGANIZATION in/U_TEMPPRED 2010/DATE Source/O :/O Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION ;/O Frey/PERSON and/O Osborne/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ;/O CEA/ORGANIZATION calculations/O ./O 
44/NUMBER 19/DATE 8/DATE 6/DATE 1/DATE 0/DATE 0/DATE 5/DATE 10/DATE 15/DATE 20/DATE 25/DATE 30/DATE 35/DATE 40/DATE 45/DATE 50/DATE Less/O than/O High/ORGANIZATION School/ORGANIZATION High/ORGANIZATION School/ORGANIZATION Degree/ORGANIZATION or/ORGANIZATION Equivalent/ORGANIZATION Trade/ORGANIZATION School/ORGANIZATION Certificate/ORGANIZATION Associates/ORGANIZATION Degree/ORGANIZATION Bachelors/ORGANIZATION Degree/ORGANIZATION Graduate/ORGANIZATION Degree/ORGANIZATION Figure/ORGANIZATION 3b/O :/O Share/O of/O Jobs/O with/O Highly/ORGANIZATION Automatable/ORGANIZATION Skills/ORGANIZATION ,/O by/O Education/ORGANIZATION Percent/ORGANIZATION Source/ORGANIZATION :/O Arntz/PERSON ,/O Gregory/PERSON ,/O and/O Zierahn/PERSON -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O calculations/O based/O on/O the/O PIAAC/O 2012/DATE ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 15/NUMBER Box/O 1/NUMBER :/O Automated/O Vehicle/O Case/O Study/O A/O helpful/O case/O in/O understanding/O the/O types/O of/O effects/O AI/O may/O have/O on/O productivity/O and/O labor/O demand/O is/O the/O development/O of/O automat/O ed/O vehicles/O -LRB-/O AVs/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Like/O other/O forms/O of/O technological/O disruption/O ,/O AV/O technology/O will/O likely/O cause/O disruptions/O in/O the/O labor/O market/O as/O the/O economy/O adapts/O to/O new/O paradigms/O ./O 
CEA/ORGANIZATION estimates/O that/O 2.2/NUMBER to/O 3/NUMBER .1/NUMBER million/NUMBER existing/O part/O -/O and/O full/O -/O time/O U.S./LOCATION jobs/O may/O be/O threatened/O or/O substantially/O altered/O by/O AV/O technology/O ./O 
Importantly/O ,/O this/O is/O not/O a/O net/O calculation/O --/O it/O does/O not/O include/O the/O types/O of/O new/O jobs/O that/O may/O be/O developed/O --/O but/O rather/O a/O tally/O of/O currently/DATE held/O jobs/O that/O are/O likely/O to/O be/O affected/O by/O AI/O -/O enabled/O AV/O technology/O ./O 
A/DURATION second/DURATION caveat/O is/O that/O these/O changes/O may/O take/O years/DURATION or/O decades/DURATION to/O occur/O because/O there/O will/O be/O a/O further/O lag/O between/O technological/O possibility/O and/O widespread/O adoption/O ./O 
This/O estimate/O of/O the/O number/O of/O current/DATE jobs/O likely/O displaced/O or/O substantially/O altered/O by/O AVs/O starts/O by/O identifying/O occupations/O that/O involve/O substantial/O driving/O and/O relatively/O few/O other/O responsibilities/O to/O lead/O and/O coordinate/O others/O ,/O drawing/O occupation/O descriptions/O from/O the/O Bur/ORGANIZATION eau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O BLS/O -RRB-/O and/O the/O Occupational/O Information/O Network/O -LRB-/O O/O */O NET/O -RRB-/O ./O 
For/O each/O of/O these/O occupations/O ,/O an/O analysis/O of/O what/O non/O -/O driving/O tasks/O the/O occupation/O also/O requires/O yields/O an/O estimate/O of/O the/O share/O of/O jobs/O that/O will/O be/O displaced/O :/O driving/O jobs/O t/O hat/O also/O involve/O less/O -/O automatable/O tasks/O have/O a/O lower/O chance/O of/O disappearing/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O the/O job/O of/O school/O -/O bus/O driver/O mixes/O both/O the/O tasks/O of/O driving/O and/O of/O attending/O to/O children/O ./O 
This/O job/O will/O not/O disappear/O ,/O though/O it/O may/O evolve/O to/O focus/O heavily/O on/O the/O t/O ask/O of/O attending/O to/O children/O ./O 
As/O a/O result/O ,/O AV/O technology/O may/O replace/O only/O a/O modest/O share/O of/O school/O -/O bus/O driver/O jobs/O ,/O but/O child/O care/O workers/O will/O still/O be/O required/O ./O 
On/O the/O other/O hand/O ,/O non/O -/O driving/O tasks/O are/O less/O important/O in/O inter/O -/O city/O bus/O driver/O jobs/O ,/O and/O AV/O technology/O will/O likely/O replace/O a/O large/O share/O of/O these/O jobs/O ./O 
Many/O jobs/O involve/O limited/O amounts/O of/O driving/O ./O 
These/O jobs/O are/O not/O included/O in/O the/O analysis/O below/O as/O individuals/O in/O these/O occupations/O would/O likely/O see/O a/O productivity/O boost/O ,/O not/O a/O threat/O of/O displac/O ement/O ,/O as/O their/O time/O allocated/O to/O driving/O is/O freed/O up/O to/O focus/O on/O other/O critical/O tasks/O ./O 
In/O addition/O to/O occupations/O identified/O from/O BLS/ORGANIZATION and/O O/O */O NET/O ,/O CEA/ORGANIZATION 's/O estimate/O of/O jobs/O threatened/O or/O likely/O to/O be/O substantially/O altered/O by/O AVs/O also/O includes/O approximately/O 36/NUMBER 4,000/NUMBER self/O -/O employed/O individuals/O driving/O either/O part/O -/O or/O full/O -/O time/O with/O ride/O -/O sharing/O services/O as/O of/O May/DATE 2015/DATE that/O may/O find/O AV/O technology/O substituting/O for/O their/O services/O ./O 
Table/O 1/NUMBER ,/O below/O ,/O presents/O the/O identified/O occupation/O categories/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 16/NUMBER 30/NUMBER Calculations/O based/O on/O Hall/PERSON and/O Krueger/PERSON ,/O 2016/DATE ,/O -LRB-/O http://www.nber.org/papers/w22843.pdf/O -RRB-/O ,/O who/O note/O the/O number/O of/O active/O driver/O -/O partners/O for/O Uber/O more/O than/O doubled/O every/O six/NUMBER mont/O hs/O in/O the/O period/O 2012/DATE -2014/DURATION ,/O and/O expect/O this/O growth/O rate/O to/O continue/O into/O 2015/DATE ./O 
CEA/ORGANIZATION uses/O data/O from/O Harris/PERSON and/O Krueger/PERSON -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O -LRB-/O http://www.hamiltonproject.org/assets/files/modernizing_labor_laws_for_twenty_first_century_work_krueger_harr/O is.pdf/O -RRB-/O for/O only/O Uber/O and/O Lyft/O ./O 
Extrapolating/O to/O May/DATE 2015/DATE with/O Hall/PERSON and/O Krueger/PERSON 's/O method/O ,/O CEA/ORGANIZATION calculates/O approximately/O 324,000/NUMBER individuals/O were/O active/O driver/O -/O partners/O with/O Uber/ORGANIZATION in/O May/DATE 2015/DATE ./O 
31/NUMBER Mean/O hourly/SET earnings/O reported/O in/O Hall/LOCATION and/O Krueger/PERSON -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Table/O 1/NUMBER Occupation/ORGANIZATION BLS/ORGANIZATION Code/O #/O Total/O Jobs/O -LRB-/O BLS/O ,/O May/DATE 2015/DATE -RRB-/O Mean/O Hourly/SET Wage/O O/O */O NET/O Occupation/O Description/O Bus/O Drivers/O ,/O Transit/O and/O Intercity/O 53/NUMBER -3021/NUMBER 168,620/NUMBER $/MONEY 19.31/MONEY Drive/O bus/O or/O motor/O coach/O ,/O including/O regular/O route/O operations/O ,/O charters/O ,/O and/O private/O carriage/O ./O 
May/O assist/O passengers/O with/O baggage/O ./O 
May/O collect/O fares/O or/O tickets/O ./O 
Light/O Truck/O or/O Delivery/ORGANIZATION Services/ORGANIZATION Drivers/ORGANIZATION 53/NUMBER -3033/NUMBER 826,510/NUMBER $/MONEY 16.38/MONEY Drive/O a/O light/O vehicle/O ,/O such/O as/O a/O truck/O or/O van/O ,/O with/O a/O capacity/O of/O less/O than/O 26,000/MONEY pounds/MONEY Gross/O Vehicle/O Weight/O -LRB-/O GVW/O -RRB-/O ,/O primarily/O to/O deliv/O er/O or/O pick/O up/O merchandise/O or/O to/O deliver/O packages/O ./O 
May/O load/O and/O unload/O vehicle/O ./O 
Heavy/O and/O Tractor/O -/O Trailer/O Truck/O Drivers/O 53/NUMBER -3032/NUMBER 1,678,280/NUMBER $/MONEY 20.43/MONEY Drive/O a/O tractor/O -/O trailer/O combination/O or/O a/O truck/O with/O a/O capacity/O of/O at/O least/O 26,000/MONEY pounds/MONEY Gross/O Vehicle/O Weight/O -LRB-/O GVW/O -RRB-/O ./O 
May/O be/O required/O to/O unload/O truck/O ./O 
Requires/O commercial/O drivers/O '/O license/O ./O 
Bus/O Drivers/O ,/O School/O or/O Special/O Client/O 53/NUMBER -3022/NUMBER 505,560/NUMBER $/MONEY 14.70/MONEY Transport/O students/O or/O special/O clients/O ,/O such/O as/O the/O elderly/O or/O persons/O with/O disabilities/O ./O 
Ensure/O adherence/O to/O safety/O rules/O ./O 
May/O assist/O passengers/O in/O boarding/O or/O exiting/O ./O 
Taxi/O Drivers/O and/O Chauffeurs/O 53/NUMBER -3041/NUMBER 180,960/NUMBER $/MONEY 12.53/MONEY Drive/O automobiles/O ,/O vans/O ,/O or/O limousines/O to/O transport/O passengers/O ./O 
May/O occasionally/O carry/O cargo/O ./O 
Includes/O hearse/O drivers/O ./O 
Self/O -/O employed/O Drivers/O N/A/O 364,000/NUMBER 30/NUMBER $/MONEY 19.35/MONEY 31/MONEY N/A/O As/O the/O above/O occupations/O involve/O other/O ,/O critical/O non/O -/O driving/O tasks/O to/O varying/O degrees/O ,/O Table/O 2/NUMBER ,/O below/O ,/O presents/O a/O weighted/O estimate/O of/O jobs/O threatened/O or/O substantially/O altered/O by/O AV/O technology/O in/O each/O occupation/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O a/O weight/O of/O 0.60/NUMBER indicates/O that/O approximately/O 60/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O jobs/O in/O an/O occupation/O are/O threatened/O ./O 
These/O weights/O are/O generated/O by/O CEA/ORGANIZATION using/O ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 17/NUMBER detailed/O job/O descriptions/O ,/O case/O studies/O ,/O and/O surveys/O of/O existing/O and/O planned/O technologies/O for/O each/O occupation/O ./O 
Table/O 2/NUMBER Occupation/ORGANIZATION #/ORGANIZATION Total/ORGANIZATION Jobs/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O BLS/O ,/O May/DATE 2015/DATE -RRB-/O Range/O of/O Replacement/O Weights/O Range/O of/O #/O Jobs/O Threatened/O Bus/O Drivers/O ,/O Transit/O and/O Intercity/O 168,620/NUMBER 0.60/NUMBER --/O 1.0/NUMBER 101,170/NUMBER --/O 168,620/NUMBER Light/O Truck/O or/O Delivery/O Services/O Drivers/O 826,510/NUMBER 0.20/NUMBER --/O 0.60/NUMBER 165,300/NUMBER --/O 495,910/NUMBER Heavy/O and/O Tractor/O -/O Trailer/O Truck/O Drivers/O 1,678,280/NUMBER 0.80/NUMBER --/O 1.0/NUMBER 1,342,620/NUMBER --/O 1,678,280/NUMBER Bu/O s/O Drivers/O ,/O School/O or/O Special/O Client/O 505,560/NUMBER 0.30/NUMBER --/O 0.40/NUMBER 151,670/NUMBER --/O 202,220/NUMBER Taxi/O Drivers/O and/O Chauffeurs/O 180,960/NUMBER 0.60/NUMBER --/O 1.0/NUMBER 108,580/NUMBER --/O 180,960/NUMBER Self/O -/O employed/O drivers/O 364,000/NUMBER 0.90/NUMBER --/O 1.0/NUMBER 328,000/NUMBER --/O 364,000/NUMBER TOTAL/O JOBS/O 3,723,930/NUMBER 2,196,940/NUMBER --/O 3,089,990/NUMBER AV/O technology/O could/O enable/O some/O workers/O to/O focus/O time/O on/O other/O job/O responsibilities/O ,/O boosting/O their/O productivity/O ,/O and/O actually/O fostering/O wage/O growth/O among/O those/O still/O holding/O the/O reshaped/O jobs/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O salespeople/O who/O currently/DATE spend/O a/O considerable/O amount/O of/O ti/O me/O driving/O could/O find/O themselves/O able/O to/O do/O other/O work/O while/O a/O car/O drives/O them/O from/O place/O to/O place/O ,/O or/O inspectors/O and/O appraisers/O could/O fill/O out/O paperwork/O while/O their/O car/O drives/O itself/O ./O 
This/O should/O make/O these/O workers/O more/O productive/O ,/O with/O AV/O technology/O serving/O as/O a/O complement/O ,/O not/O a/O substi/O tute/O ./O 
New/O jobs/O will/O also/O likely/O be/O created/O ,/O both/O in/O existing/O occupations/O --/O cheaper/O transportation/O costs/O will/O lower/O prices/O and/O increase/O demand/O for/O goods/O and/O all/O the/O related/O occupations/O such/O as/O service/O and/O fulfillment/O --/O and/O in/O new/O occupations/O not/O currently/DATE foreseeable/O ./O 
Conversely/O ,/O even/O occupations/O that/O have/O little/O connection/O to/O driving/O and/O divorced/O from/O the/O threat/O of/O automation/O could/O face/O pressure/O on/O wages/O due/O to/O an/O increased/O supply/O of/O similar/O ,/O dis/O placed/O workers/O ./O 
In/O cases/O where/O downward/O pressure/O on/O wages/O or/O consolidation/O result/O in/O displacement/O of/O workers/O ,/O private/O -/O sector/O solutions/O and/O public/O policy/O should/O aim/O to/O ensure/O smooth/O and/O quick/O transitions/O to/O new/O opportunities/O for/O these/O workers/O ./O 
CEA/ORGANIZATION analysis/O finds/O that/O a/O share/O of/O workers/O in/O a/O few/O isolated/O occupations/O --/O truck/O drivers/O and/O delivery/O service/O drivers/O ,/O in/O particular/O --/O currently/DATE enjoy/O a/O wage/O premium/O over/O others/O in/O the/O labor/O market/O with/O the/O same/O level/O of/O educational/O attainment/O ./O 
They/O may/O not/O be/O able/O to/O reg/O ain/O this/O wage/O premium/O if/O displace/O d/O ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 18/NUMBER What/O kind/O of/O jobs/O will/O AI/O create/O ?/O 
Predicting/O future/DATE job/O growth/O is/O extremely/O difficult/O ,/O as/O it/O depends/O on/O technologies/O that/O do/O not/O exist/O today/DATE and/O the/O multiple/O ways/O they/O may/O complement/O or/O substitute/O for/O existing/O human/O skills/O and/O jobs/O ./O 
To/O form/O an/O intelligent/O guess/O about/O what/O these/O jobs/O might/O be/O like/O ,/O CEA/ORGANIZATION has/O synthesized/O and/O extended/O existing/O r/O esearch/O on/O jobs/O that/O would/O be/O directly/O created/O by/O AI/O ./O 
It/O is/O important/O to/O understand/O ,/O however/O ,/O that/O AI/O will/O also/O lead/O to/O substantial/O indirect/O job/O creation/O --/O to/O the/O degree/O it/O raises/O productivity/O and/O wages/O it/O may/O also/O lead/O to/O higher/O consumption/O that/O would/O suppo/O rt/O additional/O jobs/O across/O the/O economy/O in/O everything/O from/O high/O -/O end/O craft/O production/O to/O restaurants/O and/O retail/O ./O 
CEA/ORGANIZATION has/O identified/O four/NUMBER categories/O of/O jobs/O that/O might/O experience/O direct/O AI/O -/O driven/O growth/O in/O the/DATE future/DATE ./O 
Employment/O in/O areas/O where/O humans/O engage/O wi/O th/O existing/O AI/O technologies/O ,/O develop/O new/O AI/O technologies/O ,/O supervise/O AI/O technologies/O in/O practice/O ,/O and/O facilitat/O e/O societal/O shifts/O that/O accompany/O new/O AI/O technologies/O will/O likely/O grow/O ./O 
Current/DATE limits/O on/O manual/O dexterity/O of/O robots/O and/O constraints/O on/O generative/O intelligence/O and/O creativity/O of/O AI/O technologies/O likely/O mean/O that/O employment/O requiring/O manual/O dexterity/O ,/O creativ/O ity/O ,/O social/O interactions/O and/O intelligence/O ,/O and/O general/O knowledge/O will/O thrive/O ./O 
Below/O are/O descriptions/O and/O potential/O examples/O of/O future/DATE employment/O for/O each/O category/O ./O 
Engagement/O ./O 
Humans/O will/O likely/O be/O needed/O to/O actively/O engage/O with/O AI/O technologies/O throughout/O the/O process/O of/O completing/O a/O task/O ./O 
Many/O industry/O professionals/O refer/O to/O a/O large/O swath/O of/O AI/O technologies/O as/O ``/O Augmented/O Intelligence/O ,/O ''/O stressing/O the/O technology/O 's/O role/O as/O assisting/O and/O expanding/O the/O productivity/O of/O individuals/O rather/O than/O replacing/O human/O wor/O k./O Thus/O ,/O based/O on/O the/O biased/O -/O technical/O change/O framework/O ,/O demand/O for/O labor/O will/O likely/O increase/O the/O most/O in/O the/O areas/O where/O humans/O complement/O AI/O -/O automation/O technologies/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O AI/O technology/O such/O as/O IBM/ORGANIZATION 's/O Watson/PERSON may/O improve/O early/O detection/O of/O some/O can/O cers/O or/O other/O illnesses/O ,/O but/O a/O human/O healthcare/O professional/O is/O needed/O to/O work/O with/O patients/O to/O understand/O and/O translate/O patients/O '/O symptoms/O ,/O inform/O patients/O of/O treatment/O options/O ,/O and/O guide/O patients/O through/O treatment/O plans/O ./O 
Shipping/O companies/O may/O also/O partn/O er/O workers/O who/O pickup/O and/O deliver/O goods/O over/O the/O last/O 100/NUMBER feet/O with/O AI/O -/O enabled/O autonomous/O vehicles/O that/O move/O workers/O efficiently/O from/O site/O to/O site/O ./O 
In/O such/O cases/O ,/O AI/O augments/O what/O a/O human/O is/O able/O to/O do/O and/O allows/O individuals/O to/O either/O be/O more/O effective/O in/O their/O specialty/O task/O or/O to/O operate/O on/O a/O larger/O scale/O ./O 
Development/O ./O 
In/O the/O initial/O stages/O of/O AI/O ,/O development/O jobs/O are/O crucial/O and/O span/O multiple/O industries/O and/O skill/O levels/O ./O 
Most/O intuitively/O ,/O there/O may/O be/O a/O great/O need/O for/O highly/O -/O skilled/O software/O developers/O a/O nd/O engineers/O to/O put/O these/O capacities/O into/O practical/O use/O in/O the/O world/O ./O 
To/O a/O certain/O extent/O ,/O however/O ,/O AI/O is/O only/O as/O good/O as/O the/O data/O behind/O it/O ,/O so/O there/O will/O likely/O be/O increased/O demand/O for/O jobs/O in/O generating/O ,/O collecting/O ,/O and/O managing/O relevant/O data/O to/O feed/O i/O nto/O AI/O training/O without/O intervention/O to/O help/O them/O re/O -/O skill/O ./O 
Job/O search/O assistance/O ,/O education/O ,/O training/O and/O apprenticeships/O to/O build/O and/O certify/O new/O skills/O ,/O and/O wage/O insurance/O could/O provide/O valuable/O support/O to/O them/O as/O they/O transition/O to/O f/O inding/O new/O jobs/O ./O 
Policy/O responses/O to/O these/O challenges/O are/O discussed/O later/O in/O this/O report/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 19/NUMBER processes/O ./O 
Applications/O of/O AI/O can/O range/O from/O high/O -/O skill/O tasks/O such/O as/O recognizing/O cancer/O in/O x/O -/O ray/O images/O to/O lower/O -/O skill/O tasks/O such/O as/O recognizing/O text/O in/O images/O ./O 
Finally/O ,/O to/O an/O increasing/O degree/O ,/O development/O may/O include/O those/O specializing/O i/O n/O the/O liberal/O arts/O and/O social/O sciences/O ,/O such/O as/O philosophers/O with/O frameworks/O for/O ethical/O evaluations/O and/O sociologists/O investigating/O the/O impact/O of/O technology/O on/O specific/O populations/O ,/O who/O can/O give/O input/O as/O the/O new/O technologies/O grapple/O with/O more/O social/O comple/O xities/O and/O moral/O dilemmas/O ./O 
Supervision/O ./O 
This/O category/O encompasses/O all/O roles/O related/O to/O the/O monitoring/O ,/O licensing/O ,/O and/O repair/O of/O AI/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O after/O the/O auto/O mated/O vehicle/O development/O phase/O ,/O the/O need/O for/O human/O registration/O and/O testing/O of/O such/O technology/O to/O ensure/O safety/O and/O quality/O control/O on/O the/O roads/O will/O still/O likely/O exist/O ./O 
As/O a/O widespread/O new/O technology/O ,/O AV/O will/O require/O regular/O repair/O and/O maintenance/O ,/O which/O may/O expand/O mechanic/O and/O technician/O jobs/O in/O this/O space/O as/O well/O ./O 
Real/O -/O time/O supervision/O will/O also/O be/O required/O in/O exceptional/O ,/O marginal/O ,/O or/O high/O -/O stakes/O cases/O ,/O especially/O those/O involving/O morality/O ,/O ethics/O ,/O and/O social/O intelligence/O that/O AI/O may/O lack/O ./O 
This/O might/O take/O the/O form/O of/O quality/O control/O of/O recommendations/O made/O by/O AI/O or/O online/O moderation/O when/O sensitive/O subjects/O are/O discussed/O ./O 
The/O capacity/O for/O AI/O -/O enabled/O machines/O to/O learn/O is/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O most/O exciting/O aspects/O of/O the/O technology/O ,/O but/O it/O may/O also/O require/O supervision/O to/O ensure/O that/O AI/O does/O not/O diverge/O from/O originally/O intended/O uses/O ./O 
As/O machines/O get/O smarter/O and/O have/O improved/O ability/O to/O make/O practical/O predictions/O about/O the/O environment/O ,/O the/O value/O of/O human/O judgement/O will/O increase/O because/O it/O will/O be/O the/O preferred/O way/O to/O resolve/O competing/O priorities/O ./O 
32/NUMBER Response/O to/O Paradigm/ORGANIZATION Shifts/ORGANIZATION ./O 
The/O technological/O innovation/O surround/O ing/O AI/O will/O likely/O reshape/O features/O of/O built/O environment/O ./O 
In/O the/O case/O of/O AVs/O ,/O dramatic/O shifts/O in/O the/O design/O of/O infrastructure/O and/O traffic/O laws/O --/O which/O are/O currently/DATE built/O with/O the/O safety/O and/O convenience/O of/O human/O drivers/O in/O mind/O --/O may/O be/O needed/O ./O 
The/O advent/O of/O s/O elf/O -/O driving/O cars/O may/O result/O in/O higher/O demand/O for/O urban/O planners/O and/O designers/O to/O create/O a/O new/O blueprint/O for/O the/O way/O the/O everyday/O travel/O landscape/O is/O built/O and/O used/O ./O 
Paradigm/O shifts/O in/O adjacent/O fields/O such/O as/O cybersecurity/O --/O demanding/O ,/O for/O instance/O ,/O new/O metho/O ds/O of/O detecting/O fraudulent/O transactions/O and/O messages/O --/O may/O also/O necessitate/O new/O occupations/O and/O more/O employment/O ./O 
32Ajay/O Agrawal/O ,/O Joshua/PERSON Gans/PERSON ,/O and/O Avi/PERSON Goldfarb/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O Simple/O Economics/O of/O Machine/O Intelligence/O ,/O ''/O Harvard/ORGANIZATION Business/ORGANIZATION Review/ORGANIZATION ,/O November/DATE 17/DATE ,/DATE 2016/DATE -LRB-/O https://hbr.org/2016/11/the/O -/O simple/O -/O economics/O -/O of-machine/O -/O intelligence/O -RRB-/O ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 20/NUMBER Box/O 2/NUMBER :/O The/O End/O of/O Work/O ?/O 
In/O addition/O to/O the/O arguments/O that/O AI/O and/O future/DATE technologies/O will/O broadly/O follow/O the/O same/O path/O as/O past/DATE technological/O revolutions/O ,/O others/O make/O a/O more/O radical/O argument/O about/O the/O possible/O longer/O -/O run/O effects/O ./O 
They/O posit/O that/O AI/O could/O prove/O different/O from/O previous/O technological/O change/O because/O it/O has/O the/O ability/O to/O replicate/O something/O previously/DATE exclusive/O to/O humans/O :/O intelligen/O ce/O ./O 
There/O have/O long/O been/O fears/O that/O technology/O --/O the/O machines/O ,/O the/O assembly/O lines/O ,/O or/O the/O robots/O --/O would/O replace/O all/O human/O labor/O ,/O but/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O has/O unique/O features/O that/O may/O allow/O it/O to/O replace/O substantial/O amounts/O of/O routine/O cognitive/O tasks/O in/O which/O humans/O previously/DATE maintained/O a/O stark/O comparative/O advantage/O ./O 
Initial/O waves/O of/O technology/O ,/O such/O as/O the/O wheel/O and/O lever/O ,/O allowed/O humans/O to/O do/O more/O by/O replacing/O or/O augmenting/O physical/O strength/O ./O 
Other/O processes/O allowed/O work/O to/O take/O place/O faster/O or/O more/O efficien/O tly/O in/O a/O factory/O ./O 
Computers/O allowed/O calculations/O or/O pattern/O recognition/O to/O take/O place/O faster/O and/O augment/O humans/O '/O capacity/O to/O think/O or/O reason/O ./O 
AI/O ,/O though/O ,/O may/O allow/O machines/O to/O operate/O without/O humans/O to/O such/O a/O degree/O that/O they/O fundamentally/O change/O the/O natu/O re/O of/O production/O and/O work/O ./O 
33/NUMBER It/O may/O be/O that/O the/O question/O is/O no/O longer/O which/O segment/O of/O the/O population/O will/O technology/O complement/O ,/O but/O whether/O the/O new/O technology/O will/O complement/O many/O humans/O at/O all/O ,/O or/O if/O AI/O will/O substitute/O completely/O for/O much/O of/O human/O work/O ./O 
The/O skills/O in/O which/O humans/O have/O maintained/O a/O comparative/O advantage/O are/O likely/O to/O erode/O over/O time/O as/O AI/O and/O new/O technologies/O become/O more/O sophisticated/O ./O 
Some/O of/O this/O is/O evident/O today/DATE as/O AI/O becomes/O more/O capable/O at/O tasks/O such/O as/O language/O processing/O ,/O translatio/O n/O ,/O basic/O writing/O ,/O or/O even/O music/O composition/O ./O 
AI/O -/O driven/O technological/O change/O could/O lead/O to/O even/O larger/O disparities/O in/O income/O between/O capital/O owners/O and/O labor/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION argue/O that/O current/DATE trends/O in/O the/O labor/O market/O ,/O such/O as/O decli/O ning/O wages/O in/O the/O face/O of/O rising/O productivity/O ,/O are/O indicative/O of/O a/O more/O drastic/O change/O in/O the/O distribution/O of/O economic/O benefits/O to/O come/O ./O 
Rather/O than/O everyone/O receiving/O at/O least/O some/O of/O the/O benefit/O ,/O the/O vast/O majority/O of/O that/O value/O will/O go/O to/O a/O very/O small/O po/O rtion/O of/O the/O population/O :/O ``/O superstar/O -/O biased/O technological/O change/O ./O ''/O 
Superstar/O -/O biased/O technological/O change/O is/O somewhat/O similar/O to/O skill/O -/O biased/O technological/O change/O ,/O but/O the/O benefits/O of/O technology/O accrue/O to/O an/O even/O smaller/O portion/O of/O society/O than/O just/O the/O high/O ly-skilled/O workers/O ./O 
The/O winner/O -/O take/O -/O most/O and/O winner/O -/O take/O -/O all/O nature/O of/O the/O information/O technology/O market/O means/O that/O the/O fortunate/O few/O are/O likely/O to/O emerge/O as/O victors/O of/O the/O market/O ./O 
This/O would/O exacerbate/O the/O current/DATE trend/O in/O the/O rising/O fraction/O of/O total/O inc/O ome/O going/O to/O the/O top/O 0.01/PERCENT percent/PERCENT -LRB-/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
33/NUMBER Erik/PERSON Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O Andrew/PERSON McAfee/PERSON ,/O The/O Second/ORDINAL Machine/O Age/O :/O Work/O ,/O Progre/O ss/O ,/O and/O Prosperity/O in/O a/O Time/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Brilliant/ORGANIZATION Technologies/ORGANIZATION ,/O WW/ORGANIZATION Norton/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2014/DATE ./O 
ARTIFICIAL/O INTELLIGENCE/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O AND/O THE/O ECONOMY/O 21/NUMBER In/O theory/O ,/O AI/O -/O driven/O automation/O might/O involve/O more/O than/O temporary/O disruptions/O in/O labor/O markets/O and/O drastically/O reduce/O the/O need/O for/O workers/O ./O 
I/O f/O there/O is/O no/O need/O for/O extensive/O human/O labor/O in/O the/O production/O process/O ,/O society/O as/O a/O whole/O may/O need/O to/O find/O an/O alternative/O approach/O to/O resource/O allocation/O other/O than/O compensation/O for/O labor/O ,/O requiring/O a/O fundamental/O shift/O in/O the/O way/O economies/O are/O organized/O ./O 
Although/O this/O scenario/O is/O speculative/O ,/O it/O is/O included/O in/O this/O report/O to/O foster/O discussion/O and/O shed/O light/O on/O the/O role/O and/O value/O of/O work/O in/O the/O economy/O and/O society/O ./O 
