Please/O cite/O this/O paper/O as/O :/O Arntz/PERSON ,/O M./O ,/O T./PERSON Gregory/PERSON and/O U./PERSON Zierahn/PERSON -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O ``/O The/O Risk/O ofAutomation/O for/O Jobs/O in/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Countries/O :/O A/O ComparativeAnalysis/O ''/O ,/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Social/O ,/O Employment/O and/O Migration/ORGANIZATION Working/ORGANIZATION Papers/ORGANIZATION ,/O No./O 189/NUMBER ,/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Publishing/O ,/O Paris/LOCATION ./O 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1787/5jlz9h56dvq7-en/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Social/O ,/O Employment/O and/O Migration/ORGANIZATION Working/ORGANIZATION Papers/ORGANIZATION No./ORGANIZATION 189The/ORGANIZATION Risk/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Automation/ORGANIZATION for/O Jobs/O in/O OECD/ORGANIZATION CountriesA/O COMPARATIVE/O ANALYSISMelanie/O Arntz/PERSON ,/O Terry/PERSON Gregory/PERSON ,/O Ulrich/PERSON ZierahnJEL/O Classification/O :/O J20/O ,/O J23/O ,/O J24/O For/O Official/O Use/O DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER Organisation/ORGANIZATION de/ORGANIZATION Coop?ration/ORGANIZATION et/ORGANIZATION de/ORGANIZATION D?veloppement/ORGANIZATION ?conomiques/ORGANIZATION Organisation/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Co/ORGANIZATION -/O operation/O and/O Development/O __________________________________________________________/O _________________________________/O _____________/O English/O -/O Or/O ./O 
English/O DIRECTORATE/O FOR/O EMPLOYMENT/O ,/O LABOUR/O AND/O SOCIAL/O AFFAIRS/O EMPLOYMENT/O ,/O LABOUR/O AND/O SOCIAL/O AFFAIRS/O COMMITTEE/O THE/O RISK/O OF/O AUTOMATION/O FOR/O JOBS/O IN/O OECD/ORGANIZATION COUNTRIES/O :/O A/O COMPARATIVE/O ANALYSIS/O ./O 
OECD/O SOCIAL/O ,/O EMPLOYMENT/O AND/O MIGRATION/O WORKING/O PAPERS/O No./O 189/NUMBER By/O Melanie/PERSON Arntz/PERSON -LRB-/O ZEW/ORGANIZATION Mannheim/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Heidelberg/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O ,/O Terry/PERSON Gregory/PERSON -LRB-/O ZEW/O Mannheim/O -RRB-/O and/O Ulrich/PERSON Zierahn/PERSON -LRB-/O ZEW/O Mannheim/O -RRB-/O JEL/O Classification/O :/O J20/O ,/O J23/O ,/O J24/O Authorised/O for/O publication/O by/O Stefano/PERSON Scarpetta/PERSON ,/O Director/O ,/O Directorate/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Employment/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION Labour/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Affairs/ORGANIZATION ./O 
All/O Social/O ,/O Employment/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Migration/ORGANIZATION Working/ORGANIZATION Papers/ORGANIZATION are/O now/DATE available/O through/O the/O OECD/ORGANIZATION website/O at/O www.oecd.org/els/workingpapers/O Complete/O document/O available/O on/O OLIS/O in/O its/O original/O format/O This/O document/O and/O any/O map/O included/O herein/O are/O without/O prejudice/O to/O the/O status/O of/O or/O sovereignty/O over/O any/O territory/O ,/O to/O the/O de/O limitation/O of/O international/O frontiers/O and/O bou/O ndaries/O and/O to/O the/O name/O of/O any/O territory/O ,/O city/O or/O area/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER For/O Official/O Use/O English/O -/O Or/O ./O 
English/O DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 2/NUMBER DIRECTORATE/O FOR/O EMPLOYMENT/O ,/O LABOUR/O AND/O SOCIAL/O AFFAIRS/O www.oecd.org/els/O OECD/O SOCIAL/O ,/O EMPLOYMENT/O AND/O MIGRATION/O WORKING/O PAPERS/O www.oecd.org/els/workingpapers/O OECD/O Working/O Papers/O should/O not/O be/O reported/O as/O representing/O the/O official/O views/O of/O the/O OECD/ORGANIZATION or/O of/O its/O member/O countries/O ./O 
The/O opinions/O expressed/O and/O argume/O nts/O employed/O are/O those/O of/O the/O author/O -LRB-/O s/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Working/O Papers/O describe/O preliminary/O results/O or/O research/O in/O progress/O by/O the/O author/O -LRB-/O s/O -RRB-/O and/O are/O published/O to/O stimulate/O discussion/O on/O a/O broad/O range/O of/O issues/O on/O which/O the/O OECD/ORGANIZATION works/O ./O 
Comments/O on/O Working/O Papers/O are/O welco/O med/O ,/O and/O may/O be/O sent/O to/O the/O Directorate/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Employment/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION Labour/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Affairs/ORGANIZATION OECD/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2/NUMBER rue/O Andr?/PERSON -/O Pascal/PERSON ,/O 75775/NUMBER Paris/LOCATION Cedex/O 16/NUMBER ,/O France/LOCATION ./O 
This/O series/O is/O designed/O to/O make/O available/O to/O a/O wider/O readership/O selected/O labour/O market/O ,/O social/O policy/O and/O migration/O st/O udies/O prepared/O for/O use/O within/O the/O OECD/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Authorship/O is/O usually/O collective/O ,/O but/O principal/O writers/O are/O named/O ./O 
The/O papers/O are/O generally/O available/O only/O in/O their/O original/O language/O --/O English/O or/O French/O --/O with/O a/O summary/O in/O the/O other/O ./O 
This/O document/O and/O any/O map/O included/O herein/O are/O without/O prejudice/O to/O the/O status/O of/O or/O sovereignty/O over/O any/O territory/O ,/O to/O the/O de/O limitation/O of/O international/O frontiers/O and/O boundaries/O and/O to/O the/O name/O of/O any/O territory/O ,/O city/O or/O area/O ./O 
Applications/O for/O permission/O to/O reproduce/O or/O translate/O all/O or/O part/O of/O this/O material/O should/O be/O made/O to/O :/O Head/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Publications/ORGANIZATION Service/ORGANIZATION OECD/O 2/NUMBER ,/O rue/O Andr?/PERSON -/O Pascal/PERSON 75775/NUMBER Paris/LOCATION ,/O CEDEX/O 16/NUMBER France/ORGANIZATION Copyright/ORGANIZATION OECD/ORGANIZATION 2016/DATE DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 3/NUMBER ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS/O This/O paper/O was/O commissioned/O by/O the/O Director/O of/O the/O OECD/ORGANIZATION 's/O Directorate/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Employment/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION Labour/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Affairs/ORGANIZATION as/O part/O of/O OECD/ORGANIZATION 's/O work/O on/O the/DATE future/DATE of/O work/O ./O 
Melanie/PERSON Arntz/PERSON is/O Junior/O Professor/O at/O the/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Heidelberg/ORGANIZATION and/O provisional/O head/O of/O the/O Research/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION ``/ORGANIZATION Labour/ORGANIZATION Markets/ORGANIZATION ,/O Human/O Resources/O and/O Social/O Policy/O ''/O at/O the/O Centre/O for/O European/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O ZEW/O -RRB-/O in/O Mannheim/LOCATION ./O 
Terry/PERSON Gregory/PERSON and/O Ulrich/PERSON Zierahn/PERSON are/O Senior/O Researchers/O at/O the/O Research/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION ``/ORGANIZATION Labour/ORGANIZATION Markets/ORGANIZATION ,/O Human/O Resources/O and/O Social/O Policy/O ''/O of/O the/O Centre/O for/O European/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O ZEW/O -RRB-/O in/O Mannheim/LOCATION ./O 
The/O authors/O gratefully/O acknowledge/O helpful/O comments/O by/O Holger/PERSON Bonin/PERSON and/O financial/O support/O by/O the/O OEC/O D./O DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 4/NUMBER SUMMARY/O In/O recent/DURATION years/DURATION ,/O there/O has/O been/O a/O revival/O of/O conc/O erns/O that/O automation/O and/O digitalis/O ation/O might/O after/O all/O result/O in/O a/O jobless/O future/DATE ./O 
The/O debate/O has/O been/O fuelled/O by/O studies/O for/O the/O US/LOCATION and/O Europe/LOCATION arguing/O that/O a/O substantial/O share/O of/O jobs/O is/O at/O ``/O risk/O of/O computeri/O sation/O ''/O ./O 
These/O studies/O follow/O an/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O proposed/O by/O Frey/ORGANIZATION and/O Osborne/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O i.e./O they/O assume/O that/O whole/O occupations/O rather/O than/O single/O job/O -/O tasks/O are/O automat/O ed/O by/O technology/O ./O 
As/O we/O argue/O ,/O this/O might/O lead/O to/O an/O overestimation/O of/O job/O automatibility/O ,/O as/O occupations/O labelled/O as/O high/O -/O risk/O occupations/O often/O still/O contain/O a/O substantial/O share/O of/O tasks/O that/O are/O hard/O to/O automate/O ./O 
Our/O paper/O serves/O two/NUMBER purposes/O ./O 
Firstly/O ,/O we/O estimate/O the/O job/O automatibility/O of/O jobs/O for/O 21/NUMBER OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O based/O on/O a/O task/O -/O based/O approach/O ./O 
In/O contrast/O to/O other/O studies/O ,/O we/O take/O into/O account/O the/O heterogeneity/O of/O workers/O '/O tasks/O within/O occupations/O ./O 
Overall/O ,/O we/O find/O that/O ,/O on/O average/O across/O the/O 21/NUMBER OEC/O D/O countries/O ,/O 9/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O jobs/O are/O automatable/O ./O 
The/O threat/O from/O technological/O advances/O thus/O seems/O much/O less/O pronounced/O compared/O to/O the/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O ./O 
We/O further/O find/O heterogeneities/O across/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
For/O instance/O ,/O while/O the/O share/O of/O automatable/O jobs/O is/O 6/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O Korea/LOCATION ,/O the/O corresponding/O share/O is/O 12/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O Austria/LOCATION ./O 
Differences/O between/O countries/O may/O reflect/O general/O differences/O in/O workplace/O organis/O ation/O ,/O differences/O in/O previous/O investments/O into/O automation/O technologies/O as/O well/O as/O differences/O in/O the/O educat/O ion/O of/O workers/O across/O countries/O ./O 
The/O second/ORDINAL purpose/O of/O this/O paper/O is/O to/O critically/O reflect/O on/O the/O recent/O line/O of/O studies/O that/O generate/O figures/O on/O the/O ``/O risk/O of/O computeris/O ation/O ''/O and/O to/O provide/O a/O comprehensive/O discussion/O on/O possible/O adjustment/O processes/O of/O fi/O rms/O and/O wor/O kers/O to/O automation/O and/O digitalis/O ation/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O we/O argue/O that/O the/O estimated/O share/O of/O ``/O jobs/O at/O risk/O ''/O must/O not/O be/O equated/O with/O actual/O or/O expected/O employment/O losses/O from/O technological/O advances/O for/O three/NUMBER reasons/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O the/O utilis/O ation/O of/O new/O technologies/O is/O a/O slow/O process/O ,/O due/O to/O economic/O ,/O legal/O and/O societal/O hurdles/O ,/O so/O that/O technological/O substitution/O often/O does/O not/O take/O place/O as/O expected/O ./O 
Second/ORDINAL ,/O even/O if/O new/O technologies/O are/O introduced/O ,/O workers/O can/O adjust/O to/O changing/O technological/O endowments/O by/O switching/O tasks/O ,/O thus/O preventing/O technological/O unemployment/O ./O 
Third/ORDINAL ,/O technological/O change/O also/O generates/O additional/O jobs/O through/O demand/O for/O new/O technologies/O and/O through/O higher/O competitiveness/O ./O 
The/O main/O conclusion/O from/O ou/O r/O paper/O is/O that/O automation/O and/O dig/O italisation/O are/O unlikely/O to/O destroy/O large/O numbers/O of/O jobs/O ./O 
However/O ,/O low/O qualified/O workers/O are/O likely/O to/O bear/O the/O brunt/O of/O the/O adjustment/O costs/O as/O the/O automatibility/O of/O their/O jobs/O is/O higher/O compared/O to/O highly/O qualified/O workers/O ./O 
Therefore/O ,/O the/O likely/O challen/O ge/O for/O the/DATE future/DATE lies/O in/O coping/O with/O rising/O inequality/O and/O ensuring/O sufficient/O -LRB-/O re/O -/O -RRB-/O training/O especially/O for/O low/O qualified/O workers/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 5/NUMBER R?SUM?/O Ces/O derni?res/O ann?es/O ,/O les/O craintes/O que/O l'automatisation/O et/O la/O num?risation/O aboutissent/O finalement/O ?/O un/O futur/O sans/O emploi/O se/O sont/O r?veill?es/O ./O 
Le/O d?bat/O a/O ?t?/O aliment?/O par/O des/O ?tudes/O sur/O les/O ?tats/O -/O Unis/O et/O l'Europe/O arguant/O qu'une/O grande/O partie/O des/O emplois/O ?tai/O ent/O en/O ``/O risque/O d'informatisation/O ''/O ./O 
Ces/O ?tudes/O utilisent/O une/O m?thode/O bas?e/O sur/O les/O professions/O propos?e/O par/O Frey/O et/O Osborne/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O c?est/O -/O ?-dire/O qu'elles/O supposent/O que/O les/O professions/O dans/O leur/O ensemble/O et/O non/O les/O t?ches/O isol?es/O sont/O automatis?es/O ./O 
Comme/O nous/O l'avan?ons/O ,/O cette/O hypoth?se/O peut/O mener/O ?/O la/O surestimation/O de/O l'automatisation/O des/O emplois/O ,/O puisque/O les/O professions/O dites/O ?/O haut/O risque/O comprennent/O souvent/O une/O part/O substantielle/O de/O t?ches/O difficiles/O ?/O automatiser/O ./O 
Notre/O article/O a/O un/O double/O objectif/O ./O 
D/O '/O une/O part/O ,/O nous/O estimons/O par/O une/O approche/O bas?e/O sur/O les/O t?ches/O la/O possibilit?/O d'automatiser/O les/O emplois/O pour/O 21/NUMBER pays/O de/O l'OCDE/O ./O 
A/O la/O diff?rence/O d'autres/O ?tudes/O ,/O nous/O prenons/O en/O compte/O l'h?t?rog?n?it?/O des/O t?ches/O au/O sein/O des/O professions/O ./O 
Globalement/O ,/O nous/O es/O timons/O que/O 9/PERCENT %/PERCENT des/O emplois/O sont/O automatisables/O en/O moyenne/O dans/O les/O 21/NUMBER pays/O de/O l'OCDE/O ./O 
La/O menace/O g?n?r?e/O par/O les/O avanc?es/O technologiques/O semble/O donc/O bien/O moindre/O que/O celle/O donn?e/O par/O la/O m?thode/O bas?e/O sur/O les/O professions/O ./O 
Nous/O trouvons/O ?galement/O que/O les/O pays/O de/O l'OCDE/O sont/O h?t?rog?nes/O en/O la/O mati?re/O ./O 
Par/O exemple/O ,/O alors/O que/O la/O part/O des/O emplois/O automatisables/O repr?sente/O 6/PERCENT %/PERCENT en/O Cor?e/O ,/O elle/O s/O '/O ?l?ve/O ?/O 12/PERCENT %/PERCENT en/O Autriche/O ./O 
Les/O diff?rences/O entre/O pays/O peuvent/O ?tre/O le/O reflet/O des/O diversit?s/O concernant/O l'organisation/O du/O l/O ieu/O de/O travail/O en/O g?n?ral/O ,/O des/O diff?rences/O dans/O les/O investissements/O faits/O auparavant/O dans/O les/O technologies/O d'automatisation/O ou/O encore/O des/O variations/O dans/O les/O niveaux/O d'?ducation/O des/O travailleurs/O ./O 
Le/O second/ORDINAL objectif/O de/O cet/O article/O est/O de/O proc?der/O ?/O une/O r?fl/O exion/O critique/O sur/O un/O groupe/O d'?tudes/O r?centes/O qui/O produisent/O des/O chiffres/O sur/O le/O ``/O risque/O d'informatisation/O ''/O et/O de/O fournir/O une/O discussion/O approfondie/O sur/O les/O processus/O possibles/O d'adaptation/O ?/O l'automatisation/O et/O ?/O la/O num?risation/O pour/O les/O entreprises/O co/O mme/O pour/O les/O travailleurs/O ./O 
En/O particulier/O ,/O nous/O avan?ons/O que/O l'estimation/O de/O la/O part/O des/O ``/O emplois/O ?/O risque/O ''/O ne/O doit/O pas/O ?tre/O assimil?e/O aux/O pertes/O d'emplois/O effectives/O ou/O pr?vues/O li?es/O aux/O avanc?es/O technologiques/O ./O 
D'une/O part/O ,/O l'utilisation/O de/O nouvelles/O te/O chnologies/O est/O un/O processus/O long/O ,/O ralenti/O par/O les/O obstacles/O ?conomiques/O ,/O l?gaux/O et/O sociaux/O ,/O de/O telle/O sorte/O que/O souvent/O la/O substitution/O technologique/O ne/O s/O '/O effectue/O pas/O comme/O pr?vu/O ./O 
D'autre/O part/O ,/O m?me/O si/O des/O changements/O technologiques/O sont/O introduits/O ,/O les/O travailleurs/O peuvent/O s/O '/O y/O adapter/O en/O changeant/O leurs/O t?ches/O ,/O de/O mani?re/O ?/O pr?venir/O le/O ch?mage/O technologique/O ./O 
Enfin/O ,/O le/O changement/O technologique/O g?n?re/O aussi/O des/O emplois/O suppl?mentaires/O li?s/O ?/O la/O demande/O pour/O les/O nouvelles/O technologies/O et/O ?/O l'accroissement/O de/O la/O comp?titivit?/O ./O 
La/O conclusion/O principale/O de/O notre/O article/O est/O qu'il/O est/O peu/O probable/O que/O l'automatisation/O et/O la/O num?risation/O d?truisent/O un/O grand/O nombre/O d'emplois/O ./O 
Cependant/O ,/O les/O travailleurs/O peu/O qualifi?s/O souffriront/O plus/O des/O co?ts/O d'ajustement/O car/O leur/O emploi/O est/O davantage/O susceptible/O d'?tre/O automatis?/O que/O pour/O les/O travailleurs/O qualifi?s/O ./O 
Ainsi/O ,/O le/O d?fi/O futur/O consiste/O probablement/O ?/O faire/O face/O ?/O la/O croissance/O des/O in?galit?s/O et/O ?/O veiller/O ?/O former/O -LRB-/O ou/O former/O ?/O nouveau/O -RRB-/O les/O travailleurs/O peu/O qualifi?s/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 6/NUMBER TABLE/O OF/O CONTENTS/O INTRODUCTION/O .../O .../O .../O .../O .../O 7/NUMBER THE/O THREAT/O OF/O AUTOMA/O TION/O ACCORDING/O TO/O FR/O EY/O AND/O OSBORNE/PERSON .../O .../O 9/NUMBER AUTOMATIBILITY/O OF/O JO/O BS/O IN/O OECD/ORGANIZATION COUNTRIES/O --/O A/O TASK/O -/O BASED/O APPROACH/O .../O 11/NUMBER A./ORGANIZATION Data/ORGANIZATION and/O Methodology/O .../O .../O .../O .../O 12/NUMBER B./O Results/O for/O the/O US/LOCATION .../O .../O .../O .../O 14/NUMBER C./ORGANIZATION Results/ORGANIZATION for/O other/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O .../O .../O .../O .../O 15/NUMBER INTERPRETATION/O AND/O C/O RITIQUE/O .../O .../O .../O .../O 21/NUMBER A./O Overestimation/O of/O technological/O capabilities/O and/O its/O lagging/O utilisation/O .../O .../O 21/NUMBER B./O Adjustment/O of/O workplace/O tasks/O .../O .../O .../O .../O 23/NUMBER C./ORGANIZATION Macroeconomic/ORGANIZATION adjustment/O and/O indirect/O effects/O .../O .../O .../O 23/NUMBER CONCLUSIONS/O .../O .../O .../O .../O .../O 25/NUMBER ANNEXES/O .../O .../O .../O .../O .../O 29/NUMBER ANNEX/ORGANIZATION A./ORGANIZATION Descriptive/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION and/O Variable/O Definitions/O .../O .../O .../O 29/NUMBER ANNEX/O B./O Estimation/O results/O .../O .../O .../O .../O 30/NUMBER ANNEX/ORGANIZATION C./ORGANIZATION Detailed/ORGANIZATION Results/ORGANIZATION by/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Countries/O .../O .../O .../O 33/NUMBER DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 7/NUMBER INTRODUCTION/O 1/NUMBER ./O 
In/O the/DATE past/DATE ,/O technological/O change/O often/O stoked/O fears/O that/O new/O technological/O means/O displace/O workers/O ,/O hence/O giving/O rise/O to/O what/O has/O been/O called/O technological/O unemployment/O -LRB-/O see/O Mokyr/PERSON e/O t/O al./O ,/O 2015/DATE for/O a/O comprehensive/O review/O of/O the/O literature/O -RRB-/O ./O 
While/O such/O fears/O have/O not/O proven/O true/O for/O past/DATE technological/O advances/O in/O the/O 19th/DATE and/DATE 20th/DATE century/DATE as/O the/O creation/O of/O new/O jobs/O usually/O outran/O the/O labour/O -/O saving/O impact/O of/O the/O adoption/O of/O new/O technol/O ogies/O ,/O fears/O have/O recently/DATE been/O growing/O again/O that/O technological/O advances/O in/O the/O field/O of/O automation/O and/O digitalisation/O may/O after/O all/O herald/O the/O ``/O End/O of/O Work/O ''/O ,/O as/O has/O already/O been/O proposed/O by/O Rifkin/PERSON -LRB-/O 1995/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O underlying/O notion/O is/O that/O automation/O and/O digi/ORGANIZATION talisation/O are/O increasingly/O penetrating/O the/O domain/O of/O tasks/O that/O until/O recently/DATE used/O to/O be/O genuinely/O human/O such/O as/O reasoning/O ,/O sensing/O and/O deciding/O ./O 
In/O a/O widely/O discussed/O book/O ,/O Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O present/DATE numerous/O examples/O of/O what/O they/O call/O ``/O The/O Second/ORDINAL Machine/O Age/O ''/O such/O as/O the/O driverless/O car/O ,/O the/O largely/O autonomous/O smart/O factory/O ,/O service/O robots/O or/O 3D/O printing/O ./O 
These/O technologies/O are/O driven/O by/O advances/O in/O computing/O power/O ,/O robotics/O and/O artificial/O intelligence/O and/O ultimately/O redefine/O what/O type/O of/O hum/O an/O capabilities/O machines/O are/O able/O to/O do/O ./O 
2/NUMBER ./O 
Hence/O ,/O at/O least/O in/O the/O public/O debate/O ,/O the/O prevalent/O perception/O seems/O to/O be/O that/O the/O substitutability/O of/O humans/O by/O machines/O reaches/O a/O new/O and/O unprecedented/O quality/O ./O 
Such/O fea/O rs/O have/O also/O been/O fuelled/O by/O a/O study/O conducted/O by/O Frey/ORGANIZATION and/O Osborne/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O that/O tries/O to/O estimate/O the/O susceptibi/O lity/O of/O employment/O to/O computeris/O ation/O ./O 
In/O this/O widely/O cited/O paper/O ,/O they/O classify/O occupations/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION with/O respect/O to/O the/O risk/O of/O being/O suscepti/O ble/O to/O automation/O by/O asking/O experts/O about/O the/O technological/O potential/O for/O automation/O in/O the/DATE near/DATE future/DATE ./O 
As/O a/O result/O ,/O the/O study/O suggests/O that/O 47/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O all/O persons/O employed/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION are/O working/O in/O jobs/O that/O could/O be/O performed/O by/O computers/O and/O algorithms/O with/O in/O the/DURATION next/DURATION 10/DURATION to/DURATION 20/DURATION years/DURATION ./O 
Several/O follow/O -/O up/O studies/O applied/O the/O risk/O of/O automation/O at/O the/O level/O of/O occupations/O to/O other/O countries/O ,/O thereby/O assuming/O that/O the/O risk/O of/O automation/O for/O a/O particular/O occupation/O is/O comparable/O across/O countries/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O cross/O -/O count/O ry/O differences/O in/O the/O estimated/O share/O of/O workers/O that/O are/O prone/O to/O automation/O are/O driven/O by/O differences/O in/O the/O occupational/O structure/O only/O ./O 
With/O this/O approach/O ,/O Pajarinen/PERSON and/O Rouvinen/PERSON -LRB-/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O estimate/O the/O share/O of/O jobs/O that/O are/O susceptible/O to/O automation/O to/O b/O e/O around/O 35/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O Finland/LOCATION while/O Br/O zeski/O and/O Bur/O k/O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O estimate/O the/O share/O of/O jobs/O at/O risk/O of/O automation/O to/O be/O as/O high/O as/O 59/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O Germany/LOCATION ./O 
Bowles/O -LRB-/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O finds/O the/O share/O of/O jobs/O that/O are/O susceptible/O to/O automation/O in/O Europe/LOCATION to/O range/O between/O 45/NUMBER to/O more/O than/O 60/PERCENT %/PERCENT ,/O with/O southern/O European/O workforces/O facing/O the/O highest/O exposure/O to/O a/O potential/O automation/O ./O 
3/NUMBER ./O 
Given/O these/O numbers/O ,/O the/O potential/O for/O automation/O is/O perceived/O as/O a/O threat/O that/O will/O ultimately/O foster/O technological/O unempl/O oyment/O ./O 
However/O ,/O the/O study/O by/O Frey/PERSON and/O Osborne/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O has/O also/O spurred/O a/O discussion/O about/O the/O interpretation/O of/O these/O results/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O one/NUMBER critique/O targets/O the/O fact/O that/O automation/O usually/O aims/O at/O automating/O certain/O tasks/O rather/O than/O whole/O occupatio/O ns/O ./O 
Since/O occupations/O usually/O consist/O of/O performing/O a/O bundle/O of/O tasks/O not/O all/O of/O which/O may/O be/O easily/O automatable/O -LRB-/O Autor/O 2014/DATE ,/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O the/O potential/O for/O automating/O entire/O occupations/O and/O workplaces/O may/O be/O much/O lower/O than/O suggested/O by/O the/O approach/O followed/O by/O Frey/PERSON and/O Osborne/PERSON ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O even/O within/O occupations/O ,/O the/O heterogeneity/O of/O tasks/O performed/O at/O different/O workplaces/O appears/O to/O be/O huge/O as/O recently/DATE shown/O by/O Autor/O and/O Handel/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O fact/O ,/O most/O of/O the/O a/O djustment/O to/O the/DATE past/DATE computeris/O ation/O occurred/O through/O changing/O task/O structures/O within/O occupations/O ,/O rather/O than/O changing/O employment/O shares/O between/O occupations/O -LRB-/O Spitz/PERSON -/O Oener/DATE 2006/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
4/NUMBER ./O 
A/DURATION second/DURATION critique/O aims/O at/O confounding/O the/O potential/O for/O automation/O with/O actual/O employment/O losses/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O the/O technical/O possibility/O to/O use/O machines/O rather/O than/O humans/O for/O the/O provision/O of/O certain/O tasks/O need/O not/O mean/O that/O the/O substitution/O of/O humans/O by/O machines/O actually/O takes/O place/O ./O 
In/O many/O cases/O ,/O there/O are/O legal/O as/O well/O as/O ethical/O obstac/O les/O that/O may/O prevent/O such/O a/O substitution/O or/O at/O least/O substantially/O slow/O down/O its/O pace/O ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O the/O substitution/O may/O not/O be/O reasonable/O from/O an/O economic/O DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 8/NUMBER point/O of/O view/O ./O 
However/O ,/O even/O in/O the/O absence/O of/O such/O obstacles/O ,/O workers/O may/O adjust/O to/O a/O new/O division/O of/O labour/O between/O machines/O and/O humans/O by/O switching/O tasks/O ./O 
5/NUMBER ./O 
The/O aim/O of/O this/O study/O is/O to/O estimate/O the/O risk/O of/O automation/O for/O jobs/O in/O 21/NUMBER OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O 1/NUMBER based/O on/O the/O approach/O by/O Frey/ORGANIZATION and/O Osborne/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O while/O relaxing/O one/NUMBER of/O their/O major/O assumptions/O as/O in/O our/O earlier/O study/O for/O Germany/LOCATION -LRB-/O Bonin/ORGANIZATION et/ORGANIZATION al./ORGANIZATION ./O 
2015/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Rather/O than/O assuming/O that/O it/O is/O occupations/O that/O are/O displaced/O by/O machines/O ,/O we/O argue/O that/O it/O is/O certai/O n/O tasks/O that/O can/O be/O displaced/O ./O 
To/O the/O extent/O that/O bundles/O of/O tasks/O differ/O across/O countries/O and/O also/O within/O occupations/O ,/O occupations/O at/O risk/O of/O being/O automated/O according/O to/O Frey/PERSON and/O Osborne/PERSON may/O well/O be/O less/O prone/O to/O automation/O when/O considering/O the/O fact/O that/O most/O occupations/O contain/O tasks/O that/O are/O difficult/O to/O substitute/O at/O least/O in/O the/O foreseeable/O future/DATE ./O 
6/NUMBER ./O 
In/O this/O paper/O ,/O we/O re/O -/O estimate/O the/O share/O of/O jobs/O at/O risk/O of/O automation/O for/O 21/NUMBER OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O including/O the/O US/LOCATION usi/O ng/O a/O task/O -/O based/O approach/O ./O 
For/O this/O purpose/O ,/O we/O use/O the/O recently/DATE released/O PIACC/O database/O -LRB-/O Programme/ORGANIZATION for/O the/O International/ORGANIZATION Assessment/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Adult/ORGANIZATION Competencies/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O that/O surveys/O task/O structures/O across/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
Overall/O ,/O we/O find/O the/O share/O of/O jobs/O at/O risk/O of/O aut/O omation/O to/O be/O ,/O on/O average/O across/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ,/O 9/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
However/O ,/O these/O numbers/O may/O be/O limited/O in/O informing/O us/O about/O the/O potential/O impact/O of/O technological/O advances/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O the/O paper/O discusses/O several/O reasons/O why/O these/O numbers/O may/O still/O not/O be/O equated/O with/O actual/O expected/O employment/O losses/O from/O technological/O advances/O ./O 
7/NUMBER ./O 
We/O find/O that/O applying/O a/O task/O -/O based/O approach/O results/O in/O a/O much/O lower/O risk/O of/O automation/O compared/O to/O the/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O ./O 
For/O instance/O ,/O w/O hile/O Frey/PERSON and/O Osborne/PERSON find/O that/O 47/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O US/O jobs/O are/O automatable/O ,/O our/O corresponding/O figure/O is/O only/O 9/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
The/O threat/O from/O technological/O advances/O is/O thus/O much/O less/O pronounced/O compared/O to/O the/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O by/O Frey/ORGANIZATION and/O Osborne/PERSON ./O 
This/O substantial/O diffe/O rence/O is/O driven/O by/O the/O fact/O that/O even/O in/O occupations/O that/O Frey/PERSON and/O Osborne/PERSON considered/O to/O be/O in/O the/O high/O risk/O category/O ,/O workers/O at/O least/O to/O some/O extent/O also/O perform/O tasks/O that/O are/O difficult/O to/O automate/O such/O as/O tasks/O involving/O face/O -/O to-face/O interaction/O ./O 
8/NUMBER ./O 
As/O a/O final/O result/O ,/O we/O find/O heterogeneities/O across/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
For/O instance/O ,/O while/O the/O share/O of/O automatable/O jobs/O is/O 6/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O Korea/LOCATION ,/O the/O corresponding/O rate/O is/O 12/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O Austria/LOCATION ./O 
As/O we/O show/O ,/O parts/O of/O the/O differences/O acros/O s/O countries/O may/O reflect/O general/O differences/O in/O workplace/O organis/O ation/O ,/O differences/O in/O previous/O investments/O into/O automation/O technologies/O as/O well/O as/O differences/O in/O the/O education/O of/O workers/O across/O countries/O ./O 
1/NUMBER ./O 
We/O estimate/O the/O automatibility/O for/O all/O countries/O which/O are/O included/O in/O the/O currently/DATE available/O PIAAC/O data/O ,/O excluding/O Russia/LOCATION ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 9/NUMBER THE/O THREAT/O OF/O AUTOMA/O TION/O ACCORDING/O TO/O FR/O EY/O AND/O OS/O BORNE/O 9/NUMBER ./O 
With/O their/O analysis/O of/O the/O susc/O eptibility/O of/O jobs/O to/O computeris/O ation/O ,/O FO/O -LRB-/O from/O now/DATE on/O referring/O to/O Frey/ORGANIZATION and/O Osborne/PERSON 2013/DATE -RRB-/O started/O a/O controversial/O discussion/O about/O the/O potential/O threats/O from/O current/DATE and/O future/DATE technological/O advances/O ./O 
In/O the/O public/O debate/O ,/O their/O result/O that/O 47/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O all/O US/O jobs/O might/O be/O at/O risk/O of/O being/O automated/O in/O the/DATE near/DATE future/DATE clearly/O stoked/O fears/O that/O technological/O unemployment/O is/O likely/O to/O affect/O a/O large/O and/O increasing/O share/O of/O the/O populati/O on/O ./O 
Yet/O ,/O in/O order/O to/O actually/O interpret/O these/O results/O correctly/O ,/O it/O is/O important/O to/O better/O understand/O their/O empirical/O approach/O in/O the/O first/ORDINAL place/O ./O 
10/NUMBER ./O 
FO/O focus/O on/O the/O technological/O advances/O in/O what/O they/O call/O Machine/O Learning/O -LRB-/O ML/O -RRB-/O and/O Mobile/ORGANIZATION Robotics/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O MR/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Their/O starting/O point/O is/O the/O assumption/O that/O these/O advances/O differ/O from/O previous/O technological/O advances/O in/O that/O the/O technological/O capabilities/O to/O perform/O tasks/O that/O have/O until/O recently/DATE been/O considered/O genuinely/O human/O are/O increasing/O rapidly/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O these/O tasks/O are/O no/O longer/O confined/O to/O routine/O tasks/O as/O has/O been/O the/O assumption/O of/O most/O studies/O in/O labour/O economics/O in/O the/DATE past/DATE decade/DATE -LRB-/O see/O Acemoglu/PERSON and/O Autor/O ,/O 2/NUMBER 011/NUMBER ,/O and/O Autor/O ,/O 2013/DATE ,/O for/O reviews/O of/O the/O literature/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Instead/O ,/O machines/O are/O increasingly/O capable/O of/O performing/O non/O -/O routine/O cognitive/O tasks/O such/O as/O driving/O or/O legal/O writing/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O advances/O in/O the/O field/O of/O Machine/O Learning/O -LRB-/O ML/O ,/O e.g./O computational/O st/O atistics/O and/O vision/O ,/O data/O mining/O ,/O artificial/O intelligence/O -RRB-/O allow/O for/O automating/O cognitive/O tasks/O ,/O while/O the/O use/O of/O ML/O in/O Mobile/ORGANIZATION Robotics/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O MR/O -RRB-/O also/O allows/O for/O automating/O certain/O manual/O tasks/O ./O 
11/NUMBER ./O 
FO/O argue/O that/O due/O to/O t/O hese/O advances/O ,/O creative/O destruction/O ,/O i.e./O technological/O unemployment/O as/O a/O result/O of/O workers/O seeking/O new/O jobs/O after/O being/O laid/O off/O ,/O is/O likely/O to/O exceed/O what/O has/O been/O called/O the/O capitalization/O effect/O -LRB-/O Aghion/ORGANIZATION and/O Howitt/O 1994/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O latter/O effect/O refers/O to/O the/O growth/O -/O enhancing/O and/O ultimately/O job/O -/O creating/O effect/O of/O technological/O advances/O that/O in/O the/DATE past/DATE apparently/O outweighed/O the/O initial/O ,/O labour/O -/O saving/O effect/O of/O technology/O ./O 
Since/O the/O current/DATE speed/O with/O which/O human/O labour/O becomes/O potentially/O obsolete/O is/O high/O and/O e/O ven/O increasing/O ,/O attempts/O to/O upgrade/O skills/O and/O education/O may/O no/O longer/O suffice/O to/O win/O the/O ``/O Race/O Against/O the/O Machines/O ''/O as/O titled/O by/O Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O unprecedented/O levels/O of/O technological/O unemployment/O may/O arise/O ./O 
The/O only/O domain/O of/O tasks/O that/O according/O to/O FO/O appears/O to/O be/O exempt/O from/O this/O threat/O ,/O is/O related/O to/O what/O they/O call/O Engineering/O Bottlenecks/O ./O 
Such/O bottlenecks/O refer/O to/O tasks/O that/O can/O not/O be/O substituted/O by/O machines/O in/O the/DATE near/DATE future/DATE as/O these/O tasks/O can/O not/O be/O defined/O in/O terms/O of/O codifi/O able/O rules/O and/O thus/O algorithms/O ./O 
12/NUMBER ./O 
One/NUMBER of/O these/O bottlenecks/O refers/O to/O tasks/O that/O are/O related/O to/O perception/O and/O manipulation/O ,/O especially/O when/O such/O tasks/O are/O performed/O in/O unstructured/O situations/O ./O 
The/O capability/O of/O wor/O kers/O in/O handling/O objects/O in/O such/O contexts/O is/O still/O a/O huge/O challenge/O for/O engineers/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O humans/O are/O likely/O to/O have/O long/O -/O lasting/O comparative/O advantages/O when/O it/O comes/O to/O orienting/O oneself/O in/O complex/O situations/O and/O to/O react/O to/O potential/O failures/O and/O unstructured/O challenges/O ./O 
13/NUMBER ./O 
Other/O tasks/O that/O are/O likely/O to/O remain/O the/O domain/O of/O humans/O are/O related/O to/O creativity/O and/O social/O intelligence/O ./O 
According/O to/O FO/O ,/O creativity/O is/O the/O ability/O to/O develop/O new/O and/O meaningful/O idea/O s/O or/O artefacts/O such/O as/O new/O concepts/O ,/O theories/O ,/O literature/O ,/O or/O musical/O compositions/O ./O 
Although/O certain/O parts/O of/O these/O tasks/O might/O be/O automatable/O to/O some/O extent/O ,/O FO/O consider/O true/O creativity/O that/O relates/O these/O new/O ideas/O to/O the/O cultural/O and/O contemporary/O context/O of/O changing/O societal/O perceptions/O as/O a/O domain/O that/O is/O likely/O to/O be/O dominated/O by/O humans/O in/O the/O foreseeable/O future/DATE ./O 
Similarly/O ,/O tasks/O that/O necessitate/O social/O intelligence/O ,/O i.e./O the/O ability/O to/O intelligently/O and/O empathically/O respond/O to/O a/O human/O counterpart/O ,/O rema/O in/O a/O highly/O challenging/O domain/O from/O an/O engineering/O point/O of/O view/O ./O 
Tasks/O such/O as/O persuading/O ,/O negotiating/O or/O caring/O for/O others/O are/O thus/O likely/O to/O remain/O genuinely/O human/O even/O in/O the/O long/O run/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/DATE 10/DATE 14/DATE ./O 
Against/O this/O background/O ,/O FO/O discuss/O the/O task/O model/O of/O Autor/O et/O al./O ./O 
-LRB-/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O that/O considers/O a/O constant/O return/O to/O scale/O aggregate/O production/O function/O with/O two/NUMBER types/O of/O labour/O inputs/O :/O Routine/O tasks/O that/O are/O technically/O substitutable/O by/O capital/O and/O non/O -/O routine/O tasks/O that/O are/O not/O subst/O itutable/O ./O 
FO/O adapt/O this/O model/O by/O redefining/O the/O domain/O of/O tasks/O that/O are/O susceptible/O to/O automation/O and/O those/O that/O ,/O due/O to/O the/O engineering/O bottlenecks/O ,/O are/O not/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O tasks/O that/O could/O potentially/O be/O automated/O go/O beyond/O the/O routine/O tasks/O as/O defined/O in/O Autor/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O reflecting/O new/O advances/O in/O ML/O and/O MR./DATE 15/DATE ./O 
An/O important/O difference/O between/O the/O task/O model/O as/O used/O by/O Autor/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O and/O FO/O is/O that/O the/O former/O discuss/O the/O substitution/O of/O routine/O tasks/O by/O machines/O as/O a/O result/O of/O profit/O maximi/O sing/O firms/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O whether/O substitution/O takes/O place/O hinges/O not/O only/O on/O technological/O capabilities/O ,/O but/O on/O the/O relative/O price/O of/O performing/O tasks/O by/O either/O humans/O or/O machines/O ./O 
In/O contrast/O ,/O FO/O only/O assess/O the/O technical/O capability/O of/O substituting/O a/O certain/O tasks/O by/O machines/O and/O not/O its/O economic/O feasibility/O ./O 
16/NUMBER ./O 
In/O order/O to/O identify/O the/O capability/O of/O substituting/O occupations/O with/O machines/O ,/O their/O empirical/O analysis/O is/O based/O on/O the/O 2010/DATE version/O of/O the/O O/O */O NET/O data/O ./O 
This/O database/O contains/O information/O about/O the/O task/O content/O of/O 903/NUMBER occupations/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION and/O is/O based/O on/O t/O he/O assessment/O of/O labour/O market/O analysts/O as/O well/O as/O experts/O and/O workers/O in/O a/O particular/O occupation/O ./O 
In/O order/O to/O merge/O wage/O and/O employment/O data/O to/O these/O occupations/O ,/O FO/O aggregate/O the/O 903/NUMBER O/O */O NET/O occupations/O to/O 702/NUMBER occupations/O of/O the/O Labour/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION 's/O Standar/O d/O Occupational/O Classification/O -LRB-/O SOC/O -RRB-/O by/O taking/O the/O mean/O of/O the/O tasks/O as/O reported/O in/O the/O O/O */O NET/O data/O whenever/O occupations/O had/O to/O be/O aggregated/O ./O 
17/NUMBER ./O 
Afterwards/O ,/O they/O ask/O ML/O researchers/O in/O the/O context/O of/O a/O workshop/O at/O Oxf/ORGANIZATION ord/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION Engineering/ORGANIZATION Sciences/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION to/O classify/O occupations/O into/O being/O either/O automatable/O or/O not/O based/O on/O the/O reported/O task/O structures/O ./O 
2/NUMBER From/O this/O classification/O purpose/O ,/O they/O select/O only/O 70/NUMBER occupations/O whose/O labelling/O the/O experts/O were/O highly/O co/O nfident/O about/O ./O 
FO/O then/O impute/O the/O automatibility/O to/O the/O remaining/O 632/NUMBER occupations/O by/O proceeding/O as/O follows/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O they/O examine/O whether/O this/O subjective/O classification/O is/O systematically/O related/O to/O nine/NUMBER objective/O attributes/O of/O the/O occupations/O that/O are/O relate/O d/O to/O the/O identified/O engineering/O bottlenecks/O -LRB-/O e.g./O manual/O dexterity/O ,/O originality/O ,/O social/O perceptiveness/O -RRB-/O ./O 
These/O bottleneck/O -/O tasks/O were/O defined/O only/O after/O the/O workshop/O and/O had/O not/O been/O part/O of/O the/O occupational/O task/O structures/O that/O formed/O the/O basis/O for/O the/O exp/O erts/O '/O assessment/O ./O 
FO/O then/O estimate/O various/O variants/O of/O a/O probabilistic/O model/O to/O examine/O the/O power/O of/O these/O bottleneck/O -/O related/O attributes/O in/O predicting/O an/O occupation/O 's/O automatibility/O ./O 
They/O repeat/O this/O exercise/O with/O 100/NUMBER randomly/O selected/O subsamples/O of/O the/O 70/NUMBER classified/O occupations/O and/O find/O a/O high/O predictive/O power/O of/O these/O attributes/O for/O the/O subjective/O assessment/O of/O each/O occupation/O 's/O automatibility/O ./O 
18/NUMBER ./O 
The/O model/O estimates/O are/O used/O to/O predict/O the/O probability/O with/O which/O ea/O ch/O of/O the/O 632/NUMBER occupations/O that/O had/O not/O been/O assessed/O by/O the/O experts/O could/O potentially/O be/O automated/O ./O 
FO/O then/O distinguish/O between/O low/O risk/O -LRB-/O less/O than/O 30/PERCENT %/PERCENT -RRB-/O ,/O medium/O risk/O -LRB-/O 30/PERCENT -70/PERCENT %/PERCENT -RRB-/O and/O high/O -/O risk/O -LRB-/O >/O 70/PERCENT %/PERCENT -RRB-/O occupations/O ./O 
Combining/O this/O information/O with/O the/O number/O of/O e/O mployees/O in/O each/O occupation/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION ,/O as/O reported/O for/O 2010/DATE by/O the/O Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION ,/O FO/O infer/O that/O 47/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O all/O jobs/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION are/O in/O the/O high/O risk/O category/O ,/O ``/O meaning/O that/O associated/O occupations/O are/O potentially/O automatable/O over/O some/O unspecified/O num/O ber/O of/O years/DURATION ,/O maybe/O a/DURATION decade/DURATION or/O two/NUMBER ''/O -LRB-/O FO/O 2013/DATE ,/O p./O 38/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
According/O to/O this/O ,/O it/O is/O especially/O service/O ,/O sales/O and/O office/O jobs/O that/O fall/O in/O the/O high/O -/O risk/O category/O ,/O see/O Figure/O 1/NUMBER ./O 
Beyond/O high/O -/O risk/O occupations/O ,/O FO/O assume/O that/O automation/O will/O take/O place/O at/O a/O much/O l/O ower/O pace/O as/O the/O engineering/O bottlenecks/O have/O to/O be/O resolved/O first/ORDINAL ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O they/O find/O that/O the/O risk/O of/O automation/O is/O higher/O for/O low/O -/O skilled/O workers/O and/O for/O low/O -/O wage/O occupations/O ,/O suggesting/O that/O automation/O could/O disproportionately/O affect/O these/O groups/O of/O w/O orkers/O ./O 
2/NUMBER ./O 
Experts/O were/O asked/O :/O ``/O Can/O the/O tasks/O of/O this/O job/O be/O sufficiently/O specified/O conditional/O on/O the/O availability/O of/O big/O data/O ,/O to/O be/O performed/O by/O state/O of/O the/O art/O computer/O -/O controlled/O equipment/O ``/O -LRB-/O Frey/PERSON and/O Osborne/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE :/O 30/NUMBER -RRB-/O DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/DATE 11/DATE 19/DATE ./O 
Although/O FO/O repeatedly/O stress/O that/O they/O focus/O on/O technological/O capabilities/O only/O ,/O their/O results/O of/O jobs/O being/O ``/O at/O risk/O ''/O of/O automation/O and/O the/O follow/O -/O up/O studies/O by/O other/O scholars/O -LRB-/O see/O next/O section/O -RRB-/O set/O o/O ff/O a/O heated/O debate/O about/O the/O potential/O threats/O from/O technological/O advances/O ./O 
Yet/O ,/O there/O are/O many/O reasons/O why/O the/O automatiblity/O of/O jobs/O might/O not/O resolve/O in/O actual/O job/O losses/O ./O 
Besides/O several/O other/O reasons/O -LRB-/O see/O Section/O ``/O Interpretation/O and/O Critique/O ''/O -RRB-/O ,/O one/NUMBER mai/O n/O factor/O that/O FO/O leave/O aside/O is/O that/O it/O is/O usually/O not/O an/O occupation/O ,/O but/O rather/O a/O certain/O task/O that/O can/O be/O automated/O or/O not/O ,/O i.e./O it/O is/O tasks/O rather/O than/O occupations/O that/O are/O at/O risk/O ./O 
In/O the/O next/O section/O ,/O we/O therefore/O provide/O an/O alternative/O approach/O to/O es/O timate/O the/O risk/O of/O automation/O for/O 21/NUMBER OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O based/O on/O the/O actual/O task/O content/O of/O jobs/O ./O 
Figure/O 1/NUMBER ./O 
US/O Employment/O by/O Risk/O Category/O -LRB-/O Frey/Osborne/O 2013/DATE ,/O p./O 37/NUMBER -RRB-/O Source/O :/O Frey/PERSON and/O Osborne/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Employment/O :/O How/O Susc/O eptible/O are/O Jobs/O to/O Computerization/O ?/O 
University/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Oxford/ORGANIZATION ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 12/NUMBER AUTOMATIBILITY/O OF/O JO/O BS/O IN/O OECD/ORGANIZATION COUNTRIES/O --/O A/O TASK/O -/O BASED/O APPROACH/O 20/NUMBER ./O 
Below/O ,/O we/O transfer/O the/O automatibility/O as/O provided/O by/O FO/O to/O other/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
Some/O authors/O have/O done/O this/O by/O assuming/O that/O occupations/O in/O the/O studied/O countries/O are/O comparable/O to/O US/LOCATION occupations/O ./O 
In/O order/O to/O derive/O similar/O automation/O scenarios/O as/O in/O FO/O ,/O they/O directly/O transferre/O d/O the/O automatibility/O as/O reported/O by/O FO/O at/O the/O occupational/O level/O to/O occupation/O -/O specific/O employment/O data/O in/O Germany/LOCATION -LRB-/O Brzeski/PERSON and/O Burk/PERSON 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Finland/LOCATION -LRB-/O Pajarinen/O and/O Rouvinen/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O or/O European/O Countries/O -LRB-/O Bowles/ORGANIZATION 2014/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O ./O 
We/O refer/O to/O this/O method/O as/O the/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O ./O 
A/O main/O drawback/O of/O the/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O is/O that/O it/O assumes/O occupations/O to/O be/O similar/O across/O countries/O ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O direct/O correspondences/O between/O the/O occupational/O classifications/O of/O these/O countries/O and/O the/O Standard/ORGANIZATION Occupational/ORGANIZATION Clas/ORGANIZATION sification/O -LRB-/O SOC/O -RRB-/O of/O the/O US/LOCATION typically/O do/O not/O exist/O ./O 
Finally/O ,/O FO/O assume/O that/O occupations/O can/O be/O automated/O ,/O assuming/O that/O workers/O within/O the/O same/O occupation/O have/O identical/O task/O structures/O ./O 
However/O ,/O workers/O '/O task/O structures/O differ/O remarkably/O within/O occupations/O -LRB-/O Autor/O and/O Handel/ORGANIZATION 2013/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O even/O within/O occupations/O ,/O workers/O likely/O are/O very/O differently/O exposed/O to/O automation/O depending/O on/O the/O tasks/O they/O perform/O ./O 
Therefore/O ,/O we/O follow/O an/O alternative/O task/O -/O based/O approach/O that/O copes/O with/O these/O issues/O ./O 
In/O short/O ,/O we/O esti/O mate/O the/O relevance/O of/O tasks/O for/O the/O automatibility/O of/O jobs/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION and/O use/O this/O empirical/O relationship/O to/O transfer/O the/O automatibility/O to/O other/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
In/O the/O remainder/O of/O the/O chapter/O ,/O we/O first/ORDINAL present/DATE the/O data/O and/O methodology/O ./O 
Then/O ,/O we/O present/DATE th/O e/O results/O of/O the/O task/O -/O based/O approach/O for/O the/O US/LOCATION ,/O before/O transferring/O the/O automatibility/O to/O other/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
A./ORGANIZATION Data/ORGANIZATION and/O Methodology/O 21/NUMBER ./O 
In/O this/O paper/O ,/O we/O follow/O a/O task/O -/O based/O approach/O to/O transfer/O the/O results/O by/O FO/O to/O other/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
The/O approach/O is/O based/O on/O the/O idea/O that/O the/O automatibility/O of/O jobs/O ultimately/O depends/O on/O the/O tasks/O which/O workers/O perform/O for/O these/O jobs/O ,/O and/O how/O easily/O these/O tasks/O can/O be/O automated/O ./O 
We/O therefore/O estimate/O the/O relationship/O between/O workp/O lace/O tasks/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION and/O the/O automatibility/O by/O FO/O ./O 
We/O then/O use/O this/O statistical/O relationship/O to/O transfer/O the/O automatibility/O to/O jobs/O in/O other/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
At/O first/ORDINAL sight/O ,/O this/O procedure/O has/O some/O similarities/O with/O the/O analysis/O of/O FO/O ,/O who/O estimate/O how/O the/O experts/O '/O assessment/O of/O the/O automatibility/O at/O the/O occupational/O level/O is/O related/O to/O some/O bottleneck/O -/O tasks/O ,/O to/O transfer/O these/O results/O to/O other/O occupations/O ./O 
However/O ,/O while/O they/O use/O only/O a/O limited/O set/O of/O bottleneck/O -/O tasks/O that/O reflect/O average/O task/O structures/O at/O the/O occupational/O level/O ,/O we/O rely/O on/O individual/O survey/O data/O regarding/O a/O comprehensive/O list/O of/O tasks/O that/O people/O actually/O perform/O at/O their/O workplace/O ./O 
Using/O individual/O -/O level/O data/O ,/O we/O thus/O take/O into/O account/O that/O individuals/O within/O the/O same/O occupation/O often/O perf/O orm/O quite/O different/O tasks/O ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O the/O task/O structures/O are/O self/O -/O reported/O by/O the/O individuals/O and/O thus/O likely/O a/O better/O indicator/O of/O workers/O '/O actual/O tasks/O ./O 
22/NUMBER ./O 
The/O analysis/O is/O based/O on/O data/O from/O the/O Programme/O for/O the/O I/O nternational/O Assessment/O of/O Adult/O Competencies/O -LRB-/O PIAAC/O -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O PIAAC/O data/O is/O a/O unique/O data/O source/O which/O contains/O micro/O -/O level/O indicators/O on/O socio/O -/O economic/O characteristics/O ,/O skills/O ,/O job/O -/O related/O information/O ,/O job/O -/O tasks/O and/O competencies/O ./O 
Most/O importantly/O ,/O the/O data/O i/O s/O comparable/O across/O the/O countries/O in/O the/O program/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O the/O data/O also/O allows/O for/O relaxing/O the/O assumption/O that/O task/O structures/O are/O the/O same/O across/O countries/O ./O 
23/NUMBER ./O 
To/O implement/O our/O task/O -/O based/O approach/O ,/O we/O estimate/O the/O r/O elationship/O between/O workers/O '/O tasks/O and/O the/O automatibility/O of/O jobs/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION ./O 
For/O this/O we/O match/O the/O automatibility/O indicator/O by/O FO/O to/O the/O US/LOCATION observations/O in/O the/O PIAAC/O data/O based/O on/O the/O occupational/O codes/O ./O 
As/O only/O 2/NUMBER -/O digit/O ISCO/ORGANIZATION codes/O are/O available/O in/O the/O PIAA/ORGANIZATION C/O ,/O an/O assignment/O problem/O arises/O ./O 
We/O therefore/O assign/O multiple/O values/O of/O the/O automatibility/O to/O each/O individual/O in/O the/O PIAAC/O data/O and/O follow/O a/O multiple/O imputation/O approach/O ./O 
For/O each/O individual/O in/O the/O PIACC/O data/O ,/O we/O identify/O the/O automatibility/O with/O the/O highes/O t/O probability/O based/O on/O this/O method/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O we/O follow/O Ibrahim/O -LRB-/O 1990/DATE -RRB-/O and/O implement/O the/O following/O Expectation/O -/O Maximization/O -LRB-/O EM/O -RRB-/O algorithm/O :/O DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 13/NUMBER -LRB-/O 1/NUMBER -RRB-/O In/O a/O first/ORDINAL step/O ,/O we/O regress/O the/O automatibility/O y/O on/O the/O N/O characteristics/O x/O of/O the/O jobs/O :/O &#3627408486;/O &#3627408470;/O &#3627408471;/O =/O ?/O &#55349;/O &#57085;/O &#55349;/O &#56411;/O &#3627408485;/O &#3627408470;/O &#55349;/O &#56411;/O +/O &#55349;/O &#57110;/O &#3627408470;/O &#3627408471;/O &#55349;/O &#56385;/O &#55349;/O &#56411;/O =/O 1/NUMBER where/O i/O are/O the/O individuals/O in/O the/O PIAAC/O -/O data/O and/O j/O are/O the/O duplicates/O of/O these/O individuals/O ,/O since/O multiple/O automatibilities/O yij/O are/O assigned/O to/O each/O individual/O i./O ?n/O are/O the/O parameters/O to/O be/O estimated/O ,/O which/O represent/O the/O influence/O of/O the/O jo/O b-related/O characteristics/O on/O the/O automatibility/O of/O each/O job/O ./O 
The/O automatibility/O is/O restricted/O to/O the/O interval/O 0/PERCENT %/PERCENT to/O 100/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
We/O use/O the/O Generalized/O Linear/O Model/O -LRB-/O GLM/O -RRB-/O by/O Papke/PERSON and/O Wooldridge/PERSON -LRB-/O 1996/DATE -RRB-/O where/O the/O dependent/O variable/O of/O the/O model/O is/O transferred/O to/O a/O non/O -/O restricted/O interval/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O we/O take/O into/O account/O two/NUMBER weights/O which/O we/O connect/O multiplicatively/O ./O 
The/O first/ORDINAL weight/O is/O necessary/O ,/O because/O we/O have/O duplicated/O the/O individuals/O in/O the/O dataset/O ./O 
This/O weight/O is/O therefore/O constructed/O such/O that/O it/O sums/O to/O u/O nity/O for/O each/O individual/O ./O 
For/O the/O initial/O step/O of/O the/O algorithm/O ,/O we/O set/O this/O weight/O to/O the/O inverse/O number/O of/O duplicates/O of/O each/O individual/O ./O 
The/O second/ORDINAL weight/O is/O the/O replication/O weight/O of/O the/O PIAAC/O data/O ./O 
-LRB-/O 2/NUMBER -RRB-/O In/O a/DURATION second/DURATION step/O ,/O we/O predict/O the/O automatibility/O yi?/O ./O 
Note/O that/O these/O values/O do/O not/O vary/O within/O individuals/O ,/O as/O the/O job/O -/O related/O characteristics/O xin/O are/O constant/O within/O individuals/O ./O 
By/O comparing/O the/O automatibilities/O yij/O and/O the/O predicted/O automatibility/O yi?/O we/O can/O determine/O the/O likelihood/O that/O yij/O ,/O given/O the/O job/O -/O related/O characteristics/O xin/O and/O the/O estimated/O model/O ,/O is/O the/O true/O automatibility/O ./O 
Based/O on/O this/O likelihood/O ,/O we/O recalculate/O the/O first/ORDINAL weight/O and/O continue/O with/O step/O 1/NUMBER -LRB-/O see/O Ibrahim/O 1990/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
3/NUMBER We/O run/O this/O algorithm/O until/O the/O weights/O converge/O ./O 
24/NUMBER ./O 
We/O implement/O this/O model/O for/O employed/O individuals/O based/O on/O US/LOCATION observations/O in/O the/O PIAAC/O data/O ,/O excluding/O armed/O forces/O and/O individuals/O with/O missing/O occupational/O information/O or/O individuals/O whose/O occupation/O is/O available/O only/O at/O the/O 1/NUMBER -/O digit/O ISCO/ORGANIZATION level/O ./O 
Our/O explanatory/O variables/O mostly/O cover/O indicators/O of/O workplace/O tasks/O ,/O but/O we/O further/O consider/O gender/O ,/O education/O ,/O competences/O ,/O income/O ,/O sector/O ,/O firm/O -/O size/O and/O further/O auxiliary/O variables/O ./O 
The/O explanatory/O variables/O and/O their/O descriptive/O statis/O tics/O are/O outlined/O in/O Table/O 2/NUMBER in/O Annex/ORGANIZATION A./ORGANIZATION Variable/ORGANIZATION definitions/O can/O also/O be/O found/O in/O Annex/O A/O ./O 
The/O model/O and/O estimated/O parameters/O then/O show/O the/O influence/O of/O the/O explanatory/O variables/O on/O the/O automatibility/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION ./O 
We/O then/O apply/O this/O model/O and/O the/O estimated/O parameters/O to/O the/O PIAAC/O data/O in/O other/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O to/O predict/O the/O automatibility/O for/O these/O countries/O ./O 
25/NUMBER ./O 
Through/O this/O procedure/O ,/O we/O take/O into/O account/O that/O not/O whole/O occupations/O ,/O but/O specific/O jobs/O are/O exposed/O to/O au/O tomatibility/O ,/O depending/O on/O the/O tasks/O performed/O at/O these/O particular/O jobs/O ./O 
The/O procedure/O is/O based/O on/O the/O idea/O that/O jobs/O with/O larger/O shares/O of/O automatable/O tasks/O are/O more/O exposed/O to/O automatibility/O than/O jobs/O with/O larger/O shares/O of/O non/O -/O automatable/O tasks/O -LRB-/O bottlene/O cks/O ,/O using/O the/O wording/O of/O FO/O -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O procedure/O allows/O for/O differences/O in/O task/O -/O structures/O within/O occupations/O and/O specifically/O focuses/O on/O the/O individual/O job/O ./O 
This/O approach/O is/O less/O restrictive/O than/O the/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O ,/O which/O relies/O on/O the/O assumption/O t/O hat/O occupational/O task/O structures/O are/O identical/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION and/O other/O countries/O ./O 
However/O ,/O with/O this/O procedure/O we/O assume/O that/O workers/O with/O the/O same/O task/O structure/O face/O the/O same/O automatibility/O in/O all/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
Any/O differences/O of/O automatibilities/O between/O t/O he/O countries/O then/O originate/O from/O differences/O in/O task/O structures/O or/O other/O explanatory/O variables/O between/O the/O countries/O ./O 
3/NUMBER ./O 
More/O precisely/O ,/O the/O first/ORDINAL weights/O &#3627408484;/O &#3627408470;/O &#3627408471;/O are/O calculated/O as/O &#3627408484;/O &#3627408470;/O &#3627408471;/O =/O &#55349;/O &#56403;/O -LRB-/O &#3627408486;/O &#55349;/O &#56406;/O ?/O ?/O &#3627408486;/O &#3627408470;/O &#3627408471;/O |/O &#3627408485;/O &#3627408470;/O &#55349;/O &#56411;/O ,/O &#55349;/O &#57085;/O &#55349;/O &#56411;/O -RRB-/O ?/O &#55349;/O &#56403;/O -LRB-/O &#3627408486;/O &#55349;/O &#56406;/O ?/O ?/O &#3627408486;/O &#3627408470;/O &#3627408471;/O |/O &#3627408485;/O &#3627408470;/O &#55349;/O &#56411;/O ,/O &#55349;/O &#57085;/O &#55349;/O &#56411;/O -RRB-/O &#55349;/O &#56381;/O &#3627408471;/O =/O 1/NUMBER where/O f/O -LRB-/O ./O -RRB-/O 
is/O the/O standard/O normal/O density/O ./O 
This/O is/O based/O on/O equation/O 3.4/NUMBER in/O Ibrahim/O -LRB-/O 1990/DATE -RRB-/O and/O follows/O from/O Bayes/LOCATION theorem/O ./O 
Note/O that/O Ibrahim/O -LRB-/O 1990/DATE -RRB-/O presents/O the/O EM/O algorithm/O for/O the/O case/O of/O missing/O explanatory/O va/O riables/O ,/O but/O the/O procedure/O can/O also/O be/O applied/O to/O missing/O dependent/O variables/O ,/O as/O in/O our/O case/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 14/NUMBER B./O Results/O for/O the/O US/LOCATION 26/NUMBER ./O 
We/O present/DATE the/O main/O results/O for/O the/O US/LOCATION below/O ,/O the/O detailed/O results/O of/O our/O mo/DURATION del/O can/O be/O found/O in/O Annex/O B/O ./O 
Overall/O ,/O we/O find/O that/O the/O automatibility/O of/O jobs/O is/O lower/O in/O jobs/O with/O high/O educational/O job/O requirements/O or/O jobs/O which/O require/O cooperation/O with/O other/O employees/O or/O where/O people/O spend/O more/O time/O on/O influencing/O others/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O the/O l/O ow/O -/O risk/O tasks/O partially/O reflect/O what/O FO/O called/O engineering/O bottlenecks/O ./O 
The/O automatibility/O is/O higher/O in/O jobs/O with/O a/O high/O share/O of/O tasks/O that/O are/O related/O to/O exchanging/O information/O ,/O selling/O or/O using/O fingers/O and/O hands/O ./O 
This/O resembles/O the/O evidence/O from/O the/O tas/O k-based/O literature/O which/O argues/O that/O so-called/O routine/O tasks/O are/O subject/O to/O automation/O ,/O whereas/O interactive/O or/O cognitive/O tasks/O are/O less/O likely/O to/O be/O substituted/O by/O machines/O and/O computers/O -LRB-/O see/O Acemoglu/PERSON and/O Autor/O -LRB-/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O or/O Autor/O -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O for/O an/O overview/O of/O the/O literature/O -RRB-/O ./O 
27/NUMBER ./O 
Figure/O 2/NUMBER compares/O the/O predicted/O automatibility/O of/O jobs/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION using/O the/O PIAAC/O data/O when/O applying/O the/O task/O -/O and/O the/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O ./O 
For/O the/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O ,/O we/O matched/O all/O pote/O ntial/O FO/O -/O values/O to/O each/O individual/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION -/O PIAAC/O -/O data/O based/O on/O the/O 2/NUMBER -/O digit/O ISCO/ORGANIZATION occupation/O ./O 
4/NUMBER The/O result/O strongly/O resembles/O the/O bi/O -/O polar/O structure/O which/O is/O known/O from/O FO/O and/O shown/O in/O Figure/O 1/NUMBER --/O the/O majority/O of/O jobs/O is/O assigned/O either/O a/O very/O high/O or/O a/O very/O low/O automatibility/O ,/O only/O few/O jobs/O have/O a/O medium/O automatibility/O ./O 
In/O contrast/O ,/O the/O result/O from/O the/O task/O -/O based/O approach/O show/O a/O very/O different/O pattern/O --/O the/O two/NUMBER poles/O of/O the/O distribution/O move/O to/O less/O extreme/O values/O of/O the/O automatibility/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O fewer/O jobs/O hav/O e/O either/O very/O high/O or/O very/O low/O values/O of/O automatibility/O when/O taking/O into/O account/O the/O variation/O of/O task/O -/O structures/O within/O occupations/O ./O 
As/O a/O result/O ,/O only/O 9/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O all/O individuals/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION face/O a/O high/O automatibility/O ,/O i.e./O an/O automatibility/O of/O at/O least/O 70/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
This/O figure/O stands/O in/O contrast/O to/O FO/O ,/O who/O argue/O that/O 47/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O US/O jobs/O are/O at/O high/O risk/O of/O being/O automated/O ./O 
Apparently/O ,/O not/O taking/O account/O of/O the/O variation/O of/O tasks/O within/O occupations/O exerts/O a/O huge/O impact/O on/O the/O estimated/O automatibility/O of/O jobs/O ./O 
This/O is/O because/O e/O ven/O in/O occupations/O that/O FO/O expect/O to/O be/O at/O a/O high/O risk/O of/O automation/O ,/O people/O often/O perform/O tasks/O which/O are/O hard/O to/O automate/O ,/O such/O as/O for/O example/O interactive/O tasks/O -LRB-/O e.g./O group/O work/O or/O face/O -/O to-face/O interactions/O with/O customers/O ,/O clients/O ,/O etc./O -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O can/O be/O ill/O ustrated/O by/O two/NUMBER examples/O :/O According/O to/O FO/O ,/O people/O working/O in/O the/O occupation/O ``/O Bookkeeping/O ,/O Accounting/O ,/O and/O Auditing/O Clerks/O ''/O -LRB-/O SOC/O code/O :/O 43/NUMBER -3031/NUMBER -RRB-/O face/O an/O automation/O potential/O of/O 98/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
However/O ,/O only/O 24/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O all/O employees/O in/O this/O occupation/O can/O perform/O their/O job/O with/O neither/O group/O work/O nor/O face/O -/O to-face/O interactions/O ./O 
According/O to/O FO/O ,/O people/O working/O in/O the/O occupation/O ``/O Retail/O Salesperson/O ''/O -LRB-/O SOC/O code/O 41/NUMBER -2031/NUMBER -RRB-/O face/O an/O automation/O potential/O of/O 92/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
Despite/O this/O ,/O only/O 4/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O retail/O salespersons/O perform/O their/O jobs/O with/O neith/O er/O both/O group/O work/O nor/O face/O -/O to-face/O interactions/O ./O 
5/NUMBER 4/NUMBER ./O 
For/O the/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O ,/O we/O matched/O all/O potential/O FO/O -/O values/O to/O each/O individual/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION -/O PIAAC/O -/O data/O based/O on/O the/O 2/NUMBER -/O digit/O ISCO/ORGANIZATION occupation/O ./O 
Each/O indi/O vidual/O is/O assigned/O multiple/O FO/O -/O values/O due/O to/O the/O assignment/O problem/O ./O 
We/O equally/O weight/O each/O observation/O within/O each/O individual/O ./O 
5/NUMBER ./O 
These/O results/O are/O based/O on/O the/O Princeton/ORGANIZATION Data/ORGANIZATION Improvement/ORGANIZATION Initiative/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O PDII/O -RRB-/O ./O 
We/O rely/O on/O this/O data/O rather/O than/O the/O PIAAC/O ,/O bec/ORGANIZATION ause/O in/O the/O PDII/O 6/NUMBER -/O digit/O SOC/O codes/O are/O available/O ,/O which/O allows/O us/O to/O circumvent/O the/O assignment/O problem/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 15/NUMBER Figure/O 2/NUMBER ./O 
Distribution/O of/O Automatibility/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION -LRB-/O Task/O -/O Based/O vs./O Occupation/O -/O Based/O Approach/O -RRB-/O Source/O :/O Authors/O '/O calculation/O based/O on/O the/O Survey/O of/O Adult/O Skills/O -LRB-/O PIAAC/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O 28/NUMBER ./O 
In/O conclusion/O ,/O using/O information/O on/O task/O -/O usage/O at/O the/O individual/O level/O leads/O to/O significantly/O lower/O estimates/O of/O jobs/O ``/O at/O risk/O ''/O ,/O since/O workers/O in/O occupations/O with/O --/O according/O to/O FO/O --/O high/O automatibilities/O neverthe/O less/O often/O perform/O tasks/O which/O are/O hard/O to/O automate/O ./O 
C./O Results/O for/O other/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O 29/NUMBER ./O 
Figure/O 3/NUMBER 3/NUMBER shows/O the/O share/O of/O workers/O at/O high/O risk/O by/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ,/O i.e./O the/O share/O of/O workers/O whose/O automatibility/O is/O at/O least/O 70/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
This/O share/O is/O highest/O in/O Germany/LOCATION and/O Austria/LOCATION -LRB-/O 12/PERCENT %/PERCENT -RRB-/O ,/O while/O it/O is/O lowest/O in/O Korea/LOCATION and/O Estonia/LOCATION -LRB-/O 6/PERCENT %/PERCENT -RRB-/O ./O 
6/NUMBER The/O results/O for/O Germany/LOCATION are/O very/O similar/O to/O the/O results/O of/O a/O recent/O representative/O survey/O among/O German/O employees/O ,/O where/O 13/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O employees/O consider/O it/O likely/O or/O highly/O likely/O that/O their/O job/O w/O ill/O be/O replaced/O by/O machines/O -LRB-/O BMAS/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O o/O ur/O results/O for/O Germany/LOCATION are/O comparable/O to/O a/O r/O ecent/O study/O by/O Dengler/PERSON and/O Matthes/PERSON -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O who/O use/O a/O different/O methodological/O approach/O but/O also/O find/O that/O 15/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O all/O jobs/O in/O Germany/LOCATION are/O at/O risk/O of/O automation/O ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O they/O also/O find/O a/O bi/O -/O polar/O distribution/O of/O auto/O matibility/O with/O moderate/O polaris/O ation/O ./O 
6/NUMBER ./O 
We/O exclude/O the/O Russian/ORGANIZATION Federation/ORGANIZATION from/O our/O sample/O ./O 
This/O is/O because/O when/O we/O restrict/O the/O Russian/O PIAAC/O sample/O to/O those/O observations/O where/O all/O relevan/O t/O variables/O are/O non/O -/O missing/O ,/O then/O the/O distribution/O of/O these/O variables/O is/O not/O representative/O ./O 
The/O results/O for/O Canada/LOCATION should/O be/O treated/O with/O some/O caution/O ,/O as/O relevant/O explanatory/O variables/O for/O extrapolating/O the/O automatibility/O are/O missing/O ,/O see/O Annex/O B/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 16/NUMBER Figure/O 3/NUMBER ./O 
Share/O of/O Workers/O with/O High/O Automatibility/O by/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Countries/O Source/O :/O Authors/O '/O calculation/O based/O on/O the/O Survey/O of/O Adult/O Skills/O -LRB-/O PIAAC/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O 30/NUMBER ./O 
An/O interesting/O result/O from/O Figure/O 3/NUMBER is/O that/O the/O distribution/O of/O automatibility/O across/O countries/O does/O not/O lend/O itself/O to/O an/O immediate/O interpretation/O of/O potential/O underlying/O factors/O ./O 
To/O gain/O deeper/O insights/O into/O the/O underlying/O reasons/O for/O these/O country/O differences/O ,/O we/O decompose/O the/O difference/O of/O the/O share/O of/O workers/O at/O high/O risk/O between/O each/O country/O and/O the/O US/LOCATION into/O a/O within/O -/O and/O between/O -/O industry/O component/O regarding/O three/NUMBER dimensions/O :/O industry/O ,/O occupation/O ,/O and/O education/O ./O 
7/NUMBER In/O each/O case/O ,/O the/O between/O -/O component/O reflects/O the/O difference/O in/O automatibili/O ty/O that/O is/O due/O to/O the/O cross/O -/O country/O difference/O in/O industry/O ,/O occupation/O or/O educational/O structure/O ,/O while/O the/O within/O -/O component/O reflects/O the/O difference/O in/O automatibility/O that/O is/O due/O to/O the/O fact/O that/O workers/O in/O the/O same/O industries/O ,/O occupations/O ,/O or/O education/O gro/O up/O perform/O more/O -LRB-/O or/O fewer/O -RRB-/O automatable/O tasks/O ./O 
31/NUMBER ./O 
The/O results/O in/O Table/O 1/NUMBER show/O that/O differences/O in/O industry/O and/O occupational/O structures/O explain/O only/O little/O of/O the/O differences/O in/O the/O share/O of/O workers/O at/O high/O risk/O between/O each/O country/O and/O the/O US/LOCATION ,/O as/O the/O between/O -/O industry/O and/O -/O occupation/O components/O matter/O only/O little/O for/O most/O count/O ries/O ./O 
Instead/O ,/O workers/O in/O the/O same/O industries/O and/O occupations/O perform/O differently/O automatable/O tasks/O in/O these/O countries/O than/O workers/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION ./O 
However/O ,/O education/O plays/O a/O large/O role/O for/O many/O countries/O ./O 
In/O most/O countries/O ,/O the/O within/O -/O education/O component/O is/O ne/O gative/O ,/O which/O implies/O that/O people/O with/O the/O same/O education/O typically/O perform/O less/O 7/NUMBER ./O 
To/O compute/O the/O between/O -/O industry/O component/O ,/O we/O first/ORDINAL assign/O weights/O to/O each/O individual/O ./O 
These/O weights/O are/O the/O same/O for/O all/O individuals/O of/O the/O same/O industry/O ./O 
We/O choose/O the/O weights/O such/O that/O the/O share/O of/O workers/O by/O industry/O of/O each/O country/O resembles/O the/O US/LOCATION indu/O stry/O structure/O ./O 
We/O then/O recalculate/O the/O share/O of/O workers/O at/O high/O risk/O and/O calculate/O the/O difference/O of/O this/O figure/O to/O the/O original/O share/O of/O workers/O at/O high/O risk/O in/O each/O country/O ./O 
This/O difference/O resembles/O the/O between/O -/O component/O ./O 
The/O remaining/O difference/O of/O th/O e/O country/O to/O the/O US/LOCATION -/O figures/O then/O resembles/O the/O within/O -/O component/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 17/NUMBER automatable/O tasks/O compared/O to/O the/O US/LOCATION ./O 
However/O ,/O in/O many/O countries/O the/O between/O -/O education/O component/O is/O positive/O ,/O which/O implies/O that/O in/O those/O countries/O a/O larger/O share/O of/O workers/O h/O as/O educational/O levels/O which/O are/O associated/O with/O more/O automatable/O tasks/O -LRB-/O i.e./O low/O or/O medium/O qualified/O workers/O -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O is/O because/O the/O US/LOCATION has/O a/O larger/O share/O of/O highly/O educated/O workers/O ,/O who/O typically/O perform/O fewer/O automatable/O tasks/O ./O 
These/O results/O also/O hold/O when/O focusing/O on/O educational/O requirements/O of/O the/O jobs/O rather/O than/O actual/O education/O ./O 
8/NUMBER Table/O 1/NUMBER ./O 
Decomposition/O of/O Country/O Differences/O in/O the/O Share/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Workers/ORGANIZATION at/O High/O Risk/O Source/O :/O Authors/O '/O calculation/O based/O on/O the/O Survey/O of/O Adult/O Skills/O -LRB-/O PIAAC/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O 32/NUMBER ./O 
As/O an/O example/O ,/O in/O Austria/LOCATION ,/O workers/O perform/O typically/O fewer/O automatable/O tasks/O compared/O to/O US/LOCATION -/O workers/O with/O the/O same/O educational/O level/O ,/O but/O Aus/O tria/O has/O a/O higher/O share/O of/O low/O -/O and/O medium/O -/O skilled/O workers/O which/O perform/O more/O automatable/O tasks/O ./O 
Since/O the/O latter/O effect/O dominates/O ,/O Austria/LOCATION has/O on/O aggregate/O a/O larger/O share/O of/O workers/O at/O high/O risk/O ./O 
In/O Korea/LOCATION ,/O in/O contrast/O ,/O both/O effects/O are/O negative/O ,/O which/O imp/O lies/O that/O Koreans/O both/O perform/O fewer/O automatable/O tasks/O at/O each/O educational/O level/O compared/O to/O the/O US/LOCATION ,/O and/O a/O larger/O share/O of/O Korean/O workers/O achieved/O educational/O levels/O which/O are/O associated/O with/O fewer/O automatable/O tasks/O compared/O to/O the/O US/LOCATION ./O 
33/NUMBER ./O 
Hence/O ,/O we/O can/O conclude/O that/O cross/O -/O country/O differences/O often/O reflect/O that/O individuals/O in/O the/O same/O industry/O ,/O occupation/O or/O even/O education/O group/O perform/O different/O tasks/O ./O 
But/O what/O might/O be/O the/O reason/O behind/O such/O differences/O ?/O 
In/O the/O follo/O wing/O ,/O we/O aim/O to/O briefly/O discuss/O two/NUMBER potential/O explanations/O :/O -LRB-/O 1/NUMBER -RRB-/O general/O diff/O erences/O in/O the/O workplace/O organis/O ation/O ,/O and/O -LRB-/O 2/NUMBER -RRB-/O differences/O in/O the/O adoption/O of/O new/O technologies/O ./O 
34/NUMBER ./O 
In/O order/O to/O illustrate/O the/O first/ORDINAL reason/O ,/O consider/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O two/NUMBER countries/O A/O and/O B/O which/O have/O adopted/O comparable/O technologies/O ./O 
The/O automatibility/O might/O nevertheless/O be/O higher/O in/O country/O A/O than/O in/O coun/O try/O B/O ,/O because/O workplace/O organis/O ation/O in/O country/O A/O generally/O relies/O less/O on/O group/O work/O or/O fac/O e-to-face/O interactions/O than/O country/O B/O ./O 
This/O is/O illustrated/O in/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER ,/O which/O shows/O the/O relationship/O between/O the/O share/O 8/NUMBER ./O 
Results/O are/O available/O upon/O request/O ./O 
w/O ithin/O betw/O een/O w/O ithin/O betw/O een/O w/O ithin/O betw/O een/O Austria/LOCATION 3.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT 3.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT -2.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT 5.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT Belgium/O -1.9/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT -3.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT Canada/O 0.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.9/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT Czech/O Republic/O 1.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT -2.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT 3.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT Denmark/PERCENT -0.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT -3.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2.9/PERCENT %/PERCENT Estonia/PERCENT -2.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT -3.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT -2.9/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT Finland/O -2.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT -2.9/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT -3.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.9/PERCENT %/PERCENT -2.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT France/O -0.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT Germany/O 3.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT 3.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT 3.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT Ireland/PERCENT -0.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT Italy/O 0.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT -3.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT 4.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT Japan/O -1.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT -2.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.9/PERCENT %/PERCENT Korea/PERCENT -3.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT -2.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT -3.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT Netherlands/O 0.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.9/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT -4.9/PERCENT %/PERCENT 5.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT Norway/O 1.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT -3.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT 4.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT Poland/PERCENT -1.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT -3.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT -2.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT Slovak/O Republic/O 1.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT Spain/O 2.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT 4.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT Sweden/O -1.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.0/PERCENT %/PERCENT -4.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT United/O Kingdom/O 1.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT -0.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT 0.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT 1.2/PERCENT %/PERCENT -1.3/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2.6/PERCENT %/PERCENT D/O ifference/O to/O the/O U/O S/O Industries/O O/O ccupations/O Education/O Country/O DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 18/NUMBER of/O people/O at/O high/O risk/O and/O the/O incidence/O of/O communication/O tasks/O at/O the/O country/O level/O ./O 
On/O average/O ,/O countries/O which/O have/O a/O stronger/O focus/O o/O n/O communicative/O tasks/O in/O their/O workplace/O organis/O ation/O also/O have/O a/O lower/O share/O of/O jobs/O at/O high/O risk/O ./O 
For/O instance/O ,/O jobs/O in/O Italy/LOCATION and/O Germany/LOCATION show/O low/O degrees/O of/O communication/O ,/O whereas/O jobs/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION and/O UK/O are/O more/O communicative/O ./O 
Overall/O ,/O the/O analysis/O shows/O that/O genuine/O differences/O in/O workplace/O organis/O ation/O are/O relevant/O for/O differences/O in/O automatibilities/O between/O countries/O ./O 
Figure/O 4/NUMBER ./O 
Automatibility/O and/O Communicating/O Source/O :/O Authors/O '/O calculation/O based/O on/O the/O Survey/O of/O Adult/O Skills/O -LRB-/O PIAAC/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O 35/NUMBER ./O 
To/O illustrate/O the/O second/ORDINAL reason/O ,/O assume/O that/O there/O are/O no/O genuine/O differences/O in/O the/O workplace/O organis/O ation/O of/O countries/O A/O and/O B/O ./O 
The/O autom/O atibility/O of/O country/O A/O might/O still/O be/O higher/O than/O in/O country/O B/O ,/O because/O country/O B/O invests/O stronger/O in/O new/O automation/O technologies/O and/O has/O hence/O already/O replaced/O labour/O by/O capital/O for/O performing/O the/O automatable/O tasks/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O the/O automatibility/O is/O lower/O in/O countries/O which/O already/O invest/O a/O lot/O in/O ICT/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O see/O Figure/O 5/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O a/O high/O automatibility/O may/O reflect/O an/O unused/O potential/O for/O automation/O ./O 
Whether/O an/O extended/O use/O of/O automation/O technologies/O comes/O with/O beneficial/O or/O adverse/O effects/O on/O workers/O is/O unclear/O ex/O an/O te/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 19/NUMBER Figure/O 5/NUMBER ./O 
ICT/ORGANIZATION Investments/ORGANIZATION and/O Automatibility/O Source/O :/O Authors/O '/O calculation/O based/O on/O the/O Survey/O of/O Adult/O Skills/O -LRB-/O PIAAC/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O 36/NUMBER ./O 
Overall/O ,/O we/O can/O conclude/O that/O comparing/O the/O automatibilities/O between/O countries/O is/O not/O straightforward/O and/O necessitates/O further/O insights/O into/O a/O country/O 's/O adoption/O of/O new/O technologies/O ,/O its/O economic/O and/O educational/O structure/O ,/O its/O workplace/O organis/O ation/O and/O t/O he/O resulting/O task/O structures/O ./O 
Education/O and/O in/O particular/O the/O educational/O structure/O of/O the/O workers/O seem/O to/O play/O a/O large/O role/O ./O 
Countries/O with/O a/O strong/O focus/O on/O high/O qualified/O workers/O typically/O have/O lower/O shares/O of/O workers/O at/O high/O risk/O ,/O since/O these/O workers/O typically/O perform/O fewer/O automatable/O tasks/O than/O low/O qualified/O workers/O ./O 
We/O therefore/O focus/O on/O the/O relationship/O between/O education/O and/O automatibility/O ,/O below/O ./O 
37/NUMBER ./O 
Despite/O the/O cross/O -/O country/O differences/O ,/O a/O main/O feature/O of/O all/O countries/O is/O that/O the/O automatibility/O strongly/O decreases/O in/O the/O level/O of/O education/O and/O in/O the/O income/O of/O the/O workers/O :/O It/O is/O mostly/O low/O skilled/O and/O low/O -/O income/O individuals/O who/O face/O a/O high/O risk/O of/O being/O automatable/O ./O 
This/O is/O shown/O in/O Figure/O 6/NUMBER and/O Figure/O 7/NUMBER for/O a/O weighted/O average/O 9/NUMBER of/O all/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
Results/O for/O the/O individual/O countries/O can/O be/O found/O in/O Annex/O C./O 9/NUMBER ./O 
The/O figures/O are/O based/O on/O weighted/O data/O ,/O so/O that/O large/O countries/O have/O a/O larger/O influence/O on/O the/O results/O ./O 
Nevertheless/O ,/O the/O results/O are/O very/O similar/O when/O using/O unweighted/O data/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 20/NUMBER Figure/O 6/NUMBER ./O 
Share/O of/O Workers/O with/O High/O Automatibility/O by/O Education/O Source/O :/O Authors/O '/O calculation/O based/O on/O the/O Su/O rvey/O of/O Adult/O Skills/O -LRB-/O PIAAC/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O Figure/O 7/NUMBER ./O 
Share/O of/O Workers/O with/O High/O Automatibility/O by/O Income/O Source/O :/O Authors/O '/O calculation/O based/O on/O the/O Survey/O of/O Adult/O Skills/O -LRB-/O PIAAC/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 21/NUMBER INTERPRETATION/O AND/O C/O RITIQUE/O 38/NUMBER ./O 
As/O discussed/O ,/O FO/O predict/O that/O technologies/O allow/O for/O automating/O a/O substantial/O share/O of/O jobs/O within/O the/DURATION next/DURATION two/DURATION decades/DURATION ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O they/O assume/O that/O this/O process/O continues/O beyond/O the/O most/O -/O prone/O jobs/O in/O the/O medium/O run/O and/O ultimately/O affects/O even/O those/O tha/O t/O today/DATE appear/O to/O be/O relatively/O safe/O from/O automation/O ./O 
As/O discussed/O in/O the/O last/O chapter/O ,/O applying/O a/O task/O -/O based/O approach/O that/O takes/O account/O of/O the/O heterogeneity/O of/O workplace/O tasks/O within/O occupations/O already/O strongly/O reduces/O the/O predicted/O share/O of/O jobs/O that/O a/O re/O at/O a/O high/O risk/O of/O automation/O ./O 
This/O deviating/O result/O clearly/O sounds/O a/O note/O of/O caution/O regarding/O the/O interpretation/O of/O such/O predictions/O ./O 
Apparently/O ,/O the/O mere/O fact/O that/O FO/O chose/O an/O occupation/O -/O based/O approach/O that/O abstracts/O from/O within/O -/O occupation/O variation/O i/O n/O the/O tasks/O performed/O and/O that/O transfers/O the/O expert/O assessments/O for/O 70/NUMBER occupations/O to/O the/O remaining/O occupations/O based/O on/O only/O three/NUMBER engineering/O bottlenecks/O and/O nine/NUMBER related/O tasks/O ,/O has/O a/O strong/O effect/O on/O the/O outcome/O ./O 
39/NUMBER ./O 
However/O ,/O even/O for/O the/O less/O restrictive/O task/O -/O based/O approach/O ,/O there/O are/O good/O reasons/O to/O be/O cautious/O when/O interpreting/O the/O results/O ./O 
Firstly/O ,/O the/O approach/O still/O reflects/O technological/O capabilities/O based/O on/O experts/O '/O assessments/O rather/O than/O the/O actual/O uti/O lis/O ation/O of/O such/O technologies/O ,/O which/O might/O lead/O an/O overestimation/O of/O job/O automatibility/O ./O 
Secondly/O ,/O even/O when/O new/O technologies/O are/O increasingly/O used/O ,/O the/O effect/O this/O has/O on/O employment/O prospects/O depends/O on/O whether/O workplaces/O adjust/O to/O a/O new/O division/O of/O labour/O o/O r/O not/O ./O 
Workers/O might/O adjust/O by/O increasingly/O performing/O tasks/O that/O are/O complemented/O by/O the/O new/O technologies/O ./O 
Thirdly/O ,/O the/O approach/O considers/O only/O existing/O jobs/O ./O 
Yet/O ,/O the/O use/O of/O these/O technologies/O is/O likely/O to/O create/O new/O jobs/O ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O new/O technologies/O may/O also/O exert/O positive/O effects/O on/O labour/O demand/O if/O they/O raise/O product/O demand/O due/O to/O an/O improved/O competitiveness/O and/O a/O positive/O effect/O on/O worker/O 's/O incomes/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O workplaces/O are/O likely/O to/O be/O less/O ``/O at/O risk/O ''/O than/O suspected/O at/O first/ORDINAL sight/O ./O 
In/O the/O following/O ,/O we/O di/O scuss/O these/O three/NUMBER aspects/O in/O more/O detail/O ./O 
A./O Overestimation/O of/O technological/O cap/O abilities/O and/O its/O lagging/O utilis/O ation/O 40/NUMBER ./O 
The/O experts/O assessing/O the/O automatibility/O of/O the/O 70/NUMBER occupations/O in/O the/O FO/O study/O were/O asked/O whether/O ``/O -LSB-/O .../O -RSB-/O the/O tasks/O of/O this/O job/O -LSB-/O can/O -RSB-/O be/O sufficiently/O specified/O conditional/O on/O the/O availability/O of/O big/O data/O ,/O to/O be/O performed/O by/O state/O of/O the/O art/O computer/O -/O controlled/O equipment/O ``/O -LRB-/O Frey/PERSON and/O Osborne/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE :/O 30/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
It/O is/O very/O likely/O that/O the/O resulting/O assessment/O overst/O ates/O technological/O possibilities/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL of/O all/O ,/O experts/O tend/O to/O overestimate/O the/O potential/O of/O new/O technologies/O -LRB-/O Autor/O 2014/DATE ,/O 2015/DATE ,/O Pfeiffer/PERSON and/O Suphan/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O the/O comparative/O advantage/O of/O machines/O as/O compared/O to/O workers/O is/O typically/O overstated/O for/O tasks/O involving/O flexibility/O ,/O power/O of/O judgement/O and/O common/O sense/O ./O 
More/O generally/O ,/O the/O classification/O of/O occupations/O or/O tasks/O into/O the/O distinct/O domains/O automatable/O and/O not/O -/O automatable/O is/O problematic/O -LRB-/O Green/O 2012/DATE ,/O Rohrbach/PERSON -/O Schmidt/PERSON and/O Tiemann/PERSON 2013/DATE ,/O Pfeif/O fer/O and/O Suphan/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
10/NUMBER In/O addition/O ,/O most/O jobs/O are/O probably/O not/O sufficiently/O well/O defined/O to/O be/O actually/O substituted/O by/O machines/O ./O 
As/O Pratt/O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O states/O for/O the/O advances/O in/O robotics/O ``/O specialized/O robots/O will/O improve/O at/O performing/O well/O -/O defined/O tasks/O ,/O but/O in/O t/O he/O real/O world/O ,/O there/O are/O far/O more/O problems/O yet/O to/O be/O solved/O than/O ways/O presently/O known/O to/O solve/O them/O ''/O -LRB-/O Pratt/O 2015:52/O -RRB-/O ./O 
10/NUMBER ./O 
Green/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE ,/O p./O 41/NUMBER -RRB-/O finds/O that/O the/O classification/O of/O tasks/O into/O the/O distinct/O domains/O ``/O routine/O ''/O -LRB-/O i.e./O automatable/O -RRB-/O and/O ``/O non/O -/O routine/O ''/O -LRB-/O i.e./O non/O -/O automatable/O -RRB-/O using/O UK/O data/O ./O 
Also/O Rohrbach/PERSON -/O Schmidt/PERSON and/O Tiemann/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O find/O that/O the/O results/O on/O the/O effects/O of/O technological/O change/O in/O Germany/LOCATION are/O sensitive/O to/O the/O subjective/O classification/O of/O tasks/O into/O either/O routine/O or/O non/O -/O routine/O ./O 
Pfeiffer/O and/O Suphan/O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE ,/O p./O 11/NUMBER -RRB-/O criticises/O that/O ``/O the/O reasons/O why/O specific/O tasks/O are/O characterized/O as/O ro/O utine/O or/O non/O -/O routine/O -LSB-/O .../O -RSB-/O are/O not/O clear/O ./O 
The/O decision/O process/O introduces/O a/O potential/O for/O circular/O reasoning/O because/O assignment/O follows/O an/O assumption/O already/O made/O about/O the/O likelihood/O of/O automation/O ./O ''/O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 22/NUMBER 41/NUMBER ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O the/O ne/O cessary/O condition/O for/O the/O utilis/O ation/O of/O these/O technologies/O in/O terms/O of/O data/O a/O nd/O computer/O availability/O may/O not/O be/O met/O ,/O at/O least/O not/O immediately/O ./O 
In/O fact/O ,/O a/O monitoring/O report/O on/O the/O digitalisation/O of/O the/O German/O economy/O for/O the/ORGANIZATION Federal/ORGANIZATION Ministry/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Affairs/ORGANIZATION recently/DATE revealed/O that/O the/O digitalisation/O of/O the/O manufacturing/O sector/O i/O s/O still/O rather/O low/O and/O will/O advance/O only/O slowly/O until/O 2020/DATE -LRB-/O Graumann/ORGANIZATION et/O al./O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O a/O recent/O survey/O among/O German/O firms/O by/O the/O ZEW/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O shows/O that/O only/O 18/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O all/O firms/O are/O familiar/O with/O the/O concept/O ``/O Industrie/O 4.0/NUMBER ''/O ,/O which/O is/O a/O project/O put/O forw/O ard/O by/O the/O German/O government/O to/O foster/O the/O digitalisation/O and/O interconnectedness/O of/O the/O German/O industry/O ./O 
Up/O to/O now/DATE ,/O only/O 4/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O firms/O have/O started/O or/O are/O about/O to/O start/O such/O projects/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O the/O utilis/O ation/O of/O technologies/O clearly/O lags/O behind/O the/O technologi/O cal/O possibilities/O ./O 
This/DATE may/DATE also/O be/O related/O to/O a/O shortage/O of/O qualified/O personnel/O that/O is/O able/O to/O handle/O these/O new/O technologies/O ,/O as/O the/O introduction/O of/O new/O technologies/O may/O require/O the/O supply/O of/O complementary/O skills/O on/O the/O labour/O market/O -LRB-/O Acemoglu/O 1998/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O Janssen/PERSON and/O Mohrenweiser/PERSON -LRB-/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O investigate/O the/O introduction/O of/O the/O new/O computer/O -/O based/O control/O system/O -LRB-/O Computerized/ORGANIZATION Numerical/ORGANIZATION Control/ORGANIZATION ,/O CNC/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O in/O the/O field/O of/O cutting/O machine/O operation/O into/O the/O German/O apprenticeship/O regulation/O ./O 
They/O find/O that/O this/O r/O egulatory/O change/O in/O the/O apprenticeship/O regulation/O negatively/O affected/O workers/O who/O graduated/O before/O this/O regulatory/O change/O ,/O and/O hence/O did/O not/O learn/O the/O use/O of/O the/O technology/O in/O their/O formal/O training/O ./O 
However/O ,/O only/O workers/O who/O switched/O their/O occupation/O after/O the/O change/O were/O negatively/O affected/O ,/O suggesting/O that/O the/O remaining/O workers/O learned/O the/O technology/O on/O the/O job/O ./O 
This/O indicates/O that/O the/O technology/O was/O only/O implemented/O by/O firms/O on/O a/O large/O scale/O after/O the/O application/O of/O the/O CNC/ORGANIZATION technology/O had/O been/O introduced/O to/O the/O curricular/O of/O the/O apprenticeship/O training/O program/O ./O 
42/NUMBER ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O even/O if/O sufficiently/O qualified/O personnel/O were/O available/O ,/O firms/O decide/O on/O investing/O in/O new/O technologies/O depending/O on/O the/O relative/O factor/O pric/O es/O of/O capital/O and/O labour/O in/O performing/O a/O certain/O task/O in/O the/O production/O process/O ./O 
Although/O the/O literature/O on/O routine/O -/O biased/O technological/O change/O showed/O that/O the/O reduction/O in/O prices/O for/O computer/O capital/O reduced/O the/O demand/O for/O routine/O -/O intensive/O jobs/O ,/O it/O is/O no/O t/O clear/O when/O the/O break/O -/O even/O point/O for/O machines/O to/O perform/O more/O complex/O tasks/O will/O actually/O be/O reached/O ./O 
This/O will/O ,/O of/O course/O ,/O also/O depend/O on/O the/O wage/O level/O which/O itself/O is/O endogenous/O and/O would/O thus/O react/O to/O an/O excess/O labour/O supply/O by/O lowering/O wages/O ,/O hence/O i/O mproving/O worker/O 's/O employment/O prospects/O again/O ./O 
For/O this/O reason/O ,/O technological/O capabilities/O need/O not/O translate/O into/O technological/O obsolescence/O of/O human/O labour/O -LRB-/O cf./O Acemoglu/PERSON and/O Restrepo/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O empirical/O approach/O of/O FO/O clearly/O leaves/O aside/O many/O factors/O th/O at/O ultimately/O determine/O the/O decision/O to/O automate/O tasks/O and/O substitute/O human/O labour/O and/O that/O would/O prevent/O all/O technological/O capabilities/O from/O being/O exhausted/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O FO/O explicitly/O state/O that/O their/O empirical/O approach/O focusses/O on/O technological/O capabilities/O ./O 
The/O susceptibility/O of/O jobs/O to/O automation/O that/O they/O aim/O at/O identifying/O hence/O refers/O to/O such/O capabilities/O only/O ./O 
43/NUMBER ./O 
Apart/O from/O company/O -/O related/O reasons/O for/O a/O rather/O low/O speed/O of/O technological/O adoption/O ,/O there/O may/O also/O be/O ethical/O or/O legal/O obstacles/O to/O the/O utilis/O ation/O of/O new/O technologies/O ./O 
As/O a/O prominent/O example/O that/O has/O recently/DATE been/O discussed/O by/O Thierer/PERSON and/O Hagemann/PERSON -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O and/O Bonnefon/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O the/O autonomous/O car/O bears/O new/O legal/O challenges/O regarding/O e.g./O liabilities/O i/O n/O case/O of/O an/O accident/O ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O there/O are/O unresolved/O ethical/O questions/O concerning/O how/O an/O algorithm/O should/O decide/O between/O crashing/O into/O a/O car/O or/O a/O truck/O ./O 
While/O some/O of/O these/O obstacles/O may/O be/O resolved/O at/O some/O point/O ,/O they/O clearly/O slow/O down/O the/O pace/O with/O whic/O h/O technologies/O are/O spread/O ./O 
This/O can/O be/O illustrated/O using/O the/O example/O of/O driverless/O cars/O ,/O which/O are/O often/O said/O to/O have/O a/O high/O disruptive/O potential/O ./O 
According/O to/O the/O Boston/ORGANIZATION Consulting/ORGANIZATION Group/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O the/O share/O of/O driverless/O vehicles/O will/O reach/O 10/PERCENT %/PERCENT by/B_TEMPPRED the/M_TEMPPRED year/E_TEMPPRED 2035/DATE which/O suggests/O a/O rather/O slow/O speed/O of/O change/O ./O 
44/NUMBER ./O 
Finally/O ,/O another/O aspect/O that/O should/O be/O considered/O is/O a/O strong/O societal/O preference/O for/O the/O provision/O of/O certain/O tasks/O and/O services/O by/O humans/O as/O opposed/O to/O machine/O s/O ./O 
As/O an/O example/O ,/O nursing/O or/O caring/O for/O the/O elderly/O may/O remain/O labour/O -/O intensive/O sectors/O ,/O even/O if/O service/O robots/O increasingly/O complement/O these/O professions/O in/O the/DATE future/DATE ./O 
Hence/O ,/O ``/O some/O human/O services/O will/O probably/O continue/O to/O command/O a/O premium/O compared/O to/O rob/O otically/O produced/O one/NUMBER ''/O -LRB-/O Pratt/O 2015/DATE ,/O p./O 58/NUMBER -RRB-/O ,/O meaning/O that/O there/O is/O a/O societal/O value/O attached/O to/O humans/O performing/O certain/O tasks/O that/O tends/O to/O preserve/O their/O comparative/O advantage/O ./O 
DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/DATE 23/DATE 45/DATE ./O 
For/O all/O these/O reasons/O ,/O the/O techno/O logical/O capabilities/O as/O assessed/O by/O FO/O are/O likely/O overestimated/O and/O should/O not/O b/O e/O equated/O with/O the/O actual/O utilis/O ation/O of/O technological/O advances/O ./O 
B./O Adjustment/O of/O workplace/O tasks/O 46/NUMBER ./O 
Even/O if/O a/O technology/O actually/O enters/O the/O production/O process/O ,/O the/O impact/O on/O employment/O depends/O on/O whether/O workplaces/O are/O able/O to/O adjust/O to/O new/O demands/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O the/O new/O technologies/O may/O substitute/O for/O certain/O tasks/O and/O complement/O others/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O whethe/O r/O a/O workplace/O will/O be/O automated/O or/O not/O clearly/O depends/O on/O whether/O the/O tasks/O performed/O at/O a/O certain/O workplace/O shift/O from/O the/O first/ORDINAL to/O the/O latter/O set/O of/O tasks/O ./O 
In/O fact/O ,/O several/O studies/O suggest/O that/O although/O there/O has/O been/O a/O decline/O in/O jobs/O with/O predominantly/O routine/O and/O automatable/O tasks/O ,/O the/O adjustment/O mainly/O takes/O place/O by/O changing/O the/O set/O of/O tasks/O within/O occupations/O -LRB-/O e.g./O Autor/O at/O al./O ./O 
2003/DATE ,/O Spitz/PERSON -/O Oener/DATE 2006/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Workers/O seem/O to/O shift/O worktime/O from/O routine/O and/O automatable/O tasks/O to/O tasks/O that/O are/O complementary/O to/O machines/O ./O 
47/NUMBER ./O 
The/O adoption/O of/O new/O technologies/O seems/O to/O come/O along/O with/O a/O new/O division/O of/O labour/O where/O workers/O increasingly/O perform/O tasks/O that/O complement/O machines/O -LRB-/O Autor/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O of/O new/O and/O more/O complex/O tasks/O -LRB-/O Acemog/O lu/O and/O Restrepo/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
As/O an/O example/O ,/O tasks/O involving/O the/O monitoring/O of/O machines/O are/O likely/O to/O gain/O in/O importance/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O new/O technologies/O are/O unlikely/O to/O fully/O automate/O workplaces/O or/O occupations/O on/O a/O large/O scale/O ,/O but/O rather/O change/O workplaces/O and/O the/O tasks/O involved/O in/O certain/O occupations/O ./O 
As/O long/O as/O workers/O are/O able/O to/O adjust/O to/O these/O new/O task/O demands/O ,/O machines/O need/O not/O crowd/O out/O workers/O ./O 
However/O ,/O as/O the/O findings/O from/O FO/O as/O well/O as/O the/O predictions/O in/O chapter/O 3/NUMBER suggest/O ,/O low/O -/O qualified/O workers/O perform/O a/O much/O h/O igher/O share/O of/O potentially/O automatable/O tasks/O than/O high/O -/O qualified/O workers/O ./O 
If/O the/O tasks/O that/O complement/O machines/O become/O increasingly/O complex/O and/O demanding/O ,/O the/O employment/O prospects/O for/O workers/O lacking/O certain/O skills/O may/O deteriorate/O ./O 
C./O Macroeconomic/O adjustmen/O t/O and/O indirect/O effects/O 48/NUMBER ./O 
The/O risk/O of/O automation/O as/O predicted/O by/O FO/O refers/O to/O the/O -LRB-/O likely/O overestimated/O -RRB-/O threat/O regarding/O the/O labour/O -/O saving/O impact/O of/O new/O technologies/O ./O 
This/O ``/O risk/O of/O automation/O ''/O ,/O however/O ,/O must/O not/O be/O equated/O with/O employment/O losses/O since/O there/O are/O macroeconomic/O feedback/O mechanisms/O that/O may/O also/O result/O in/O an/O increase/O in/O labour/O demand/O ./O 
Arntz/O et/O al./O ./O 
-LRB-/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O review/O the/O literature/O regarding/O these/O macroeconomic/O adjustment/O mechanisms/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O there/O are/O t/O hree/O mechanisms/O that/O counteract/O the/O labour/O -/O saving/O impact/O of/O technological/O advances/O ./O 
49/NUMBER ./O 
First/ORDINAL of/O all/O ,/O labour/O -/O saving/O technologies/O need/O to/O be/O produced/O in/O the/O first/ORDINAL place/O ,/O thereby/O creating/O a/O demand/O for/O labour/O in/O new/O sect/O ors/O and/O occupations/O ./O 
According/O to/O the/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Digital/ORGANIZATION Economy/ORGANIZATION Outlook/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O OECD/ORGANIZATION 2015/DATE -RRB-/O the/O ICT/ORGANIZATION sector/O is/O a/O key/O driver/O of/O economic/O growth/O in/O OCED/ORGANIZATION countries/O ./O 
Between/O 15/NUMBER and/O 52/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O all/O investments/O in/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O were/O related/O to/O the/O ICT/ORGANIZATION sector/O between/O 2008/DATE and/O 2013/DATE ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O after/O a/O slack/O in/O the/O sector/O 's/O contribution/O to/O employment/O growth/O during/O the/O economic/O crises/O ,/O the/O share/O of/O jobs/O created/O by/O the/O ICT/ORGANIZATION sector/O in/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O amounts/O to/O 22/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/U_TEMPPRED 2013/DATE ./O 
FO/O do/O not/O take/O into/O account/O such/O positive/O demand/O effects/O ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O due/O to/O focusing/O on/O the/O perceived/O risk/O for/O currently/DATE existing/O jobs/O only/O ,/O FO/O neglect/O the/O fact/O that/O jobs/O of/O the/DATE future/DATE are/O likely/O to/O be/O complementary/O to/O the/O new/O technologies/O ./O 
50/NUMBER ./O 
Secondly/O ,/O new/O technologies/O may/O boost/O a/O firm/O 's/O competitiveness/O since/O new/O technologies/O typically/O increase/O a/O firm/O 's/O productivity/O ./O 
With/O lower/O costs/O and/O prices/O ,/O firms/O face/O a/O higher/O product/O demand/O and/O hence/O demand/O more/O labour/O ,/O which/O can/O -LRB-/O partially/O -RRB-/O compensate/O for/O the/O labour/O -/O saving/O effect/O of/O technolo/O gies/O ./O 
Graetz/O and/O Michaels/PERSON -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O examine/O the/O effect/O of/O the/O utilis/O ation/O of/O industrial/O robots/O in/O 17/NUMBER countries/O and/O find/O no/O negative/O impact/O on/O the/O total/O working/O hours/DURATION at/O the/O sector/O level/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O the/O use/O of/O new/O labour/O -/O saving/O technologies/O did/O not/O r/O educe/O the/O demand/O for/O labour/O ./O 
Similarly/O ,/O Goos/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O develop/O a/O model/O of/O labour/O demand/O at/O the/O industry/O level/O for/O 16/NUMBER European/O countries/O and/O find/O that/O routine/O -/O intensive/O industries/O that/O are/O at/O a/O higher/O risk/O of/O introducing/O labour/O -/O saving/O technologies/O gain/O in/O competitiveness/O and/O face/O an/O DELSA/ELSA/WD/O //O SEM/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 15/NUMBER 24/NUMBER increasing/O product/O demand/O ./O 
Similarly/O ,/O Gregory/PERSON et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O estimate/O a/O labour/O demand/O model/O at/O the/O level/O of/O European/O NUTS2/O regions/O and/O show/O that/O regions/O with/O an/O initially/O high/O share/O of/O routine/O and/O highly/O automatable/O tasks/O actu/O ally/O gained/O in/O competitiveness/O ,/O with/O the/O indirect/O positive/O effect/O on/O the/O regional/O product/O demand/O more/O than/O compensating/O the/O labour/O -/O saving/O substitution/O effect/O ./O 
In/O total/O ,/O they/O find/O that/O the/O computeri/O sation/O in/O fact/O generated/O 11.6/NUMBER Million/NUMBER jobs/O on/O net/O across/O 27/NUMBER European/O countries/O between/O 1999/DATE and/O 2010/DATE ./O 
51/NUMBER ./O 
Thirdly/O ,/O to/O the/O extent/O that/O the/O new/O technologies/O complement/O workers/O ,/O labour/O productivity/O increases/O ./O 
This/DATE may/DATE lead/O to/O either/O higher/O wages/O ,/O or/O higher/O employment/O ,/O or/O both/O ,/O w/O hich/O in/O turn/O raises/O labour/O income/O ./O 
As/O a/O consequence/O ,/O these/O workers/O may/O demand/O more/O products/O and/O services/O ,/O thereby/O again/O increasing/O the/O demand/O for/O labour/O in/O the/O economy/O ./O 
In/O their/O labour/O demand/O model/O ,/O Gregory/PERSON et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O take/O these/O adjustment/O processes/O int/O o/O account/O and/O find/O that/O they/O played/O a/O strong/O role/O for/O the/O positive/O net/O effect/O of/O technological/O change/O on/O employment/O in/O Europe/LOCATION ./O 
