So/O the/O company/O CEO/O will/O still/O be/O human/O in/O 2025/DATE ,/O but/O what/O about/O the/O board/O of/O directors/O ?/O 
Board/O members/O who/O just/O use/O anecdotal/O evidence/O and/O 30/O years/O of/O gut/O experience/O to/O evaluate/O major/O decisions/O are/O n't/O going/O to/O cut/O it/O in/O today/O 's/O environment/O ,/O says/O Warren/PERSON Stippich/PERSON ,/O who/O advises/O corporate/O boards/O as/O a/O partner/O in/O Advisory/ORGANIZATION Services/ORGANIZATION at/O professional-services/O firm/O Grant/ORGANIZATION Thornton/ORGANIZATION LLP/ORGANIZATION ./O 
In/O many/O cases/O ,/O adding/O an/O artificial-intelligence/O tool/O to/O the/O boardroom/O ,/O Stippich/PERSON says/O ,/O could/O help/O synthesize/O the/O massive/O amounts/O of/O data/O board/O members/O are/O being/O asked/O to/O review/O and/O help/O improve/O decision-making/O ./O 
Robots/O on/O the/O board/O is/O n't/O that/O uncommon/O of/O a/O dream/O ./O 
In/O another/O World/O Economic/O Forum/O survey/O ,/O nearly/O half/O of/O executives/O said/O that/O there/O will/O be/O an/O AI/O appointed/O to/O a/O firm/O 's/O board/O of/O directors/O by/O 2025/DATE ./O 
Already/O ,/O IBM/ORGANIZATION Corp./ORGANIZATION is/O using/O an/O algorithm/O to/O help/O its/O directors/O evaluate/O potential/O acquisition/O targets/O ./O 
-LRB-/O Big/ORGANIZATION Blue/ORGANIZATION has/O n't/O yet/O put/O a/O supercomputer/O on/O its/O corporate/O board/O ./O -RRB-/O 
