JANUARY/DATE 2017/DATE A/O FUTURE/DATE THAT/O WORKS/O :/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O EMPLOYMENT/O ,/O AND/O PRODUCTIVITY/O Copyright/O ?/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION 2017/ORGANIZATION Since/ORGANIZATION its/O founding/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1990/DATE ,/O the/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O MGI/O -RRB-/O has/O sought/O to/O develop/O a/O deeper/O understanding/O of/O the/O evolving/O global/O economy/O ./O 
As/O the/O business/O and/O economics/O research/O arm/O of/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION ,/O MGI/ORGANIZATION aims/O to/O provide/O leaders/O in/O the/O commercial/O ,/O public/O ,/O and/O social/O sectors/O with/O the/O facts/O and/O insights/O on/O which/O to/O base/O management/O and/O policy/O decisions/O ./O 
The/O Lauder/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION at/O the/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Pennsylvania/ORGANIZATION ranked/O MGI/ORGANIZATION the/O world/O 's/O number-one/O private-sector/O think/O tank/O in/O its/O 2015/DATE Global/O Think/O Tank/O Index/O ./O 
MGI/ORGANIZATION research/O combines/O the/O disciplines/O of/O economics/O and/O management/O ,/O employing/O the/O analytical/O tools/O of/O economics/O with/O the/O insights/O of/O business/O leaders/O ./O 
Our/O ``/O micro-to-macro/O ''/O methodology/O examines/O microeconomic/O industry/O trends/O to/O better/O understand/O the/O broad/O macroeconomic/O forces/O affecting/O business/O strategy/O and/O public/O policy/O ./O 
MGI/ORGANIZATION 's/O in-depth/O reports/O have/O covered/O more/O than/O 20/NUMBER countries/O and/O 30/NUMBER industries/O ./O 
Current/DATE research/O focuses/O on/O six/NUMBER themes/O :/O productivity/O and/O growth/O ,/O natural/O resources/O ,/O labor/O markets/O ,/O the/O evolution/O of/O global/O financial/O markets/O ,/O the/O economic/O impact/O of/O technology/O and/O innovation/O ,/O and/O urbanization/O ./O 
Recent/O reports/O have/O assessed/O the/O economic/O benefits/O of/O tackling/O gender/O inequality/O ,/O a/O new/O era/O of/O global/O competition/O ,/O Chinese/O innovation/O ,/O and/O digital/O globalization/O ./O 
MGI/ORGANIZATION is/O led/O by/O four/NUMBER McKinsey/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION senior/O partners/O :/O Jacques/PERSON Bughin/PERSON ,/O James/PERSON Manyika/PERSON ,/O Jonathan/PERSON Woetzel/PERSON ,/O and/O Frank/PERSON Mattern/PERSON ,/O MGI/ORGANIZATION 's/O chairman/O ./O 
Michael/PERSON Chui/PERSON ,/O Susan/PERSON Lund/PERSON ,/O Anu/PERSON Madgavkar/PERSON ,/O Sree/PERSON Ramaswamy/PERSON ,/O and/O Jaana/PERSON Remes/PERSON serve/O as/O MGI/ORGANIZATION partners/O ./O 
Project/O teams/O are/O led/O by/O the/O MGI/ORGANIZATION partners/O and/O a/O group/O of/O senior/O fellows/O and/O include/O consultants/O from/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION offices/O around/O the/O world/O ./O 
These/O teams/O draw/O on/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION 's/O global/O network/O of/O partners/O and/O industry/O and/O management/O experts/O ./O 
Input/O is/O provided/O by/O the/O MGI/ORGANIZATION Council/ORGANIZATION ,/O which/O coleads/O projects/O and/O provides/O guidance/O ;/O members/O are/O Andres/PERSON Cadena/PERSON ,/O Richard/PERSON Dobbs/PERSON ,/O Katy/PERSON George/PERSON ,/O Rajat/PERSON Gupta/PERSON ,/O Eric/PERSON Hazan/PERSON ,/O Eric/PERSON Labaye/PERSON ,/O Acha/PERSON Leke/PERSON ,/O Scott/PERSON Nyquist/PERSON ,/O Gary/PERSON Pinkus/PERSON ,/O Shirish/PERSON Sankhe/PERSON ,/O Oliver/PERSON Tonby/PERSON ,/O and/O Eckart/PERSON Windhagen/PERSON ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O leading/O economists/O ,/O including/O Nobel/O laureates/O ,/O act/O as/O research/O advisers/O ./O 
The/O partners/O of/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION fund/O MGI/ORGANIZATION 's/O research/O ;/O it/O is/O not/O commissioned/O by/O any/O business/O ,/O government/O ,/O or/O other/O institution/O ./O 
For/O further/O information/O about/O MGI/ORGANIZATION and/O to/O download/O reports/O ,/O please/O visit/O www.mckinsey.com/mgi/O ./O 
James/PERSON Manyika/PERSON |/PERSON San/PERSON Francisco/PERSON Michael/PERSON Chui/PERSON |/O San/ORGANIZATION Francisco/ORGANIZATION Mehdi/ORGANIZATION Miremadi/ORGANIZATION |/ORGANIZATION Chicago/ORGANIZATION Jacques/ORGANIZATION Bughin/ORGANIZATION |/ORGANIZATION Brussels/ORGANIZATION Katy/ORGANIZATION George/ORGANIZATION |/ORGANIZATION New/ORGANIZATION Jersey/ORGANIZATION Paul/ORGANIZATION Willmott/ORGANIZATION |/ORGANIZATION London/ORGANIZATION Martin/ORGANIZATION Dewhurst/ORGANIZATION |/O London/LOCATION JANUARY/DATE 2017/DATE A/O FUTURE/DATE THAT/O WORKS/O :/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O EMPLOYMENT/O ,/O AND/O PRODUCTIVITY/O PREFACE/O Automation/O is/O an/O idea/O that/O has/O inspired/O science/O fiction/O writers/O and/O futurologists/O for/O more/DURATION than/DURATION a/DURATION century/DURATION ./O 
Today/DATE it/O is/O no/O longer/O fiction/O ,/O as/O companies/O increasingly/O use/O robots/O on/O production/O lines/O or/O algorithms/O to/O optimize/O their/O logistics/O ,/O manage/O inventory/O ,/O and/O carry/O out/O other/O core/O business/O functions/O ./O 
Technological/O advances/O are/O creating/O a/O new/O automation/O age/O in/O which/O ever-smarter/O and/O more/O flexible/O machines/O will/O be/O deployed/O on/O an/O ever-larger/O scale/O in/O the/O workplace/O ./O 
In/O reality/O ,/O the/O process/O of/O automating/O tasks/O done/O by/O humans/O has/O been/O under/O way/O for/O centuries/DURATION ./O 
What/O has/O perhaps/O changed/O is/O the/O pace/O and/O scope/O of/O what/O can/O be/O automated/O ./O 
It/O is/O a/O prospect/O that/O raises/O more/O questions/O than/O it/O answers/O ./O 
How/O will/O automation/O transform/O the/O workplace/O ?/O 
What/O will/O be/O the/O implications/O for/O employment/O ?/O 
And/O what/O is/O likely/O to/O be/O its/O impact/O both/O on/O productivity/O in/O the/O global/O economy/O and/O on/O employment/O ?/O 
This/O report/O was/O produced/O as/O part/O of/O the/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION 's/O overall/O research/O on/O the/O impact/O of/O technology/O on/O business/O and/O society/O ,/O and/O specifically/O our/O ongoing/O research/O program/O on/O the/DATE future/DATE of/O work/O and/O the/O potential/O impacts/O on/O the/O global/O economy/O of/O data/O and/O analytics/O ,/O automation/O ,/O robotics/O and/O artificial/O intelligence/O ./O 
In/O this/O report/O ,/O we/O analyze/O how/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O technologies/O could/O potentially/O automate/O current/DATE work/O activities/O that/O people/O are/O paid/O to/O do/O in/O the/O global/O workforce/O ,/O and/O what/O the/O impact/O could/O be/O on/O global/O productivity/O ./O 
This/O work/O does/O not/O define/O what/O the/O new/O activities/O and/O occupations/O that/O will/O be/O developed/O will/O be/O ,/O nor/O does/O it/O analyze/O in/O depth/O how/O the/O economic/O gains/O of/O automation/O will/O be/O distributed/O or/O provide/O specific/O policy/O recommendations/O for/O governments/O ./O 
While/O we/O consider/O a/O broad/O range/O of/O automation/O technologies/O ,/O we/O do/O not/O focus/O specifically/O on/O any/O particular/O technologies/O ./O 
We/O realize/O that/O this/O area/O of/O research/O is/O evolving/O rapidly/O ,/O given/O the/O pace/O of/O technological/O advancement/O ,/O and/O we/O plan/O to/O update/O the/O perspectives/O presented/O in/O this/O report/O regularly/O ./O 
The/O research/O was/O led/O by/O James/PERSON Manyika/PERSON ,/O a/O director/O of/O the/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION and/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION senior/O partner/O based/O in/O San/LOCATION Francisco/LOCATION ;/O Michael/PERSON Chui/PERSON ,/O an/O MGI/ORGANIZATION partner/O in/O San/LOCATION Francisco/LOCATION ;/O and/O Mehdi/PERSON Miremadi/PERSON ,/O a/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION partner/O based/O in/O Chicago/LOCATION ./O 
MGI/ORGANIZATION and/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION senior/O partner/O Jacques/PERSON Bughin/PERSON and/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION senior/O partners/O Martin/PERSON Dewhurst/PERSON ,/O Katy/PERSON George/PERSON ,/O Andrew/PERSON Grant/PERSON ,/O Bill/PERSON Schaninger/PERSON ,/O Stefan/PERSON Spang/PERSON ,/O and/O Paul/PERSON Willmott/PERSON guided/O and/O contributed/O to/O the/O research/O ./O 
We/O would/O especially/O like/O to/O acknowledge/O the/O work/O of/O Sean/PERSON Kane/PERSON ,/O Rick/PERSON Cavolo/PERSON ,/O and/O Tong/PERSON Chen/PERSON ,/O who/O each/O headed/O the/O research/O team/O at/O different/O times/O over/O the/O course/O of/O the/O two-year/DURATION project/O and/O who/O played/O invaluable/O roles/O in/O coordinating/O and/O driving/O it/O forward/O ./O 
The/O team/O comprised/O Anuj/PERSON Abrol/PERSON ,/O Jared/PERSON Barnett/PERSON ,/O Jackson/ORGANIZATION Beard/ORGANIZATION ,/O Lily/PERSON Cheng/PERSON ,/O Josh/PERSON Cogan/PERSON ,/O Arielle/PERSON Copeland/PERSON ,/O Sam/PERSON Doniger/PERSON ,/O Rachel/PERSON Garber/PERSON ,/O Paul/PERSON Gilson/PERSON ,/O Bob/PERSON Glied/PERSON ,/O Sartaj/PERSON Grover/PERSON ,/O Gauri/PERSON Gupta/PERSON ,/O Benjamin/PERSON Harrison/PERSON ,/O Alex/PERSON Hinch/PERSON ,/O Tanay/PERSON Juipuria/PERSON ,/O Daniel/PERSON Langer/PERSON ,/O Kunal/PERSON Mehta/PERSON ,/O Andrey/PERSON Mironenko/PERSON ,/O Vaishal/PERSON Patel/PERSON ,/O Steven/PERSON Pecht/PERSON ,/O Jonathan/PERSON Sands/PERSON ,/O Santhosh/PERSON Suresh/PERSON ,/O Adam/PERSON Tourgee/PERSON ,/O Roshin/PERSON Unnikrishnan/PERSON ,/O Jean/PERSON Xin/PERSON ,/O Roger/PERSON Yang/PERSON ,/O Gordon/PERSON Yu/PERSON ,/O and/O Vicki/PERSON Yu/PERSON ./O 
We/O are/O grateful/O to/O colleagues/O within/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION who/O provided/O valuable/O advice/O and/O analytical/O support/O :/O Jonathan/PERSON Ablett/PERSON ,/O Praveen/ORGANIZATION Adhi/ORGANIZATION ,/O Adriana/PERSON Aragon/PERSON ,/O Mandar/ORGANIZATION P/ORGANIZATION Atre/ORGANIZATION ,/O Gretchen/PERSON Berlin/PERSON ,/O Dilip/PERSON Bhattacharjee/PERSON ,/O Urs/PERSON Binggeli/PERSON ,/O Bede/PERSON Broome/PERSON ,/O Anders/PERSON Brun/PERSON ,/O Jamie/PERSON Chang/PERSON ,/O Zinaida/PERSON Cherevan/PERSON ,/O Ari/PERSON Chester/PERSON ,/O Jeffrey/PERSON Condon/PERSON ,/O Sebas/PERSON Cordero/PERSON ,/O Subbi/PERSON Reddy/PERSON Dwarampudi/PERSON ,/O Alan/PERSON Fitzgerald/PERSON ,/O Christopher/PERSON Forr-Rydgren/PERSON ,/O Daniel/PERSON Garnier/PERSON ,/O Panco/PERSON Georgiev/PERSON ,/O Timo/PERSON Glave/PERSON ,/O Davide/PERSON Gronchi/PERSON ,/O Saif/PERSON Hameed/PERSON ,/O Holger/PERSON Hurtgen/PERSON ,/O Andrew/PERSON Jordan/PERSON ,/O Joshua/PERSON Katz/PERSON ,/O Richard/PERSON Kelly/PERSON ,/O Aimee/PERSON Kim/PERSON ,/O Sajal/PERSON Kohli/PERSON ,/O Paul/PERSON Kolter/PERSON ,/O Michelle/PERSON Lin/PERSON ,/O Joy/O Long/O ,/O Murdock/PERSON Martin/PERSON ,/O Anne/PERSON Martinelli/PERSON ,/O Inga/PERSON Maurer/PERSON ,/O Jan/PERSON Mischke/PERSON ,/O Sebastian/PERSON Montero/PERSON ,/O Thomas/PERSON Netzer/PERSON ,/O Robin/PERSON Nuttall/PERSON ,/O Catherine/PERSON O'Connor/PERSON ,/O Darryl/PERSON Piasecki/PERSON ,/O Lauren/PERSON Ratner/PERSON ,/O Ron/PERSON Ritter/PERSON ,/O Kelsey/PERSON Robinson/PERSON ,/O Elido/PERSON Rodriguez/PERSON ,/O Arushi/PERSON Saksena/PERSON ,/O Sam/PERSON Samdani/PERSON ,/O Richard/PERSON Sellschop/PERSON ,/O Jeongmin/PERSON Seong/PERSON ,/O Raman/PERSON Sharma/PERSON ,/O Vivien/PERSON Singer/PERSON ,/O Katarzyna/PERSON Smietana/PERSON ,/O Giacomo/PERSON Sonnino/PERSON ,/O Jonathan/PERSON Tilley/PERSON ,/O Soyoko/PERSON Umeno/PERSON ,/O Sari/PERSON Varpa/PERSON ,/O Susanne/PERSON Wagner/PERSON ,/O Richard/PERSON Ward/PERSON ,/O Rob/PERSON Whiteman/PERSON ,/O Ting/PERSON Wu/PERSON ,/O and/O Mauricio/PERSON Zamora/PERSON ./O 
This/O report/O was/O edited/O and/O produced/O by/O MGI/ORGANIZATION senior/O editor/O Peter/PERSON Gumbel/PERSON ,/O editorial/O production/O manager/O Julie/PERSON Philpot/PERSON ,/O senior/O graphic/O designers/O Marisa/PERSON Carder/PERSON ,/O Margo/PERSON Shimasaki/PERSON ,/O and/O Patrick/PERSON White/PERSON ,/O and/O data/O visualization/O editor/O Richard/PERSON Johnson/PERSON ./O 
Rebeca/PERSON Robboy/PERSON ,/O MGI/ORGANIZATION director/O of/O external/O communications/O ,/O managed/O communications/O ./O 
We/O would/O like/O to/O thank/O our/O academic/O advisers/O for/O their/O invaluable/O insights/O and/O guidance/O :/O Martin/PERSON Baily/PERSON ,/O Bernard/PERSON L./PERSON Schwartz/PERSON Chair/O in/O Economic/ORGANIZATION Policy/ORGANIZATION Development/ORGANIZATION and/O senior/O fellow/O and/O director/O of/O the/O Business/O and/O Public/ORGANIZATION Policy/ORGANIZATION Initiative/ORGANIZATION at/O the/O Brookings/O Institution/O ;/O Matthew/PERSON J./PERSON Slaughter/PERSON ,/O Paul/PERSON Danos/PERSON Dean/PERSON of/O the/O Tuck/ORGANIZATION School/ORGANIZATION and/O the/O Earl/PERSON C./PERSON Daum/PERSON 1924/DATE Professor/O of/O International/ORGANIZATION Business/ORGANIZATION at/O Dartmouth/ORGANIZATION College/ORGANIZATION ;/O and/O Hal/PERSON Varian/PERSON ,/O chief/O economist/O at/O Google/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Many/O other/O external/O experts/O informed/O our/O research/O ,/O including/O those/O whom/O we/O surveyed/O about/O the/O timing/O of/O technological/O progression/O ./O 
We/O are/O deeply/O grateful/O for/O their/O insight/O and/O assistance/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O our/O research/O has/O benefited/O from/O the/O work/O of/O other/O researchers/O ,/O including/O Daron/PERSON Acemoglu/PERSON ,/O David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON ,/O Erik/PERSON Brynjolfsson/PERSON ,/O Carl/PERSON Benedikt/PERSON Frey/PERSON ,/O Jason/PERSON Furman/PERSON ,/O Andrew/PERSON McAfee/PERSON ,/O Michael/PERSON Osborne/PERSON ,/O and/O Tim/PERSON O'Reilly/PERSON ./O 
This/O report/O contributes/O to/O MGI/ORGANIZATION 's/O mission/O to/O help/O business/O and/O policy/O leaders/O understand/O the/O forces/O transforming/O the/O global/O economy/O ,/O identify/O strategic/O locations/O ,/O and/O prepare/O for/O the/O next/O wave/O of/O growth/O ./O 
As/O with/O all/O MGI/ORGANIZATION research/O ,/O this/O work/O is/O independent/O and/O has/O not/O been/O commissioned/O or/O sponsored/O in/O any/O way/O by/O any/O business/O ,/O government/O ,/O or/O other/O institution/O ./O 
While/O we/O are/O grateful/O for/O all/O the/O input/O we/O have/O received/O ,/O the/O report/O is/O ours/O ,/O including/O any/O errors/O ./O 
We/O welcome/O your/O comments/O on/O this/O research/O at/O MGI@mckinsey.com/O ./O 
Jacques/O Bughin/O Director/O ,/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION Senior/ORGANIZATION Partner/ORGANIZATION ,/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION Brussels/ORGANIZATION James/ORGANIZATION Manyika/ORGANIZATION Director/ORGANIZATION ,/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION Senior/ORGANIZATION Partner/ORGANIZATION ,/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION San/ORGANIZATION Francisco/ORGANIZATION Jonathan/ORGANIZATION Woetzel/ORGANIZATION Director/ORGANIZATION ,/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION Senior/ORGANIZATION Partner/ORGANIZATION ,/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION Shanghai/ORGANIZATION January/DATE 2017/DATE A/O restaurant/O in/O Yiwu/ORGANIZATION ,/O Zhejiang/LOCATION province/O of/O China/LOCATION ./O 
?/O Visual/ORGANIZATION China/ORGANIZATION Group/Getty/ORGANIZATION Images/ORGANIZATION CONTENTS/ORGANIZATION HIGHLIGHTS/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION is/O advancing/O rapidly/O A/O vision/O of/O future/DATE automation/O Humans/O will/O interact/O more/O with/O machines/O 23/NUMBER 53/NUMBER 114In/O brief/O Executive/O summary/O Page/O 1/NUMBER Overview/O of/O select/O recent/O studies/O on/O the/O impact/O of/O automation/O and/O future/DATE of/O work/O Page/O 21/NUMBER 1/NUMBER ./O 
The/O new/O frontier/O Page/O 23/NUMBER Automation/O technologies/O including/O robotics/O and/O artificial/O intelligence/O have/O advanced/O rapidly/O ,/O but/O some/O key/O hurdles/O still/O need/O to/O be/O cleared/O 2/NUMBER ./O 
The/O technical/O potential/O for/O automation/O Page/O 29/NUMBER Almost/O half/O of/O the/O work/O activities/O in/O all/O sectors/O across/O the/O economy/O have/O the/O potential/O to/O be/O automated/O by/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technologies/O 3/NUMBER ./O 
Five/NUMBER case/O studies/O Page/O 53/NUMBER How/O automation/O could/O potentially/O transform/O hospital/O emergency/O departments/O ,/O aircraft/O maintenance/O ,/O mortgage/O brokering/O ,/O oil/O and/O gas/O control/O rooms/O ,/O and/O grocery/O stores/O 4/NUMBER ./O 
Factors/O affecting/O the/O pace/O and/O extent/O of/O automation/O Page/O 65/NUMBER Five/NUMBER technical/O and/O economic/O factors/O that/O will/O together/O determine/O the/O pace/O at/O which/O automation/O arrives/O in/O the/O workplace/O 5/NUMBER ./O 
An/O engine/O of/O productivity/O Page/O 87/NUMBER Automation/O could/O compensate/O for/O demographic/O trends/O by/O giving/O a/O major/O boost/O to/O the/O global/O economy/O 6/NUMBER ./O 
Preparing/O for/O disruption/O Pa/ORGANIZATION g/O e/O 10/NUMBER 9/NUMBER The/O implications/O of/O automation/O for/O business/O leaders/O ,/O policy/O makers/O ,/O and/O workers/O Technical/O appendix/O P/O a/O g/O e/O 119/NUMBER Bibliography/O P/O a/O g/O e/O 13/NUMBER 3/NUMBER IN/O BRIEF/O A/O FUTURE/DATE THAT/O WORKS/O :/O AUTOMATION/O ,/O EMPLOYMENT/O ,/O AND/O PRODUCTIVITY/O Advances/O in/O robotics/O ,/O artificial/O intelligence/O ,/O and/O machine/O learning/O are/O ushering/O in/O a/O new/O age/O of/O automation/O ,/O as/O machines/O match/O or/O outperform/O human/O performance/O in/O a/O range/O of/O work/O activities/O ,/O including/O ones/O requiring/O cognitive/O capabilities/O ./O 
In/O this/O report/O ,/O part/O of/O our/O ongoing/O research/O into/O the/DATE future/DATE of/O work/O ,/O we/O analyze/O the/O automation/O potential/O of/O the/O global/O economy/O ,/O the/O factors/O that/O will/O determine/O the/O pace/O and/O extent/O of/O workplace/O adoption/O ,/O and/O the/O economic/O impact/O associated/O with/O its/O potential/O ./O 
&#131;/O Automation/O of/O activities/O can/O enable/O businesses/O to/O improve/O performance/O ,/O by/O reducing/O errors/O and/O improving/O quality/O and/O speed/O ,/O and/O in/O some/O cases/O achieving/O outcomes/O that/O go/O beyond/O human/O capabilities/O ./O 
Automation/O also/O contributes/O to/O productivity/O ,/O as/O it/O has/O done/O historically/O ./O 
At/O a/O time/O of/O lackluster/O productivity/O growth/O ,/O this/O would/O give/O a/O needed/O boost/O to/O economic/O growth/O and/O prosperity/O and/O help/O offset/O the/O impact/O of/O a/O declining/O share/O of/O the/O working-age/O population/O in/O many/O countries/O ./O 
Based/O on/O our/O scenario/O modeling/O ,/O we/O estimate/O automation/O could/O raise/O productivity/O growth/O globally/O by/O 0.8/NUMBER to/O 1.4/PERCENT percent/PERCENT annually/SET ./O 
&#131;/O Almost/O half/O the/O activities/O people/O are/O paid/O almost/O $/MONEY 16/MONEY trillion/MONEY in/O wages/O to/O do/O in/O the/O global/O economy/O have/O the/O potential/O to/O be/O automated/O by/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technology/O ,/O according/O to/O our/O analysis/O of/O more/O than/O 2,000/NUMBER work/O activities/O across/O 800/NUMBER occupations/O ./O 
While/O less/O than/O 5/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O all/O occupations/O can/O be/O automated/O entirely/O using/O demonstrated/O technologies/O ,/O about/O 60/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O all/O occupations/O have/O at/O least/O 30/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O constituent/O activities/O that/O could/O be/O automated/O ./O 
More/O occupations/O will/O change/O than/O will/O be/O automated/O away/O ./O 
&#131;/O Activities/O most/O susceptible/O to/O automation/O involve/O physical/O activities/O in/O highly/O structured/O and/O predictable/O environments/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O the/O collection/O and/O processing/O of/O data/O ./O 
In/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O these/O activities/O make/O up/O 51/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O activities/O in/O the/O economy/O accounting/O for/O almost/O $/MONEY 2.7/MONEY trillion/MONEY in/O wages/O ./O 
They/O are/O most/O prevalent/O in/O manufacturing/O ,/O accommodation/O and/O food/O service/O ,/O and/O retail/O trade/O ,/O and/O include/O some/O middle-skill/O jobs/O ./O 
&#131;/O Technical/O ,/O economic/O ,/O and/O social/O factors/O will/O determine/O the/O pace/O and/O extent/O of/O automation/O ./O 
Continued/O technical/O progress/O ,/O for/O example/O in/O areas/O such/O as/O natural/O language/O processing/O ,/O is/O a/O key/O factor/O ./O 
Beyond/O technical/O feasibility/O ,/O the/O cost/O of/O technology/O ,/O competition/O with/O labor/O including/O skills/O and/O supply/O and/O demand/O dynamics/O ,/O performance/O benefits/O including/O and/O beyond/O labor/O cost/O savings/O ,/O and/O social/O and/O regulatory/O acceptance/O will/O affect/O the/O pace/O and/O scope/O of/O automation/O ./O 
Our/O scenarios/O suggest/O that/O half/O of/O today/DATE 's/O work/O activities/O could/O be/O automated/O by/U_TEMPPRED 2055/DATE ,/O but/O this/O could/O happen/O up/DATE to/DATE 20/DATE years/DATE earlier/DATE or/O later/O depending/O on/O the/O various/O factors/O ,/O in/O addition/O to/O other/O wider/O economic/O conditions/O ./O 
&#131;/O People/O will/O need/O to/O continue/O working/O alongside/O machines/O to/O produce/O the/O growth/O in/O per/O capita/O GDP/O to/O which/O countries/O around/O the/O world/O aspire/O ./O 
Our/O productivity/O estimates/O assume/O that/O people/O displaced/O by/O automation/O will/O find/O other/O employment/O ./O 
The/O anticipated/O shift/O in/O the/O activities/O in/O the/O labor/O force/O is/O of/O a/O similar/O order/O of/O magnitude/O as/O the/O long-term/O shift/O away/O from/O agriculture/O and/O decreases/O in/O manufacturing/O share/O of/O employment/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O both/O of/O which/O were/O accompanied/O by/O the/O creation/O of/O new/O types/O of/O work/O not/O foreseen/O at/O the/O time/DATE ./O 
&#131;/O For/O business/O ,/O the/O performance/O benefits/O of/O automation/O are/O relatively/O clear/O ,/O but/O the/O issues/O are/O more/O complicated/O for/O policy-makers/O ./O 
They/O should/O embrace/O the/O opportunity/O for/O their/O economies/O to/O benefit/O from/O the/O productivity/O growth/O potential/O and/O put/O in/O place/O policies/O to/O encourage/O investment/O and/O market/O incentives/O to/O encourage/O continued/O progress/O and/O innovation/O ./O 
At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O they/O must/O evolve/O and/O innovate/O policies/O that/O help/O workers/O and/O institutions/O adapt/O to/O the/O impact/O on/O employment/O ./O 
This/O will/O likely/O include/O rethinking/O education/O and/O training/O ,/O income/O support/O and/O safety/O nets/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O transition/O support/O for/O those/O dislocated/O ./O 
Individuals/O in/O the/O workplace/O will/O need/O to/O engage/O more/O comprehensively/O with/O machines/O as/O part/O of/O their/O everyday/O activities/O ,/O and/O acquire/O new/O skills/O that/O will/O be/O in/O demand/O in/O the/O new/O automation/O age/O ./O 
Automation/O will/O boost/O global/O productivity/O and/O raise/O GDP/O G19/O plus/O Nigeria/LOCATION Five/NUMBER factors/O affecting/O pace/O and/O extent/O of/O adoption/O 12345/NUMBER TECHNICAL/O FEASIBILITY/O Technology/O has/O to/O be/O invented/O ,/O integrated/O ,/O and/O adapted/O into/O solutions/O for/O speci/O c/O case/O use/O COST/O OF/O DEVELOPING/O AND/O DEPLOYING/O SOLUTIONS/O Hardware/O and/O software/O costs/O LABOR/O MARKET/O DYNAMICS/O The/O supply/O ,/O demand/O ,/O and/O costs/O of/O human/O labor/O affect/O which/O activities/O will/O be/O automatedECONOMIC/O BENEFITS/O Include/O higher/O throughput/O and/O increased/O quality/O ,/O alongside/O labor/O cost/O savings/O REGULATORY/O AND/O SOCIAL/O ACCEPTANCE/O Even/O when/O automation/O makes/O business/O sense/O ,/O adoption/O can/O take/O time/O Last/DATE 50/DATE years/DATE Next/DATE 50/DATE years/DATE Growth/DATE aspiration/O Next/DATE 50/DATE years/DATE Potential/O impact/O of/O automation/O 1.7/NUMBER 1.8/NUMBER 2.8/NUMBER 0.1/NUMBER 0.1/NUMBER 0.1/NUMBER Required/O to/O achieve/O projected/O growth/O in/O GDP/O per/O capita/O Historical/O 2.9/NUMBER 3.5/NUMBER 0.8/NUMBER 1.4/NUMBER Early/O scenario/O Late/O scenario/O 0.9/NUMBER 1.5/NUMBER Productivity/O growth/O ,/O %/O Automation/O can/O help/O provide/O some/O of/O the/O productivity/O needed/O to/O achieve/O future/DATE economic/O growth/O Employment/O growth/O ,/O %/O will/O slow/O drastically/O because/O of/O aging/O 2040/DATE 2030?205020602/O 065/NUMBER 2020/DATE 100/NUMBER 80/NUMBER 60/NUMBER 40/NUMBER 200/NUMBER Scenarios/O around/O time/O spent/O on/O current/DATE work/O activities/O ,/O %/O Adoption/O ,/O Early/O scenario/O Adoption/O ,/O Late/O scenario/O Technical/O automation/O potential/O ,/O Early/O scenario/O Technical/O automation/O potential/O ,/O Late/O scenario/O Technical/O ,/O economic/O ,/O and/O social/O factors/O affect/O pace/O of/O adoptionTechnical/O automation/O potential/O must/O precede/O adoption/O Technical/O automation/O potential/O by/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technol/O \/O ogies/O A/O global/O force/O that/O will/O transform/O economies/O and/O the/O workforce/O Labor/O associated/O with/O technically/O automatable/O activities/O Million/NUMBER full-time/O equivalents/O -LRB-/O FTEs/O -RRB-/O Remaining/O countries/O China/LOCATION Japan/LOCATION India/LOCATION Big/O 5/NUMBER in/O Europe/LOCATION 1/LOCATION United/LOCATION States/LOCATION 1/LOCATION France/LOCATION ,/O Germany/LOCATION ,/O Italy/LOCATION ,/O Spain/LOCATION ,/O and/O the/O United/LOCATION Kingdom/LOCATION ./O 
332/PERCENT 54/PERCENT 394/PERCENT 60/PERCENT 35/PERCENT 233/PERCENT 100/PERCENT %/PERCENT =/O 1.1/NUMBER B/O Wages/O assoc/O iated/O w/O ith/O t/O echnic/O ally/O au/O tom/O atab/O le/O ac/O tiv/O itie/O s/O $/MONEY t/MONEY ril/O lion/O Indi/O a/O 1.1/NUMBER Ja/O pan/O 1.7/NUMBER Bi/O g/O 5/NUMBER i/O n/O Eur/O op/O e/O 1/NUMBER C/O hin/O a/O 1.1/NUMBER 5.1/NUMBER 4.1/NUMBER U/O nit/O e/O d/O S/O ta/O te/O s/O 2.7/NUMBER Re/O main/O ing/O co/O unt/O rie/O s/O 100/PERCENT %/PERCENT =/O $/MONEY 15.8/MONEY T/O About/O 60/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O occupations/O have/O at/O least/O 30/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O their/O activities/O that/O are/O automatable/O </O 5/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O occupations/O consist/O of/O activities/O that/O are/O 100/PERCENT %/PERCENT automatable/O Wh/O ile/O f/O e/O w/O occupat/O ions/O are/O f/O u/O lly/O au/O tom/O atab/O le/O ,/O 60/NUMBER percen/O t/O of/O all/O occupat/O ions/O h/O av/O e/O at/O le/O ast/O 30/PERCENT percen/PERCENT t/O t/O echnic/O ally/O au/O tom/O atab/O le/O ac/O tiv/O itie/O s/O ACTIVITIES/O WITH/O HIGHEST/O AUTOMATION/O POTENTIAL/O :/O Predictable/O physical/O activities/O 81/PERCENT %/PERCENT Processing/O data/O 69/PERCENT %/PERCENT Collecting/O data/O 64/PERCENT %/PERCENT 100/NUMBER 91/DATE 73/DATE 62/DATE 51/DATE 42/DATE 34/DATE 26/DATE 18/DATE 8/DATE 1/DATE >/O 50/NUMBER >/O 60/NUMBER >/O 30/NUMBER >/O 20/NUMBER >/O 70/NUMBER >/O 80/NUMBER >/O 90/NUMBER 100/NUMBER >/O 40/NUMBER >/O 0/NUMBER >/O 10/NUMBER T/O echnical/O automatio/O n/O po/O tential/O ,/PERCENT %/PERCENT Share/O of/O ro/O les/O 100/PERCENT %/PERCENT =/O 820/NUMBER roles/O viii/O ?/O Starship/ORGANIZATION Technologies/ORGANIZATION McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION EXECUTIVE/ORGANIZATION SUMMARY/ORGANIZATION Automation/ORGANIZATION is/O not/O a/O new/O phenomenon/O ,/O and/O questions/O about/O its/O promise/O and/O effects/O have/O long/O accompanied/O its/O advances/O ./O 
More/O than/O a/DATE half/DATE century/DATE ago/DATE ,/O US/LOCATION President/O Lyndon/PERSON B./PERSON Johnson/PERSON established/O a/O national/O commission/O to/O examine/O the/O impact/O of/O technology/O on/O the/O economy/O and/O employment/O ,/O declaring/O that/O automation/O did/O not/O have/O to/O destroy/O jobs/O but/O ``/O can/O be/O the/O ally/O of/O our/O prosperity/O if/O we/O will/O just/O look/O ahead/O ./O ''/O 
1/NUMBER Many/O of/O the/O same/O questions/O have/O come/O to/O the/O fore/O again/O today/DATE ,/O as/O a/O result/O of/O remarkable/O recent/O advances/O in/O technologies/O including/O robotics/O ,/O artificial/O intelligence/O -LRB-/O AI/O -RRB-/O ,/O and/O machine/O learning/O ./O 
Automation/O now/DATE has/O the/O potential/O to/O change/O the/O daily/SET work/O activities/O of/O everyone/O ,/O from/O miners/O and/O landscape/O gardeners/O to/O commercial/O bankers/O ,/O fashion/O designers/O ,/O welders/O --/O and/O CEOs/O ./O 
But/O how/O quickly/O will/O these/O technologies/O become/O a/O reality/O in/O the/O workplace/O ?/O 
And/O what/O will/O their/O impact/O be/O on/O employment/O and/O on/O productivity/O in/O the/O global/O economy/O ?/O 
Over/O the/DURATION past/DURATION two/DURATION years/DURATION ,/O we/O have/O been/O conducting/O a/O research/O program/O on/O automation/O technologies/O and/O their/O potential/O effects/O ./O 
Some/O of/O our/O key/O findings/O include/O the/O following/O ./O 
&#131;/O We/O are/O living/O in/O a/O new/O automation/O age/O in/O which/O robots/O and/O computers/O can/O not/O only/O perform/O a/O range/O of/O routine/O physical/O work/O activities/O better/O and/O more/O cheaply/O than/O humans/O ,/O but/O are/O also/O increasingly/O capable/O of/O accomplishing/O activities/O that/O include/O cognitive/O capabilities/O ./O 
These/O include/O making/O tacit/O judgments/O ,/O sensing/O emotion/O ,/O or/O even/O driving/O --/O activities/O that/O used/O to/O be/O considered/O too/O difficult/O to/O automate/O successfully/O ./O 
2/NUMBER &#131;/O The/O automation/O of/O activities/O can/O enable/O productivity/O growth/O and/O other/O benefits/O at/O both/O the/O level/O of/O individual/O process/O and/O businesses/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O at/O the/O level/O of/O entire/O economies/O ,/O where/O productivity/O acceleration/O is/O sorely/O needed/O ,/O especially/O as/O the/O share/O of/O the/O working/O -/O age/O population/O declines/O in/O many/O countries/O ./O 
At/O a/O microeconomic/O level/O ,/O businesses/O everywhere/O will/O have/O an/O opportunity/O to/O capture/O benefits/O and/O achieve/O competitive/O advantage/O from/O automation/O technologies/O ,/O not/O just/O from/O labor/O cost/O reductions/O ,/O but/O also/O from/O performance/O benefits/O such/O as/O increased/O throughput/O ,/O higher/O quality/O ,/O and/O decreased/O downtime/O ./O 
At/O a/O macroeconomic/O level/O ,/O based/O on/O our/O scenario/O modeling/O ,/O we/O estimate/O automation/O could/O raise/O productivity/O growth/O on/O a/O global/O basis/O by/O as/O much/O as/O 0.8/NUMBER to/O 1.4/PERCENT percent/PERCENT annually/SET ./O 
&#131;/O Our/O approach/O to/O analyzing/O the/O potential/O impact/O of/O automation/O is/O through/O a/O focus/O on/O individual/O activities/O rather/O than/O entire/O occupations/O ./O 
Given/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technologies/O ,/O very/O few/O occupations/O --/O less/O than/O 5/PERCENT percent/PERCENT --/O are/O candidates/O for/O full/O automation/O today/DATE ,/O meaning/O that/O every/O activity/O constituting/O these/O occupations/O is/O automated/O ./O 
However/O ,/O almost/O every/O occupation/O has/O partial/O automation/O potential/O ,/O as/O a/O significant/O percentage/O of/O its/O activities/O could/O be/O automated/O ./O 
We/O estimate/O that/O about/O half/O of/O all/O the/O activities/O people/O are/O paid/O to/O do/O in/O the/O world/O 's/O workforce/O could/O potentially/O be/O automated/O by/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technologies/O ./O 
1/NUMBER President/O Johnson/PERSON signed/O the/O bill/O creating/O the/O National/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION on/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION ,/O Automation/O ,/O and/O Economic/ORGANIZATION Progress/ORGANIZATION ,/O on/O August/DATE 19/DATE ,/DATE 1964/DATE ./O 
The/O report/O was/O published/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1966/DATE ./O 
Technology/O and/O the/O American/O economy/O :/O Report/O of/O the/O National/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION on/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION ,/O Automation/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Progress/ORGANIZATION ,/O US/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION Education/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Welfare/ORGANIZATION ,/O February/DATE 1966/DATE ./O 
In/O December/DATE 2016/DATE ,/O the/O White/ORGANIZATION House/ORGANIZATION released/O a/O new/O report/O on/O the/O same/O subject/O ,/O Artificial/O intelligence/O ,/O automation/O ,/O and/O the/O economy/O ./O 
2/NUMBER In/O this/O report/O we/O focus/O on/O the/O implications/O of/O automation/O technologies/O rather/O tha/O \/O n/O on/O the/O technologies/O themselves/O ./O 
For/O a/O more/O detailed/O discussion/O of/O machine/O learning/O and/O deep/O learning/O technologies/O see/O the/O corresponding/O chapter/O in/O The/O age/O of/O analytics/O :/O Competing/O in/O a/O data-driven/O world/O ,/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION ,/O December/DATE 2016/DATE ./O 
2/NUMBER Executive/O summary/O &#131;/O The/O pace/O and/O extent/O of/O automation/O ,/O and/O thus/O its/O impact/O on/O workers/O ,/O will/O vary/O across/O different/O activities/O ,/O occupations/O ,/O and/O wage/O and/O skill/O levels/O ./O 
Many/O workers/O will/O continue/O to/O work/O alongside/O machines/O as/O various/O activities/O are/O automated/O ./O 
Activities/O that/O are/O likely/O to/O be/O automated/O earlier/O include/O predictable/O physical/O activities/O ,/O especially/O prevalent/O in/O manufacturing/O and/O retail/O trade/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O collecting/O and/O processing/O data/O ,/O which/O are/O activities/O that/O exist/O across/O the/O entire/O spectrum/O of/O sectors/O ,/O skills/O and/O wages/O ./O 
Some/O forms/O of/O automation/O will/O be/O skill-biased/O ,/O tending/O to/O raise/O the/O productivity/O of/O high-skill/O workers/O even/O as/O they/O reduce/O the/O demand/O for/O lower-skill/O and/O routine-intensive/O occupations/O ,/O such/O as/O filing/O clerks/O or/O assembly-line/O workers/O ./O 
3/NUMBER Other/O automation/O has/O disproportionately/O affected/O middle-skill/O workers/O ./O 
4/NUMBER As/O technology/O development/O makes/O the/O activities/O of/O both/O low-skill/O and/O high-skill/O workers/O more/O susceptible/O to/O automation/O ,/O these/O polarization/O effects/O could/O be/O reduced/O ./O 
&#131;/O Automation/O will/O have/O wide-ranging/O effects/O ,/O across/O geographies/O and/O sectors/O ./O 
Although/O automation/O is/O a/O global/O phenomenon/O ,/O four/NUMBER economies/O --/O China/LOCATION ,/O India/LOCATION ,/O Japan/LOCATION ,/O and/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION --/O account/O for/O just/O over/O half/O of/O the/O total/O wages/O and/O almost/O two-thirds/O the/O number/O of/O employees/O associated/O with/O activities/O that/O are/O technically/O automatable/O by/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technologies/O ./O 
Within/O countries/O ,/O automation/O potential/O will/O be/O affected/O by/O their/O sector/O mix/O ,/O and/O the/O mix/O of/O activities/O within/O sectors/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O industries/O such/O as/O manufacturing/O and/O agriculture/O include/O predictable/O physical/O activities/O that/O have/O a/O high/O technical/O potential/O to/O be/O automated/O ,/O but/O lower/O wage/O rates/O in/O some/O developing/O countries/O could/O constrain/O adoption/O ./O 
&#131;/O Automation/O will/O not/O happen/O overnight/TIME ,/O and/O five/NUMBER key/O factors/O will/O influence/O the/O pace/O and/O extent/O of/O its/O adoption/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL is/O technical/O feasibility/O ,/O since/O the/O technology/O has/O to/O be/O invented/O ,/O integrated/O and/O adapted/O into/O solutions/O that/O automate/O specific/O activities/O ./O 
Second/ORDINAL is/O the/O cost/O of/O developing/O and/O deploying/O solutions/O ,/O which/O affects/O the/O business/O case/O for/O adoption/O ./O 
Third/ORDINAL are/O labor/O market/O dynamics/O ,/O including/O the/O supply/O ,/O demand/O ,/O and/O costs/O of/O human/O labor/O as/O an/O alternative/O to/O automation/O ./O 
Fourth/ORDINAL are/O economic/O benefits/O ,/O which/O could/O include/O higher/O throughput/O and/O increased/O quality/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O labor/O cost/O savings/O ./O 
Finally/O ,/O regulatory/O and/O social/O acceptance/O can/O affect/O the/O rate/O of/O adoption/O even/O when/O deployment/O makes/O business/O sense/O ./O 
Taking/O all/O of/O these/O factors/O into/O account/O ,/O we/O estimate/O it/O will/O take/O decades/DURATION for/O automation/O 's/O effect/O on/O current/DATE work/O activities/O to/O play/O out/O fully/O ./O 
While/O the/O effects/O of/O automation/O might/O be/O slow/O at/O a/O macro/O level/O within/O entire/O sectors/O or/O economies/O ,/O they/O could/O be/O quite/O fast/O at/O a/O micro/O level/O ,/O for/O an/O individual/O worker/O whose/O activities/O are/O automated/O ,/O or/O a/O company/O whose/O industry/O is/O disrupted/O by/O competitors/O using/O automation/O ./O 
&#131;/O While/O much/O of/O the/O current/DATE debate/O about/O automation/O has/O focused/O on/O the/O potential/O for/O mass/O unemployment/O ,/O predicated/O on/O a/O surplus/O of/O human/O labor/O ,/O the/O world/O 's/O economy/O will/O actually/O need/O every/O erg/O of/O human/O labor/O working/O ,/O in/O addition/O to/O the/O robots/O ,/O to/O overcome/O demographic/O aging/O trends/O in/O both/O developed/O and/O developing/O economies/O ./O 
In/O other/O words/O ,/O a/O surplus/O of/O human/O labor/O is/O much/O less/O likely/O to/O occur/O than/O a/O deficit/O of/O human/O labor/O ,/O unless/O automation/O is/O deployed/O widely/O ./O 
However/O ,/O the/O nature/O of/O work/O will/O change/O ./O 
As/O processes/O are/O transformed/O by/O the/O automation/O of/O individual/O activities/O ,/O people/O will/O perform/O activities/O that/O are/O complementary/O to/O the/O work/O that/O machines/O do/O -LRB-/O and/O vice/O versa/O -RRB-/O ./O 
These/O shifts/O will/O change/O the/O organization/O of/O companies/O ,/O the/O structure/O and/O bases/O of/O competition/O of/O industries/O ,/O and/O business/O models/O ./O 
3/NUMBER For/O a/O discussion/O of/O skill-biased/O and/O unskill-biased/O technical/O change/O see/O \/O David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON ,/O Frank/PERSON Levy/PERSON ,/O and/O Richard/PERSON J./PERSON Murnane/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O skill/O content/O of/O recent/O technological/O change/O :/O An/O empirical/O explanation/O ,/O ''/O Quarterly/SET Journal/O of/O Economics/O ,/O November/DATE 2003/DATE ,/O and/O Daron/PERSON Acemoglu/PERSON and/O David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON ,/O ''/O Skills/O ,/O tasks/O ,/O and/O technologies/O :/O Implications/O for/O employment/O and/O earnings/O ,/O ''/O in/O Handbook/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Economics/ORGANIZATION ,/O volume/O 4B/O ,/O David/PERSON Card/PERSON and/O Orley/PERSON Ashenfelter/PERSON ,/O eds./O ,/O Elsevier/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE ./O 
4/NUMBER David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON ,/O ``/O Why/O are/O there/O still/O so/O many/O jobs/O ?/O 
McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION 3/ORGANIZATION &#131;/O For/O business/O ,/O the/O performance/O benefits/O of/O automation/O are/O relatively/O clear/O ,/O but/O the/O issues/O are/O more/O complicated/O for/O policy/O makers/O ./O 
They/O should/O embrace/O the/O opportunity/O for/O their/O economies/O to/O benefit/O from/O the/O productivity/O growth/O potential/O and/O put/O in/O place/O policies/O to/O encourage/O investment/O and/O market/O incentives/O to/O encourage/O continued/O progress/O and/O innovation/O ./O 
At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O they/O must/O evolve/O and/O innovate/O policies/O that/O help/O workers/O and/O institutions/O adapt/O to/O the/O impact/O on/O employment/O ./O 
This/O will/O likely/O include/O rethinking/O education/O and/O training/O ,/O income/O support/O ,/O and/O safety/O nets/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O transition/O support/O for/O those/O dislocated/O ./O 
Individuals/O in/O the/O workplace/O will/O need/O to/O engage/O more/O comprehensively/O with/O machines/O as/O part/O of/O their/O everyday/O activities/O ,/O and/O acquire/O new/O skills/O that/O will/O be/O in/O demand/O in/O the/O new/O automation/O age/O ./O 
The/O scale/O of/O shifts/O in/O the/O labor/O force/O over/O many/O decades/DURATION that/O automation/O technologies/O can/O unleash/O is/O of/O a/O similar/O order/O of/O magnitude/O to/O the/O long-term/O technology-enabled/O shifts/O in/O the/O developed/O countries/O '/O workforces/O away/O from/O agriculture/O in/O the/DATE 20th/DATE century/DATE ./O 
Those/O shifts/O did/O not/O result/O in/O long-term/O mass/O unemployment/O because/O they/O were/O accompanied/O by/O the/O creation/O of/O new/O types/O of/O work/O not/O foreseen/O at/O the/O time/DATE ./O 
We/O can/O not/O definitively/O say/O whether/O historical/O precedent/O will/O be/O upheld/O this/O time/O ./O 
But/O our/O analysis/O shows/O that/O humans/O will/O still/O be/O needed/O in/O the/O workforce/O :/O the/O total/O productivity/O gains/O we/O estimate/O will/O come/O about/O only/O if/O people/O work/O alongside/O machines/O ./O 
GAUGING/O AUTOMATION/O POTENTIAL/O IN/O THE/O GLOBAL/O WORKPLACE/O TODAY/DATE The/O Czech/O writer/O Karel/PERSON Capek/PERSON coined/O the/O word/O ``/O robot/O ''/O almost/O a/DATE century/DATE ago/DATE ,/O in/O a/O 1920/DATE play/O about/O factory/O androids/O that/O each/O do/O the/O work/O of/O two-and-a-half/O humans/O at/O a/O fraction/O of/O the/O cost/O ./O 
5/NUMBER Science/O fiction/O has/O since/O become/O business/O fact/O ./O 
Robots/O are/O commonplace/O in/O manufacturing/O ,/O and/O algorithms/O are/O playing/O an/O ever-larger/O role/O in/O companies/O from/O UPS/ORGANIZATION to/O Amazon/LOCATION ./O 
6/NUMBER With/O recent/O developments/O in/O robotics/O ,/O artificial/O intelligence/O ,/O and/O machine/O learning/O ,/O technologies/O not/O only/O do/O things/O that/O we/O thought/O only/O humans/O could/O do/O ,/O but/O also/O can/O increasingly/O do/O them/O at/O superhuman/O levels/O of/O performance/O ./O 
Some/O robots/O that/O are/O far/O more/O flexible/O --/O and/O a/O fraction/O of/O the/O cost/O --/O of/O those/O used/O in/O manufacturing/O environments/O today/DATE can/O be/O ``/O trained/O ''/O by/O frontline/O staff/O to/O perform/O tasks/O that/O were/O previously/DATE thought/O to/O be/O too/O difficult/O for/O machines/O ,/O and/O are/O even/O starting/O to/O take/O over/O service/O activities/O ,/O from/O cooking/O hamburgers/O to/O dispensing/O drugs/O in/O hospital/O pharmacies/O ./O 
Artificial/O intelligence/O is/O also/O making/O major/O strides/O :/O in/O one/NUMBER recent/O test/O ,/O computers/O were/O able/O to/O read/O lips/O with/O 95/PERCENT percent/PERCENT accuracy/O ,/O outperforming/O professional/O human/O lip/O readers/O who/O tested/O at/O 52/PERCENT percent/PERCENT accuracy/O ./O 
7/NUMBER We/O used/O the/O state/O of/O technology/O in/O respect/O to/O 18/NUMBER performance/O capabilities/O to/O estimate/O the/O technical/O automation/O potential/O of/O more/O than/O 2,000/NUMBER work/O activities/O from/O more/O than/O 800/NUMBER occupations/O across/O the/O US/LOCATION economy/O ,/O and/O then/O broadened/O our/O analysis/O across/O the/O global/O economy/O -LRB-/O see/O Box/O E1/O ,/O ``/O How/O we/O established/O the/O technical/O automation/O potential/O of/O the/O global/O economy/O ''/O -RRB-/O ./O 
5/NUMBER The/O word/O ``/O robot/O ''/O comes/O from/O the/O Slavic/O word/O for/O work/O ,/O ``/O robota/O ./O ''/O 
Karel/PERSON Capek/PERSON ,/O R.U.R./O -LRB-/O Rossum/ORGANIZATION 's/O Universal/O Robots/O -RRB-/O ,/O 1920/DATE ./O 
The/O play/O is/O available/O at/O www.gutenberg.org/O ./O 
6/NUMBER Steven/PERSON Rosenbush/PERSON and/O Laura/PERSON Stevens/PERSON ,/O ``/O At/O UPS/ORGANIZATION ,/O the/O algorithm/O is/O the/O dri/ORGANIZATION \/O ver/O ,/O ''/O Wall/O Street/O Journal/O ,/O February/DATE 16/DATE ,/DATE 2015/DATE ./O 
Amazon/O employees/O can/O pick/O and/O pack/O three/NUMBER times/O as/O many/O products/O per/O hour/DURATION with/O the/O help/O of/O robots/O ./O 
Eugene/PERSON Kim/PERSON ,/O ``/O Amazon/LOCATION is/O now/DATE using/O a/O whole/O lot/O more/O of/O the/O robots/O from/O the/O company/O it/O bought/O for/O $/MONEY 775/MONEY million/MONEY ,/O ''/O Business/O Insider/O ,/O October/DATE 22/DATE ,/DATE 2015/DATE ;/O Kim/PERSON Bhasin/PERSON and/O Patrick/PERSON Clark/PERSON ,/O ``/O How/O Amazon/LOCATION trigger/O \/O ed/O a/O robot/O arms/O race/O ,/O ''/O Bloomberg/ORGANIZATION ,/O June/DATE 29/DATE ,/DATE 2016/DATE ./O 
7/NUMBER Hal/PERSON Hodson/PERSON ,/O ``/O Google/ORGANIZATION 's/O DeepMind/O AI/O can/O lip-read/O TV/O shows/O better/O than/O a/O pro/O ,/O ''/O New/O Scientist/O ,/O November/DATE 21/DATE ,/DATE 2016/DATE ./O 
McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION InstituteA/ORGANIZATION future/DATE that/O works/O :/O Automation/O ,/O employment/O ,/O and/O productivity/O 4/NUMBER Executive/O summary/O Box/O E1/O ./O 
How/O we/O established/O the/O technical/O automation/O potential/O of/O the/O global/O economy/O To/O assess/O the/O technical/O automation/O potential/O of/O the/O global/O economy/O ,/O we/O used/O a/O disaggregation/O of/O occupations/O into/O constituent/O activities/O that/O people/O are/O paid/O to/O do/O in/O the/O global/O workplace/O ./O 
Each/O of/O these/O activities/O requires/O some/O combination/O of/O 18/NUMBER performance/O capabilities/O ,/O which/O we/O list/O in/O Exhibit/O E1/O ./O 
They/O are/O in/O five/NUMBER groups/O :/O sensory/O perception/O ,/O cognitive/O capabilities/O ,/O natural/O language/O processing/O ,/O social/O and/O emotional/O capabilities/O ,/O and/O physical/O capabilities/O ./O 
We/O estimated/O the/O level/O of/O performance/O for/O each/O of/O these/O capabilities/O that/O is/O required/O to/O perform/O each/O work/O activity/O successfully/O ,/O based/O on/O the/O way/O humans/O currently/DATE perform/O activities/O --/O that/O is/O ,/O whether/O the/O capability/O is/O required/O at/O all/O ,/O and/O if/O so/O ,/O whether/O the/O required/O level/O of/O performance/O was/O at/O roughly/O a/O median/O human/O level/O ,/O below/O median/O human/O level/O ,/O or/O at/O a/O high/O human/O level/O of/O performance/O -LRB-/O for/O example/O ,/O top/O 25th/ORDINAL percentile/O -RRB-/O ./O 
We/O then/O assessed/O the/O performance/O of/O existing/O technologies/O today/DATE based/O on/O the/O same/O criteria/O ./O 
This/O analysis/O enabled/O us/O to/O estimate/O the/O technical/O automation/O potential/O of/O more/O than/O 2,000/NUMBER work/O activities/O in/O more/O than/O 800/NUMBER occupations/O across/O the/O economy/O ,/O based/O on/O data/O from/O the/O US/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION ./O 
By/O estimating/O the/O amount/O of/O time/O spent/O on/O each/O of/O these/O work/O activities/O ,/O we/O were/O able/O to/O estimate/O the/O automation/O potential/O of/O occupations/O in/O sectors/O across/O the/O economy/O ,/O comparing/O them/O with/O hourly/SET wage/O levels/O ./O 
Drawing/O on/O industry/O experts/O ,/O we/O also/O developed/O scenarios/O for/O how/O rapidly/O the/O performance/O of/O automation/O technologies/O could/O improve/O in/O each/O of/O these/O capabilities/O ./O 
The/O analysis/O we/O conducted/O for/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION provided/O us/O with/O a/O template/O for/O estimating/O the/O automation/O potential/O and/O creating/O adoption/O timing/O scenarios/O for/O 45/NUMBER other/O economies/O representing/O about/O 80/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O the/O global/O workforce/O ./O 
For/O details/O of/O our/O methodology/O ,/O see/O the/O technical/O appendix/O ./O 
Exhibit/O E/O 1/NUMBER Social/O and/O emotional/O capabilities/O ?/O Social/O and/O emotional/O sensing/O ?/O Social/O and/O emotional/O reasoning/O ?/O Emotional/O and/O social/O output/O Physical/O capabilities/O ?/O Fine/O motor/O skills/dexterity/O ?/O Gross/O motor/O skills/O ?/O Navigation/O ?/O Mobility/O SOURCE/O :/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION analysis/O To/O assess/O the/O technical/O potential/O of/O automation/O ,/O we/O structure/O our/O analysis/O around/O 2,000/NUMBER distinct/O work/O activities/O Occupations/ORGANIZATION Activities/ORGANIZATION Capability/ORGANIZATION requirements/O Retail/O salespeople/O Food/O and/O beverage/O service/O workers/O Teachers/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION practitioners/O ?/O ?/O ?/O ~/O 800/NUMBER occupations/O Greet/O customers/O Answer/O questions/O about/O products/O and/O services/O Clean/O and/O maintain/O work/O areas/O Demonstrate/O product/O features/O ?/O ?/O ?/O ~/O 2,000/NUMBER activities/O assessed/O across/O all/O occupations/O Process/O sales/O and/O transactions/O Sensory/O perception/O ?/O Sensory/O perception/O Cognitive/O capabilities/O ?/O Retrieving/O information/O ?/O Recognizing/O known/O patterns/categories/O -LRB-/O supervised/O learning/O -RRB-/O ?/O Generating/O novel/O patterns/categories/O ?/O Logical/O reasoning/problem/O solving/O ?/O Optimizing/O and/O planning/O ?/O Creativity/O ?/O Articulating/display/O output/O ?/O Coordination/O with/O multiple/O agents/O Natural/ORGANIZATION language/O processing/O ?/O Natural/O language/O generation/O ?/O Natural/O language/O understanding/O Automation/O Exhibits/O --/O ES/O mc/O 0117/DATE Box/ORGANIZATION E1/ORGANIZATION McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION 5/ORGANIZATION Only/O a/O small/O percentage/O of/O occupations/O can/O be/O fully/O automated/O by/O adapting/O current/DATE technologies/O ,/O but/O some/O work/O activities/O of/O almost/O all/O occupations/O could/O be/O automated/O Unlike/O some/O other/O studies/O ,/O the/O core/O of/O our/O analysis/O focuses/O on/O work/O activities/O rather/O than/O whole/O occupations/O ./O 
We/O consider/O work/O activities/O a/O more/O relevant/O and/O useful/O measure/O since/O occupations/O are/O made/O up/O of/O a/O range/O of/O activities/O with/O different/O potential/O for/O automation/O ./O 
8/NUMBER For/O example/O ,/O a/O retail/O salesperson/O will/O spend/O some/O time/O interacting/O with/O customers/O ,/O stocking/O shelves/O ,/O or/O ringing/O up/O sales/O ./O 
Each/O of/O these/O activities/O is/O distinct/O and/O requires/O different/O capabilities/O to/O perform/O successfully/O ./O 
Overall/O ,/O we/O estimate/O that/O 49/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O the/O activities/O that/O people/O are/O paid/O to/O do/O in/O the/O global/O economy/O have/O the/O potential/O to/O be/O automated/O by/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technology/O ./O 
While/O less/O than/O 5/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O occupations/O can/O be/O fully/O automated/O ,/O about/O 60/PERCENT percent/PERCENT have/O at/O least/O 30/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O activities/O that/O can/O technically/O be/O automated/O -LRB-/O Exhibit/O E2/O -RRB-/O ./O 
While/O certain/O categories/O of/O activity/O ,/O such/O as/O processing/O or/O collecting/O data/O ,/O or/O performing/O physical/O activities/O and/O operating/O machinery/O in/O a/O predictable/O environment/O ,/O have/O a/O high/O technical/O potential/O for/O automation/O ,/O the/O susceptibility/O is/O significantly/O lower/O for/O other/O activities/O including/O interfacing/O with/O stakeholders/O ,/O applying/O expertise/O to/O decision/O making/O ,/O planning/O ,/O and/O creative/O tasks/O ,/O or/O managing/O and/O developing/O people/O -LRB-/O Exhibit/O E3/O -RRB-/O ./O 
8/NUMBER Most/O recent/O studies/O estimating/O the/O impact/O of/O automation/O in/O the/O workplace/O focus/O \/O on/O occupations/O ./O 
See/O Carl/PERSON Benedikt/PERSON Frey/PERSON and/O Michael/PERSON A./PERSON Osborne/PERSON ,/O The/DATE future/DATE of/O employment/O :/O How/O susceptible/O are/O jobs/O to/O computerisation/O ?/O 
Oxford/ORGANIZATION Martin/ORGANIZATION School/ORGANIZATION ,/O September/DATE 17/DATE ,/DATE 2013/DATE ;/O The/DATE future/DATE of/O jobs/O :/O Employment/O ,/O skills/O ,/O and/O workforce/O strategy/O for/O the/O fourth/ORDINAL Industrial/O Revolution/O ,/O World/O Economic/O Forum/O ,/O January/DATE 2016/DATE ./O 
Exhibit/O E/O 2/NUMBER 100/DATE 91/DATE 73/DATE 62/DATE 51/DATE 42/DATE 34/DATE 26/DATE 18/DATE 8/DATE 1/DATE >/O 10/NUMBER >/O 20/NUMBER >/O 0/NUMBER >/O 30/NUMBER >/O 40/NUMBER >/O 60/NUMBER >/O 50/NUMBER >/O 70/NUMBER >/O 90/NUMBER 100/NUMBER >/O 80/NUMBER Technical/O automation/O potential/O -LRB-/O %/O -RRB-/O Share/O of/O roles/O -LRB-/O %/O -RRB-/O 100/PERCENT %/PERCENT =/O 820/NUMBER roles/O While/O few/O occupations/O are/O fully/O automatable/O ,/O 60/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O all/O occupations/O have/O at/O least/O 30/PERCENT percent/PERCENT technically/O automatable/O activities/O SOURCE/O :/O US/ORGANIZATION Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION ;/ORGANIZATION McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION analysis/O 1W/O e/O define/O automation/O potential/O according/O to/O the/O work/O activities/O that/O can/O be/O automated/O by/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technology/O ./O 
REPEATS/O in/O report/O Automation/O potential/O based/O on/O demonstrated/O technology/O of/O occupation/O titles/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION -LRB-/O cumulative/O -RRB-/O 1/NUMBER Example/O occupations/O Sewing/O machine/O operators/O ,/O graders/O and/O sorters/O of/O agricultural/O products/O Stock/O clerks/O ,/O travel/O agents/O ,/O watch/O repairers/O Chemicaltechnicians/O ,/O n/O ursing/O assistants/O ,/O Web/O developers/O Fashion/O designers/O ,/O chief/O executives/O ,/O statisticians/O Psychiatrists/O ,/O legislators/O About/O 60/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O occupations/O have/O at/O least/O 30/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O their/O activities/O that/O are/O automatable/O </O 5/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O occupations/O consist/O of/O activities/O that/O are/O 100/PERCENT %/PERCENT automatable/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION InstituteA/ORGANIZATION future/DATE that/O works/O :/O Automation/O ,/O employment/O ,/O and/O productivity/O 6/NUMBER Executive/O summary/O The/O degree/O of/O automation/O potential/O varies/O considerably/O among/O sectors/O and/O countries/O A/O significant/O degree/O of/O variation/O among/O sectors/O of/O the/O economy/O ,/O and/O among/O the/O occupations/O within/O those/O sectors/O ,/O emerges/O from/O this/O analysis/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O almost/O one-fifth/ORDINAL of/O the/O time/O spent/O in/O US/LOCATION workplaces/O involves/O predictable/O physical/O activity/O and/O is/O prevalent/O in/O such/O sectors/O as/O manufacturing/O and/O retail/O trade/O ./O 
Accordingly/O ,/O these/O sectors/O have/O a/O relatively/O high/O technical/O potential/O for/O automation/O using/O today/DATE 's/O technology/O ./O 
Exhibit/O E4/O shows/O a/O range/O of/O sectors/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION economy/O broken/O down/O into/O different/O categories/O of/O work/O activity/O ./O 
9/NUMBER 9/NUMBER An/O interactive/O mapping/O of/O the/O automation/O potential/O of/O multiple/O sectors/O o/O \/O f/O the/O economy/O is/O available/O online/O at/O http://public.tableau.com/profile/mckinsey.analytics#!//O Exhibit/O E/O 3/NUMBER SOURCE/O :/O US/ORGANIZATION Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION ;/ORGANIZATION McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION analysis/O Three/NUMBER categories/O of/O work/O activities/O have/O significantly/O higher/O technical/O automation/O potential/O 1Managing/O and/O developing/O people/O .2/NUMBER Applying/O expertise/O to/O decision/O making/O ,/O planning/O ,/O and/O creative/O tasks/O .3/NUMBER Interfacing/O with/O stakeholders/O .4/NUMBER Performing/O physical/O activities/O and/O operating/O machinery/O in/O unpredictable/O environments/O .5/NUMBER Performing/O physical/O activities/O and/O operating/O machinery/O in/O predictable/O environments.NOTE/O :/O Numbers/O may/O not/O sum/O due/O to/O rounding/O ./O 
REPEATS/O in/O report/O 714/NUMBER 1612/DATE 17/DATE 16/DATE 18/DATE Process/O data/O Unpredict/PERSON -/O able/O physical/O 4/NUMBER Predictable/O physical/O 5/NUMBER Interface/O 3/NUMBER Expertise/O 2/NUMBER Manage/O 1/NUMBER Collect/O data/O Time/ORGANIZATION spent/O in/O all/O US/LOCATION occupations/PERCENT %/PERCENT Time/O spent/O on/O activities/O that/O can/O be/O automated/O by/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technology/O %/DATE 9/DATE 18/DATE 20/DATE 26/DATE 64/DATE 69/DATE 81/DATE Total/O wages/O in/O US/LOCATION ,/O 2014/DATE $/MONEY billion/MONEY 596/MONEY 1,190/MONEY 8965041,030/MONEY 931766/MONEY Most/O susceptible/O activities/O 51/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O total/O working/O hours/DURATION $/MONEY 2.7/MONEY trillion/MONEY in/O wages/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION 7/ORGANIZATION Exhibit/O E/O 4/NUMBER SOURCE/O :/O US/ORGANIZATION Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION ;/ORGANIZATION McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION analysis/O Technical/O potential/O for/O automation/O across/O sectors/O varies/O depending/O on/O mix/O of/O activity/O types/O Manage/O Expertise/O Inter/O -/O face/O Process/O data/O Predict/O -/O able/O physical/O Unpredict/PERSON -/O able/O physical/O Collect/O data/O Automation/O potential/O %/O Sectors/O by/O activity/O type/O Accommodation/O and/O food/O services/O Manufacturing/ORGANIZATION Agriculture/ORGANIZATION Transportation/ORGANIZATION and/O warehousing/O Retail/O trade/O Mining/O Other/O services/O Construction/O Utilities/O Wholesale/O trade/O Finance/O and/O insurance/O Arts/O ,/O entertainment/O ,/O and/O recreation/ORGANIZATION Real/ORGANIZATION estate/ORGANIZATION Administrative/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION care/O and/O social/O assistances/O Information/ORGANIZATION Professionals/ORGANIZATION Management/ORGANIZATION Educational/ORGANIZATION services/O 0/NUMBER 50/NUMBER 100/NUMBER Ability/O to/O automate/O -LRB-/O %/O -RRB-/O Size/O of/O bubble/O indicates/O %/O of/O time/O spent/O in/O US/LOCATION occupations/O 2735/DATE 3536/NUMBER 36/NUMBER 394041/NUMBER 4344/DATE 44/DATE 47/DATE 49/DATE 5153/DATE 5758/NUMBER 60/NUMBER 73/NUMBER McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION InstituteA/ORGANIZATION future/DATE that/O works/O :/O Automation/O ,/O employment/O ,/O and/O productivity/O 8/NUMBER Executive/O summary/O Within/O sectors/O ,/O too/O ,/O there/O is/O considerable/O variation/O ./O 
In/O manufacturing/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O occupations/O that/O have/O a/O large/O proportion/O of/O physical/O activities/O in/O predictable/O environments/O such/O as/O factory/O welders/O ,/O cutters/O ,/O and/O solderers/O have/O a/O technical/O automation/O potential/O above/O 90/PERCENT percent/PERCENT based/O on/O adapting/O currently/DATE developed/O technologies/O ,/O whereas/O for/O customer/O service/O representatives/O that/O susceptibility/O is/O less/O than/O 30/PERCENT percent/PERCENT ./O 
While/O wage/O and/O skill/O levels/O are/O negatively/O correlated/O with/O technical/O automation/O potential/O -LRB-/O on/O average/O ,/O occupations/O with/O higher/O wages/O and/O skill/O requirements/O have/O lower/O automation/O potential/O ,/O reflecting/O some/O skill/O bias/O -RRB-/O ,/O a/O large/O amount/O of/O variation/O underlies/O the/O averages/O ./O 
Essentially/O all/O occupations/O ,/O whether/O high/O skill/O or/O low/O skill/O ,/O have/O some/O technical/O automation/O potential/O ,/O including/O CEOs/O ;/O we/O estimate/O about/O 25/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O their/O work/O could/O potentially/O be/O automated/O ,/O primarily/O such/O tasks/O as/O analyzing/O reports/O and/O data/O to/O inform/O decisions/O ,/O reviewing/O status/O reports/O ,/O preparing/O staff/O assignments/O ,/O and/O so/O on/O ./O 
At/O a/O global/O level/O ,/O technically/O automatable/O activities/O touch/O the/O equivalent/O of/O 1.1/NUMBER billion/NUMBER employees/O and/O $/MONEY 15.8/MONEY trillion/MONEY in/O wages/O -LRB-/O Exhibit/O E5/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Four/NUMBER economies/O --/O China/LOCATION ,/O India/LOCATION ,/O Japan/LOCATION ,/O and/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION --/O account/O for/O just/O over/O half/O of/O these/O total/O wages/O and/O employees/O ;/O China/LOCATION and/O India/LOCATION together/O account/O for/O the/O largest/O technically/O automatable/O employment/O potential/O --/O more/O than/O 700/NUMBER million/NUMBER full-time/O equivalents/O between/O them/O --/O because/O of/O the/O relative/O size/O of/O their/O labor/O forces/O ./O 
The/O potential/O is/O also/O large/O in/O Europe/LOCATION :/O according/O to/O our/O analysis/O ,/O 54/NUMBER million/NUMBER full-time/O employee/O equivalents/O and/O more/O than/O $/MONEY 1.7/MONEY trillion/MONEY in/O wages/O are/O associated/O with/O technically/O automatable/O activities/O in/O the/O five/NUMBER largest/O economies/O --/O France/LOCATION ,/O Germany/LOCATION ,/O Italy/LOCATION ,/O Spain/LOCATION ,/O and/O the/O United/LOCATION Kingdom/LOCATION ./O 
Our/O analysis/O of/O the/O technical/O automation/O potential/O of/O the/O global/O economy/O shows/O that/O there/O is/O a/O range/O among/O countries/O of/O about/O 15/PERCENT percentage/PERCENT points/PERCENT ./O 
Two/NUMBER factors/O explain/O this/O range/O ./O 
The/O first/ORDINAL is/O the/O sectoral/O makeup/O of/O each/O economy/O ,/O that/O is/O ,/O the/O proportion/O of/O a/O national/O economy/O that/O is/O in/O sectors/O such/O as/O manufacturing/O or/O accommodation/O and/O food/O services/O ,/O both/O of/O which/O have/O relatively/O high/O automation/O potential/O ,/O compared/O with/O the/O proportion/O in/O sectors/O with/O lower/O automation/O potential/O such/O as/O education/O ./O 
The/O second/ORDINAL factor/O is/O the/O occupational/O makeup/O of/O sectors/O in/O different/O countries/O ,/O in/O other/O words/O ,/O the/O extent/O to/O which/O workers/O in/O these/O sectors/O are/O engaged/O in/O job/O titles/O with/O high/O automation/O potential/O ,/O such/O as/O manufacturing/O production/O ,/O and/O those/O in/O job/O titles/O with/O lower/O automation/O potential/O such/O as/O management/O and/O administration/O ./O 
A/O detailed/O look/O at/O all/O 46/NUMBER countries/O we/O have/O examined/O is/O available/O online/O ./O 
10/NUMBER 10/NUMBER The/O data/O visualization/O can/O be/O found/O on/O the/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION pub/ORGANIZATION \/ORGANIZATION lic/ORGANIZATION site/O at/O tableau.com/O :/O http://public.tableau.com/profile/mckinsey.analytics#!//O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION 9/ORGANIZATION Exhibit/O E/O 5/NUMBER The/O technical/O automation/O potential/O of/O the/O global/O economy/O is/O significant/O ,/O although/O there/O is/O some/O variation/O among/O countries/O SOURCE/O :/O Oxford/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Forecasts/ORGANIZATION ;/O Emsi/O database/O ;/O US/ORGANIZATION Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION ;/ORGANIZATION McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION analysis/O 1Pakistan/O ,/O Bangladesh/LOCATION ,/O Vietnam/LOCATION ,/O and/O Iran/LOCATION are/O largest/O countries/O by/O population/O not/O included/O .2/NUMBER France/LOCATION ,/O Germany/LOCATION ,/O Italy/LOCATION ,/O Spain/LOCATION ,/O and/O the/O United/O Kingdom.NOTE/O :/O Numbers/O may/O not/O sum/O due/O to/O rounding/O ./O 
</O 45/NUMBER 45/NUMBER --/O 47/NUMBER 47/NUMBER --/O 49/NUMBER 49/NUMBER --/O 51/NUMBER >/O 51/NUMBER No/O data/O Employee/O weighted/O overall/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O activities/O that/O can/O be/O automated/O b/O y/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technologies/O 1/NUMBER Technical/O automation/O potential/O is/O concentrated/O in/O countries/O with/O the/O largest/O populations/O and/or/O high/O wages/O Potential/O impact/O due/O to/O automation/O ,/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technology/O -LRB-/O 46/NUMBER countries/O -RRB-/O Wages/O associated/O with/O technically/O automatable/O activities/O $/MONEY trillion/MONEY Labor/O associated/O with/O technically/O automatable/O activities/O Million/NUMBER FTE/O Remaining/O countries/O 1.1/NUMBER 1.1/NUMBER 4.1/NUMBER United/LOCATION States/LOCATION India/LOCATION Europe/LOCATION Big/O 5/NUMBER 2/NUMBER 5.1/NUMBER Japan/LOCATION 1.7/NUMBER China/LOCATION 2.7/NUMBER Japan/LOCATION Europe/LOCATION Big/O 5/NUMBER 254/NUMBER United/LOCATION States/LOCATION 35/NUMBER 60/NUMBER 233/NUMBER China/LOCATION 332/NUMBER 394/NUMBER India/LOCATION Remaining/O countries/O 100/PERCENT %/PERCENT =/O $/MONEY 15.8/MONEY trillion/MONEY 100/MONEY %/MONEY =/O 1,109/NUMBER million/NUMBER FTEs/O Automation/O potential/PERCENT %/PERCENT 50/NUMBER 46/NUMBER 46/NUMBER 51/NUMBER 52/NUMBER 55/NUMBER Japan/LOCATION India/LOCATION China/LOCATION United/LOCATION States/LOCATION Europe/LOCATION Big/O 5/NUMBER 2/NUMBER Rest/O of/O world/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION InstituteA/ORGANIZATION future/DATE that/O works/O :/O Automation/O ,/O employment/O ,/O and/O productivity/O 10/NUMBER Executive/O summary/O FACTORS/O AFFECTING/O PACE/O AND/O EXTENT/O OF/O AUTOMATION/O While/O the/O technology/O is/O advancing/O ,/O the/O journey/O from/O technical/O automation/O potential/O to/O full/O adoption/O is/O nonetheless/O likely/O to/O take/O decades/DURATION ./O 
The/O timing/O is/O affected/O by/O five/NUMBER sets/O of/O factors/O :/O &#131;/O Technical/O feasibility/O ./O 
Technology/O has/O to/O be/O invented/O ,/O integrated/O and/O adapted/O into/O solutions/O that/O automate/O specific/O activities/O ./O 
Deployment/O in/O the/O workplace/O can/O begin/O only/O when/O machines/O have/O reached/O the/O required/O level/O of/O performance/O in/O the/O capabilities/O required/O to/O carry/O out/O particular/O activities/O ./O 
While/O machines/O can/O already/O match/O or/O outperform/O humans/O on/O some/O of/O the/O 18/NUMBER capabilities/O in/O our/O framework/O ,/O including/O information/O retrieval/O ,/O gross/O motor/O skills/O ,/O and/O optimization/O and/O planning/O ,/O many/O other/O capabilities/O require/O more/O technological/O development/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O advancements/O in/O natural/O language/O understanding/O could/O unlock/O significantly/O more/O technical/O automation/O potential/O ./O 
Emotional/O and/O social/O reasoning/O capabilities/O will/O also/O need/O to/O become/O more/O sophisticated/O for/O many/O work/O activities/O ./O 
For/O typical/O work/O activities/O ,/O multiple/O capabilities/O ,/O such/O as/O sensory/O perception/O and/O mobility/O ,/O will/O be/O needed/O simultaneously/O ,/O and/O thus/O solutions/O that/O integrate/O specific/O capabilities/O in/O context/O must/O be/O engineered/O ./O 
&#131;/O Cost/O of/O developing/O and/O deploying/O solutions/O ./O 
The/O cost/O of/O automation/O affects/O the/O business/O case/O for/O adoption/O ./O 
Developing/O and/O engineering/O automation/O technologies/O takes/O capital/O ./O 
Hardware/O solutions/O range/O from/O standard/O computers/O to/O highly/O designed/O ,/O application-specific/O hardware/O such/O as/O robots/O with/O arms/O and/O other/O moving/O parts/O requiring/O dexterity/O ./O 
Cameras/O and/O sensors/O are/O needed/O for/O any/O activity/O requiring/O sensory/O perception/O capabilities/O ,/O while/O mobility/O requires/O wheels/O or/O other/O hardware/O that/O enable/O machines/O to/O move/O ./O 
Such/O attributes/O increase/O costs/O relative/O to/O a/O general-purpose/O hardware/O platform/O ./O 
Even/O ``/O virtual/O ''/O solutions/O that/O are/O based/O on/O software/O require/O real/O investments/O in/O engineering/O to/O create/O solutions/O ./O 
For/O deployment/O ,/O hardware/O requires/O significant/O capital/O spending/O ,/O and/O thus/O automation/O that/O requires/O it/O has/O high/O initial/O costs/O compared/O to/O wages/O ./O 
Software/O solutions/O ,/O by/O comparison/O ,/O tend/O to/O have/O a/O minimal/O marginal/O cost/O ,/O which/O usually/O makes/O them/O less/O expensive/O than/O wages/O and/O thus/O they/O tend/O to/O be/O adopted/O earlier/O ./O 
Over/O time/O ,/O both/O hardware/O and/O software/O costs/O decline/O ,/O making/O solutions/O competitive/O with/O human/O labor/O for/O an/O increasing/O number/O of/O activities/O ./O 
&#131;/O Labor/O market/O dynamics/O ./O 
The/O quality/O -LRB-/O for/O instance/O ,/O skills/O -RRB-/O ,/O quantity/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O supply/O ,/O demand/O ,/O and/O costs/O of/O human/O labor/O as/O an/O alternative/O affect/O which/O activities/O will/O be/O automated/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O restaurant/O cooking/O has/O high/O automation/O potential/O ,/O more/O than/O 75/PERCENT percent/PERCENT ,/O based/O on/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technologies/O ,/O but/O the/O decision/O to/O deploy/O the/O technology/O will/O need/O to/O take/O into/O account/O the/O wage/O costs/O of/O cooks/O ,/O who/O earn/O $/MONEY 11/MONEY per/O hour/DURATION on/O average/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O and/O the/O abundance/O of/O people/O willing/O to/O working/O as/O cooks/O at/O that/O wage/O ./O 
Labor/O market/O dynamics/O also/O differ/O by/O geography/O ,/O not/O only/O in/O terms/O of/O how/O different/O and/O evolving/O demographics/O affect/O the/O base/O supply/O of/O labor/O ,/O but/O also/O different/O wage/O rates/O ./O 
Manufacturing/O automation/O is/O more/O likely/O to/O be/O adopted/O sooner/O in/O countries/O with/O high/O manufacturing/O wages/O ,/O such/O as/O North/LOCATION America/LOCATION and/O Western/LOCATION Europe/LOCATION ,/O than/O in/O developing/O countries/O with/O lower/O wages/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O the/O effects/O of/O automation/O can/O interact/O with/O labor/O market/O skills/O and/O supply/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O if/O middle-income/O workers/O such/O as/O clerks/O and/O factory/O workers/O are/O displaced/O by/O the/O automation/O of/O data/O collection/O and/O processing/O and/O predictable/O physical/O activities/O ,/O they/O could/O find/O themselves/O moving/O into/O lower/O paid/O occupations/O ,/O increasing/O supply/O ,/O and/O potentially/O putting/O downward/O pressure/O on/O wages/O ./O 
Conversely/O ,/O they/O might/O take/O time/O to/O retrain/O into/O other/O high/O -/O skill/O positions/O ,/O delaying/O their/O re-entry/O into/O the/O labor/O force/O ,/O and/O temporarily/O reducing/O labor/O supply/O ./O 
&#131;/O Economic/O benefits/O ./O 
In/O addition/O to/O labor/O cost/O savings/O ,/O a/O business/O case/O for/O automation/O could/O include/O performance/O gains/O such/O as/O increased/O profit/O ,/O increased/O throughput/O and/O productivity/O ,/O improved/O safety/O ,/O and/O higher/O quality/O ,/O which/O sometimes/O exceed/O the/O benefits/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION 11/NUMBER of/O labor/O substitution/O -LRB-/O see/O Box/O E2/O ,/O ``/O Automation/O technologies/O could/O provide/O significant/O performance/O benefits/O for/O companies/O beyond/O labor/O substitution/O ''/O -RRB-/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O the/O benefits/O of/O increased/O production/O and/O lower/O overall/O maintenance/O costs/O by/O automating/O the/O control/O room/O of/O an/O oil/O and/O gas/O production/O facility/O dwarf/O those/O associated/O with/O reduced/O labor/O costs/O in/O the/O control/O room/O ./O 
Automated/O driving/O of/O cars/O and/O trucks/O could/O not/O only/O reduce/O the/O labor/O costs/O associated/O with/O drivers/O ;/O it/O could/O also/O potentially/O improve/O safety/O -LRB-/O the/O vast/O majority/O of/O accidents/O are/O the/O result/O of/O driver/O errors/O -RRB-/O and/O fuel/O efficiency/O ./O 
Box/O E2/O ./O 
Automation/O technologies/O could/O provide/O significant/O performance/O benefits/O for/O companies/O beyond/O labor/O substitution/O 1/NUMBER Productivity/O improvements/O in/O a/O changing/O world/O ,/O presentation/O by/O Michael/PERSON Gollschewski/PERSON ,/O managing/O director/O Pilbara/ORGANIZATION Mines/ORGANIZATION ,/O Rio/LOCATION Tinto/LOCATION ,/O July/DATE 13/DATE ,/DATE 2015/DATE ./O 
2/NUMBER Rich/PERSON Evans/PERSON and/O Jim/PERSON Gao/PERSON ,/O DeepMind/O AI/O reduces/O energy/O used/O for/O cooling/O Google/ORGANIZATION data/O centers/O by/O 40/PERCENT %/PERCENT ,/O Google/ORGANIZATION ,/O blog/O post/O ,/O July/DATE 20/DATE ,/DATE 2016/DATE ./O 
3/NUMBER Jo?o/PERSON Bueno/PERSON ,/O Yran/PERSON Bartolumeu/PERSON Dias/PERSON ,/O Alexandre/PERSON Sawaya/PERSON ,/O Jorge/PERSON Valadas/PERSON ./O 
``/O End-to-end/O digitization/O for/O securities/O services/O ,/O ''/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION on/ORGANIZATION Payments/ORGANIZATION ,/O September/DATE 2014/DATE ./O 
4/NUMBER ``/O Barack/PERSON Obama/PERSON :/O Self-driving/O ,/O yes/O ,/O but/O also/O safe/O ,/O ''/O Pittsburgh/ORGANIZATION Post-Gazette/ORGANIZATION ,/O September/DATE 19/DATE ,/DATE 2016/DATE ./O 
The/O deployment/O of/O automation/O technologies/O could/O bring/O a/O range/O of/O performance/O benefits/O for/O companies/O ./O 
These/O benefits/O are/O varied/O ,/O depending/O on/O the/O individual/O use/O case/O ,/O and/O potentially/O very/O substantial/O --/O in/O some/O cases/O ,/O considerably/O larger/O than/O cost/O reductions/O associated/O with/O labor/O substitution/O ./O 
They/O include/O ,/O but/O are/O not/O limited/O to/O ,/O greater/O throughput/O ,/O higher/O quality/O ,/O improved/O safety/O ,/O reduced/O variability/O ,/O a/O reduction/O of/O waste/O ,/O and/O higher/O customer/O satisfaction/O ./O 
We/O developed/O several/O hypothetical/O case/O studies/O to/O gain/O a/O better/O understanding/O of/O the/O potential/O for/O automation/O in/O different/O settings/O and/O sought/O to/O quantify/O the/O economic/O impact/O of/O realizing/O this/O vision/O ./O 
The/O case/O studies/O are/O of/O a/O hospital/O emergency/O department/O ,/O aircraft/O maintenance/O ,/O oil/O and/O gas/O operations/O ,/O a/O grocery/O store/O ,/O and/O mortgage/O brokering/O ./O 
The/O results/O --/O while/O forward-looking/O --/O are/O nonetheless/O striking/O ./O 
The/O value/O of/O the/O potential/O benefits/O of/O automation/O ,/O calculated/O as/O a/O percentage/O of/O operating/O costs/O ,/O ranges/O from/O between/O 10-15/PERCENT percent/PERCENT for/O a/O hospital/O emergency/O department/O and/O a/O grocery/O store/O ,/O to/O 25/PERCENT percent/PERCENT for/O aircraft/O maintenance/O ,/O and/O more/O than/O 90/PERCENT percent/PERCENT for/O mortgage/O origination/O ./O 
We/O also/O see/O automation/O being/O deployed/O today/DATE that/O is/O already/O generating/O real/O value/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O Rio/ORGANIZATION Tinto/ORGANIZATION has/O deployed/O automated/O haul/O trucks/O and/O drilling/O machines/O at/O its/O mines/O in/O Pilbara/LOCATION ,/O Australia/LOCATION ,/O and/O says/O it/O is/O seeing/O 10/NUMBER --/O 20/PERCENT percent/PERCENT increases/O in/O utilization/O there/O as/O a/O result/O ./O 
1/NUMBER Google/ORGANIZATION has/O applied/O artificial/O intelligence/O from/O its/O DeepMind/O machine/O learning/O to/O its/O own/O data/O centers/O ,/O cutting/O the/O amount/O of/O energy/O they/O use/O by/O 40/PERCENT percent/PERCENT ./O 
2/NUMBER In/O financial/O services/O ,/O automation/O in/O the/O form/O of/O ``/O straight-through/O processing/O ,/O ''/O where/O transaction/O workflows/O are/O digitized/O end-to-end/O ,/O can/O increase/O the/O scalability/O of/O transaction/O throughput/O by/O 80/PERCENT percent/PERCENT ,/O while/O concurrently/O reducing/O errors/O by/O half/O ./O 
3/NUMBER Safety/O is/O another/O area/O that/O could/O benefit/O from/O increased/O automation/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O of/O the/O approximately/O 35,000/NUMBER road/O death/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION annually/SET ,/O about/O 94/PERCENT percent/PERCENT are/O the/O result/O of/O human/O error/O or/O choice/O ./O 
4/NUMBER The/O relative/O cost/O of/O automation/O can/O be/O modest/O compared/O with/O the/O value/O it/O can/O create/O ./O 
The/O types/O and/O sizes/O of/O investment/O needed/O to/O automate/O will/O differ/O by/O industry/O and/O sector/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O industries/O with/O high/O capital/O intensity/O that/O require/O substantial/O hardware/O solutions/O to/O automate/O and/O are/O subject/O to/O heavy/O safety/O regulation/O will/O likely/O see/O longer/O lags/O between/O the/O time/O of/O investment/O and/O the/O benefits/O than/O sectors/O where/O automation/O will/O be/O mostly/O software/O -/O based/O and/O less/O capital-intensive/O ./O 
For/O the/O former/O ,/O this/O will/O mean/O a/O longer/O journey/O to/O breakeven/O on/O automation/O investment/O ./O 
However/O ,/O our/O analysis/O suggests/O that/O the/O business/O case/O can/O be/O compelling/O regardless/O of/O the/O degree/O of/O capital/O intensity/O ./O 
McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION InstituteA/ORGANIZATION future/DATE that/O works/O :/O Automation/O ,/O employment/O ,/O and/O productivity/O 12/NUMBER Executive/O summary/O &#131;/O Regulatory/O and/O social/O acceptance/O ./O 
Even/O when/O deploying/O automation/O makes/O business/O sense/O ,/O the/O rate/O of/O adoption/O can/O be/O affected/O by/O contextual/O factors/O such/O as/O regulatory/O approval/O and/O the/O reaction/O of/O users/O ./O 
There/O are/O multiple/O reasons/O that/O technology/O adoption/O does/O not/O happen/O overnight/TIME ./O 
The/O shift/O of/O capital/O investment/O into/O these/O new/O technologies/O takes/O time/O -LRB-/O in/O aggregate/O -RRB-/O ,/O as/O does/O changing/O organizational/O processes/O and/O practices/O to/O adapt/O to/O new/O technologies/O ./O 
Reconfiguring/O supply/O chains/O and/O ecosystems/O can/O be/O laborious/O ,/O and/O regulations/O sometimes/O need/O to/O change/O ./O 
Government/O policy/O can/O slow/O adoption/O ,/O and/O different/O businesses/O adopt/O technologies/O at/O different/O rates/O ./O 
Changing/O the/O activities/O that/O workers/O do/O also/O requires/O dedicated/O effort/O ,/O even/O if/O they/O are/O not/O actively/O resisting/O ./O 
And/O especially/O in/O the/O case/O of/O automation/O ,/O individuals/O may/O feel/O uncomfortable/O about/O a/O new/O world/O where/O machines/O replace/O human/O interaction/O in/O some/O intimate/O life/O settings/O ,/O such/O as/O a/O hospital/O ,/O or/O in/O places/O where/O machines/O are/O expected/O to/O make/O life-and/O -/O death/O decisions/O ,/O such/O as/O when/O driving/O ./O 
Automation/O adoption/O will/O take/O decades/DURATION ,/O across/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O possible/O scenarios/O To/O analyze/O a/O range/O of/O potential/O scenarios/O for/O the/O pace/O at/O which/O automation/O will/O affect/O activities/O across/O the/O global/O economy/O ,/O we/O constructed/O a/O model/O that/O simplifies/O the/O effects/O of/O these/O five/NUMBER factors/O into/O four/NUMBER timing/O stages/O :/O capability/O development/O ,/O solution/O development/O ,/O economic/O feasibility/O ,/O and/O final/O adoption/O ./O 
The/O S-curve/O in/O Exhibit/O E6/O indicates/O the/O potential/O time/O range/O that/O emerges/O from/O our/O scenario/O analyses/O ,/O with/O the/O dark/O blue/O line/O representing/O an/O ``/O earliest/O adoption/O ''/O scenario/O and/O the/O light/O blue/O line/O a/O ``/O latest/O adoption/O ''/O scenario/O ,/O aggregating/O across/O all/O of/O the/O activities/O that/O account/O for/O about/O 80/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O the/O world/O 's/O workforce/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O we/O estimate/O that/O adapting/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technology/O has/O the/O technical/O potential/O to/O automate/O roughly/O 50/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O the/O world/O 's/O current/DATE work/O activities/O ./O 
While/O the/O date/O at/O which/O this/O could/O happen/O could/O be/O around/O 2055/DATE ,/O assuming/O all/O the/O factors/O are/O in/O place/O for/O successful/O adoption/O by/O then/O ,/O we/O modeled/O possible/O scenarios/O where/O that/O level/O of/O adoption/O occurs/O up/O to/O almost/O 20/DATE years/DATE earlier/DATE or/O later/O ./O 
Among/O the/O first/ORDINAL sectors/O likely/O to/O feel/O the/O impact/O of/O automation/O will/O be/O those/O that/O involve/O types/O of/O activities/O we/O categorize/O as/O having/O the/O highest/O automation/O potential/O today/DATE based/O on/O currently/DATE demonstrated/O technology/O ./O 
From/O a/O geographical/O perspective/O ,/O advanced/O economies/O are/O also/O likely/O to/O deploy/O automation/O ahead/O of/O many/O emerging/O economies/O ,/O largely/O because/O of/O higher/O wage/O levels/O ,/O which/O make/O a/O stronger/O business/O case/O for/O deployment/O ./O 
This/O magnitude/O of/O shifts/O in/O work/O activities/O over/O multiple/O decades/DURATION is/O not/O unprecedented/O ./O 
In/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O for/O example/O ,/O the/O share/O of/O farm/O employment/O fell/O from/O 40/PERCENT percent/PERCENT in/U_TEMPPRED 1900/DATE to/O 2/PERCENT percent/PERCENT in/U_TEMPPRED 2000/DATE ,/O while/O the/O share/O of/O manufacturing/O employment/O fell/O from/O approximately/O 25/PERCENT percent/PERCENT in/U_TEMPPRED 1950/DATE to/O less/O than/O 10/PERCENT percent/PERCENT in/U_TEMPPRED 2010/DATE -LRB-/O Exhibit/O E/O 7/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
11/NUMBER In/O both/O cases/O ,/O new/O activities/O and/O jobs/O were/O created/O that/O offset/O those/O that/O disappeared/O ,/O although/O it/O was/O not/O possible/O to/O predict/O what/O those/O new/O activities/O and/O jobs/O would/O be/O while/O these/O shifts/O were/O occurring/O ./O 
11/NUMBER Stanley/PERSON Lebergott/PERSON ,/O ``/O Labor/O force/O and/O employment/O 1800/DATE --/O 1960/DATE ,/O ''/O in/O Output/O ,/O employment/O ,/O and/O productivity/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION after/O 1800/DATE ,/O Dorothy/PERSON S./PERSON Brady/PERSON ,/O ed./O ,/O NBER/ORGANIZATION ,/O 1966/DATE ;/O World/O Bank/O data/O ;/O Mack/PERSON Ott/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O growing/O share/O of/O services/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION economy/O --/O degeneration/O or/O evolution/O ?/O ''/O 
Federal/ORGANIZATION Reserve/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION St./ORGANIZATION Louis/ORGANIZATION Review/ORGANIZATION ,/O June/July/DATE 1987/DATE ./O 
McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION 13/ORGANIZATION Exhibit/ORGANIZATION E/ORGANIZATION 6/ORGANIZATION 202100/DATE 80/DATE 75/DATE 70/DATE 65/DATE 100/DATE 85/DATE 95/DATE 60/DATE 90/DATE 50/DATE 55/DATE 50/DATE 60/DATE 20/DATE 70/DATE 30/DATE 10/DATE 90/DATE 0/DATE 80/DATE 40/DATE 45/DATE 35/DATE 25/DATE 30/DATE 40/DATE Automation/O will/O be/O a/O global/O force/O ,/O but/O adoption/O will/O take/O decades/DURATION and/O there/O is/O significant/O uncertainty/O on/O timing/O SOURCE/O :/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION analysis/O 1Forty-six/O countries/O used/O in/O this/O calculation/O ,/O representing/O about/O 80/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O global/O labor/O force/O ./O 
Time/O spent/O on/O current/DATE work/O activities/O 1/PERCENT %/PERCENT 2016/DATE REPEATS/O in/O report/O Adoption/O Early/O scenario/O Late/O scenario/O Technical/O automation/O potential/O Early/O scenario/O Late/O scenario/O Exhibit/O E/O 7/NUMBER SOURCE/O :/O Stanley/PERSON Lebergott/PERSON ,/O ``/O Labor/O force/O and/O employment/O 1800/DATE --/O 1960/DATE ,/O ''/O in/O Output/O ,/O employment/O ,/O and/O productivity/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION after/O 1800/DATE ,/O Dorothy/PERSON S./PERSON Brady/PERSON ,/O ed./O ,/O NBER/ORGANIZATION ,/O 1966/DATE ;/O W/O orld/O Data/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION ,/O W/O orld/O Bank/ORGANIZATION Group/ORGANIZATION ;/O FRED/O :/O Economic/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION ,/O Federal/ORGANIZATION Reserve/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION St./ORGANIZATION Louis/ORGANIZATION ;/O Mack/PERSON Ott/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O growing/O share/O of/O services/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION economy/O --/O degeneration/O or/O evolution/O ?/O ''/O 
Federal/ORGANIZATION Reserve/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION St./ORGANIZATION Louis/ORGANIZATION Review/ORGANIZATION ,/O June/July/O 1987/DATE ;/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION analysis/O Employment/O in/O agriculture/O has/O fallen/O from/O 40/PERCENT percent/PERCENT in/U_TEMPPRED 1900/DATE to/O less/O than/O 2/PERCENT percent/PERCENT today/DATE 50/DATE 1900/DATE 4070/DATE 50/DATE 30/DATE 10/DATE 60/DATE 20/DATE 60/DATE 50/DATE 70/DATE 90/DATE 1840/DATE 80/DATE 40/DATE 80/DATE 60/DATE 2000/DATE 80/DATE 90/DATE 70/DATE 20/DATE 30/DATE 10/DATE 2010/DATE 90/DATE 0/DATE Rest/O of/O the/O economy/O Manufacturing/ORGANIZATION Agriculture/ORGANIZATION Distribution/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION labor/ORGANIZATION share/O by/O sector/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O 1840/DATE --/O 2010/PERCENT %/PERCENT REPEATS/O in/O report/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION InstituteA/ORGANIZATION future/DATE that/O works/O :/O Automation/O ,/O employment/O ,/O and/O productivity/O 14/NUMBER Executive/O summary/O Modeling/O scenarios/O for/O the/O pace/O and/O extent/O of/O automation/O adoption/O Capability/O development/O is/O the/O first/ORDINAL stage/O that/O we/O modeled/O for/O the/O timing/O of/O automation/O adoption/O ./O 
Deployment/O in/O the/O workplace/O can/O begin/O only/O when/O machines/O have/O reached/O the/O required/O level/O of/O performance/O in/O the/O capabilities/O required/O to/O carry/O out/O particular/O activities/O ./O 
Once/DATE the/O technical/O capabilities/O have/O been/O developed/O ,/O they/O must/O be/O integrated/O into/O solutions/O that/O can/O execute/O specific/O activities/O in/O context/O ,/O that/O is/O ,/O to/O create/O commercially/O available/O systems/O ./O 
Our/O analysis/O suggests/O that/O ,/O on/O average/O ,/O this/O solution/O development/O process/O can/O take/O between/O one/NUMBER and/O nine/DURATION years/DURATION ./O 
The/O third/ORDINAL stage/O we/O modeled/O for/O scenario/O timelines/O is/O when/O automation/O is/O economically/O feasible/O ./O 
For/O modeling/O purposes/O ,/O we/O assume/O that/O adoption/O begins/O when/O the/O developed/O solution/O for/O any/O given/O activity/O is/O at/O or/O below/O the/O cost/O for/O human/O workers/O to/O perform/O that/O activity/O in/O a/O specific/O occupation/O and/O within/O a/O particular/O country/O ./O 
12/NUMBER While/O the/O performance/O benefits/O of/O automation/O sometimes/O exceed/O those/O related/O to/O labor/O cost/O savings/O ,/O our/O conservative/O modeling/O assumes/O that/O decision-makers/O discount/O the/O benefits/O of/O initial/O labor/O cost/O savings/O by/O roughly/O the/O same/O amount/O as/O they/O believe/O the/O also/O uncertain/O non-labor/O cost/O -/O related/O benefits/O will/O be/O captured/O ./O 
Adoption/O and/O deployment/O of/O automation/O ,/O the/O fourth/ORDINAL stage/O we/O modeled/O to/O develop/O scenarios/O ,/O can/O also/O be/O a/O slow/O process/O ./O 
For/O our/O analysis/O ,/O we/O looked/O at/O the/O historical/O adoption/O rates/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O 25/NUMBER technologies/O ,/O involving/O both/O hardware/O and/O software/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O business/O and/O consumer/O technologies/O ./O 
The/O time/O between/O the/O commercial/O availability/O of/O these/O technologies/O and/O their/O eventual/O maximum/O level/O of/O adoption/O generally/O took/O at/DURATION least/DURATION nearly/DURATION a/DURATION decade/DURATION and/O in/O some/O cases/O multiple/O decades/DURATION ,/O with/O the/O time/O range/O between/O eight/NUMBER and/O 28/DURATION years/DURATION ./O 
13/NUMBER EVEN/O AS/O IT/O CAUSES/O SHIFTS/O IN/O EMPLOYMENT/O ,/O AUTOMATION/O CAN/O GIVE/O A/O STRONG/O BOOST/O TO/O PRODUCTIVITY/O AND/O GLOBAL/O GDP/O GROWTH/O Automation/O will/O cause/O significant/O labor/O displacement/O and/O could/O exacerbate/O a/O growing/O skills/O and/O employment/O gap/O that/O already/O exists/O between/O high-skill/O and/O low-skill/O workers/O ./O 
14/NUMBER Our/O analysis/O of/O automation/O potential/O also/O suggests/O that/O many/O occupations/O could/O be/O partially/O automated/O before/O they/O are/O fully/O automated/O ,/O which/O could/O have/O different/O implications/O for/O high/O -/O and/O low-skill/O workers/O ./O 
15/NUMBER Especially/O for/O low-skill/O workers/O ,/O this/O process/O could/O depress/O wages/O unless/O demand/O grows/O ./O 
Viewed/O through/O a/O long-term/O perspective/O ,/O however/O ,/O as/O we/O described/O previously/DATE ,/O large-scale/O historical/O structural/O shifts/O in/O the/O workplace/O where/O technology/O has/O caused/O job/O losses/O have/O ,/O over/O time/O ,/O been/O accompanied/O by/O the/O creation/O of/O a/O multitude/O of/O new/O jobs/O ,/O activities/O ,/O and/O types/O of/O work/O ./O 
16/NUMBER Furthermore/O ,/O labor/O markets/O can/O be/O quite/O dynamic/O :/O almost/O five/NUMBER million/NUMBER people/O leave/O their/O jobs/O every/SET month/SET in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O of/O whom/O about/O 12/NUMBER By/O costs/O in/O this/O case/O ,/O we/O mean/O wages/O plus/O benefits/O ,/O calculated/O globall/O \/O y/O on/O a/O purchasing/O power/O parity/O basis/O .13/NUMBER Some/O of/O the/O technologies/O we/O modeled/O have/O not/O likely/O yet/O reached/O their/O eventual/O peak/O in/O adoption/O .14/NUMBER There/O has/O been/O a/O proliferation/O of/O books/O by/O competing/O schools/O of/O ``/O techno-optimists/O ''/O an/O \/O d/O ``/O techno-pessimists/O ./O ''/O 
They/O notably/O include/O Erik/PERSON Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O Andrew/PERSON McAfee/PERSON ,/O The/O second/ORDINAL machine/O age/O :/O Work/O ,/O progress/O ,/O and/O prosperity/O in/O a/O time/O of/O brilliant/O technologies/O ,/O W./ORGANIZATION W./ORGANIZATION Norton/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2014/DATE ;/O Robert/PERSON Gordon/PERSON ,/O The/O rise/O and/O fall/O of/O American/O growth/O :/O The/O US/LOCATION standard/O of/O living/O since/O the/O Civil/O War/O ,/O Princeton/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION Press/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2016/DATE ;/O and/O Martin/PERSON Ford/PERSON ,/O Rise/O of/O the/O robots/O :/O Technology/O and/O the/O threat/O of/O a/O jobless/O future/DATE ,/O Basic/O Books/O ,/O 2015/DATE ./O 
Also/O Jason/PERSON Furman/PERSON ,/O ``/O Is/O this/O time/O different/O ?/O 
The/O opportunities/O and/O challenges/O of/O artificial/O intelligence/O ,/O ''/O \/O remarks/O at/O AI/O Now/DATE :/O The/O Social/O and/O Economic/ORGANIZATION Implications/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Artificial/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION Technologies/ORGANIZATION in/O the/O Near/O Term/O conference/O in/O New/LOCATION York/LOCATION ,/O July/DATE 7/DATE ,/DATE 2016/DATE ./O 
15/NUMBER For/O a/O discussion/O of/O the/O polarization/O of/O the/O labor/O market/O ,/O see/O David/PERSON H./PERSON A/O \/O utor/O and/O David/PERSON Dorn/PERSON ,/O ``/O The/O growth/O of/O low-skill/O service/O jobs/O and/O the/O polarization/O of/O the/O US/LOCATION labor/O market/O ,/O ''/O \/O American/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Review/ORGANIZATION ,/O volume/O 103/NUMBER ,/O number/O 5/NUMBER ,/O August/DATE 2013/DATE ./O 
16/NUMBER For/O example/O ,/O a/O study/O conducted/O by/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION 's/O French/O office/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2011/DATE showed/O that/O for/O every/O job/O that/O had/O been/O lost/O in/O France/LOCATION as/O the/O result/O of/O the/O advent/O of/O the/O internet/O in/O the/DURATION previous/DURATION 15/DURATION years/DURATION ,/O 2.4/NUMBER new/O jobs/O had/O been/O created/O ./O 
Impact/O d'internet/O sur/O l'?conomie/O fran?aise/O :/O Comment/O internet/O \/O transforme/O notre/O pays/O -LRB-/O The/O internet/O 's/O impact/O on/O the/O French/O economy/O :/O How/O the/O internet/O is/O transforming/O our/O cou/O \/O ntry/O -RRB-/O ,/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION ,/O March/DATE 2011/DATE ./O 
McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION 15/ORGANIZATION three/NUMBER million/NUMBER do/O so/O voluntarily/O ./O 
Most/O of/O these/O people/O are/O not/O unemployed/O for/O long/O periods/O as/O they/O move/O on/O to/O other/O jobs/O ./O 
17/NUMBER That/O said/O ,/O automation/O also/O represents/O a/O very/O substantial/O opportunity/O to/O support/O global/O economic/O growth/O ./O 
Our/O estimates/O suggest/O it/O has/O the/O potential/O to/O contribute/O meaningfully/O to/O the/O growth/O necessary/O to/O meet/O the/O per/O capita/O GDP/O aspirations/O of/O every/O country/O ,/O at/O a/O time/O when/O changing/O demographics/O call/O those/O aspirations/O into/O question/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O for/O this/O growth/O to/O take/O place/O ,/O rather/O than/O having/O a/O massive/O labor/O surplus/O ,/O everyone/O needs/O to/O keep/O working/O --/O with/O the/O robots/O working/O alongside/O them/O ./O 
Automation/O can/O help/O close/O a/O GDP/O growth/O gap/O resulting/O from/O declining/O growth/O rates/O of/O working-age/O populations/O GDP/O growth/O was/O brisk/O over/O the/DATE past/DATE half/DATE century/DATE ,/O driven/O by/O the/O twin/O engines/O of/O employment/O growth/O and/O rising/O productivity/O ,/O both/O contributing/O approximately/O the/O same/O amount/O ./O 
However/O ,/O declining/O birthrates/O and/O the/O trend/O toward/O aging/O in/O many/O advanced/O and/O some/O emerging/O economies/O mean/O that/O peak/O employment/O will/O occur/O in/O most/O countries/O within/O 50/DURATION years/DURATION ./O 
18/NUMBER The/O expected/O decline/O in/O the/O share/O of/O the/O working-age/O population/O will/O open/O an/O economic/O growth/O gap/O :/O roughly/O half/O of/O the/O sources/O of/O economic/O growth/O from/O the/DATE past/DATE half/O century/DURATION -LRB-/O employment/O growth/O -RRB-/O will/O evaporate/O as/O populations/O age/O ./O 
Even/O at/O historical/O rates/O of/O productivity/O growth/O ,/O economic/O growth/O could/O be/O nearly/O halved/O ./O 
Automation/O could/O compensate/O for/O at/O least/O some/O of/O these/O demographic/O trends/O ./O 
We/O estimate/O the/O productivity/O injection/O it/O could/O give/O to/O the/O global/O economy/O as/O being/O between/O 0.8/NUMBER and/O 1.4/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O global/O GDP/O annually/SET ,/O assuming/O that/O human/O labor/O replaced/O by/O automation/O would/O rejoin/O the/O workforce/O and/O be/O as/O productive/O as/O it/O was/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2014/DATE ./O 
Considering/O the/O labor/O substitution/O effect/O alone/O ,/O we/O calculate/O that/O ,/O by/U_TEMPPRED 2065/DATE ,/O automation/O could/O potentially/O add/O productivity/O growth/O in/O the/O largest/O economies/O in/O the/O world/O -LRB-/O G19/ORGANIZATION plus/O Nigeria/LOCATION -RRB-/O that/O is/O the/O equivalent/O of/O an/O additional/O 1.1/NUMBER billion/NUMBER to/O 2.3/NUMBER billion/NUMBER full-time/O workers/O -LRB-/O Exhibit/O E8/O -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O productivity/O growth/O enabled/O by/O automation/O can/O ensure/O continued/O prosperity/O in/O aging/O nations/O and/O provide/O an/O additional/O boost/O to/O fast-growing/O ones/O ./O 
Automation/O on/O its/O own/O will/O not/O be/O sufficient/O to/O achieve/O long-term/O economic/O growth/O aspirations/O across/O the/O world/O ;/O for/O that/O ,/O additional/O productivity-boosting/O measures/O will/O be/O needed/O ,/O including/O reworking/O business/O processes/O or/O developing/O new/O products/O and/O services/O ./O 
Potential/O impact/O of/O automation/O in/O three/NUMBER groups/O of/O countries/O Automation/O could/O boost/O productivity/O and/O help/O close/O the/O economic/O growth/O gap/O in/O the/O 20/NUMBER largest/O economies/O in/O the/O medium/O term/O ,/O to/U_TEMPPRED 2030/DATE ./O 
We/O have/O divided/O these/O countries/O into/O three/NUMBER groups/O ,/O each/O of/O which/O could/O use/O automation/O to/O further/O national/O economic/O growth/O objectives/O ,/O depending/O on/O their/O demographic/O trends/O and/O growth/O aspirations/O ./O 
The/O three/NUMBER groups/O are/O :/O &#131;/O Advanced/O economies/O ,/O including/O Australia/LOCATION ,/O Canada/LOCATION ,/O France/LOCATION ,/O Germany/LOCATION ,/O Italy/LOCATION ,/O Japan/LOCATION ,/O South/LOCATION Korea/LOCATION ,/O the/O United/LOCATION Kingdom/LOCATION ,/O and/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ./O 
These/O economies/O typically/O face/O an/O aging/O workforce/O ,/O with/O the/O decline/O in/O working-age/O population/O growth/O more/O immediate/O in/O some/O -LRB-/O Germany/LOCATION ,/O Italy/LOCATION ,/O and/O Japan/LOCATION -RRB-/O than/O in/O others/O ./O 
Automation/O can/O provide/O the/O productivity/O boost/O required/O to/O meet/O economic/O growth/O projections/O that/O they/O otherwise/O would/O struggle/O to/O attain/O without/O other/O significant/O productivity/O growth/O accelerators/O ./O 
These/O economies/O thus/O have/O a/O major/O interest/O in/O pursuing/O rapid/O automation/O adoption/O ./O 
&#131;/O Emerging/O economies/O with/O aging/O populations/O ./O 
This/O category/O includes/O Argentina/LOCATION ,/O Brazil/LOCATION ,/O China/LOCATION ,/O and/O Russia/LOCATION ,/O which/O face/O economic/O growth/O gaps/O as/O a/O result/O of/O projected/O declines/O in/O 17/NUMBER US/ORGANIZATION Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION job/O openings/O and/O labor/O turnover/O survey/O database/O .18/NUMBER Global/O growth/O :/O Can/O productivity/O save/O the/DATE day/DATE in/O an/O aging/O world/O ?/O 
McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION ,/O January/DATE 2015/DATE ./O 
Our/O estimate/O of/O employment/O growth/O 's/O contribution/O to/O GDP/O growth/O in/O this/O report/O differs/O slightly/O from/O this/O earlier/O research/O ,/O as/O we/O have/O assumed/O productivity/O measured/O in/O each/O country/O ,/O rather/O than/O a/O global/O average/O ./O 
McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION InstituteA/ORGANIZATION future/DATE that/O works/O :/O Automation/O ,/O employment/O ,/O and/O productivity/O 16/NUMBER Executive/O summary/O the/O growth/O of/O their/O working/O population/O ./O 
19/NUMBER For/O these/O economies/O ,/O automation/O can/O provide/O the/O productivity/O injection/O needed/O just/O to/O maintain/O current/DATE GDP/O per/O capita/O ./O 
To/O achieve/O a/O faster/O growth/O trajectory/O that/O is/O more/O commensurate/O with/O their/O developmental/O aspirations/O ,/O these/O countries/O would/O need/O to/O supplement/O automation/O with/O additional/O sources/O of/O productivity/O ,/O such/O as/O process/O transformations/O ,/O and/O would/O benefit/O from/O more/O rapid/O adoption/O of/O automation/O ./O 
&#131;/O Emerging/O economies/O with/O younger/O populations/O ./O 
