1/NUMBER The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O Skills/O and/O Resilience/O for/O a/O World/O of/O Change/O Issue/O 13/NUMBER //O 201610/NUMBER June/DATE EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O Work/O glues/O societies/O together/O ./O 
It/O translates/O talent/O into/O broader/O economic/O virtue/O and/O lends/O meaning/O as/O \/O well/O as/O structure/O to/O most/O people/O 's/O lives/O ./O 
In/O Europe/LOCATION ,/O the/O majority/O of/O workers/O hold/O permanent/O contracts/O ./O 
However/O ,/O tectonic/O shifts/O are/O re-shaping/O the/O ways/O that/O work/O is/O performed/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O the/O very/O architecture/O of/O the/O corporation/O is/O changing/O profoundly/O ,/O largely/O powered/O by/O the/O Internet/O and/O digital/O technologies/O ./O 
Second/ORDINAL ,/O the/O perceived/O volatility/O of/O the/O economic/O recovery/O and/O the/O continuous/O exposure/O of/O the/O private/O sector/O to/O disruptive/O innovation/O push/O businesses/O to/O offer/O short-term/O contracts/O to/O respond/O quickly/O if/O a/O crisis/O strikes/O ./O 
Thus/O ,/O many/O more/O job/O seekers/O are/O forced/O into/O short-term/O contracts/O ,/O part-time/O work/O or/O other/O forms/O of/O labour/O which/O they/O see/O as/O undesirable/O ./O 
At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O in/O the/O digital/O economy/O `/O precarious/O '/O or/O `/O temporary/O '/O do/O not/O necessarily/O mean/O sub-optimal/O :/O more/O people/O voluntarily/O check/O out/O of/O t/O \/O he/O traditional/O `/O 9/NUMBER to/O 5/NUMBER '/O job/O routine/O to/O pursue/O more/O independent/O and/O flexible/O work/O arrangements/O ./O 
Autonomy/O can/O be/O experienced/O as/O more/O empowering/O and/O satisfactory/O ./O 
This/O rise/O in/O freelancing/O runs/O parallel/O to/O the/O growth/O of/O the/O gig/O economy/O ,/O where/O digital/O technologies/O enable/O teams/O to/O be/O assembled/O around/O a/O given/O project/O --/O and/O often/O across/O borders/O --/O while/O platforms/O seamlessly/O connect/O buyers/O with/O sellers/O ./O 
Much/O of/O the/O latter/O takes/O place/O under/O the/O heading/O collaborative/O economy/O ,/O which/O is/O offering/O opportunity/O not/O only/O for/O people/O seeking/O more/O flexibility/O but/O also/O to/O those/O who/O have/O often/O had/O fewer/O chances/O of/O landing/O a/O permanent/O job/O ./O 
The/O World/O of/O Work/O Has/O Always/O Evolved/O The/O nature/O of/O work/O and/O the/O ways/O it/O is/O performed/O have/O changed/O multiple/O times/O and/O throughout/O human/O history/O ./O 
However/O ,/O the/O pace/O of/O change/O has/O accelerated/O significantly/O ,/O largely/O due/O to/O digital/O technologies/O ./O 
Many/O of/O today/DATE 's/O jobs/O and/O most/O sought-after/O skills/O did/O not/O exist/O a/DATE decade/DATE ago/DATE ,/O while/O routine/O occupations/O are/O vulnerable/O to/O automation/O ./O 
Opportunities/O ,/O Disruptions/O and/O Transitions/O Job/O polarisation/O and/O job/O displacement/O have/O intensified/O in/O advanced/O economies/O ./O 
At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O technological/O innovations/O offer/O new/O and/O flexible/O opportunities/O which/O often/O include/O those/O traditionally/O at/O the/O fringes/O of/O the/O labour/O markets/O ./O 
Policymakers/O need/O to/O manoeuvre/O between/O these/O two/NUMBER trends/O :/O preserving/O the/O core/O of/O a/O social/O market/O economy/O while/O being/O open/O to/O innovation/O and/O technology-driven/O change/O that/O impacts/O organisations/O and/O individuals/O alike/O ./O 
Keep/O Learning/O for/O Life-Long/O Resilience/O Skills/O continue/O to/O be/O the/O best/O guarantor/O of/O social/O mobility/O and/O opportunity/O ./O 
But/O skills/O are/O not/O static/O and/O need/O to/O be/O updated/O and/O fine-tuned/O throughout/O working/O lives/O ./O 
This/O too/O often/O contrasts/O with/O Europe/LOCATION 's/O educational/O systems/O which/O tend/O to/O be/O frontloaded/O ./O 
Opportunities/O for/O life-long/O learning/O are/O critical/O to/O support/O the/O numerous/O transitions/O that/O will/O likely/O characterise/O future/DATE employment/O ./O 
Public/O Policies/O Must/O Pave/O the/O Way/O and/O Accompany/O Change/O Well-crafted/O public/O policies/O need/O to/O keep/O track/O of/O changes/O in/O the/O world/O of/O work/O ,/O using/O data/O and/O digital/O technologies/O to/O better/O understand/O evolving/O trends/O ,/O and/O offer/O more/O targeted/O support/O to/O individuals/O ./O 
Active/O labour/O market/O policies/O will/O seek/O to/O buttress/O potential/O fallouts/O and/O adapt/O to/O new/O realities/O ./O 
For/O instance/O ,/O they/O will/O ease/O the/O transition/O from/O employment/O to/O freelancing/O and/O back/O ,/O seeking/O ways/O to/O provide/O more/O security/O to/O gig/O economy/O workers/O ,/O or/O making/O greater/O efforts/O to/O provide/O customised/O skills/O and/O trainings/O that/O maximise/O employment/O potential/O ./O 
EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O are/O analytical/O papers/O on/O topics/O chosen/O by/O the/O President/O of/O the/O European/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION ./O 
They/O are/O produced/O by/O the/O European/O Political/O Strategy/O Centre/O -LRB-/O EPSC/O -RRB-/O ,/O the/O European/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION s/O in-house/O think/O tank/O ./O 
DisclaimerThe/O views/O expressed/O in/O the/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O series/O are/O those/O of/O the/O \/O authors/O and/O do/O not/O necessarily/O correspond/O to/O those/O of/O the/O European/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION ./O 
2/NUMBER 1/NUMBER ./O 
Work/O 4.0/NUMBER and/O Beyond/O 1.1/NUMBER ./O 
Trends/O and/O Transformations/ORGANIZATION Work/ORGANIZATION has/O always/O covered/O a/O diverse/O set/O of/O economic/O realities/O ./O 
It/O includes/O paid/O employment/O ,/O own-account/O work/O ,/O volunteering/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O unpaid/O family/O work/O ./O 
Today/DATE ,/O `/O work/O '/O is/O increasingly/O becoming/O an/O umbrella/O concept/O for/O tasks/O performed/O under/O different/O legal/O ,/O functional/O and/O geographic/O frameworks/O ./O 
Jobs/O are/O being/O broken/O down/O into/O projects/O that/O may/O either/O be/O outsourced/O to/O independent/O professionals/O and/O experts/O ,/O or/O be/O reconfigured/O into/O projects/O that/O assemble/O physical/O or/O virtual/O teams/O ,/O across/O borders/O and/O time-zones/O ./O 
Non-essential/O tasks/O and/O functions/O have/O long/O been/O outsourced/O to/O allow/O companies/O to/O cut/O costs/O and/O focus/O their/O added/O value/O on/O core/O competences/O ./O 
Retail/O companies/O have/O used/O external/O contractors/O for/O their/O call/O centres/O and/O 24/7/O customer/O support/O services/O for/O decades/DURATION ./O 
Similarly/O ,/O consulting/O and/O accounting/O firms/O outsource/O basic/O research/O and/O accounting/O tasks/O ,/O while/O publishing/O houses/O outsource/O type-setting/O and/O editing/O to/O production/O teams/O on/O other/O continents/O ./O 
This/O allows/O them/O to/O benefit/O from/O time-zone/O differences/O to/O get/O a/O speedier/O turn-around/O on/O their/O projects/O at/O lower/O costs/O ./O 
Companies/O have/O moved/O from/O vertical/O integration/O to/O restructured/O contractual/O relations/O allowing/O them/O to/O tap/O into/O global/O value/O chains/O and/O international/O talent/O as/O their/O needs/O and/O growth/O strategies/O evolve/O ./O 
In/O fact/O ,/O as/O a/O global/O landscape/O of/O abundant/O and/O specialised/O knowledge/O becomes/O increasingly/O accessible/O ,/O companies/O embrace/O the/O open/O innovation/O paradigm/O ./O 
In/O short/O ,/O this/O involves/O harnessing/O external/O ideas/O and/O knowledge/O from/O multiple/O sources/O and/O combining/O these/O with/O internal/O capacities/O and/O R&D/O ./O 
The/O result/O is/O the/O ability/O to/O deliver/O efficient/O and/O innovative/O solutions/O to/O the/O marketplace/O ./O 
In/O today/DATE 's/O economy/O ,/O the/O ability/O to/O scale/O rapidly/O and/O internationally/O is/O fundamental/O ,/O thereby/O transforming/O the/O `/O crowd/O '/O into/O part/O of/O the/O value-added/O chain/O ./O 
In/O addition/O to/O its/O global/O dimension/O ,/O outsourcing/O has/O taken/O on/O an/O added/O dimension/O through/O the/O rise/O of/O the/O gig/O economy/O 1/NUMBER ./O 
It/O has/O created/O a/O dynamic/O environment/O in/O which/O temporary/O positions/O are/O common/O and/O organisations/O contract/O with/O independent/O workers/O for/O short-term/O engagements/O ./O 
Tasks/O can/O be/O broken/O down/O and/O distributed/O even/O more/O widely/O through/O apps/O and/O online/O platforms/O ./O 
The/O bidding-style/O process/O through/O which/O tasks/O are/O offered/O ,/O assigned/O ,/O and/O performed/O allows/O for/O real-time/O ,/O interactive/O and/O often/O mutual/O rating/O of/O the/O performance/O of/O service/O providers/O -LRB-/O both/O for/O seller/O and/O buyer/O -RRB-/O and/O the/O reliability/O of/O users/O ./O 
Whether/O it/O is/O looking/O for/O a/O babysitter/O on/O care.com/O ,/O assigning/O a/O local/O house-errand/O on/O Taskrabbit/O ,/O or/O turning/O to/O 99designs.com/O to/O get/O designers/O from/O around/O the/O world/O From/O Work/O as/O Employment/O to/O the/O Open/O Talent/O Economy/O `/O On/O demand/O '/O work/O is/O on/O the/O rise/O as/O is/O a/O `/O project-focused/O '/O approach/O to/O work/O ./O 
What/O has/O been/O referred/O to/O as/O the/O `/O Hollywood/O model/O '/O is/O a/O discernible/O trend/O across/O numerous/O sectors/O ./O 
\/O How/O does/O this/O work/O in/O practice/O ?/O 
Once/DATE a/O specific/O project/O ,/O product/O or/O assignment/O is/O identified/O ,/O a/O team/O of/O different/O people/O from/O different/O professions/O with/O distinct/O but/O complementary/O skills/O ,/O comes/O together/O and/O collaborates/O in/O order/O to/O accomplish/O the/O task/O ./O 
Once/DATE the/O project/O is/O comple/O \/O ted/O ,/O the/O team/O disassembles/O and/O reconfigures/O with/O other/O members/O on/O another/O project/O -LRB-/O just/O like/O in/O Hollywood/LOCATION ,/O teams/O and/O artists/O move/O on/O to/O the/O production/O of/O another/O film/O -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O pharmaceutical/O industry/O is/O an/O interesting/O area/O within/O which/O this/O model/O has/O developed/O ./O 
For/O decades/DURATION ,/O the/O entire/O process/O from/O early-stage/O research/O to/O consumer/O sales/O was/O undertaken/O within/O one/NUMBER company/O ./O 
Recently/DATE ,/O research/O is/O often/O ceded/O to/O startups/O or/O research/O labs/O ,/O where/O teams/O of/O scientists/O ,/O senior/O executives/O ,/O and/or/O supporting/O managers/O and/O staff/O work/O on/O a/O single/O development/O project/O with/O venture/O capitalist/O funding/O ./O 
If/O successful/O ,/O the/O team/O might/O sell/O the/O \/O medication/O or/O its/O marketing/O rights/O to/O a/O company/O ,/O disband/O ,/O and/O move/O on/O to/O another/O project/O ./O 
This/O short/O -/O term/O ,/O highly/O flexible/O project-based/O business/O approach/O assembles/O people/O who/O hold/O specific/O skills/O and/O expertise/O for/O the/O particular/O requirements/O of/O the/O project/O and/O with/O a/O limited/O time/O and/O financial/O commitment/O ./O 
The/O adaptability/O of/O this/O approach/O is/O its/O advantage/O ,/O particul/O \/O arly/O in/O conditions/O of/O economic/O uncertainty/O ./O 
It/O contrasts/O with/O the/O traditional/O corporate/O model/O ,/O where/O employees/O are/O hired/O in/O long/O er/O term/O ,/O open-ended/O jobs/O ./O 
In/O this/O project-based/O reality/O ,/O there/O are/O real/O concerns/O that/O the/O bidding/O or/O competition/O processes/O between/O workers/O may/O negatively/O impact/O employment/O ,/O protection/O and/O safety/O standards/O ./O 
To/O reap/O the/O opportunities/O offered/O ,/O public/O policy/O needs/O to/O adapt/O and/O better/O target/O those/O who/O fall/O through/O the/O cracks/O of/O the/O traditional/O social/O system/O ,/O which/O was/O designed/O for/O full-time/O workers/O with/O permanent/O contracts/O ./O 
Adam/PERSON Davidson/PERSON ,/O `/O What/O Hollywood/O can/O teach/O us/O about/O the/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O ,/O '/O New/ORGANIZATION York/ORGANIZATION Times/ORGANIZATION ,/O 5-5-2015/DATE ,/O http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/10//DATE magazine/what-hollywood-can-teach-us-about-the-future-of-work.html/O ?/O 
_/O r/O =/O 0/NUMBER ;/O Robert/PERSON Weisman/PERSON ,/O `/O Pharma/O gives/O drug/O development/O the/O Hollywood/O treatment/O ,/O '/O Boston/ORGANIZATION Globe/ORGANIZATION ,/O 27-9-2015/O ,/O https://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2015/09/27/biotech-startups-adopt-hollywood/DATE -/O model/hR5Mh6jwOV7w6v4SeGEpeJ/story.html/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O 3/NUMBER to/O submit/O brand/O logo/O ideas/O in/O a/O contest/O round-the-clock/O ,/O the/O gig/O economy/O offers/O ways/O to/O tap/O into/O talent/O ,/O services/O and/O expertise/O at/O a/O global/O level/O with/O unprecedented/O affordability/O and/O transparency/O while/O rewarding/O the/O reputation/O ,/O demand/O and/O compensation/O of/O the/O best/O performers/O ./O 
1.2/NUMBER ./O 
Rise/O of/O Independent/O and/O Alternative/O Working/O Arrangements/O While/O the/O majority/O of/O workers/O are/O on/O permanent/O contracts/O ,/O the/O preference/O for/O lean/O teams/O has/O led/O to/O a/O marked/O shift/O from/O `/O employees/O '/O to/O `/O independent/O suppliers/O of/O services/O '/O and/O `/O independent/O contractors/O ./O '/O 
Self-employment/O in/O the/O EU/ORGANIZATION constitutes/O 16.4/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O the/O labour/O market/O 2/NUMBER ,/O with/O wide/O variation/O across/O Member/O States/O ./O 
Temps/O 3/NUMBER ,/O agency/O workers/O ,/O on-call/O workers/O ,/O contract/O company/O workers/O ,/O independent/O contractors/O ,/O independent/O professionals/O or/O freelancers/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O part-timers/O ,/O have/O been/O on/O the/O rise/O 4/NUMBER -LRB-/O see/O Figure/O 1/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O the/O case/O of/O Belgium/LOCATION for/O example/O ,/O the/O number/O of/O hours/DURATION worked/O by/O agency/O workers/O rose/O by/O over/O 11/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/U_TEMPPRED 2015/DATE alone/O ./O 
5/NUMBER Similarly/O ,/O in/O the/O USA/ORGANIZATION ,/O recent/O research/O suggests/O that/O all/O net/O employment/O growth/O since/O 2005/DATE appears/O to/O have/O occurred/O in/O `/O alternative/O '/O -LRB-/O i.e./O non-standard/O -RRB-/O work/O arrangements/O -/O including/O temporary/O ,/O gig/O and/O contract/O work/O ./O 
The/O overall/O percentage/O of/O workers/O engaged/O in/O alternative/O work/O arrangements/O rose/O from/O 10.1/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O February/DATE 2005/DATE to/O 15.8/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O late/DATE 2014/DATE ./O 
6/NUMBER In/O the/O post-2008/O period/O ,/O companies/O are/O much/O more/O reluctant/O to/O offer/O full-term/O employment/O contracts/O given/O the/O volatile/O economic/O environment/O and/O the/O accelerating/O pace/O of/O global/O competition/O ./O 
This/O is/O more/O than/O likely/O to/O prevail/O in/O the/DURATION years/DURATION ahead/O ./O 
These/O trends/O are/O feeding/O a/O patchwork/O of/O parallel/O employment/O realities/O that/O characterise/O today/DATE 's/O developed/O economies/O ./O 
`/O Non-standard/O '/O work/O ,/O in/O its/O numerous/O varieties/O ,/O may/O offer/O greater/O flexibility/O and/O autonomy/O ./O 
At/O the/O same/O time/O it/O does/O tend/O to/O be/O less/O paid/O than/O the/O full-time/O equivalent/O ,/O and/O is/O associated/O with/O less/O access/O to/O training/O ./O 
It/O is/O not/O the/O preferred/O option/O for/O many/O and/O it/O also/O brings/O greater/O risks/O due/O to/O frequent/O periods/O without/O or/O with/O very/O little/O income/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O less/O favourable/O conditions/O in/O terms/O of/O accessing/O social/O security/O and/O necessary/O protection/O -LRB-/O healthcare/O ,/O accident/O coverage/O and/O pensions/O primarily/O -RRB-/O ./O 
On/O the/O other/O hand/O ,/O these/O new/O forms/O of/O work/O can/O be/O a/O great/O accelerator/O for/O individuals/O who/O have/O been/O persistently/O shut/O out/O of/O the/O formal/O labour/O market/O ./O 
This/O is/O not/O to/O be/O under-estimated/O in/O times/O of/O a/O sluggish/O economic/O recovery/O creating/O too/O few/O jobs/O ,/O and/O where/O concerns/O about/O the/O consequences/O of/O socio-economic/O marginalisation/O range/O from/O petty/O crime/O to/O the/O risks/O of/O radicalisation/O ./O 
Source/O :/O Eurostat/ORGANIZATION Over/O 50/NUMBER year-olds/O self-employment/O Million/NUMBER persons/O 2002/DATE 2014/DATE 16.120.4/O 11/NUMBER 14/NUMBER Self-employed/O without/O employees/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O self-employed/O by/O gender/O 72/NUMBER 76/NUMBER 63/NUMBER 69/NUMBER 2002?201520022/O 015/NUMBER Part-time/O employment/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O total/O employment/O 20022014/NUMBER 2002/DATE 2014/DATE 26.5/NUMBER 32.2/NUMBER Temporary/O employment/O %/O of/O total/O employees/O Female/O Male/O +4/NUMBER pp/O +6/NUMBER pp/O Figure/O 1/NUMBER :/O Employment/O Trends/O in/O the/O European/LOCATION Union/LOCATION :/O A/O Snapshot/ORGANIZATION Full-Time/ORGANIZATION ,/O Life-Long/O Corporate/O Jobs/O More/O Likely/O an/O Interlude/O than/O the/O Norm/O Although/O there/O is/O widespread/O conviction/O that/O long-term/O corporate/O jobs/O ar/O \/O e/O the/O norm/O and/O that/O temporary/O work/O is/O a/O novel/O form/O of/O `/O non-standard/O '/O work/O ,/O the/O opposite/O is/O likely/O the/O case/O ./O 
Long-term/O corporate/O jobs/O guaranteeing/O full-time/O ,/O life-long/O job/O security/O and/O benefits/O only/O became/O dominant/O in/O the/O `/O trentes/O glorieuses/O '/O after/O 1945/DATE 7/DATE ./O 
These/O developed/O as/O assembly/O lines/O and/O industrial/O machinery/O grew/O more/O complicated/O in/O times/O of/O full/O employment/O ,/O making/O the/O need/O for/O a/O stable/O trained/O workforce/O to/O control/O quality/O and/O maximise/O production/O more/O pressing/O on/O the/O employers/O '/O side/O ./O 
In/O parallel/O ,/O the/O urban/O concentration/O of/O workers/O encouraged/O the/O advocacy/O for/O better/O employment/O conditions/O ,/O and/O eventually/O privileges/O ,/O in/O exchange/O for/O loyalty/O ./O 
Full-time/O ,/O life-long/O corporate/O jobs/O that/O emerged/O in/O the/O post-World-War/O II/O period/O have/O been/O overwhelmingly/O occupied/O by/O prime/O -/O and/O working-age/O men/O ./O 
The/O employment/O trajectories/O of/O women/O ,/O younger/O workers/O ,/O people/O with/O a/O migrant/O background/O ,/O or/O also/O people/O with/O disabilities/O have/O been/O rather/O different/O ,/O characterised/O by/O lower/O rates/O of/O employment/O and/O higher/O rates/O of/O part-time/O ,/O temporary/O or/O self-employment/O ./O 
They/O have/O also/O faced/O more/O implicit/O forms/O of/O discrimination/O in/O the/O workplace/O ,/O even/O though/O officially/O the/O legal/O framework/O for/O equal/O opportunities/O and/O non-discrimination/O should/O prevent/O this/O 8/NUMBER ./O 
EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O 4/NUMBER 2/NUMBER ./O 
Gains/O ,/O Losses/O and/O Changes/O in/O the/O World/O of/O Work/O 2.1/NUMBER ./O 
What/O Is/O Changing/O ,/O And/O What/O is/O Not/O Labour/O reallocation/O ,/O i.e./O the/O sum/O of/O job/O creation/O and/O job/O destruction/O ,/O is/O intensifying/O ./O 
As/O new/O jobs/O are/O created/O ,/O others/O risk/O being/O destroyed/O ./O 
9/NUMBER Depending/O on/O which/O tasks/O we/O currently/DATE assume/O may/O be/O replaced/O ,/O estimates/O on/O the/O impact/O of/O automation/O on/O jobs/O vary/O ,/O but/O there/O are/O certain/O telling/O trends/O ./O 
Machines/O are/O already/O capable/O of/O answering/O email/O and/O drafting/O summaries/O of/O sports/O '/O games/O ./O 
We/O may/O soon/O see/O driverless/O cars/O at/O the/O traffic/O lights/O ,/O drones/O delivering/O goods/O ,/O and/O algorithms/O replacing/O accountants/O ,/O bank/O staff/O and/O legal/O assistance/O ./O 
10/NUMBER The/O sectors/O most/O at/O risk/O of/O contraction/O in/O the/DATE future/DATE world/O of/O work/O are/O those/O that/O rely/O heavily/O on/O routine/O tasks/O ,/O such/O as/O low-skill/O manufacturing/O jobs/O ,/O but/O also/O some/O craft/O and/O clerical/O occupations/O -LRB-/O Figure/O 2/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
Where/O tasks/O are/O routine/O ,/O automation/O is/O likely/O ./O 
As/O the/O trend/O towards/O more/O service-oriented/O economies/O is/O likely/O to/O continue/O 11/NUMBER ,/O job/O growth/O in/O the/DATE future/DATE can/O be/O expected/O to/O be/O in/O the/O service/O sector/O and/O particularly/O in/O non-routine/O elementary/O occupations/O such/O as/O personal/O care/O services/O ./O 
Automation/O is/O by/O no/O means/O a/O synonym/O for/O work/O extinction/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O `/O substitution/O may/O mean/O the/O destruction/O of/O certain/O jobs/O ,/O but/O not/O the/O destruction/O of/O employment/O ./O '/O 
12/NUMBER Certain/O estimates/O expect/O automation/O to/O lead/O to/O a/O net/O loss/O of/O more/O than/O 5.1/NUMBER million/NUMBER jobs/O across/O 15/NUMBER major/O advanced/O economies/O -LRB-/O see/O Figure/O 3/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
13/NUMBER Source/O :/O Future/DATE Skills/O Supply/O and/O Demand/O in/O Europe/LOCATION Forecast/LOCATION 2012/LOCATION ,/O Cedefop/LOCATION 10/DATE 20/DATE 30/DATE 40/DATE 50/DATE 60/DATE 70/DATE 2000/DATE 2010/DATE 2020/DATE Primary/O sector/O and/O utilities/O Non-marketed/O services/O Business/O and/O other/O services/O Construction/O Manufacturing/O Distribution/O and/O transport/O Figure/O 2/NUMBER :/O Change/O in/O Employment/O by/O Activities/O in/O the/O European/ORGANIZATION Union/ORGANIZATION Millions/ORGANIZATION Source/ORGANIZATION :/O David/PERSON Deming/PERSON ,/O Harvard/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION Fell/ORGANIZATION About/ORGANIZATION the/O same/O Grew/O Requires/O social/O skills/O Math/O skills/O Financial/ORGANIZATION managers/ORGANIZATION Police/ORGANIZATION Economist/ORGANIZATION Computer/ORGANIZATION scientist/O Dentist/O Laborers/O WeldersMachine/O operators/O Accounting/O clerks/O Food/O scientists/O Electricians/ORGANIZATION Lawyers/ORGANIZATION and/O judges/O Mgmt/O ./O 
analyst/O Physicians/ORGANIZATION Accountants/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION technicians/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION workers/O Designers/O R.N.s/O Vocational/O counselors/O Truck/O drivers/O Auto/O mechanics/O Janitors/ORGANIZATION Carpenters/ORGANIZATION Biological/ORGANIZATION technicians/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION tellers/ORGANIZATION Machinists/ORGANIZATION Stastical/ORGANIZATION clerks/O Tool/O and/O die/O markers/O Nurse/O aides/O Child-care/O workers/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER :/O Social/O Skills/O and/O Change/O in/O Share/O of/O Jobs/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O 1980/DATE to/O 2012/DATE Note/O :/O Medium/O risk/O of/O automation/O affects/O 5/PERCENT %/PERCENT to/O 70/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O tasks/O ./O 
High/O risk/O of/O automation/O affects/O over/O 70/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O tasks/O ./O 
Source/O :/O Arntz/PERSON ,/O M./O ,/O T./PERSON Gregory/PERSON and/O U./PERSON Zierahn/PERSON ,/O The/O Risk/O of/O Automation/O for/O Jobs/O in/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Countries/O :/O A/O Comparative/O Analysis/O ,/O 2016/DATE ,/O OECD/ORGANIZATION ./O 
0/NUMBER 10/DATE 20/DATE 30/DATE 40/DATE 50/DATE 60/NUMBER Medium/O risk/O High/O risk/O Slovakia/ORGANIZATION Austria/ORGANIZATION Germany/ORGANIZATION Czech/ORGANIZATION Republic/ORGANIZATION Italy/ORGANIZATION Netherlands/ORGANIZATION Spain/ORGANIZATION United/ORGANIZATION Kingdom/ORGANIZATION CanadaPoland/ORGANIZATION Denmark/ORGANIZATION France/ORGANIZATION United/ORGANIZATION States/ORGANIZATION Norway/ORGANIZATION Belgium/ORGANIZATION Japan/ORGANIZATION Ireland/ORGANIZATION Sweden/ORGANIZATION EstoniaFinland/ORGANIZATION Korea/LOCATION Russia/LOCATION Figure/O 3/NUMBER :/O Risk/O of/O Automatibility/O of/O Jobs/O Percentage/O of/O people/O at/O risk/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O 5/NUMBER At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O the/O digital/O revolution/O has/O generated/O a/O surge/O in/O demand/O for/O new/O jobs/O and/O occupational/O categories/O that/O did/O not/O even/O exist/O a/DATE decade/DATE ago/DATE ./O 
14/NUMBER These/O include/O people/O with/O a/O high/O technology/O quotient/O such/O as/O big/O data/O specialists/O ,/O social/O media/O managers/O ,/O cognitive/O computing/O engineers/O ,/O Internet/O of/O Things/O architects/O and/O blockchain/O developers/O ./O 
The/O transformative/O trends/O of/O the/O digital/O revolution/O have/O also/O highlighted/O that/O some/O jobs/O will/O quite/O simply/O always/O be/O performed/O by/O humans/O ,/O either/O because/O of/O the/O sort/O of/O skills/O required/O ,/O or/O simply/O because/O of/O our/O preferences/O ./O 
Child/O care/O ,/O care/O for/O the/O elderly/O ,/O social/O work/O ,/O mental/O health/O care/O for/O instance/O ,/O easily/O stand/O out/O as/O jobs/O with/O low/O risk/O of/O automation/O ./O 
The/O fact/O that/O certain/O tasks/O can/O be/O performed/O by/O technology/O means/O that/O time/O is/O `/O freed/O '/O up/O for/O workers/O to/O perform/O other/O tasks/O and/O create/O value/O ./O 
As/O automation/O and/O artificial/O intelligence/O are/O leaping/O into/O new/O areas/O ,/O the/O human-robot/O partnership/O will/O further/O transform/O the/O nature/O of/O work/O ./O 
Until/O now/DATE ,/O the/O challenge/O for/O workers/O was/O to/O learn/O how/O to/O operate/O machines/O ./O 
Looking/O ahead/O ,/O interactions/O will/O change/O with/O humans/O monitoring/O rather/O than/O operating/O machines/O and/O creatively/O defining/O what/O needs/O to/O be/O done/O and/O how/O ,/O and/O then/O using/O robots/O to/O achieve/O precisely/O that/O ./O 
If/O recent/O trends/O are/O telling/O indicators/O ,/O creativity/O ,/O emotional/O intelligence/O and/O transversal/O skills/O are/O undoubtedly/O what/O will/O make/O the/O difference/O in/O the/DATE future/DATE -LRB-/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
Research/O has/O shown/O that/O occupations/O requiring/O strong/O social/O ,/O interpersonal/O skills/O and/O non-routine/O analytical/O skills/O have/O grown/O dynamically/O since/O 1980/DATE with/O consistent/O wage/O growth/O ./O 
15/NUMBER Even/O in/O the/O tech/O industry/O ,/O it/O is/O jobs/O that/O require/O both/O technical/O and/O interpersonal/O skills/O that/O are/O on/O the/O rise/O ./O 
Cultures/O of/O sharing/O ,/O negotiating/O with/O others/O and/O finding/O compromises/O seems/O to/O be/O what/O can/O `/O save/O us/O '/O from/O the/O robots/O ./O 
Europe/LOCATION 's/O advantage/O in/O the/DATE future/DATE highly/O -/O automated/O world/O of/O work/O lies/O in/O its/O creativity/O and/O highly/O -/O skilled/O workforce/O -LRB-/O Figure/O 5/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
A/O 2015/DATE study/O 16/NUMBER finds/O that/O 21/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O US/LOCATION employment/O is/O highly/O creative/O --/O including/O occupations/O like/O artists/O ,/O architects/O ,/O web/O designers/O ,/O IT/O specialists/O and/O public/O relations/O professionals/O ./O 
Economies/O like/O the/O UK/ORGANIZATION where/O creative/O occupations/O make/O up/O a/O large/O proportion/O -LRB-/O around/O 24/PERCENT %/PERCENT -RRB-/O of/O the/O workforce/O may/O be/O better/O placed/O than/O others/O to/O resist/O the/O employment/O fallouts/O of/O automation/O ./O 
2.2/NUMBER ./O 
Capturing/O Value/O in/O the/O New/LOCATION World/LOCATION of/O Work/O In/O this/O transformative/O context/O ,/O charting/O a/O successful/O course/O in/O the/O world/O of/O work/O depends/O to/O a/O large/O extent/O on/O the/O quality/O of/O firms/O ./O 
Entrants/O and/O young/O firms/O remain/O the/O biggest/O contributors/O to/O employment/O creation/O in/O the/O OECD/ORGANIZATION countries/O 17/NUMBER -LRB-/O see/O Figure/O 6/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
However/O ,/O it/O is/O highly/O -/O productive/O and/O internationally-active/O firms/O that/O have/O an/O exceptional/O impact/O on/O economic/O growth/O and/O expansion/O of/O employment/O ./O 
On/O average/O ,/O about/O one/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O the/O internationalised/O ,/O high-performing/O manufacturing/O firms/O in/O Europe/LOCATION produce/O more/O than/O 75/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O output/O or/O foreign/O sales/O ./O 
18/NUMBER The/O changing/O world/O of/O work/O means/O that/O they/O will/O increasingly/O compete/O for/O the/O pool/O of/O available/O global/O talent/O ./O 
Source/O :/O Science/O ,/O Technology/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Industry/ORGANIZATION Scoreboard/ORGANIZATION 2015/ORGANIZATION ,/O OECD/ORGANIZATION -0.10/NUMBER -0.08/NUMBER -0.06/NUMBER -0.04/NUMBER -0.02/NUMBER 0.00/NUMBER 0.02/NUMBER 0.04/NUMBER 0.06/NUMBER 2001-02/DATE 2002-03/DATE 2003-04/DATE 2004-05/DATE 2005-06/DATE 2006-07/DATE 2007-08/DATE 2008-09/DATE 2009-10/DATE 2010-11/DATE Entry/O Young/O incumbents/O Young/O exit/O Old-small/O exit/O Old-large/O exit/O Old-small/O incumbents/O Old-large/O incumbents/O 0.08/NUMBER Figure/O 6/NUMBER :/O Contribution/O to/O Net/ORGANIZATION Job/ORGANIZATION Creation/ORGANIZATION by/ORGANIZATION Group/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Firms/ORGANIZATION in/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Unweighted/O average/O in/O the/O non-financial/O business/O sector/O Source/O :/O Future/DATE Skills/O Supply/O and/O Demand/O in/O Europe/LOCATION Forecast/O 2012/DATE ,/O Cedefop/O Low/O 2010/DATE 2020/DATE 0/NUMBER 50/NUMBER 100/NUMBER 150/NUMBER 200/NUMBER 250/NUMBER 2000/DATE Medium/O High/O 37/PERCENT %/PERCENT 22/PERCENT %/PERCENT 47/PERCENT %/PERCENT 47/PERCENT %/PERCENT 31/PERCENT %/PERCENT 16/PERCENT %/PERCENT Figure/O 5/NUMBER :/O Labour/ORGANIZATION Force/ORGANIZATION by/O Level/O of/O Qualification/O in/O the/O European/ORGANIZATION Union/ORGANIZATION Millions/ORGANIZATION EPSC/ORGANIZATION Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O 6/NUMBER Indeed/O ,/O the/O most/O job-creating/O --/O and/O productive/O --/O firms/O ,/O the/O so-called/O `/O frontier/O firms/O '/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O the/O younger/O gazelles/O -LRB-/O a/O subset/O of/O rapidly/O growing/O firms/O -RRB-/O are/O seeking/O high-skilled/O and/O digitally-savvy/O workers/O 19/NUMBER -LRB-/O see/O Table/O 1/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
As/O productivity/O gains/O result/O from/O investments/O in/O knowledge-based/O capital/O ,/O it/O is/O no/O coincidence/O that/O top/O growth/O occupations/O in/O employee/O numbers/O are/O mostly/O high/O skilled/O ones/O ,/O including/O software/O and/O sales/O professionals/O ,/O where/O ICTs/O increase/O the/O returns/O to/O labour/O for/O highly/O skilled/O workers/O performing/O cognitive/O tasks/O ./O 
20/NUMBER A/O particular/O concern/O for/O Europe/LOCATION is/O the/O projected/O skills/O shortage/O in/O the/O area/O of/O ICT/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O Information/O and/O Communications/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O ,/O which/O is/O forecast/O to/O lead/O to/O up/O to/O 825,000/NUMBER unfilled/O vacancies/O by/U_TEMPPRED 2020/DATE ./O 
This/O is/O not/O only/O a/O lost/O opportunity/O for/O job/O seekers/O but/O also/O has/O the/O potential/O to/O be/O a/O real/O break/O on/O productivity/O and/O innovation/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O the/O wider/O modernisation/O of/O the/O economy/O ./O 
3/NUMBER ./O 
Changing/O Work-Life/O Patterns/O and/O Preferences/O The/O profound/O changes/O underway/O are/O also/O accompanied/O by/O substantial/O transformations/O in/O people/O 's/O working/O life/O ./O 
Until/O recently/DATE ,/O there/O has/O been/O a/O rather/O linear/O pattern/O in/O the/O transition/O from/O education/O and/O training/O ,/O to/O work/O and/O retirement/O ./O 
This/O linearity/O is/O now/DATE largely/O a/O thing/O of/O the/DATE past/DATE ./O 
Given/O the/O changes/O in/O the/O workplace/O ,/O people/O will/O have/O to/O increasingly/O learn/O new/O skills/O to/O remain/O employable/O throughout/O their/O working/O life/O ./O 
They/O will/O be/O increasingly/O likely/O to/O change/O employers/O ,/O jobs/O ,/O employment/O status/O and/O professions/O numerous/O times/O and/O at/O faster/O paces/O than/O ever/O before/O ./O 
And/O ,/O given/O that/O people/O live/O longer/O ,/O they/O will/O most/O likely/O also/O have/O to/O work/O longer/O ,/O either/O out/O of/O choice/O or/O necessity/O ./O 
While/O some/O have/O the/O tools/O and/O mindset/O to/O embrace/O this/O flexibly/O ,/O not/O all/O are/O equipped/O with/O the/O skills/O ,/O competences/O and/O support/O system/O to/O be/O able/O to/O respond/O to/O these/O changes/O ./O 
At/O present/DATE ,/O multiple/O and/O divergent/O realities/O coexist/O in/O Europe/LOCATION 's/O job/O markets/O ./O 
It/O remains/O difficult/O for/O women/O to/O re-enter/O the/O labour/O market/O after/O they/O have/O taken/O time/O out/O to/O raise/O children/O ./O 
Young/O graduates/O who/O have/O spent/O numerous/O years/DURATION in/O full-time/O university/O education/O have/O the/O hardest/O time/O getting/O their/O first/ORDINAL job/O ,/O and/O often/O lack/O the/O skills/O necessary/O in/O spite/O of/O their/O formal/O qualifications/O ./O 
Similarly/O ,/O 45-year/DURATION olds/DURATION who/O where/O laid/O off/O due/O to/O sectoral/O restructuring/O find/O it/O difficult/O to/O get/O a/O new/O job/O as/O they/O are/O often/O deemed/O `/O too/O expensive/O '/O ,/O or/O even/O `/O too/O old/O '/O to/O retrain/O ./O 
In/O short/O ,/O many/O people/O find/O themselves/O excluded/O from/O gainful/O employment/O ,/O let/O alone/O the/O opportunity/O to/O pursue/O quality/O work/O --/O a/O challenge/O which/O has/O been/O accentuated/O by/O the/O crisis/O ./O 
For/O these/O reasons/O ,/O training/O and/O reskilling/O will/O matter/O more/O throughout/O people/O 's/O working/O lives/O ./O 
Education/O obtained/O before/O one/NUMBER 's/O professional/O life/O will/O have/O to/O be/O regularly/O `/O topped-up/O '/O ./O 
Transitions/O will/O be/O more/O frequent/O and/O complex/O -/O particularly/O with/O regards/O to/O family/O and/O care/O responsibilities/O on/O the/O one/NUMBER hand/O ,/O and/O employment/O and/O training/O on/O the/O other/O ./O 
These/O will/O have/O to/O be/O better/O supported/O than/O they/O are/O today/DATE ./O 
At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O work-life/O balance/O preferences/O are/O changing/O ./O 
Millennials/O are/O keen/O to/O have/O more/O diversity/O and/O also/O more/O flexibility/O in/O their/O work/O patterns/O and/O commitments/O ./O 
They/O are/O reinventing/O the/O essence/O of/O economic/O exchange/O ,/O professional/O fulfilment/O ,/O and/O even/O consumption/O itself/O through/O the/O collaborative/O economy/O and/O a/O growing/O army/O of/O `/O prosumers/O '/O ,/O with/O products/O and/O services/O being/O delivered/O on-demand/O and/O just-in-time/O ./O 
As/O for/O more/O mature/O workers/O ,/O especially/O highly/O skilled/O ,/O they/O are/O less/O and/O less/O interested/O in/O retirement/O and/O prefer/O to/O stay/O in/O the/O workforce/O for/O longer/O ,/O albeit/O with/O flexible/O arrangements/O ./O 
21/NUMBER Table/O 1/NUMBER :/O `/O Hottest/O '/O Skills/O of/U_TEMPPRED 2015/DATE LinkedIn/O Global/O 1/NUMBER Cloud/O and/O Distributed/O Computing/O 2/NUMBER Statistical/O Analysis/O and/O Data/ORGANIZATION Mining/ORGANIZATION 3/ORGANIZATION Marketing/ORGANIZATION Campaign/ORGANIZATION Management/ORGANIZATION 4/ORGANIZATION SEO/SEM/ORGANIZATION Marketing/ORGANIZATION 5/ORGANIZATION Middleware/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Integration/ORGANIZATION Software/ORGANIZATION 6/ORGANIZATION Mobile/ORGANIZATION Development/ORGANIZATION 7/ORGANIZATION Network/ORGANIZATION and/O Information/O Security/O 8/NUMBER Storage/O Systems/O and/O Management/O 9/NUMBER Web/O Architecture/O and/O Development/O Frameworks/O 10/NUMBER User/O Interface/O Design/O 11/NUMBER Data/ORGANIZATION Engineering/ORGANIZATION and/O Data/O Warehousing/O 12/NUMBER Algorithm/O Design/O 13/NUMBER Perl/Python/Ruby/O 14/NUMBER Shell/ORGANIZATION Scripting/ORGANIZATION Languages/ORGANIZATION 15/ORGANIZATION Mac/ORGANIZATION ,/O Linux/O and/O Unix/O Systems/O 16/NUMBER Channel/O Marketing/O 17/NUMBER Virtualisation/O 18/NUMBER Business/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION 19/ORGANIZATION Java/ORGANIZATION Development/ORGANIZATION 20/ORGANIZATION Electronic/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Electrical/ORGANIZATION Engineering/ORGANIZATION 21/ORGANIZATION Database/ORGANIZATION Management/ORGANIZATION and/O Software/O 22/NUMBER Software/O Modeling/O and/O Process/O Design/O 23/NUMBER Software/O QA/O and/O User/O Testing/O 24/NUMBER Economics/O 25/NUMBER Corporate/O Law/O and/O Governance/O Source/O :/O LinkedIn/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O 7/NUMBER Work/O tenure/O is/O also/O changing/O at/O a/O rapid/O pace/O ./O 
In/O the/O US/LOCATION ,/O the/O median/O tenure/O of/O workers/O aged/O 25/DURATION to/DURATION 34/DURATION years/DURATION is/O 3/DURATION years/DURATION which/O is/O three/NUMBER times/O less/O than/O that/O for/O workers/O aged/O 55/NUMBER to/O 64/NUMBER -LRB-/O 10.4/DURATION years/DURATION -RRB-/O ./O 
As/O for/O the/O EU/ORGANIZATION 28/NUMBER ,/O the/O changes/O for/O the/O 25-34/O year/DURATION olds/O between/O 2000/DATE and/O 2014/DATE ,/O are/O telling/O too/O ./O 
Job/O tenure/O of/O 10/DURATION years/DURATION and/O over/O decreased/O from/O 17.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT to/O 12.5/PERCENT %/PERCENT ,/O while/O job/O tenure/O for/O 3-5/O years/DURATION increased/O from/O 17.7/PERCENT %/PERCENT to/O 19.4/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
22/NUMBER This/O shorter/O tenure/O is/O not/O just/O the/O result/O of/O shorter/O time/O spent/O on/O the/O job/O market/O ,/O it/O is/O also/O a/O conscious/O choice/O ./O 
It/O follows/O that/O one/NUMBER might/O soon/O have/O 15/NUMBER -/O 20/DATE different/O jobs/O in/O a/O lifetime/O ./O 
As/O work/O patterns/O change/O and/O preferences/O shift/O ,/O one/NUMBER dimension/O that/O does/O remain/O constant/O is/O a/O rather/O fundamental/O human/O need/O for/O belonging/O to/O a/O community/O ./O 
Freelancers/O and/O independent/O professionals/O are/O forming/O groups/O and/O associations/O ,/O formally/O ,/O informally/O and/O virtually/O ./O 
One/NUMBER such/O group/O is/O the/O Freelancers/ORGANIZATION Union/ORGANIZATION ,/O based/O in/O New/LOCATION York/LOCATION ./O 
Through/O associations/O such/O as/O these/O ,/O they/O exchange/O experiences/O ,/O seek/O advice/O ,/O even/O lobby/O on/O work/O --/O and/O welfare/O --/O related/O issues/O ./O 
They/O also/O create/O community/O co-working/O spaces/O which/O allow/O new/O businesses/O to/O be/O created/O and/O create/O hubs/O of/O innovation/O that/O help/O kick/O start/O entrepreneurial/O ideas/O ./O 
In/O the/O new/O world/O of/O work/O ,/O attention/O is/O increasingly/O on/O the/O individual/O ./O 
The/O de-construction/O of/O work/O ,/O the/O multiplication/O of/O professional/O pursuits/O in/O one/NUMBER 's/O lifetime/O ,/O the/O growing/O burden/O on/O individual/O adaptation/O to/O employment/O driven/O by/O automation/O and/O competition/O in/O the/O high-value/O segment/O are/O some/O of/O the/O more/O evident/O manifestations/O ./O 
While/O the/O jury/O is/O out/O on/O which/O of/O these/O trends/O will/O have/O positive/O or/O negative/O outcomes/O ,/O resilient/O skills/O will/O be/O the/O game/O changers/O ./O 
4/NUMBER ./O 
The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O is/O All/O About/O Skills/O The/O novel/O fluidity/O of/O work/O puts/O a/O premium/O on/O personal/O initiative/O and/O professional/O resilience/O ./O 
The/O link/O between/O employer/O and/O employee/O is/O being/O loosened/O ,/O and/O this/O has/O repercussions/O for/O both/O ./O 
For/O employers/O who/O have/O to/O operate/O in/O a/O global/O context/O of/O high/O economic/O uncertainty/O ,/O investing/O in/O the/O systematic/O development/O of/O their/O staff/O is/O often/O a/O challenge/O ./O 
This/O is/O particularly/O so/O in/O the/O case/O of/O temporary/O or/O contract/O staff/O ./O 
At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O it/O matters/O hugely/O to/O a/O company/O 's/O success/O to/O be/O able/O to/O access/O a/O workforce/O with/O directly/O usable/O skills/O and/O qualifications/O ./O 
As/O for/O workers/O ,/O the/O burden/O of/O employment/O is/O shifted/O to/O her/O //O his/O abilities/O to/O adapt/O and/O remain/O relevant/O ,/O and/O to/O ensure/O adequate/O access/O to/O welfare/O ,/O decent/O and/O fair/O work/O conditions/O and/O sustainable/O employment/O protection/O ./O 
While/O many/O are/O driven/O by/O the/O preference/O for/O agency/O and/O autonomy/O ,/O not/O all/O workers/O have/O the/O tools/O to/O be/O equally/O self-resilient/O nor/O to/O sustainably/O tackle/O societal/O ,/O personal/O and/O professional/O risks/O ./O 
Access/O to/O up/O -/O and/O re-skilling/O opportunities/O that/O have/O currency/O on/O the/O job-market/O ,/O and/O to/O adequate/O welfare/O protection/O are/O the/O most/O fundamental/O challenges/O that/O workers/O and/O job/O seekers/O are/O confronted/O with/O in/O the/O changing/O world/O of/O work/O ./O 
In/O recent/DURATION years/DURATION ,/O the/O polarisation/O of/O today/DATE 's/O workforce/O between/O highly-skilled/O ,/O well-paid/O jobs/O and/O lower-paid/O ,/O low/O -/O skilled/O ones/O has/O intensified/O ./O 
23/NUMBER Meanwhile/O ,/O the/O share/O of/O the/O low-educated/O is/O contracting/O across/O all/O major/O occupational/O groups/O ,/O even/O in/O `/O elementary/O occupations/O '/O where/O it/O fell/O by/O four/NUMBER percentage/O points/O between/O 2008/DATE and/O 2012/DATE ./O 
Such/O an/O environment/O may/O compound/O the/O efficient/O matching/O of/O skills/O and/O jobs/O available/O in/O Europe/LOCATION ./O 
Evidence/O from/O Sweden/LOCATION suggests/O a/O link/O between/O displacement/O rates/O and/O educational/O level/O :/O well-educated/O ,/O native-born/O prime/O age/O men/O have/O the/O highest/O chances/O of/O re-employment/O ./O 
Workers/O who/O are/O involuntarily/O separated/O from/O their/O job/O due/O to/O economic/O or/O -LRB-/O increasingly/O -RRB-/O technological/O reasons/O tend/O to/O suffer/O wage/O losses/O upon/O entering/O a/O new/O job/O ,/O typically/O attributed/O to/O a/O loss/O of/O job-specific/O skills/O ./O 
24/NUMBER The/O risks/O of/O growing/O polarisation/O and/O displacement/O can/O be/O addressed/O by/O bolstering/O the/O resilience/O of/O workers/O through/O re-skilling/O and/O up-skilling/O opportunities/O throughout/O one/NUMBER 's/O life/O ,/O especially/O at/O a/O time/O when/O career/O transitions/O and/O self/O -/O or/O temporary/O employment/O are/O increasingly/O the/O new/O normal/O ./O 
In-work/O access/O to/O training/O remains/O highly/O dependent/O on/O the/O type/O of/O contract/O :/O almost/O one/NUMBER in/O two/NUMBER employees/O on/O permanent/O contracts/O receive/O training/O compared/O to/O 32/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O employees/O with/O fixed/O contracts/O and/O 19/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O self-employed/O ./O 
25/NUMBER Thus/O ,/O it/O is/O often/O the/O case/O that/O those/O who/O need/O life-long/O training/O the/O most/O are/O those/O who/O have/O the/O least/O access/O to/O it/O ./O 
5/NUMBER ./O 
Dynamic/O and/O Resilience/O -/O Building/O Public/O Policies/O Zygmunt/PERSON Bauman/PERSON ,/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O world/O 's/O leading/O sociologists/O ,/O has/O described/O the/O current/DATE uncertainty/O and/O unpredictability/O --/O as/O well/O as/O the/O inequalities/O in/O the/O ways/O risks/O and/O opportunities/O are/O experienced/O --/O as/O living/O in/O `/O liquid/O times/O '/O ./O 
26/NUMBER The/O post-crisis/O environment/O is/O characterised/O by/O particularly/O high/O levels/O of/O unpredictability/O for/O both/O workers/O and/O businesses/O ./O 
The/O transitions/O that/O the/O digital/O revolution/O is/O `/O There/O 's/O never/O been/O a/O better/O time/O to/O be/O a/O worker/O with/O special/O skills/O or/O the/O right/O education/O ,/O because/O these/O people/O can/O use/O technology/O to/O create/O and/O capture/O value/O ./O 
However/O ,/O there/O 's/O never/O been/O a/O worse/O time/O to/O be/O a/O worker/O with/O only/O `/O ordinary/O '/O skills/O and/O abilities/O to/O offer/O ,/O because/O computers/O ,/O robots/O ,/O and/O other/O digital/O technologies/O are/O acquiring/O these/O skills/O and/O abilities/O at/O an/O extraordinary/O rate/O ./O '/O 
Brynjolfsson/PERSON E./O and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION A./O ,/O -LRB-/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O The/O Second/ORDINAL Machine/O Age/O ./O 
Work/O ,/O Progress/ORGANIZATION ,/O and/O Prosperity/O in/O a/O Time/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Brilliant/ORGANIZATION Technologies/ORGANIZATION ,/O New/LOCATION York/LOCATION :/O W./ORGANIZATION W./ORGANIZATION Norton/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION EPSC/ORGANIZATION Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O 8/NUMBER bringing/O to/O all/O aspects/O of/O our/O work/O and/O life/O -/O both/O in/O their/O challenges/O and/O their/O opportunities/O are/O likely/O to/O magnify/O the/O sense/O of/O unpredictability/O and/O complexity/O even/O further/O ./O 
Public/O policy/O therefore/O needs/O to/O respond/O more/O dynamically/O to/O the/O changing/O reality/O of/O the/O world/O of/O work/O ./O 
Rather/O than/O being/O about/O the/O anonymous/O and/O largely/O uniform/O membership/O of/O the/O labour/O market/O ,/O it/O needs/O to/O respond/O to/O the/O diverse/O journeys/O people/O undertake/O throughout/O their/O life/O and/O careers/O with/O anticipation/O and/O innovation/O ./O 
This/O requires/O a/O comprehensive/O approach/O that/O includes/O :/O refitting/O education/O ,/O supporting/O firms/O in/O growth/O and/O job/O creation/O through/O investing/O in/O skills/O ,/O customising/O and/O ensuring/O portability/O of/O social/O rights/O ,/O and/O developing/O indicators/O that/O enable/O public/O investment/O to/O lead/O to/O effective/O social/O outcomes/O ./O 
The/O European/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION 's/O initiative/O to/O launch/O a/O European/O Pillar/O of/O Social/O Rights/O aims/O to/O identify/O the/O most/O transformative/O trends/O within/O work/O and/O welfare/O systems/O ,/O the/O changing/O needs/O in/O employment/O and/O social/O policies/O ,/O and/O the/O good/O practices/O in/O meeting/O these/O challenges/O and/O opportunities/O ./O 
In/O effect/O ,/O a/O dedicated/O focus/O of/O the/O on-going/O public/O consultation/O process/O -LRB-/O March/O --/O December/DATE 2016/DATE -RRB-/O is/O on/O the/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O ./O 
5.1/NUMBER ./O 
Refitting/O Education/O The/O changing/O world/O of/O work/O requires/O a/O multi-layered/O policy/O response/O ,/O covering/O the/O entire/O life-trajectory/O ,/O from/O cradle/O to/O retirement/O ./O 
Education/O ,/O training/O and/O the/O opportunity/O for/O retraining/O throughout/O one/NUMBER 's/O life/O need/O to/O be/O the/O starting/O point/O ./O 
The/O most/O important/O capital/O for/O the/O world/O of/O work/O ahead/O is/O skills/O ,/O and/O yet/O ,/O many/O youths/O as/O well/O as/O adults/O across/O Europe/LOCATION have/O considerable/O basic/O cognitive/O and/O non-cognitive/O skills/O '/O deficits/O even/O if/O they/O hold/O formal/O qualifications/O ./O 
27/NUMBER The/O importance/O of/O non-cognitive/O skills/O for/O the/O labour/O market/O has/O been/O widely/O recognised/O ./O 
Such/O skills/O range/O from/O achievement/O motivation/O ,/O perseverance/O ,/O problem/O -/O solving/O ,/O resilience/O ,/O self-control/O ,/O team-work/O ,/O initiative/O ,/O the/O ability/O to/O socialise/O and/O to/O follow/O an/O ethical/O code/O of/O behaviour/O ./O 
28/NUMBER However/O ,/O today/DATE 's/O education/O systems/O are/O not/O always/O proficient/O in/O the/O provision/O of/O these/O sorts/O of/O skills/O ./O 
In/O many/O EU/ORGANIZATION Member/O States/O ,/O training/O in/O basic/O economic/O and/O financial/O literacy/O is/O not/O part/O of/O the/O standard/O curriculum/O and/O training/O on/O digital/O literacy/O and/O entrepreneurship/O has/O still/O much/O room/O to/O cover/O ./O 
Figure/O 8/NUMBER :/O Skills/O and/O Resilience/O For/O a/O World/O of/O Change/O Note/O :/O This/O framework/O is/O inspired/O by/O the/O T-Skill/O framework/O -LRB-/O see/O endnote/O 31/NUMBER -RRB-/O Source/O :/O Skills/O Outlook/O 2013/DATE ,/O OECD/ORGANIZATION Over-quali?ed/O who/O are/O under-skilledUnder-quali?ed/O who/O are/O over-skilled/O 0/DATE 5/DATE 10/DATE 15/DATE 20/DATE 25/DATE 30/DATE 0/DATE 510?15202530/ORGANIZATION Germany/ORGANIZATION Austria/ORGANIZATION Finland/ORGANIZATION Japan/ORGANIZATION Netherlands/ORGANIZATION Czech/ORGANIZATION Republic/ORGANIZATION Korea/ORGANIZATION Australia/ORGANIZATION Spain/ORGANIZATION Ireland/ORGANIZATION Canada/ORGANIZATION Slovak/ORGANIZATION Republic/ORGANIZATION Average/ORGANIZATION United/ORGANIZATION States/ORGANIZATION Flanders/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O Belgium/LOCATION -RRB-/O Poland/LOCATION Norway/ORGANIZATION Estonia/ORGANIZATION Sweden/ORGANIZATION United/ORGANIZATION Kingdom/ORGANIZATION Italy/ORGANIZATION Denmark/ORGANIZATION Cyprus/ORGANIZATION Over-quali?ed/O who/O are/O over-skilled/O Under-quali?ed/O who/O are/O under-skilled/O Figure/O 7/NUMBER :/O Qualification/O and/O Skills/O Mismatch/O in/O Literacy/O Percentage/O of/O qualification-mismatched/O who/O are/O in/O each/O literacy/O mismatch/O status/O CORE/O LITERACIES/O ?/O Reading/O and/O writing/O ?/O Numeracy/O ?/O Scientific/O literacy/O ?/O ICT/ORGANIZATION fluency/O ?/O Language/O skills/O -LRB-/O mothertongue/O +1/NUMBER -RRB-/O ?/O Cultural/O and/O civic/O awareness/O Critical/O thinking/O Creativity/ORGANIZATION Communication/ORGANIZATION Collaboration/ORGANIZATION Curiosity/ORGANIZATION Initiative/ORGANIZATION Persistence/ORGANIZATION Empathy/ORGANIZATION Adaptability/ORGANIZATION DOMAIN/ORGANIZATION KNOWLEDGE/O Area/O of/O specialisation/O Expertise/O COMPETENCES/O MINDSET/O &/O TALENT/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O 9/NUMBER 5.2/NUMBER ./O 
Skills/O Endowment/O The/O increased/O likelihood/O of/O job/O changes/O ,/O contractual/O and/O on/O -/O demand/O work/O ,/O means/O that/O it/O will/O be/O more/O difficult/O to/O target/O training/O and/O retraining/O ./O 
Therefore/O ,/O the/O risk/O of/O human/O capital/O depletion/O could/O grow/O ./O 
As/O already/O mentioned/O ,/O employers/O may/O be/O more/O selective/O when/O investing/O in/O their/O employees/O '/O training/O or/O reskilling/O ./O 
This/O means/O that/O new/O arrangements/O will/O have/O to/O be/O crafted/O to/O effectively/O share/O the/O burden/O of/O -LRB-/O regular/O -RRB-/O training/O between/O individual/O workers/O ,/O employers/O ,/O and/O the/O state/O ./O 
Today/DATE ,/O publically-financed/O education/O is/O mainly/O directed/O towards/O children/O and/O young/O adults/O not/O yet/O in/O employment/O ./O 
In/O the/DATE future/DATE ,/O such/O arrangements/O need/O to/O focus/O just/O as/O much/O on/O workers/O and/O job-seekers/O aiming/O to/O fundamentally/O improve/O their/O employability/O ./O 
Innovative/O public/O --/O private/O partnerships/O between/O schools/O ,/O universities/O and/O private/O training/O providers/O ,/O should/O be/O encouraged/O to/O invest/O in/O skills-development/O and/O human/O capital/O of/O a/O fluid/O and/O highly/O mobile/O workforce/O ./O 
Such/O a/O `/O skills/O endowment/O '/O could/O be/O pre-financed/O through/O education-linked/O loans/O that/O would/O only/O have/O to/O be/O paid/O back/O when/O and/O if/O the/O recipient/O achieves/O a/O certain/O level/O of/O income/O through/O their/O subsequent/O employment/O ./O 
This/O investment/O approach/O draws/O from/O the/O English/O student/O loans/O model/O ./O 
Skill/O Development/O in/O Flagship/O EU/ORGANIZATION Funding/O Programmes/O The/O European/O Social/O Fund/O and/O the/O European/O Regional/O Development/O Fund/O will/O inject/O over/O EUR/O 30/NUMBER billion/NUMBER to/O support/O skills/O development/O in/O the/O period/O 2014-2020/DURATION ,/O while/O the/O Erasmus/O +/O programme/O supports/O skills/O development/O in/O education/O and/O training/O with/O nearly/O EUR/O 15/MONEY billion/MONEY ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O through/O the/O European/O Structural/O and/O Investment/O Funds/O -LRB-/O ESIF/O -RRB-/O ,/O the/O EU/ORGANIZATION plans/O to/O invest/O EUR/O 454/NUMBER billion/NUMBER in/O Europe/LOCATION 's/O cities/O and/O regions/O ,/O while/O channelling/O funding/O to/O over/O 2/NUMBER million/NUMBER enterprises/O to/O support/O growth/O ,/O increase/O competitiveness/O ,/O develop/O projects/O and/O most/O importantly/O ,/O create/O new/O jobs/O ./O 
In/O addition/O to/O the/O ESIF/ORGANIZATION ,/O bridging/O the/O investment/O gap/O through/O the/O implementation/O of/O the/O European/O Fund/O for/O Strategic/ORGANIZATION Investments/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O EFSI/O -RRB-/O can/O have/O a/O significant/O impact/O on/O improving/O Europe/LOCATION 's/O job/O prospects/O ./O 
Human/O capital/O formation/O is/O a/O core/O priority/O area/O of/O EFSI/O while/O its/O most/O successful/O spending/O vehicle/O to/O date/O is/O aimed/O at/O SMEs/ORGANIZATION and/O mid-cap/O companies/O ./O 
It/O is/O estimated/O that/O 1.8/NUMBER million/NUMBER jobs/O can/O be/O created/O directly/O or/O indirectly/O through/O the/O leveraging/O effect/O of/O the/O Investment/O Plan/O on/O the/O assumption/O that/O projects/O selected/O do/O not/O `/O \/O crowd/O out/O '/O private/O investment/O ./O 
32/NUMBER Mainstreaming/O EFSI/O to/O areas/O with/O highest/O unemployment/O levels/O can/O help/O address/O labour/O market/O disparities/O across/O the/O EU/ORGANIZATION while/O synergy/O should/O also/O be/O established/O with/O the/O smart/O sp/O \/O ecialisation/O strategy/O ./O 
Complementary/O support/O to/O skill/O development/O can/O generate/O additional/O positive/O gains/O in/O t/O \/O he/O volume/O of/O employment/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O the/O EFSI/O regulation/O states/O clearly/O that/O projects/O in/O the/O field/O of/O human/O capital/O ,/O culture/O and/O health/O should/O include/O education/O ,/O training/O ,/O the/O development/O of/O ICT/ORGANIZATION skills/O and/O digital/O education/O ./O 
Member/O States/O should/O off/O er/O customised/O training/O programmes/O to/O improve/O the/O skills-matching/O performance/O of/O the/O labour/O market/O in/O the/O sectors/O benefiting/O from/O the/O EFSI/O ./O 
Beyond/O complementing/O Member/O States/O actions/O ,/O a/O dedicated/O `/O human/O capital/O investment/O '/O instrument/O could/O be/O added/O to/O the/O EFSI/O ,/O providing/O pooled/O finance/O for/O investment/O in/O this/O area/O in/O the/O same/O way/O that/O the/O framework/O already/O does/O for/O SMEs/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Refitting/O education/O for/O the/O demands/O of/O the/O world/O of/O work/O requires/O novel/O forms/O of/O schooling/O and/O teaching/O with/O a/O focus/O on/O the/O application/O of/O knowledge/O ./O 
Transversal/O competences/O -/O such/O as/O better/O management/O of/O one/NUMBER 's/O own/O learning/O ,/O social/O and/O interpersonal/O relations/O and/O communication/O -/O need/O to/O be/O integrated/O in/O all/O learning/O methods/O from/O pre-school/O to/O training/O schemes/O for/O mature/O workers/O -LRB-/O Figure/O 8/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
29/NUMBER As/O David/PERSON Deming/PERSON of/O Harvard/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION once/DATE observed/O ,/O the/O most/O advanced/O preschool/O classrooms/O `/O look/O a/O lot/O like/O the/O modern/O work/O world/O '/O ./O 
`/O Children/O move/O from/O art/O projects/O to/O science/O experiments/O to/O the/O playground/O in/O small/O groups/O ,/O and/O their/O most/O important/O skills/O are/O sharing/O and/O negotiating/O with/O others/O ./O '/O 
30/NUMBER Similarly/O ,/O social/O skills/O need/O to/O be/O part/O of/O the/O curriculum/O to/O create/O conditions/O for/O complementing/O technology/O with/O the/O human/O touch/O ./O 
In/O many/O business/O and/O medical/O schools/O ,/O so/O -/O called/O flipped/O classrooms/O focus/O on/O interactive/O discussion/O while/O lectures/O are/O to/O be/O followed/O online/O outside/O of/O the/O classroom/O ./O 
Vocational/O training/O schemes/O that/O successfully/O complement/O vocational/O skills/O with/O instruction/O in/O maths/O ,/O science/O and/O language/O ,/O like/O in/O Germany/LOCATION 's/O dual/O education/O system/O ,/O are/O well/O equiped/O for/O the/O changing/O employment/O landscape/O while/O providing/O flexibility/O for/O life-long/O learning/O ./O 
Apart/O from/O promoting/O new/O ways/O of/O learning/O ,/O it/O is/O equally/O important/O to/O ensure/O access/O to/O world-class/O education/O and/O talent/O ,/O to/O make/O sure/O that/O the/O EU/ORGANIZATION 's/O younger/O generation/O sources/O from/O international/O best/O practices/O ./O 
In/O the/O collaborative/O work/O culture/O and/O economy/O of/O the/DATE future/DATE ,/O having/O broader/O analytical/O skills/O and/O knowledge/O ,/O and/O being/O able/O to/O learn/O fast/O by/O linking/O up/O different/O perspectives/O from/O different/O disciplines/O ,/O appears/O more/O relevant/O than/O ever/O ./O 
31/NUMBER This/O competence/O is/O often/O referred/O to/O as/O T-shaped/O skills/O ,/O where/O the/O T/O represents/O the/O depth/O of/O an/O expertise/O in/O a/O single/O field/O ,/O whereas/O the/O horizontal/O bar/O is/O the/O ability/O to/O collaborate/O across/O disciplines/O ./O 
EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O W/O 10/NUMBER 5.3/NUMBER ./O 
Customisation/O of/O Social/O Policy/O Re-designing/O employment/O services/O and/O active/O employment/O policies/O for/O a/O flexible/O world/O of/O work/O calls/O for/O governments/O to/O find/O more/O innovative/O ways/O of/O policy/O intervention/O ./O 
Supporting/O employability/O can/O no/O longer/O be/O a/O one-off/O action/O ./O 
It/O involves/O a/O series/O of/O measures/O and/O instruments/O that/O may/O be/O personalised/O at/O different/O stages/O of/O one/NUMBER 's/O working/O life/O ./O 
As/O workers/O are/O more/O likely/O to/O change/O employers/O ,/O jobs/O ,/O sectors/O and/O even/O countries/O ,/O benefits/O and/O protection/O must/O be/O linked/O to/O the/O individual/O and/O not/O to/O jobs/O or/O unemployment/O ,/O which/O disadvantages/O those/O with/O non-standard/O employment/O or/O risks/O unwillingly/O incentivising/O informal/O work/O or/O inactivity/O ./O 
Examples/O of/O Customised/O Policy/O in/O Member/O States/O ?/O France/LOCATION 's/O Compte/O Personnel/O d'Activit?/O -LRB-/O CPA/O -RRB-/O 33/NUMBER is/O anticipated/O to/O be/O in/O place/O early/DATE 2017/DATE ,/O as/O introduced/O by/O the/O 2015/DATE Bill/O on/O Social/O Dialogue/O and/O Employment/O ./O 
Its/O aim/O is/O to/O enable/O individuals/O to/O decide/O how/O to/O best/O mobilise/O their/O benefits/O to/O fit/O their/O individual/O circumstances/O ./O 
The/O CPA/ORGANIZATION would/O guarantee/O that/O benefits/O are/O no/O longer/O contingent/O on/O an/O individual/O 's/O job/O ./O 
Instead/O ,/O an/O individual/O activity/O account/O would/O provide/O each/O active/O member/O of/O the/O labour/O force/O their/O social/O benefits/O -LRB-/O training/O ,/O support/O to/O start/O a/O business/O ,/O shift/O to/O part-time/O work/O ,/O early/O retirement/O -RRB-/O in/O the/O form/O of/O points/O ,/O regardless/O of/O employment/O status/O ./O 
These/O benefits/O --/O in/O the/O form/O of/O `/O points/O '/O --/O would/O be/O adjusted/O to/O correct/O for/O different/O inequalities/O ,/O targeting/O in/O particular/O early/O school/O leavers/O ,/O under/O 26/DURATION year/DURATION olds/O in/O precarious/O employment/O ,/O granting/O them/O more/O points/O than/O their/O university-graduate/O peers/O for/O example/O ./O 
?/O The/O Czech/O `/O Education/O and/O work/O '/O web/O portal/O 34/NUMBER was/O established/O as/O part/O of/O the/O reform/O of/O education/O and/O training/O policies/O aimed/O at/O ensuring/O that/O individuals/O are/O better/O able/O to/O \/O discover/O ,/O validate/O and/O further/O develop/O outcomes/O of/O prior/O learning/O ./O 
The/O tool/O links/O existing/O vacancy/O databases/O to/O \/O information/O on/O training/O courses/O ,/O providers/O ,/O and/O generic/O occupation/O overviews/O ./O 
It/O intends/O to/O create/O practical/O individual/O pathways/O to/O benefit/O from/O the/O possibilities/O of/O the/O national/O qualifications/O framework/O ./O 
Through/O user/O self-assessment/O ,/O using/O the/O skill/O descriptions/O found/O in/O the/O vocational/O qualifications/O ,/O and/O by/O suggesting/O possibilities/O for/O gaining/O a/O vocational/O qualification/O that/O is/O purely/O skill/competence-based/O and/O matched/O to/O labour/O mark/O et/O needs/O ,/O the/O instrument/O matches/O skills/O with/O jobs/O -LRB-/O and/O the/O other/O way/O around/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Assembling/O Individual/O Tasks/O into/O a/O Standard/ORGANIZATION Contract/ORGANIZATION Care/ORGANIZATION and/O non-care/O personal/O and/O household/O services/O in/O Europe/LOCATION are/O increasi/O \/O ngly/O outsourced/O by/O households/O to/O third/ORDINAL parties/O ./O 
The/O care/O sector/O ,/O which/O has/O a/O notable/O potential/O in/O terms/O of/O job/O creation/O ,/O is/O largely/O cha/O \/O racterised/O by/O undeclared/O labour/O and/O therefore/O uncertain/O and/O even/O risky/O working/O conditions/O ./O 
Certain/O schemes/O ,/O however/O ,/O have/O been/O particularly/O successful/O in/O creating/O formal/O jobs/O leading/O to/O standard/O contracts/O and/O full/O social/O protection/O coverage/O ./O 
The/O Titres-Services/O voucher/O model/O established/O in/O Belgium/LOCATION since/O 2004/DATE is/O one/NUMBER such/O successful/O example/O ./O 
Workers/O are/O employed/O by/O an/O organisation/O -LRB-/O private/O or/O public/O ,/O for-profit/O or/O not/O -RRB-/O that/O sells/O the/O services/O to/O different/O households/O ./O 
Households/O pre-purchase/O vouchers/O ,/O usually/O on-line/O and/O use/O these/O to/O request/O the/O services/O they/O need/O -LRB-/O cleaning/O ,/O washing/O ,/O ironing/O ,/O gardening/O ,/O shopping/O ,/O meal/O preparation/O ,/O etc/O -RRB-/O from/O the/O \/O company/O ./O 
The/O company/O then/O assigns/O the/O tasks/O to/O a/O worker/O ./O 
The/O price/O of/O each/SET hourly/SET voucher/O is/O set/O by/O the/O state/O which/O also/O offers/O a/O 30/PERCENT %/PERCENT tax/O deduction/O to/O users/O of/O Titres-Services/O ,/O thereby/O providing/O users/O with/O an/O incentive/O to/O prefer/O a/O formal/O arrangement/O for/O these/O services/O over/O undeclared/O work/O ./O 
For/O the/O worker/O ,/O the/O accumulation/O of/O vouchers/O by/O working/O in/O different/O households/O each/SET day/SET offers/O them/O access/O to/O a/O formal/O labour/O contract/O guaranteeing/O the/O same/O rights/O as/O any/O other/O worker/O ,/O including/O paid/O vacation/O ,/O health/O and/O pension/O rights/O ./O 
Depending/O on/O the/O number/O of/O vouchers/O \/O collected/O the/O worker/O may/O choose/O to/O work/O part-time/O or/O full-time/O and/O after/O three/NUMBER consecutive/O months/DURATION with/O the/O same/O provider/O ,/O fixed-term/O contracts/O become/O open-ended/O ./O 
Employers/O can/O benefit/O from/O a/O reduction/O in/O their/O social/O contribution/O if/O they/O recruit/O long-term/O unemployed/O participating/O in/O activation/O programmes/O ./O 
Unemployed/O persons/O and/O recipients/O of/O social/O assistance/O are/O targeted/O by/O this/O measure/O ,/O as/O 60/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O jobs/O under/O the/O scheme/O must/O be/O attributed/O to/O such/O categories/O of/O people/O ./O 
The/O scheme/O is/O quite/O costly/O for/O the/O public/O purse/O due/O to/O the/O tax-reduction/O offered/O ./O 
However/O ,/O the/O direct/O and/O indirect/O advantages/O far/O outnumber/O the/O costs/O ./O 
Among/O these/O :/O decrease/O in/O unemployment/O ;/O new/O social/O contributions/O ;/O new/O receipts/O on/O personal/O income/O tax/O ;/O the/O impact/O on/O consumption/O from/O new/O work/O \/O ers/O ;/O the/O indirect/O creation/O of/O new/O jobs/O like/O administrative/O jobs/O in/O the/O agencies/O and/O freeing/O up/O women/O who/O use/O the/O v/O \/O ouchers/O to/O free/O up/O time/O so/O they/O can/O pursue/O their/O own/O careers/O ./O 
And/O of/O course/O ,/O the/O societal/O benefits/O of/O creating/O new/O jobs/O particularly/O for/O low-skilled/O workers/O under/O decent/O working/O conditions/O and/O social/O protection/O ,/O and/O reducing/O \/O the/O informal/O sector/O ./O 
Sources/O :/O ORSEU/O -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Developing/O personal/O and/O household/O services/O in/O the/O EU/ORGANIZATION -/O A/O f/O ocus/O on/O housework/O activities/O ;/O Report/O for/O the/O DG/ORGANIZATION Employment/ORGANIZATION ,/O Social/ORGANIZATION Affairs/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Inclusion/ORGANIZATION ./O 
http://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=738&langId=en&pubId=7664/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O 11/NUMBER One/NUMBER way/O of/O going/O about/O customisation/O of/O social/O policy/O could/O be/O the/O establishment/O of/O notional/O personal/O human/O capital/O accounts/O to/O create/O a/O pool/O of/O resources/O for/O everyone/O to/O use/O throughout/O their/O careers/O ./O 
Depending/O on/O specific/O requirements/O ,/O the/O resources/O could/O be/O used/O for/O training/O and/O retraining/O purposes/O related/O to/O work/O assignments/O ./O 
Apart/O from/O a/O fraction/O of/O their/O salary/O being/O designated/O for/O the/O function/O ,/O workers/O would/O be/O in/O the/O position/O to/O benefit/O from/O tax-free/O contributions/O to/O their/O schemes/O from/O employers/O and/or/O public/O and/O private/O partners/O ./O 
The/O scheme/O could/O be/O relevant/O for/O all/O workers/O ,/O whether/O holding/O fixed/O contracts/O or/O being/O self-employed/O ,/O further/O levelling/O the/O field/O in/O the/O world/O of/O work/O ./O 
5.4/NUMBER ./O 
Data/O is/O Knowledge/O and/O Key/O for/O Effective/O Policies/O We/O still/O know/O little/O about/O the/O new/O dynamics/O described/O above/O and/O how/O firms/O and/O workers/O cope/O with/O them/O ./O 
Measuring/O resilience/O ,/O targeting/O investment/O ,/O assessing/O the/O return/O ,/O and/O turning/O public/O intervention/O to/O where/O it/O is/O needed/O the/O most/O requires/O the/O use/O of/O micro-data/O ./O 
Big/O data/O offers/O an/O unprecedented/O opportunity/O to/O track/O and/O anticipate/O gaps/O in/O skills/O ,/O map/O mismatches/O and/O polarisation/O in/O the/O job/O market/O ,/O and/O marry/O employers/O '/O need/O with/O employees/O '/O capabilities/O ./O 
It/O also/O offers/O transparency/O for/O individuals/O to/O understand/O potential/O career/O options/O ,/O education/O and/O training/O requirements/O and/O how/O these/O are/O remunerated/O in/O the/O labour/O market/O ./O 
Modernising/O and/O expanding/O job/O classifications/O may/O also/O be/O necessary/O given/O the/O transformations/O underway/O ./O 
What/O is/O more/O ,/O big/O data/O offers/O policymakers/O the/O chance/O to/O leverage/O behavioural/O insights/O and/O avoid/O inefficiencies/O in/O implementation/O ./O 
Experience/O of/O agencies/O such/O as/O the/O UK/O Behavioural/O Insights/O Team/O with/O the/O Department/ORGANIZATION for/O Work/O and/O Pensions/O shows/O that/O studying/O the/O behaviour/O of/O job-seekers/O can/O substantially/O increase/O policy/O returns/O ./O 
There/O is/O a/O case/O for/O accelerating/O and/O streamlining/O the/O adoption/O of/O data-driven/O and/O evidence-based/O policy/O and/O decision-making/O ./O 
A/O number/O of/O ongoing/O projects/O yield/O very/O promising/O results/O ,/O including/O Vacancies/O for/O ICT/ORGANIZATION --/O Online/O Repository/O -LRB-/O Victory/O project/O -RRB-/O ,/O which/O is/O a/O big/O data/O related/O pilot/O initiative/O to/O map/O online/O vacancies/O for/O jobs/O and/O associated/O skills/O ./O 
Another/O example/O is/O www/O ./O 
data4policy.eu/O ,/O which/O supports/O big/O data/O and/O other/O innovative/O data-driven/O approaches/O for/O evidence-based/O policy/O making/O ./O 
Finally/O ,/O combining/O the/O potential/O of/O big/O data/O with/O more/O regular/O labour/O force/O surveys/O would/O permit/O to/O better/O monitor/O changes/O in/O the/O pace/O and/O nature/O of/O work/O relationships/O ./O 
This/O is/O fundamental/O to/O understand/O the/O forces/O affecting/O the/O European/O economy/O ,/O the/O working/O conditions/O ,/O and/O the/O quality/O of/O life/O of/O European/O workers/O ./O 
These/O precise/O efforts/O are/O already/O underway/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION with/O the/O RAND-Princeton/O Contingent/O Worker/O Survey/O -LRB-/O RPCWS/O -RRB-/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2015/DATE ./O 
The/O Contingent/O Worker/O Survey/O tracks/O alternative/O -LRB-/O or/O non-standard/O -RRB-/O work/O relationships/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ./O 
It/O had/O not/O been/O conducted/O since/O 2005/DATE meaning/O there/O was/O a/O substantial/O lack/O of/O data/O on/O on/O -/O going/O labour/O market/O developments/O ./O 
To/O respond/O to/O this/O data-void/O ,/O Lawrence/PERSON F./PERSON Katz/PERSON from/O Harvard/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION and/O Alan/PERSON B./PERSON Krueger/PERSON from/O Princeton/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION based/O themselves/O on/O the/O Bureau/ORGANIZATION 's/ORGANIZATION Contingent/ORGANIZATION Worker/ORGANIZATION Survey/ORGANIZATION and/O expanded/O it/O to/O gain/O more/O complete/O information/O on/O work/O arrangements/O ./O 
Having/O more/O dynamic/O data/O is/O core/O to/O be/O able/O to/O monitor/O and/O diagnose/O developments/O in/O Europe/LOCATION 's/O labour/O markets/O ./O 
Effectively/O investing/O in/O people/O requires/O that/O governments/O make/O their/O instruments/O for/O social/O investment/O user-centred/O ./O 
Drawing/O on/O the/O pools/O of/O available/O data/O governments/O identify/O future/DATE needs/O for/O policy/O intervention/O as/O well/O as/O emerging/O vulnerabilities/O and/O opportunities/O that/O may/O be/O better/O tapped/O into/O through/O early/O activation/O measures/O ./O 
Conclusions/O The/O world/O of/O work/O is/O part-and-parcel/O of/O the/O changing/O economy/O ,/O heavily/O influenced/O by/O globalisation/O ,/O international/O value/O and/O supply/O chains/O ,/O more/O division/O of/O labour/O ,/O and/O digital/O disruption/O ./O 
Work/O is/O no/O longer/O a/O static/O concept/O but/O an/O umbrella/O term/O for/O roles/O performed/O in/O a/O different/O manner/O and/O under/O different/O legal/O arrangements/O ./O 
Public/O policy/O needs/O to/O adapt/O to/O this/O new/O situation/O and/O benefit/O from/O the/O agility/O that/O comes/O with/O it/O while/O mitigating/O the/O downsides/O ./O 
Europe/LOCATION has/O a/O strong/O manufacturing/O base/O ,/O a/O diverse/O and/O talented/O workforce/O and/O a/O large/O creative/O economy/O that/O offer/O a/O rich/O backdrop/O for/O a/O future/DATE of/O work/O with/O creative/O and/O fulfilling/O jobs/O ./O 
By/O orchestrating/O more/O tailor-made/O ,/O customised/O interventions/O ,/O based/O on/O granular/O insights/O provided/O by/O big/O data/O sources/O ,/O it/O can/O achieve/O better/O results/O and/O foster/O the/O context/O within/O which/O both/O individuals/O and/O firms/O can/O thrive/O ./O 
Governments/O need/O to/O find/O more/O innovative/O ways/O to/O offer/O life-long/O and/O personalised/O support/O for/O employment/O ,/O skills/O and/O welfare/O ,/O adapted/O to/O the/O needs/O of/O individuals/O ./O 
EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O 12/NUMBER Notes/O 1/NUMBER ./O 
See/O inter/O alia/O :/O France/PERSON Strat?gie/PERSON -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O L'/O avenir/O du/O travail/O :/O quelles/O red?finitions/O de/O l'emploi/O ,/O des/O statuts/O et/O des/O protections/O ?/O 
;/O German/ORGANIZATION Federal/ORGANIZATION Ministry/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Labour/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Affairs/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Green/O Paper/O Arbeit/O 4.0/NUMBER ;/O HBR/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O The/O Rise/O of/O the/O Supertemp/O ,/O https://hbr/O ./O 
org/2012/05/O //O the-rise-of-the-supertemp/O 2/NUMBER ./O 
Labour/O market/O and/O Labour/ORGANIZATION force/O survey/O -LRB-/O LFS/O -RRB-/O statistics/O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php/Labour_/O market/O _/O and/O _/O Labour/O _/O force/O _/O survey/O _/O -LRB-/O LFS/O -RRB-/O _/O statistics/O 3/NUMBER ./O 
1/NUMBER in/O 10/NUMBER employees/O in/O the/O EU/ORGANIZATION are/O employed/O on/O temporary/O contracts/O -LRB-/O Eurofound/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O rise/O of/O temporary/O contracts/O in/O Europe/LOCATION ,/O https/O :/O //O //O www.eurofound.europa.eu/news/spotlight-on/employment/the-rise-of/O -/O temporary-contracts-in-europe/O ./O 
The/O number/O of/O temporary/O employees/O grew/O by/O 25/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O the/O EU27/O from/O 2001/DATE and/O 2012/DATE compared/O with/O a/O growth/O of/O 7/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O permanent/O employees/O -LRB-/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2001/DATE 11/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O all/O employee/O in/O EU27/O were/O working/O under/O temporary/O contract/O ,/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2012/DATE this/O rose/O to/O 13/PERCENT %/PERCENT -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O impact/O of/O the/O crisis/O on/O this/O trend/O is/O evident/O but/O this/O is/O \/O a/O trend/O across/O all/O countries/O ./O 
The/O countries/O that/O witnessed/O this/O growth/O the/O most/O are/O :/O Poland/LOCATION -LRB-/O 2/NUMBER million/NUMBER -RRB-/O ,/O Germany/LOCATION 1.1/NUMBER million/NUMBER -RRB-/O ,/O Italy/LOCATION -LRB-/O 900,000/NUMBER -RRB-/O ,/O France/LOCATION -LRB-/O 400,000/NUMBER -RRB-/O and/O the/LOCATION Netherlands/LOCATION -LRB-/O 300,000/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
4/NUMBER ./O 
European/O Commission/O ,/O SWD/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 51/NUMBER final/O ,/O Key/O economic/O ,/O employment/O and/O social/O trends/O behind/O a/O European/O Pillar/O of/O Social/O Rights/O 08.03.2016/DATE ;/O ec.europa.eu/O //O social/BlobServlet/O ?/O 
docId/O =/O 15142/NUMBER &/O langId/O =/O en/O European/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION ,/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Employment/O and/O Social/O Developments/O in/O Europe/LOCATION -LRB-/O ESDE/O -RRB-/O 2015/DATE http://ec.europa.eu/social/main/O ./O 
jsp?catId/O =/O 738/NUMBER &/O langId/O =/O en/O &/O pubId/O =/O 7859/NUMBER &/O furtherPubs/O =/O yes/O ;/O Similarly/O for/O the/O USA/ORGANIZATION see/O :/O Freelancers/ORGANIZATION Union/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Upwork/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Freelancing/O in/O America/LOCATION :/O 2015/DATE ,/O https://fu-web-storage-prod.s3.amazonaws.com/content/filer_public/59//O e7/59e70be1-5730-4db8-919f-1d9b5024f939/survey_2015.pdf/O 5/NUMBER ./O 
Eurociett/O ,/O Agency/ORGANIZATION Work/ORGANIZATION Indicator/ORGANIZATION ,/O January/DATE 2016/DATE ,/O http://www.eurociett.eu//O uploads/media/January_2016_Eurociett_Agency_Work_Business_Indicator.pdf/O 6/NUMBER ./O 
Katz/PERSON L.F./O and/O Krueger/PERSON A./PERSON B./PERSON -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O The/O Rise/O and/O Nature/O of/O Alternative/O Work/O Arrangements/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O 1995-2015/DATE ,/O http://krueger.princeton.edu//O sites/default/files/O //O akrueger/files/katz/O _/O krueger/O _/O cws/O _/O -/O _/O march_29_20165.pdf/O 7/NUMBER ./O 
Harvard/ORGANIZATION Business/ORGANIZATION Review/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O The/O Rise/O of/O the/O Supertemp/O :/O https://hbr.org/2012/05/the-rise-of-the-supertemp/O 8/NUMBER ./O 
Directive/O on/O Equal/ORGANIZATION Treatment/ORGANIZATION in/ORGANIZATION Employment/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Occupation/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2000/78/EC/O -RRB-/O http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/en//O TXT/O //O ?/O 
uri/O =/O CELEX/O :/O 32000L0078/O ;/O and/O the/O Directive/O on/O Equal/ORGANIZATION Treatment/ORGANIZATION in/ORGANIZATION Respect/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Racial/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Ethnic/ORGANIZATION Origin/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2000/43/EC/O -RRB-/O ./O 
http://eur-lex/O ./O 
europa.eu/O //O legal-content/en/TXT/O //O ?/O 
uri/O =/O CELEX/PERCENT %/PERCENT 3A32000L0043/O 9/NUMBER ./O 
For/O an/O excellent/O discussion/O of/O the/O phenomenon/O ,/O see/O :/O http://www/O ./O 
bankofengland.co.uk/O //O publications/Documents/speeches/O //O 2015/DATE //O speech864.pdf/O ;/O https://hbr.org/2012/05/the-rise-of-the-supertemp/O ;/O Economic/ORGANIZATION History/ORGANIZATION Association/ORGANIZATION ,/O History/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Turnover/ORGANIZATION in/O the/O U.S./LOCATION ,/O https://eh.net/encyclopedia/history-of-labor-turnover-in-the-u-s//O 10/NUMBER ./O 
Frey/O ,/O C./PERSON B./PERSON ,/O Osborne/PERSON ,/O M./O A./O -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O `/O The/DATE future/DATE of/O employment/O :/O how/O susceptible/O are/O jobs/O to/O computerisation/O '/O ,/O Study/O for/O the/O Oxford/ORGANIZATION Martin/ORGANIZATION Programme/ORGANIZATION on/O the/O Impacts/O of/O Future/DATE Technology/O ;/O Thompson/PERSON D./O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O A/O World/O Without/O Work/O ,/O The/O Atlantic/LOCATION -LRB-/O http://www.theatlantic/O ./O 
com/magazine/archive/O //O 2015/07/world-without-work/O //O 395294/NUMBER //O -RRB-/O 11/NUMBER ./O 
CEDEFOP/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Future/DATE skills/O supply/O and/O demand/O in/O Europe/LOCATION ,/O Forecast/O 2012/DATE ,/O http://www.cedefop.europa.eu/en/publications-and/O -/O resources/publications/5526/O 12/NUMBER ./O 
OECD/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O Future/DATE of/O Work/O in/O figures/O ./O 
http://www.oecd.org//O employment/ministerial/future-of-work-in-figures.htm/O 13/NUMBER ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Jobs/O ,/O Employment/O ,/O Skills/O and/O Workforce/O Strategy/O for/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ,/O http/O :/O //O //O www3.weforum.org/docs/WEF_FOJ_Executive_Summary_Jobs.pdf/O 14/NUMBER ./O 
PwC/O ,/O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O UK/O Economic/O Outlook/O ,/O March/DATE 2015/DATE http://www.pwc/O ./O 
co.uk/O //O the-economy/publications/uk-economic-outlook/O //O ;/O Bowels/O ,/O J./O -LRB-/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O The/O Computerisation/O of/O European/O Jobs/O ,/O Bruegel/LOCATION ,/O http/O :/O //O //O bruegel.org/2014/07/the-computerisation-of-european-jobs//O 15/NUMBER ./O 
OECD/O Skills/O Outlook/O -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O First/ORGANIZATION Results/ORGANIZATION from/O the/O Survey/O of/O Adult/O Skills/O ,/O http/O :/O //O //O www.oecd-ilibrary.org/education/oecd-skills-outlook-2013_9789264204256/O -/O en/O ;/O EPSC/O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O The/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Dimension/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Monetary/ORGANIZATION Union/ORGANIZATION :/O Towards/O Convergence/O and/O Resilience/O ,/O Issue/O 5/NUMBER //O June2015/DATE ,/O http://ec.europa.eu//O epsc/publications/notes/O //O sn5/O _/O en.htm/O ;/O David/PERSON J./PERSON Deming/PERSON ,/O The/O Growing/O Importance/O of/O Social/O Skills/O in/O the/O Labor/O Market/O ,/O http://www.nber.org/papers/w21473/O ;/O 16/NUMBER ./O 
Oxford/ORGANIZATION Dictionary/ORGANIZATION defines/O creativity/O as/O `/O the/O use/O of/O broad/O imagination/O or/O original/O ideas/O to/O create/O something/O '/O http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition//O english/creativity/O ;/O Bakhshi/PERSON ,/O H./O ,/O Frey/PERSON ,/O C./PERSON B./PERSON ,/O and/O Osborne/PERSON ,/O M./O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O Creativity/O vs./O Robots/O :/O the/O Creative/O economy/O and/O the/DATE future/DATE of/O employment/O ,/O Nesta/PERSON :/O UK/O http/O :/O //O //O www.nesta.org.uk/sites/default/files/creativity_vs._robots_wv.pdf/O 17/NUMBER ./O 
See/O :/O OECD/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O Science/O Technology/O and/O Industry/O Scoreboard/O 2015/DATE Innovation/O for/O Growth/O and/O Society/O http://www.keepeek.com/Digital-Asset/O -/O Management/oecd/science-and-technology/O //O oecd-science-technology-and/O -/O industry-scoreboard-2015/O _/O sti/O _/O scoreboard-2015-en/O #page25/O 18/NUMBER ./O 
Bruegel/O Blueprint/O Series/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Measuring/O competitiveness/O in/O Europe/LOCATION :/O resource/O allocation/O ,/O granularity/O and/O trade/O ,/O by/O C./ORGANIZATION Altomonte/ORGANIZATION and/O G./PERSON Bekes/PERSON -LRB-/O Eds/O -RRB-/O http://bruegel.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Blueprint-XXIV.pdf/O 19/NUMBER ./O 
Henrekson/O ,/O M./O and/O Johansson/PERSON ,/O D./O -LRB-/O 2010/DATE -RRB-/O `/O Gazelles/O as/O job/O creators/O :/O a/O survey/O and/O interpretation/O of/O the/O evidence/O '/O ,/O in/O Small/ORGANIZATION Business/ORGANIZATION Economics/ORGANIZATION ,/O 35:227-244/O ,/O DOI/O 10.1007/NUMBER //O s11187-009-9172-z/O 20/NUMBER ./O 
MacCrory/O ,/O F./O ,/O Westerman/PERSON ,/O G./O ,/O Al/PERSON Hammadi/PERSON ,/O Y./O ,/O and/O Brynjolfsson/PERSON ,/O E./O -LRB-/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O `/O Racing/O with/O and/O against/O the/O machine/O :/O Changes/O in/O occupational/O skill/O composition/O in/O an/O era/O of/O rapid/O technological/O advance/O '/O ./O 
Thirty/ORDINAL fifth/ORDINAL International/ORGANIZATION Conference/ORGANIZATION on/ORGANIZATION Information/ORGANIZATION Systems/ORGANIZATION ,/O Auckland/LOCATION 2014/DATE ./O 
21/NUMBER ./O 
Harvard/ORGANIZATION Business/ORGANIZATION Review/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Next-Gen/O Retirement/O ,/O by/O H.C./PERSON Vough/PERSON ,/O C.D./PERSON Bataille/PERSON ,/O L./PERSON Sargent/PERSON ,/O and/O M.D./PERSON Lee/PERSON https://hbr.org/2016/06/next-gen-retirement/O 22/NUMBER ./O 
US/O ,/O Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION ,/O Employee/ORGANIZATION Tenure/ORGANIZATION Summary/ORGANIZATION ,/O http://www/O ./O 
bls.gov/O //O news.release/O //O tenure.nr0.htm/O ;/O Labour/ORGANIZATION Market/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION ,/O OECD/ORGANIZATION ./O 
23/NUMBER ./O 
OECD/O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O In/O it/O Together/O :/O Why/O Less/O Inequality/O Benefits/O All/O ,/O http/O :/O //O //O www.oecd.org/social/in-it-together-why-less-inequality-benefits-all/O -/O 9789264235120-en.htm/O 24/NUMBER ./O 
OECD/ORGANIZATION ,/O Back/O to/O work/O :/O Sweden/LOCATION Improving/O the/O Re-employment/O Prospects/O of/O Displaced/O Workers/O ./O 
http://www.keepeek.com//O Digital-Asset-Management/oecd/employment/O //O back-to-work/O -/O sweden/LOCATION _/O 9789264246812-en/O #page47/O 25/NUMBER ./O 
European/O Commission/O ,/O SWD/O -LRB-/O 2016/DATE -RRB-/O 51/NUMBER final/O ,/O Key/O economic/O ,/O employment/O and/O social/O trends/O behind/O a/O European/O Pillar/O of/O Social/O Rights/O ,/O 08.03.2016/DATE ec.europa.eu/O //O social/BlobServlet/O ?/O 
docId/O =/O 15142/NUMBER &/O langId/O =/O en/O 26/NUMBER ./O 
McKay/O ,/O S./O et/O al/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Study/O on/O Precarious/O work/O and/O social/O rights/O ,/O Carried/O out/O for/O the/O European/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O VT/2010/084/O -RRB-/O Working/ORGANIZATION Lives/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION ,/O Faculty/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Sciences/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Humanities/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION London/ORGANIZATION Metropolitan/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION 27/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Bauman/O ,/O Z./O -LRB-/O 2007/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Liquid/O Times/O :/O Living/O in/O an/O Age/O of/O Uncertainty/O ,/O Polity/O :/O London/LOCATION ./O 
28/NUMBER ./O 
The/O World/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2014/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Developing/O Social-Emotional/O Skills/O for/O the/O Labor/O Market/O ,/O The/O PRACTICE/O Model/O ,/O http://www-wds.worldbank.org//O external/default/WDSContentServer/O //O WDSP/IB/2014/DATE //DATE 11/25/00015834/DATE 9_20141125090117/Rendered/PDF/WPS7123.pdf/O 29/NUMBER ./O 
European/O Commission/O -LRB-/O 2007/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Key/O Competences/O for/O Lifelong/O Learning/O ,/O European/ORGANIZATION Reference/ORGANIZATION Framework/ORGANIZATION ./O 
30/NUMBER ./O 
Cited/O in/O :/O http://www.nytimes.com/2015/10/18/upshot/how-the/DATE -/O modern-workplace-has-become-more-like-preschool.html/O ?/O 
smid/O =/O tw/ORGANIZATION -/O upshotnyt/O &/O smtyp/O =/O cur/O &/O _/O r/O =/O 0/NUMBER 31/NUMBER ./O 
The/O vertical/O bar/O of/O the/O T/O refers/O to/O the/O expert/O knowledge/O and/O experience/O in/O a/O particular/O area/O or/O discipline/O //O field/O ./O 
The/O top/O of/O the/O T/O refers/O to/O the/O ability/O to/O collaborate/O with/O experts/O in/O other/O disciplines/O and/O a/O willingness/O to/O use/O the/O knowledge/O gained/O in/O areas/O of/O expertise/O other/O than/O one/NUMBER 's/O own/O from/O this/O collaboration/O ./O 
32/NUMBER ./O 
ILO/O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O An/O Employment-Oriented/O Investment/O Strategy/O for/O Europe/LOCATION ./O 
http://www.ilo.org/wcmsp5/groups/public/---dgreports//O --/O dcomm/O //O --/O publ/documents/publication/wcms_338674.pdf/O 33/NUMBER ./O 
France/O Strat?gie/O -LRB-/O 2015/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O Rapport/O :/O Le/O compte/O personnel/O d'activit?/O ,/O de/O l'utopie/O au/O concret/O ;/O http://www.strategie.gouv.fr/publications/compte/O -/O personnel-dactivite-de-lutopie-concret/O 34/NUMBER ./O 
Cedefop/O 2015/DATE ,/O Tackling/O unemployment/O while/O addressing/O skill/O mismatch/O ,/O http://www.cedefop.europa.eu/en/publications-and/O -/O resources/publications/5546/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O EPSC/O Strategic/O Notes/O -/O The/DATE Future/DATE of/O Work/O 
