The/DATE Future/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION Care/ORGANIZATION :/O deep/O data/O ,/O smart/O sensors/O ,/O virtual/O patients/O and/O the/O Internet/O -/O of/O -/O Humans/O White/O Paper/O 11/NUMBER th/O May/DATE 2016/DATE Future/DATE Health/O 1/NUMBER Every/SET day/SET European/ORGANIZATION Union/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O EU/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O member/O states/O collectively/O spend/O close/O to/O ?/MONEY 4/MONEY billion/MONEY on/O health/O care/O By/U_TEMPPRED 2025/DATE more/O than/O 20/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O Europeans/O will/O be/O 65/NUMBER or/O older/O ,/O with/O many/O in/O ill/O health/O and/O dependent/O on/O the/O work/O of/O others/O ./O 
2/NUMBER We/O are/O standing/O at/O an/O inflection/O point/O ,/O with/O technological/O progress/O in/O a/O number/O of/O areas/O generating/O new/O ideas/O to/O solve/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O biggest/O challenges/O in/O our/O lives/O today/DATE --/O providing/O sustainable/O health/O care/O to/O a/O rapidly/O ageing/O population/O ./O 
The/O current/DATE challeng/O e/O is/O harnessing/O this/O progress/O for/O the/O benefit/O of/O Europe/LOCATION 's/O 500/NUMBER million/NUMBER citizens/O ./O 
The/DATE Future/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION Community/ORGANIZATION is/O asking/O the/O European/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION for/O support/O through/O a/O large/O -/O scale/O FETF/O lagship/O initiative/O to/O stimulate/O a/O paradigm/O change/O in/O health/O care/O by/O explo/O iting/O the/O most/O advanced/O sensing/O ,/O computing/O and/O communication/O technologies/O to/O enable/O personalised/O and/O preventative/O medicine/O in/O the/O framework/O of/O the/O Internet/O -/O of/O Humans/O ./O 
Support/O for/O Future/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION will/O enable/O Europe/LOCATION to/O extend/O and/O increase/O its/O scientific/O exce/O llence/O and/O competitiveness/O ,/O driven/O forward/O by/O the/O creation/O of/O a/O cost/O -/O effective/O ,/O sustainable/O ,/O equitable/O and/O truly/O personalised/O pan/O -/O European/O heath/O care/O system/O ./O 
3/NUMBER Grand/O Challenge/O Our/O individual/O existence/O and/O well/O -/O being/O depend/O primarily/O on/O remaining/O healthy/O and/O during/O ill/O health/O ,/O receiving/O the/O individualised/O ,/O optimal/O therapy/O ./O 
The/O continuing/O `/O health/O '/O of/O our/O societies/O is/O ,/O in/O contrast/O ,/O increasingly/O threatened/O by/O the/O enormous/O cost/O of/O providing/O appropriate/O healthcare/O -LRB-/O current/DATE ly/O 4/MONEY billion/MONEY euros/MONEY PER/O DAY/DURATION in/O Europe/LOCATION alone/O -RRB-/O in/O the/O rapidly/O ageing/O societies/O of/O Europe/LOCATION ./O 
When/O faced/O with/O similar/O challenges/O with/O harmful/O and/or/O expensive/O consequences/O in/O other/O areas/O we/O have/O followed/O a/O very/O simple/O principle/O :/O mistakes/O are/O unavoidable/O in/O dealin/O g/O with/O highly/O complex/O processes/O ./O 
While/O we/O can/O not/O avoid/O making/O these/O mistakes/O ,/O we/O can/O avoid/O most/O or/O all/O of/O their/O consequences/O by/O making/O these/O mistakes/O in/O silico/O ./O 
This/O change/O of/O strategy/O has/O been/O implemented/O in/O most/O areas/O of/O our/O existence/O ,/O increasing/O efficie/O ncy/O ,/O saving/O lives/O and/O reducing/O costs/O ./O 
This/O enormous/O progress/O has/O ,/O as/O yet/O ,/O reached/O neither/O our/O health/O care/O system/O nor/O the/O way/O we/O develop/O new/O drugs/O ./O 
Drug/O based/O therapy/O and/O prevention/O is/O still/O statistical/O ,/O with/O many/O patients/O receiving/O drugs/O ,/O which/O are/O ineffec/O tive/O or/O ,/O even/O worse/O ,/O harmful/O ./O 
Unavoidable/O errors/O in/O drug/O development/O still/O cause/O the/O cost/O per/O drug/O reaching/O the/O market/O to/O remain/O in/O the/O multi/O -/O billion/MONEY euro/MONEY range/O and/O endanger/O patients/O participating/O in/O large/O ,/O non/O -/O stratified/O clinical/O trials/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O our/O `/O health/O '/O care/O system/O is/O still/O far/O too/O much/O a/O `/O disease/O '/O care/O system/O ./O 
The/O majority/O of/O our/O efforts/O are/O focused/O on/O treating/O rather/O than/O preventing/O diseases/O ;/O or/O at/O least/O diagnosing/O diseases/O -LRB-/O or/O their/O progression/O -RRB-/O early/O enough/O to/O be/O able/O to/O react/O ./O 
Changing/O this/O will/O require/O nothing/O less/O than/O a/O revolution/O ,/O based/O on/O technical/O developments/O ,/O but/O intimately/O linked/O to/O many/O other/O aspects/O of/O the/O organisation/O of/O health/O care/O and/O its/O legal/O and/O regulatory/O basis/O -LRB-/O see/O also/O www.healthcarecompacteurope.eu/O -RRB-/O ./O 
4/NUMBER Game/O Changer/O We/O propose/O a/O vision/O of/O a/O truly/O individualised/O health/O care/O and/O disease/O prevention/O system/O in/O Europe/LOCATION ,/O based/O on/O a/O detailed/O characterisation/O -LRB-/O e.g./O clinical/O ,/O molecular/O ,/O imaging/O and/O sensor/O based/O -RRB-/O of/O the/O patient/individual/O and/O their/O wellness/O ,/O health/O and/O disease/O course/O ./O 
A/O vision/O that/O is/O related/O to/O a/O paradigm/O change/O in/O healthcare/O by/O exploiting/O the/O most/O advanced/O sensing/O ,/O computing/O and/O communication/O technologies/O to/O enable/O personalis/O ed/O and/O preventive/O medicine/O in/O the/O frame/O work/O of/O the/O Internet/O -/O of/O -/O Humans/O -LRB-/O IOH/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Future/DATE Health/O objectives/O :/O To/O develop/O the/O technology/O ,/O the/O required/O infrastructure/O ,/O and/O the/O legal/O ,/O regulatory/O and/O educational/O environment/O for/O a/O fully/O sustainable/O health/O care/O system/O that/O will/O offer/O truly/O personalised/O medicine/O ,/O prevention/O and/O wellness/O for/O European/O citizens/O ,/O providing/O a/O completely/O new/O Quality/O -/O of/O -/O Life/O ./O 
To/O develop/O novel/O --/O omics/O ,/O imaging/O and/O multi/O -/O level/O advanced/O smart/O sensor/O technologies/O and/O big/O data/deep/O data/O analytics/O for/O problem/O solving/O in/O IoH/O ./O 
To/O revolutionize/O personalized/O and/O preventive/O medicine/O by/O unique/O technology/O -/O model/O -/O simulation/O interactions/O ./O 
To/O address/O the/O full/O value/O chain/O of/O the/O virtual/O human/O at/O all/O multidisciplinary/O levels/O required/O ,/O from/O --/O omics/O ,/O imaging/O and/O sensor/O data/O to/O complex/O simulation/O models/O ./O 
5/NUMBER M/O edicine/O and/O prevention/O have/O historically/O been/O statistical/O ,/O treating/O individuals/O as/O members/O of/O -LRB-/O usually/O quite/O heterogeneous/O -RRB-/O groups/O ./O 
To/O switch/O f/O ocus/O from/O the/O statistically/O best/O therapy/O for/O billions/O to/O the/O individual/O ,/O will/O ultimately/O require/O much/O more/O information/O on/O EVERY/O patient/O ,/O than/O we/O had/O on/O the/O whole/O of/O human/O biology/O just/O a/O short/O time/O ago/O ./O 
We/O go/O from/O bytes/O to/O terabytes/O ,/O from/O handwritten/O notes/O to/O a/O deep/O -/O omics/O characterisation/O ,/O from/O a/O cursory/O check/O at/O irregular/O doctor/O visits/O to/O continuous/O monitoring/O of/O all/O relevant/O parameters/O throughout/O life/O ./O 
Our/O vision/O is/O a/O game/O changer/O ,/O of/O a/O future/DATE in/O which/O no/O patient/O will/O ever/O again/O receive/O harmful/O therapies/O ,/O flagged/O by/O observing/O n/O egative/O effects/O first/ORDINAL on/O the/O in/O silico/O model/O of/O the/O individual/O patient/O ./O 
This/O will/O :/O Directly/O address/O the/O enormous/O -LRB-/O and/O almost/O certainly/O irreducible/O -RRB-/O complexity/O of/O the/O biological/O differences/O between/O every/O patient/O and/O every/O disease/O by/O deep/O clinical/O ,/O molecular/O and/O imaging/O analyses/O ./O 
Provide/O a/O new/O generation/O of/O frictionless/O autonomous/O smart/O sensors/O at/O all/O levels/O required/O by/O health/O care/O data/O collection/O :/O implantable/O ,/O wearable/O ,/O environmental/O ./O 
Develop/O new/O feedback/O -/O interfaces/O for/O life/O -/O style/O feedback/O loops/O and/O related/O diseases/O ./O 
Develop/O computer/O models/O of/O every/O patient/O and/O disease/O state/O that/O allow/O physicians/O to/O test/O th/O e/O consequences/O of/O all/O possible/O therapies/preventative/O and/O life/O style/O measures/O in/O a/O virtual/O rather/O than/O the/O real/O patient/O ,/O computational/O `/O Guardian/O Angels/O '/O potentially/O guarding/O every/O European/O from/O before/O birth/O into/O old/O age/O ./O 
Acquire/O ,/O store/O and/O redistribute/O th/O e/O ever/O -/O accumulating/O amounts/O of/O data/O per/O patient/O required/O to/O fulfil/O this/O goal/O ,/O within/O a/O strong/O governance/O framework/O which/O protects/O personal/O data/O from/O misuse/O and/O ensures/O privacy/O ./O 
6/NUMBER Scientific/O Developments/O To/O achieve/O its/O objectives/O ,/O Future/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION will/O develop/O :/O Clinical/imaging/molecular/O survey/O techniques/O -LRB-/O genome/O ,/O epigenome/O ,/O transcriptome/O ,/O proteome/O ,/O metabolome/O ,/O immune/O status/O etc./O -RRB-/O to/O provide/O a/O detailed/O characterisation/O of/O individuals/O in/O health/O and/O disease/O ./O 
New/O self/O -/O powered/O families/O of/O revolutionary/O sensors/O for/O IoH/truly/O personalised/O health/O care/O based/O on/O energy/O efficient/O approaches/O and/O heterogeneous/O integration/O solutions/O in/O bio/O -/O compatible/O form/O factors/O to/O extend/O human/O senses/O and/O to/O support/O specific/O prevention/O strategies/O ./O 
Self/O -/O learning/O mechanistic/machine/O learning/O models/O translating/O this/O information/O into/O predictions/O on/O the/DATE future/DATE development/O of/O diseases/O -LRB-/O prevention/O -RRB-/O and/O the/O likely/O response/O to/O specific/O therapies/O and/O preventive/O measures/O ./O 
Data/O security/O and/O availability/O :/O hardware/O to/O software/O solutions/O specific/O for/O IoH/personalised/O medicine/O data/O ./O 
New/O human/O -/O machine/O interfaces/O for/O IoH/personalised/O medicine/O ,/O personalised/O and/O capable/O of/O non/O -/O verbal/O interactions/O ./O 
We/O need/O to/O know/O much/O more/O about/O the/O patient/O -LRB-/O or/O the/O potential/O patient/O -RRB-/O ,/O based/O on/O advanced/O -/O omics/O -LRB-/O e.g./O genomics/O ,/O proteomics/O ,/O metabolomics/O -RRB-/O analyses/O ,/O imaging/O techniques/O ,/O and/O information/O from/O sensors/O deployed/O in/O various/O form/O factors/O ./O 
We/O will/O draw/O primarily/O on/O concepts/O developed/O under/O two/NUMBER separate/O Flag/O ship/O proposals/O -LRB-/O both/O of/O which/O had/O reached/O the/O final/O stage/O of/O the/O last/O competition/O -RRB-/O :/O IT/O Future/DATE of/O Medicine/O -LRB-/O ITFoM/O :/O www.itfom.eu/O -RRB-/O ,/O with/O a/O very/O strong/O -/O omics/O component/O ,/O and/O `/O Guardian/O Angels/O for/O a/O Smarter/O Life/O '/O -LRB-/O www.ga/O -/O project.eu/O //O -RRB-/O ,/O with/O a/O particular/O focus/O on/O the/O development/O of/O novel/O autonomous/O 7/NUMBER sensors/low/O energy/O computing/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O we/O plan/O to/O incorporate/O a/O similarly/O strong/O imaging/O component/O ,/O from/O the/O level/O of/O individual/O cells/O up/O to/O the/O entire/O organism/O ./O 
Data/O is/O however/O not/O everything/O ./O 
We/O also/O need/O concept/O s/O to/O integrate/O this/O information/O and/O to/O predict/O the/O effects/O and/O side/O effects/O of/O possible/O therapies/O -LRB-/O or/O preventive/O measures/O -RRB-/O on/O every/O individual/O ./O 
Towards/O this/O we/O will/O build/O on/O the/O concept/O of/O the/O `/O virtual/O patient/virtual/O individual/O '/O ,/O proposed/O in/O ITFoM/O ./O 
Such/O a/O `/O virtual/O twin/O '/O ,/O updated/O intermittently/O by/O medical/omics/imaging/O information/O ,/O and/O essentially/O continuously/O by/O a/O multitude/O of/O sensors/O could/O ,/O in/O theory/O ,/O accompany/O every/O European/O through/O life/O as/O a/O true/O `/O Guardian/O Angel/O '/O ./O 
These/O `/O Guardian/O Angel/O '/O models/O will/O ,/O to/O a/O large/O extent/O ,/O be/O based/O on/O modelling/O the/O biology/O of/O every/O patient/O and/O the/O diseases/O mechanistically/O ,/O providing/O by/O far/O the/O best/O chance/O to/O translate/O complex/O data/O sets/O into/O accurate/O predictions/O ,/O complemented/O by/O machine/O learning/statistical/O techniques/O ,/O wheneve/O r/O mechanistic/O models/O can/O not/O be/O established/O due/O to/O insufficient/O knowledge/O ,/O e.g./O on/O disease/O mechanisms/O ./O 
Development/O in/O these/O areas/O will/O however/O also/O help/O to/O accelerate/O and/O de/O -/O risk/O the/O development/O of/O new/O drugs/O ,/O based/O e.g./O on/O virtual/O `/O clinical/O trials/O '/O ,/O startin/O g/O shortly/O after/O -LRB-/O and/O maybe/O even/O before/O -RRB-/O the/O synthesis/O of/O new/O candidate/O compounds/O ,/O in/O a/O `/O virtualisation/O '/O of/O drug/O development/O matching/O the/O enormous/O positive/O effects/O that/O a/O similar/O virtualisation/O has/O had/O on/O e.g./O the/O car/O industry/O ./O 
Technology/O is/O only/O a/O part/O of/O the/O solution/O ./O 
We/O will/O ,/O in/O addition/O ,/O have/O to/O reconsider/O many/O aspects/O of/O our/O health/O care/O system/O ,/O its/O legal/O basis/O ,/O regulations/O and/O reimbursement/O mechanisms/O ,/O to/O draw/O maximal/O benefits/O from/O the/O significant/O progress/O in/O technologies/O allowing/O us/O to/O truly/O personalis/O e/O medicine/O and/O prevention/O ./O 
We/O propose/O a/O vision/O of/O a/O truly/O individualised/O health/O care/O and/O disease/O prevention/O system/O in/O Europe/LOCATION ,/O based/O on/O a/O detailed/O characterisation/O -LRB-/O e.g./O clinical/O ,/O molecular/O ,/O imaging/O and/O sensor/O based/O -RRB-/O of/O the/O patient/individual/O and/O their/O well/O ness/O ,/O health/O and/O disease/O course/O ,/O exploiting/O the/O most/O advanced/O molecular/O ,/O imaging/O ,/O sensing/O ,/O computing/O and/O communication/O technologies/O ,/O through/O an/O internet/O -/O of/O -/O humans/O ,/O for/O truly/O personalised/O and/O preventive/O medicine/O ./O 
8/NUMBER Benefits/O for/O :/O EU/ORGANIZATION citizens/O ,/O through/O a/O radical/O improvement/O of/O their/O health/O care/O -LRB-/O up/O to/O 50/PERCENT %/PERCENT improvement/O in/O treating/O serious/O diseases/O ,/O halving/O the/O negative/O side/O effects/O of/O today/DATE 's/O generic/O medicine/O methods/O -RRB-/O and/O through/O a/O new/O quality/O of/O life/O ,/O in/O which/O preventive/O medicine/O could/O induce/O a/O long/O -/O term/O pa/O radigm/O change/O ./O 
European/O economy/O ,/O through/O new/O job/O and/O employment/O opportunities/O ./O 
Formation/O of/O a/O new/O vibrant/O economic/O ecosystem/O bridging/O traditional/O engineering/O ,/O computer/O sciences/O and/O health/O care/O ,/O with/O unique/O opportunities/O for/O production/O in/O Europe/LOCATION ./O 
Reduction/O s/O in/O sick/O leave/O and/O health/O related/O early/O retirement/O ;/O the/O development/O of/O a/O new/O European/O high/O -/O tech/O industry/O uniting/O health/O care/O and/O IT/O will/O also/O be/O catalysed/O ,/O providing/O a/O platform/O to/O exploit/O key/O technological/O advances/O and/O commercial/O opportunities/O that/O will/O s/O timulate/O the/O growth/O and/O development/O of/O regional/O economies/O ./O 
Although/O difficult/O to/O quantify/O completely/O ,/O we/O can/O expect/O long/O -/O term/O economic/O benefits/O many/O orders/O of/O magnitude/O higher/O than/O the/O anticipated/O costs/O of/O the/O proposed/O concept/O ./O 
-LRB-/O Even/O a/O 1/PERCENT %/PERCENT saving/O of/O healthc/O are/O costs/O in/O Europa/LOCATION alone/O would/O ,/O over/O a/O ten/DURATION year/DURATION period/O ,/O generate/O savings/O of/O 140/NUMBER billion/NUMBER -RRB-/O European/O industry/O ,/O particularly/O related/O to/O the/O goals/O of/O having/O ,/O within/O Europe/LOCATION ,/O the/O highly/O added/O value/O production/O facilities/O on/O smart/O sensors/O and/O smart/O systems/O ,/O vital/O for/O the/O medical/O and/O automotive/O industries/O -LRB-/O as/O per/O the/O concepts/O of/O Smart/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION ,/O Smart/ORGANIZATION Production/ORGANIZATION ,/O Smart/ORGANIZATION Society/ORGANIZATION proposed/O by/O ECSEL/O -/O http://www.ecsel/O -/O ju.eu/web/index.php/O but/O taken/O in/O our/O flagship/O in/O a/O much/O longer/O term/O perspective/O and/O in/O an/O approach/O that/O is/O beyond/O the/O one/NUMBER of/O a/O bottom/O -/O up/O technology/O enabler/O -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O this/O field/O we/O expect/O a/O strong/O emergence/O of/O startups/O and/O creation/O of/O a/O new/O ecosystem/O of/O industries/O with/O high/O innova/O tion/O content/O ,/O aiming/O at/O supporting/O new/O services/O for/O a/O Quality/O -/O of/O -/O Life/O in/O Europe/LOCATION ./O 
Public/O finances/O ,/O by/O curbing/O the/O uncontrolled/O increase/O in/O health/O care/O spending/O -LRB-/O potential/O savings/O of/O hundreds/O of/O billions/O of/O euros/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Under/O our/O current/DATE model/O of/O personnel/O inten/O sive/O ,/O statistics/O driven/O health/O care/O ,/O costs/O will/O inherently/O continue/O to/O rise/O in/O tandem/O with/O our/O ageing/O societies/O ,/O leading/O sooner/O or/O later/O to/O some/O form/O of/O health/O care/O rationing/O ./O 
In/O contrast/O ,/O data/O and/O computational/O model/O driven/O health/O care/O will/O continue/O to/O be/O come/O more/O cost/O effective/O ,/O driven/O by/O significant/O progress/O 9/NUMBER in/O computational/O and/O analytical/O techniques/O ,/O and/O an/O exponentially/O increasing/O information/O base/O flowing/O back/O into/O an/O evolving/O ,/O self/O -/O learning/O system/O ./O 
``/O One/NUMBER in/O three/NUMBER people/O in/O the/O Western/LOCATION world/O develop/O cancer/O and/O one/NUMBER in/O five/NUMBER die/O of/O the/O disease/O ''/O -LRB-/O The/O Wellcome/ORGANIZATION Trust/ORGANIZATION ,/O UK/O -RRB-/O ``/O Cancer/O deaths/O worldwide/O are/O projected/O to/O continue/O rising/O ,/O with/O an/O estimated/O 12/NUMBER million/NUMBER deaths/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2030/DATE ''/O -LRB-/O National/ORGANIZATION Cancer/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION ,/O USA/O -RRB-/O 10/NUMBER Next/O Steps/O We/O have/O devised/O a/O 10/DURATION year/DURATION plan/O that/O has/O ambitious/O but/O practical/O goals/O ,/O which/O will/O be/O addressed/O in/O a/O series/O of/O `/O working/O prototypes/O '/O until/O final/O rollout/O of/O a/O system/O ready/O to/O be/O implemented/O for/O multiple/O disease/O areas/O on/O large/O scale/O in/O European/O health/O care/O ./O 
The/O effort/O is/O well/O balanced/O between/O :/O -LRB-/O i/O -RRB-/O deep/O -/O omics/O and/O imaging/O technologies/O ,/O data/O analysis/O -LRB-/O ii/O -RRB-/O smart/O sensing/O technologies/O ,/O energy/O efficient/O computing/O ,/O big/O data/O analytics/O for/O IoH/O ,/O -LRB-/O iii/O -RRB-/O data/O integration/O ,/O virtual/O patient/O models/O and/O -LRB-/O iv/O -RRB-/O personalised/O medicine/O validations/O and/O field/O tr/O ials/O ./O 
There/O are/O four/NUMBER major/O phases/O for/O development/O :/O Phase/O I/O :/O Initiation/O ./O 
Initial/O infrastructure/O development/O ,/O development/O of/O improved/O pipelines/O for/O omics/O and/O imaging/O data/O integration/O in/O virtual/O patient/O models/O ,/O implantable/O or/O wearable/O sensor/O solutions/O ,/O pilot/O projects/O in/O oncology/O and/O life/O -/O style/O related/O diseases/O -LRB-/O e.g./O Type/O II/O Diabetes/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Phase/O II/O :/O Expansion/O and/O Consolidation/O ./O 
Development/O of/O virtual/O patient/virtual/O individual/O models/O for/O the/O vast/O majority/O of/O multi/O -/O factorial/O ,/O non/O -/O infectious/O diseases/O ,/O integrating/O -/O omics/O ,/O imaging/O and/O sensor/O data/O ./O 
Phase/O III/O :/O Maturation/O and/O Innovation/O penetration/O ./O 
Scale/O out/O and/O clinical/O engagement/O across/O Europe/LOCATION by/O full/O adoption/O of/O the/O new/O methods/O and/O innovation/O by/O technology/O -/O health/O care/O interactions/O ,/O -/O omics/O and/O all/O -/O scale/O imaging/O and/O s/O ensing/O technologies/O ,/O model/O validation/O and/O model/O improvements/O through/O feedback/O of/O treatment/O results/O ./O 
Phase/O IV/O :/O Full/O Implementation/O of/O paradigm/O shifts/O ./O 
Establishment/O and/O deployment/O in/O practicing/O health/O care/O systems/O ,/O effect/O and/O impact/O of/O personalised/O and/O prev/O entive/O medicine/O quantifiable/O ./O 
11/NUMBER Collaborators/O and/O Support/O The/O idea/O and/O the/O related/O goals/O of/O this/O proposal/O find/O support/O in/O previous/O FET/O Flagship/O initiatives/O :/O `/O ITFoM/O :/O IT/O Future/DATE of/O Medicine/O '/O ,/O led/O by/O Prof./O Hans/PERSON Lehrach/PERSON -LRB-/O Max/ORGANIZATION Planck/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Molecular/ORGANIZATION Genetics/ORGANIZATION ,/O Berlin/LOCATION -RRB-/O ,/O and/O `/O Guardian/O Angels/O for/O Smarter/O Life/O '/O ,/O led/O by/O Prof./O Adrian/PERSON Ionescu/PERSON -LRB-/O Ecole/ORGANIZATION Polytechnique/ORGANIZATION F?d?rale/ORGANIZATION de/ORGANIZATION Lausanne/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O technological/O roadmaps/O and/O the/O networks/O of/O partners/O generated/O by/O these/O two/NUMBER pilot/O flagship/O projects/O create/O a/O unique/O opport/O unity/O for/O implementing/O a/O joint/O concept/O proposed/O here/O ./O 
In/O this/O way/O partners/O from/O medicine/O ,/O science/O and/O engineering/O ,/O industry/O ,/O finance/O ,/O health/O care/O funders/O ,/O patient/O organisations/O ,/O regulators/O ,/O administrators/O and/O the/O general/O public/O will/O join/O to/O develop/O a/O stepw/O ise/O ,/O global/O ,/O coherent/O and/O integrated/O path/O towards/O truly/O personalised/O medicine/O and/O prevention/O in/O Europe/LOCATION -LRB-/O and/O beyond/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Key/O supporters/O :/O CEA/ORGANIZATION ,/O France/LOCATION :/O Nora/PERSON Benhabiles/PERSON ,/O Professor/O ./O 
Director/O ,/O External/O Collaborations/O and/O Industrial/O Partnerships/O at/O CEA/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Consorzio/O I/O nteruniversitario/O Risonanze/O Magnetiche/O di/O Metallo/O Proteine/O -LRB-/O CIRMMP/O -RRB-/O ,/O Italy/LOCATION :/O Claudio/PERSON Luchinat/PERSON ,/O Professor/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Chemistry/ORGANIZATION ./O 
ETH/O Z?rich/O ,/O Switzerland/LOCATION :/O Christofer/PERSON Hierold/PERSON ,/O Professor/O ,/O Chair/O in/O Micro/LOCATION and/O Nanosystems/ORGANIZATION ,/O Lothar/PERSON Thiele/PERSON ,/O Professor/O ,/O Chair/O Computer/O Engineeri/O ng/O and/O Networks/O ./O 
Medical/O University/O Graz/LOCATION ,/O Austria/LOCATION :/O Kurt/PERSON Zatloukal/PERSON ,/O Professor/O of/O Pathology/O ./O 
University/ORGANIZATION College/ORGANIZATION London/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION UK/ORGANIZATION :/O Stefan/PERSON Beck/PERSON ,/O Professor/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Medical/ORGANIZATION Genomics/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Kings/O College/O London/LOCATION ,/O UK/O :/O Tony/PERSON Ng/PERSON ,/O Richard/PERSON Dimbleby/PERSON Professor/O of/O Cancer/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION ,/O King/ORGANIZATION 's/ORGANIZATION College/ORGANIZATION London/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Professor/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Molecular/ORGANIZATION Oncology/ORGANIZATION at/O UCL/O -/O Cancer/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION College/ORGANIZATION London/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Infineon/ORGANIZATION Technologies/ORGANIZATION AG/ORGANIZATION Munich/LOCATION ,/O Germany/LOCATION :/O Knut/PERSON Hufeld/PERSON ,/O Director/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Development/ORGANIZATION Funding/ORGANIZATION ,/O Infineon/ORGANIZATION Technologies/ORGANIZATION AG/ORGANIZATION ;/O Reinhard/PERSON Pufall/PERSON ,/O Dr./O Centre/O of/O Systems/O Biology/O -LRB-/O SYSBIO/O -RRB-/O ,/O Italy/LOCATION :/O Lilia/PERSON Alberghina/PERSON ,/O Professor/O ,/O Director/O ./O 
12/NUMBER CEA/ORGANIZATION -/O LETI/O ,/O Grenoble/LOCATION ,/O France/LOCATION :/O Marie/PERSON -/O Noelle/PERSON Semeria/PERSON ,/O Director/O ;/O Thomas/PERSON Ernst/PERSON ,/O Chief/O Scientist/O ./O 
Fraunhofer/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION Institution/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Microsystems/ORGANIZATION and/O Solid/ORGANIZATION State/ORGANIZATION Technologies/ORGANIZATION ,/O Germany/LOCATION :/O Pet/O er/O Ramm/PERSON ,/O Head/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION Heterogeneous/ORGANIZATION System/ORGANIZATION Integration/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Charit?/O ,/O University/ORGANIZATION Medicine/ORGANIZATION Berlin/ORGANIZATION ,/O Germany/LOCATION :/O Antonia/PERSON Joussen/PERSON ,/O Professor/O of/O Ophthalmology/O ./O 
Chair/O ,/O Department/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Ophthalmology/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Maastricht/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION ,/O Netherlands/LOCATION :/O Angela/ORGANIZATION Brand/ORGANIZATION ,/O Founding/O Director/O ,/O Professor/O ,/O Institute/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Public/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION Genomics/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O IPHG/O -RRB-/O ./O 
IMEC/ORGANIZATION ,/O Leuven/LOCATION ,/O Belgium/LOCATION and/O IMEC/ORGANIZATION -/O NL/ORGANIZATION ,/O Eindhoven/LOCATION ,/O the/O Netherlands/O :/O Chris/PERSON Van/PERSON Hoof/PERSON ,/O Program/ORGANIZATION Director/ORGANIZATION Wearable/ORGANIZATION Healthcare/ORGANIZATION ,/O Professor/O KULeuven/O ,/O Leuven/LOCATION ,/O Belgium/LOCATION ./O 
Universit?/O di/O Bologna/LOCATION ,/O Italy/LOCATION :/O Enrico/O Sangior/O gi/O ,/O Vice/O Rector/O ,/O Professor/O ,/O Giorgio/PERSON Baccaranni/PERSON ,/O Professor/O ,/O Luca/PERSON Selmi/PERSON ,/O Professor/O ./O 
Sinano/O Institute/O and/O IMEP/ORGANIZATION -/O Grenoble/ORGANIZATION INP/ORGANIZATION -/O IMEP/O -/O Grenoble/LOCATION ,/O France/LOCATION :/O Francis/PERSON Balestra/PERSON ,/O Director/O of/O research/O NRS/ORGANIZATION ./O 
SINTEF/O ,/O Norway/LOCATION :/O Maaike/PERSON M/PERSON Visser/PERSON Taklo/PERSON ,/O Chief/O Scientist/O ./O 
IBM/O Zurich/LOCATION ,/O Switzerland/LOCATION :/O Heike/PERSON Riel/PERSON ,/O Director/ORGANIZATION Physical/ORGANIZATION Sciences/ORGANIZATION IBM/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Intel/ORGANIZATION Corporation/ORGANIZATION ,/O Ireland/LOCATION :/O Charlie/PERSON Sheridan/PERSON ,/O Director/O ,/O Internet/O of/O Things/O -LRB-/O IoT/O -RRB-/O research/O Lab/O at/O Intel/ORGANIZATION Corporation/ORGANIZATION Science/ORGANIZATION for/ORGANIZATION Life/ORGANIZATION Laboratory/ORGANIZATION ,/O Stockholm/LOCATION ,/O Uppsala/LOCATION ,/O Sweden/LOCATION ,/O Olli/PERSON Kallioniemi/PERSON ,/O Director/O INSERM/ORGANIZATION ,/O France/LOCATION :/O Georges/PERSON Dagher/PERSON ,/O Infrastructure/O Biobanques/O ,/O Director/O Institut/PERSON ROCHE/PERSON ,/O France/LOCATION :/O Patrice/PERSON Denefle/PERSON ,/O Head/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION UCL/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Neurology/ORGANIZATION ,/O UK/O :/O Xavier/PERSON Golay/PERSON ,/O Professor/O ,/O MR/ORGANIZATION Neurophysics/ORGANIZATION and/O Translational/ORGANIZATION NeuroscienceHead/ORGANIZATION ,/O Department/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Brain/ORGANIZATION Repair/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Rehabilitation/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION College/ORGANIZATION Dublin/ORGANIZATION ,/O Ireland/LOCATION :/O Walter/PERSON Koch/PERSON ,/O Professor/O ,/O Director/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Systems/ORGANIZATION Biology/ORGANIZATION Ireland/ORGANIZATION Centro/ORGANIZATION Nacional/ORGANIZATION de/ORGANIZATION Analisis/ORGANIZATION Genomico/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O CNAG/O -/O CRG/O -RRB-/O ,/O Spain/LOCATION :/O Ivo/PERSON Gut/PERSON ,/O Professor/O ,/O Director/O CEA/ORGANIZATION -/O CNG/O -LRB-/O Centre/ORGANIZATION National/ORGANIZATION de/ORGANIZATION G?notypage/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O ,/O France/LOCATION :/O Jean/O -/O Fran?ois/PERSON Deleuze/PERSON ,/O Director/ORGANIZATION Acabidem/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION ,/O Turkey/LOCATION :/O Ugur/PERSON Sezermen/PERSON ,/O Professor/ORGANIZATION Uppsala/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION ,/O Sweden/LOCATION :/O Ulf/PERSON Landegren/PERSON ,/O Professor/O 13/NUMBER Tyndall/ORGANIZATION National/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION ,/O Ireland/LOCATION :/O Dr./O Alan/PERSON Mathewson/PERSON ,/O Deputy/O Head/O -/O Circuits/O and/O Systems/O &/O Dr./O Kieran/PERSON Drain/PERSON ,/O CEO/O of/O Tyndall/ORGANIZATION National/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION ./O 
KTH/O ,/O Royal/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION ,/O Sweden/LOCATION :/O Prof./O Mikael/PERSON ?stling/PERSON European/PERSON Alliance/PERSON for/O Personalised/O Medicine/O ,/O Brussels/LOCATION :/O Denis/PERSON Horgan/PERSON ,/O Executive/O Director/O Countries/O Institution/O Type/O 14/NUMBER Contact/O :/O Prof./O Hans/PERSON Lehrach/PERSON Max/PERSON Planck/PERSON I/O nstitute/O for/O Molecular/ORGANIZATION Genetics/ORGANIZATION ,/O Berlin/LOCATION ,/O Germany/LOCATION lehrach@molgen.mpg.de/O Prof/O ./O 
Adrian/PERSON Ionescu/PERSON ?cole/PERSON polytechnique/O f?d?rale/O de/O Lausanne/ORGANIZATION EPFL/ORGANIZATION adrian.ionescu@epfl.ch/ORGANIZATION 15/ORGANIZATION Future/ORGANIZATION Health/ORGANIZATION 
