Technological/ORGANIZATION Forecasting/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Change/ORGANIZATION 114/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2017/DATE -RRB-/O 254/NUMBER --/O 280/NUMBER Contents/O lists/O available/O atScienceDirect/O Technological/ORGANIZATION Forecasting/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Change/ORGANIZATION The/DATE future/DATE of/O employment/O :/O How/O susceptible/O are/O jobs/O to/O computerisation/O ?/O 
Carl/PERSON Benedikt/PERSON Frey/PERSON a/O ,/O */O ,/O Michael/PERSON A./PERSON Osborne/PERSON b/O aOxford/O Martin/ORGANIZATION School/ORGANIZATION ,/O University/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Oxford/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION Oxford/ORGANIZATION OX1/ORGANIZATION 1/ORGANIZATION PT/ORGANIZATION ,/O United/ORGANIZATION KingdombDepartment/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Engineering/ORGANIZATION Science/ORGANIZATION ,/O University/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Oxford/ORGANIZATION ,/O Oxford/ORGANIZATION OX1/ORGANIZATION 3PJ/ORGANIZATION ,/O United/LOCATION Kingdom/LOCATION ARTICLE/O INFO/O Article/O history/O :/O Received/O 24/DATE September/DATE 2015/DATE Accepted/DATE 19/DATE August/DATE 2016/DATE Available/O online/O 29/DATE September/DATE 2016/DATE JEL/O classi?cation/O :/O E24/O J24/O J31/O J62/O O33/O Keywords/O :/O Occupational/O choice/O Technological/O change/O Wage/O inequality/O Employment/O Skill/O demand/O ABSTRACT/O We/O examine/O how/O susceptible/O jobs/O are/O to/O computerisation/O ./O 
To/O assess/O this/O ,/O we/O begin/O by/O implementing/O a/O novel/O methodology/O to/O estimate/O the/O probability/O of/O computerisation/O for/O 702/NUMBER detailed/O occupations/O ,/O using/O a/O Gaussian/O process/O classi?er/O ./O 
Based/O on/O these/O estimates/O ,/O we/O examine/O expected/O impacts/O of/O future/DATE computerisation/O on/O US/LOCATION labour/O market/O outcomes/O ,/O with/O the/O primary/O objective/O of/O analysing/O the/O number/O of/O jobs/O at/O risk/O and/O the/O relationship/O between/O an/O occupations/O probability/O of/O computerisation/O ,/O wages/O and/O educational/O attainment/O ./O 
?/O 2016/DATE Published/O by/O Elsevier/ORGANIZATION Inc./ORGANIZATION ./O 
1/NUMBER ./O 
Introduction/O In/O this/O paper/O ,/O we/O address/O the/O question/O :/O how/O susceptible/O are/O jobs/O to/O computerisation/O ?/O 
Doing/O so/O ,/O we/O build/O on/O the/O existing/O literature/O in/O two/NUMBER ways/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O drawing/O upon/O recent/O advances/O in/O Machine/O Learning/O -LRB-/O ML/O -RRB-/O and/O Mobile/ORGANIZATION Robotics/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O MR/O -RRB-/O ,/O we/O develop/O a/O novel/O methodol/O -/O ogy/O to/O categorise/O occupations/O according/O to/O their/O susceptibility/O to/O computerisation/O ./O 
1Second/O ,/O we/O implement/O this/O methodology/O to/O esti/O -/O mate/O the/O probability/O of/O computerisation/O for/O 702/NUMBER detailed/O occupa/O -/O tions/O ,/O and/O examine/O expected/O impacts/O of/O future/DATE computerisation/O on/O US/LOCATION labour/O market/O outcomes/O ./O 
We/O thank/O the/O Oxford/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION Engineering/ORGANIZATION Sciences/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION and/O the/O Oxford/ORGANIZATION Martin/ORGANIZATION Programme/ORGANIZATION on/O the/O Impacts/O of/O Future/DATE Technology/O for/O hosting/O the/O ``/O Machines/O and/O Employment/O ''/O Workshop/O ./O 
We/O are/O indebted/O to/O Stuart/PERSON Armstrong/PERSON ,/O Nick/PERSON Bostrom/PERSON ,/O Eris/PERSON Chinellato/PERSON ,/O Mark/PERSON Cummins/PERSON ,/O Daniel/PERSON Dewey/PERSON ,/O Alex/PERSON Flint/PERSON ,/O John/PERSON Muellbauer/PERSON ,/O Vincent/PERSON Mueller/PERSON ,/O Paul/PERSON Newman/PERSON ,/O Se?n/O ?/O h?igeartaigh/O ,/O Anders/PERSON Sandberg/PERSON ,/O Murray/PERSON Shanahan/PERSON ,/O and/O Keith/PERSON Woolcock/PERSON for/O their/O excellent/O suggestions/O ./O 
*/O Corresponding/O author/O ./O 
E-mail/O addresses/O :/O carl.frey@philosophy.ox.ac.uk/O -LRB-/O C./O Frey/O -RRB-/O ,/O mosb@robots.ox.ac.uk/O -LRB-/O M./PERSON Osborne/PERSON -RRB-/O ./O 
1We/O refer/O to/O computerisation/O as/O job/O automation/O by/O means/O of/O computer-controlled/O equipment/O ./O 
Our/O paper/O is/O motivated/O by/O John/PERSON Maynard/PERSON Keynes/PERSON 's/O frequently/O cited/O prediction/O of/O widespread/O technological/O unemployment/O ``/O due/O to/O our/O discovery/O of/O means/O of/O economising/O the/O use/O of/O labour/O outrun/O -/O ning/O the/O pace/O at/O which/O we/O can/O ?nd/O new/O uses/O for/O labour/O ''/O -LRB-/O Keynes/PERSON ,/O 1933/DATE ,/O p./O 3/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O over/O the/DATE past/DATE decades/DATE ,/O computers/O have/O sub/O -/O stituted/O for/O a/O number/O of/O jobs/O ,/O including/O the/O functions/O of/O book/O -/O keepers/O ,/O cashiers/O and/O telephone/O operators/O -LRB-/O Bresnahan/PERSON ,/O 1999/DATE ;/O MGI/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
More/O recently/DATE ,/O the/O poor/O performance/O of/O labour/O markets/O across/O advanced/O economies/O has/O intensi?ed/O the/O debate/O about/O technological/O unemployment/O among/O economists/O ./O 
While/O there/O is/O ongoing/O disagree/O -/O ment/O about/O the/O driving/O forces/O behind/O the/O persistently/O high/O unem/O -/O ployment/O rates/O ,/O a/O number/O of/O scholars/O have/O pointed/O at/O computer/O -/O controlled/O equipment/O as/O a/O possible/O explanation/O for/O recent/O jobless/O growth/O -LRB-/O see/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
2/NUMBER The/O impact/O of/O computerisation/O on/O labour/O market/O outcomes/O is/O well-established/O in/O the/O literature/O ,/O documenting/O the/O decline/O of/O employment/O in/O routine/O intensive/O occupations/O --/O i.e.occupations/O 2This/O view/O ?nds/O support/O in/O a/O recent/O survey/O by/O the/O McKinsey/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O MGI/O -RRB-/O ,/O showing/O that/O 44/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O ?rms/O which/O reduced/O their/O headcount/O since/O the/O ?nancial/O crisis/O of/U_TEMPPRED 2008/DATE had/O done/O so/O by/O means/O of/O automation/O -LRB-/O MGI/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.techfore.2016.08.019/O 0040-1625/DURATION //O ?/O 2016/DATE Published/O by/O Elsevier/ORGANIZATION Inc./ORGANIZATION ./O 
C./PERSON Frey/PERSON ,/O M./ORGANIZATION Osborne/ORGANIZATION //ORGANIZATION Technological/ORGANIZATION Forecasting/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Change/ORGANIZATION 114/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2017/DATE -RRB-/O 254/NUMBER --/O 280255/NUMBER mainly/O consisting/O of/O tasks/O following/O well-de?ned/O procedures/O that/O can/O easily/O be/O performed/O by/O sophisticated/O algorithms/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O studies/O byCharles/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O and/O Jaimovich/O and/O Siu/O -LRB-/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O empha/O -/O sise/O that/O the/O ongoing/O decline/O in/O manufacturing/O employment/O and/O the/O disappearance/O of/O other/O routine/O jobs/O is/O causing/O the/O current/DATE low/O rates/O of/O employment/O ./O 
3In/O addition/O to/O the/O computerisation/O of/O routine/O manufacturing/O tasks/O ,/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O document/O a/O structural/O shift/O in/O the/O labour/O market/O ,/O with/O workers/O reallocating/O their/O labour/O supply/O from/O middle-income/O manufacturing/O to/O low-income/O service/O occupations/O ./O 
Arguably/O ,/O this/O is/O because/O the/O manual/O tasks/O of/O service/O occupations/O are/O less/O susceptible/O to/O computerisation/O ,/O as/O they/O require/O a/O higher/O degree/O of/O ?exibility/O and/O physical/O adaptability/O -LRB-/O Autor/O et/O al./O ,/O 2003/DATE ;/O Goos/O and/O Manning/PERSON ,/O 2007/DATE ;/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O with/O falling/O prices/O of/O computing/O ,/O problem/O -/O solving/O skills/O are/O becoming/O relatively/O productive/O ,/O explaining/O the/O sub/O -/O stantial/O employment/O growth/O in/O occupations/O involving/O cognitive/O tasks/O where/O skilled/O labour/O has/O a/O comparative/O advantage/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O the/O persistent/O increase/O in/O returns/O to/O education/O -LRB-/O Katz/PERSON and/O Murphy/PERSON ,/O 1992/DATE ;/O Acemoglu/PERSON ,/O 2002/DATE ;/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O title/O ``/O Lousy/O and/O Lovely/O Jobs/O ''/O ,/O of/O recent/O work/O by/O Goos/O and/O Manning/PERSON -LRB-/O 2007/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O thus/O captures/O the/O essence/O of/O the/O current/DATE trend/O towards/O labour/O market/O polarisa/O -/O tion/O ,/O with/O growing/O employment/O in/O high-income/O cognitive/O jobs/O and/O low-income/O manual/O occupations/O ,/O accompanied/O by/O a/O hollowing-out/O of/O middle-income/O routine/O jobs/O ./O 
According/O to/O Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O the/O pace/O of/O tech/O -/O nological/O innovation/O is/O still/O increasing/O ,/O with/O more/O sophisticated/O software/O technologies/O disrupting/O labour/O markets/O by/O making/O work/O -/O ers/O redundant/O ./O 
What/O is/O striking/O about/O the/O examples/O in/O their/O book/O is/O that/O computerisation/O is/O no/O longer/O con?ned/O to/O routine/O manufac/O -/O turing/O tasks/O ./O 
The/O autonomous/O driverless/O cars/O ,/O developed/O by/O Google/ORGANIZATION ,/O provide/O one/NUMBER example/O of/O how/O manual/O tasks/O in/O transport/O and/O logistics/O may/O soon/O be/O automated/O ./O 
In/O the/O section/O ``/O In/O Domain/O After/O Domain/O ,/O Computers/O Race/O Ahead/O ''/O ,/O they/O emphasise/O how/O fast/O moving/O these/O developments/O have/O been/O ./O 
Less/DATE than/DATE ten/DATE years/DATE ago/DATE ,/O in/O the/O chapter/O ``/O Why/O People/O Still/O Matter/O ''/O ,/O Levy/O and/O Murnane/PERSON -LRB-/O 2004/DATE -RRB-/O pointed/O at/O the/O di?culties/O of/O replicating/O human/O perception/O ,/O asserting/O that/O driving/O in/O tra?c/O is/O insusceptible/O to/O automation/O :/O ``/O But/O executing/O a/O left/O turn/O against/O oncoming/O tra?c/O involves/O so/O many/O factors/O that/O it/O is/O hard/O to/O imagine/O discovering/O the/O set/O of/O rules/O that/O can/O replicate/O a/O driver/O 's/O behaviour/O -LSB-/O .../O -RSB-/O ''/O ./O 
Six/DATE years/DATE later/DATE ,/O in/O October/DATE 2010/DATE ,/O Google/ORGANIZATION announced/O that/O it/O had/O modi?ed/O several/O Toyota/ORGANIZATION Priuses/O to/O be/O fully/O autonomous/O -LRB-/O Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
To/O our/O knowledge/O ,/O no/O study/O has/O yet/O quanti?ed/O what/O recent/O technological/O progress/O is/O likely/O to/O mean/O for/O the/DATE future/DATE of/O employ/O -/O ment/O ./O 
The/O present/DATE study/O intends/O to/O bridge/O this/O gap/O in/O the/O literature/O ./O 
Although/O there/O are/O indeed/O existing/O useful/O frameworks/O for/O examining/O the/O impact/O of/O computers/O on/O the/O occupational/O employment/O composi/O -/O tion/O ,/O they/O seem/O inadequate/O in/O explaining/O the/O impact/O of/O technological/O trends/O going/O beyond/O the/O computerisation/O of/O routine/O tasks/O ./O 
Semi/O -/O nal/ORGANIZATION work/O by/O Autor/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O distinguishes/O between/O cognitive/O and/O manual/O tasks/O on/O the/O one/NUMBER hand/O ,/O and/O routine/O and/O non/O -/O routine/O tasks/O on/O the/O other/O ./O 
While/O the/O computer/O substitution/O for/O both/O cognitive/O and/O manual/O routine/O tasks/O is/O evident/O ,/O non-routine/O tasks/O involve/O everything/O from/O legal/O writing/O ,/O truck/O driving/O and/O medical/O diagnoses/O ,/O to/O persuading/O and/O selling/O ./O 
In/O the/O present/DATE study/O ,/O we/O will/O argue/O that/O legal/O writing/O and/O truck/O driving/O will/O soon/O be/O automated/O ,/O while/O persuading/O ,/O for/O instance/O ,/O will/O not/O ./O 
Drawing/O upon/O recent/O devel/O -/O opments/O in/O Engineering/O Sciences/O ,/O and/O in/O particular/O advances/O in/O the/O ?elds/O of/O ML/O ,/O including/O Data/O Mining/O ,/O Machine/ORGANIZATION Vision/ORGANIZATION ,/O Computational/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION and/O other/O sub-?elds/O of/O Arti?cial/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION ,/O as/O well/O as/O MR/ORGANIZATION ,/O we/O derive/O additional/O dimensions/O required/O to/O understand/O the/O 3Because/O the/O core/O job/O tasks/O of/O manufacturing/O occupations/O follow/O well-de?ned/O repetitive/O procedures/O ,/O they/O can/O easily/O be/O codi?ed/O in/O computer/O software/O and/O thus/O performed/O by/O computers/O -LRB-/O Acemoglu/PERSON and/O Autor/O ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
susceptibility/O of/O jobs/O to/O computerisation/O ./O 
Needless/O to/O say/O ,/O a/O number/O of/O factors/O are/O driving/O decisions/O to/O automate/O and/O we/O can/O not/O capture/O these/O in/O full/O ./O 
Rather/O we/O aim/O ,/O from/O a/O technological/O capabilities/O point/O of/O view/O ,/O to/O determine/O which/O problems/O engineers/O need/O to/O solve/O for/O spe/O -/O ci?c/O occupations/O to/O be/O automated/O ./O 
By/O highlighting/O these/O problems/O ,/O their/O di?culty/O and/O to/O which/O occupations/O they/O relate/O ,/O we/O categorise/O jobs/O according/O to/O their/O susceptibility/O to/O computerisation/O ./O 
The/O char/O -/O acteristics/O of/O these/O problems/O were/O matched/O to/O different/O occupational/O characteristics/O ,/O using/O O/O */O NET/O data/O ,/O allowing/O us/O to/O examine/O the/DATE future/DATE direction/O of/O technological/O change/O in/O terms/O of/O its/O impact/O on/O the/O occu/O -/O pational/O composition/O of/O the/O labour/O market/O ,/O but/O also/O the/O number/O of/O jobs/O at/O risk/O should/O these/O technologies/O materialise/O ./O 
The/O present/DATE study/O relates/O to/O two/NUMBER literatures/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O our/O analysis/O builds/O on/O the/O labour/O economics/O literature/O on/O the/O task/O content/O of/O employment/O -LRB-/O Autor/O et/O al./O ,/O 2003/DATE ;/O Goos/O and/O Manning/PERSON ,/O 2007/DATE ;/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE ;/O Ingram/PERSON and/O Neumann/PERSON ,/O 2006/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Based/O on/O de?ned/O premises/O about/O what/O computers/O do/O ,/O this/O literature/O examines/O the/O his/O -/O torical/O impact/O of/O computerisation/O on/O the/O occupational/O composition/O of/O the/O labour/O market/O ./O 
However/O ,/O the/O scope/O of/O what/O computers/O do/O has/O recently/DATE expanded/O ,/O and/O will/O inevitably/O continue/O to/O do/O so/O -LRB-/O Brynjolf/PERSON -/O sson/O and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE ;/O MGI/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Drawing/O upon/O recent/O progress/O in/O ML/O ,/O we/O expand/O the/O premises/O about/O the/O tasks/O computers/O are/O and/O will/O be/O suited/O to/O accomplish/O ./O 
Doing/O so/O ,/O we/O build/O on/O the/O task/O con/O -/O tent/O literature/O in/O a/O forward-looking/O manner/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O whereas/O this/O literature/O has/O largely/O focused/O on/O task/O measures/O from/O the/O Dictio/PERSON -/O nary/O of/O Occupational/O Titles/O -LRB-/O DOT/O -RRB-/O ,/O last/O revised/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1991/DATE ,/O we/O rely/O on/O the/O 2010/DATE version/O of/O the/O DOT/ORGANIZATION successor/O O/O */O NET/O --/O an/O online/O service/O developed/O for/O the/O US/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION ./O 
4In/O particular/O ,/O Ingram/PERSON and/O Neumann/PERSON -LRB-/O 2006/DATE -RRB-/O use/O various/O DOT/O measurements/O to/O examine/O returns/O to/O different/O skills/O ./O 
Our/O analysis/O builds/O on/O their/O approach/O by/O classify/O -/O ing/O occupations/O according/O to/O their/O susceptibility/O to/O computerisation/O using/O O/O */O NET/O data/O ./O 
Second/ORDINAL ,/O our/O study/O relates/O to/O the/O literature/O examining/O the/O offshoring/O of/O information/based/O tasks/O to/O foreign/O worksites/O -LRB-/O Blinder/O ,/O 2009/DATE ;/O Blinder/O and/O Krueger/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE ;/O Jensen/PERSON and/O Kletzer/PERSON ,/O 2005/DATE ,/O 2010/DATE ;/O Oldenski/O ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O literature/O consists/O of/O different/O methodologies/O to/O rank/O and/O categorise/O occupations/O according/O to/O their/O susceptibility/O to/O offshoring/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O using/O O/O */O NET/O data/O on/O the/O nature/O of/O work/O done/O in/O differ/O -/O ent/O occupations/O ,/O Blinder/O -LRB-/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O estimates/O that/O 22/NUMBER to/O 29/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O US/O jobs/O are/O or/O will/O be/O offshorable/O in/O the/DATE next/DATE decade/DATE or/O two/NUMBER ./O 
These/O estimates/O are/O based/O on/O two/NUMBER de?ning/O characteristics/O of/O jobs/O that/O can/O not/O be/O off/O -/O shored/O :/O -LRB-/O a/O -RRB-/O the/O job/O must/O be/O performed/O at/O a/O speci?c/O work/O location/O ;/O and/O -LRB-/O b/O -RRB-/O the/O job/O requires/O face-to-face/O personal/O communication/O ./O 
Naturally/O ,/O the/O characteristics/O of/O occupations/O that/O can/O be/O offshored/O are/O differ/O -/O ent/O from/O the/O characteristics/O of/O occupations/O that/O can/O be/O automated/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O the/O work/O of/O cashiers/O ,/O which/O has/O largely/O been/O substi/O -/O tuted/O by/O self/O -/O service/O technology/O ,/O must/O be/O performed/O at/O speci?c/O work/O location/O and/O requires/O face-to-face/O contact/O ./O 
The/O extent/O of/O computeri/O -/O sation/O is/O therefore/O likely/O to/O go/O beyond/O that/O of/O offshoring/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O while/O the/O implementation/O of/O our/O methodology/O is/O similar/O to/O that/O of/O Blinder/O -LRB-/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O we/O rely/O on/O different/O occupational/O characteristics/O ./O 
The/O remainder/O of/O this/O paper/O is/O structured/O as/O follows/O ./O 
In/O Section/O 2/NUMBER ,/O we/O review/O the/O literature/O on/O the/O historical/O relationship/O between/O technological/O progress/O and/O employment/O ./O 
Section/O 3describes/O recent/O and/O expected/O future/DATE technological/O developments/O ./O 
In/O Section/O 4/NUMBER ,/O we/O describe/O our/O methodology/O ,/O and/O in/O Section/O 5/NUMBER ,/O we/O examine/O the/O expected/O impact/O of/O these/O technological/O developments/O on/O labour/O market/O outcomes/O ./O 
Finally/O ,/O in/O Section/O 6/NUMBER ,/O we/O derive/O some/O conclusions/O ./O 
2/NUMBER ./O 
A/O history/O of/O technological/O revolutions/O and/O employment/O The/O concern/O over/O technological/O unemployment/O is/O hardly/O a/O recent/O phenomenon/O ./O 
Throughout/O history/O ,/O the/O process/O of/O creative/O 4Goos/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O provides/O a/O notable/O exception/O ./O 
256C/O ./O 
Frey/O ,/O M./ORGANIZATION Osborne/ORGANIZATION //ORGANIZATION Technological/ORGANIZATION Forecasting/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Change/ORGANIZATION 114/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2017/DATE -RRB-/O 254/NUMBER --/O 280/NUMBER destruction/O ,/O following/O technological/O inventions/O ,/O has/O created/O enor/O -/O mous/O wealth/O ,/O but/O also/O undesired/O disruptions/O ./O 
As/O stressed/O by/O Schum/PERSON -/O peter/O -LRB-/O 1962/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O it/O was/O not/O the/O lack/O of/O inventive/O ideas/O that/O set/O the/O boundaries/O for/O economic/O development/O ,/O but/O rather/O powerful/O social/O and/O economic/O interests/O promoting/O the/O technological/O status/O quo/O ./O 
This/O is/O nicely/O illustrated/O by/O the/O example/O of/O William/PERSON Lee/PERSON ,/O inventing/O the/O stocking/O frame/O knitting/O machine/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1589/DATE ,/O hoping/O that/O it/O would/O relieve/O workers/O of/O hand-knitting/O ./O 
Seeking/O patent/O protection/O for/O his/O inven/O -/O tion/O ,/O he/O travelled/O to/O London/LOCATION where/O he/O had/O rented/O a/O building/O for/O his/O machine/O to/O be/O viewed/O by/O Queen/PERSON Elizabeth/PERSON I./PERSON To/O his/O disappointment/O ,/O the/O Queen/O was/O more/O concerned/O with/O the/O employment/O impact/O of/O his/O invention/O and/O refused/O to/O grant/O him/O a/O patent/O ,/O claiming/O that/O ``/O Thou/O aimest/O high/O ,/O Master/O Lee/O ./O 
Consider/O thou/O what/O the/O invention/O could/O do/O to/O my/O poor/O subjects/O ./O 
It/O would/O assuredly/O bring/O to/O them/O ruin/O by/O depriving/O them/O of/O employment/O ,/O thus/O making/O them/O beggars/O ''/O -LRB-/O cited/O in/O Acemoglu/LOCATION and/O Robinson/PERSON ,/O 2012/DATE ,/O p./O 182f/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Most/O likely/O the/O Queen/O 's/O concern/O was/O a/O manifestation/O of/O the/O hosiers/O '/O guilds/O fear/O that/O the/O inven/O -/O tion/O would/O make/O the/O skills/O of/O its/O artisan/O members/O obsolete/O ./O 
5The/O guilds/O '/O opposition/O was/O indeed/O so/O intense/O that/O William/PERSON Lee/PERSON had/O to/O leave/O Britain/LOCATION ./O 
That/O guilds/O systematically/O tried/O to/O weaken/O market/O forces/O as/O aggregators/O to/O maintain/O the/O technological/O status/O quo/O is/O persua/O -/O sively/O argued/O by/O Kellenbenz/PERSON -LRB-/O 1974/DATE ,/O p./O 243/NUMBER -RRB-/O ,/O stating/O that/O ``/O guilds/O defended/O the/O interests/O of/O their/O members/O against/O outsiders/O ,/O and/O these/O included/O the/O inventors/O who/O ,/O with/O their/O new/O equipment/O and/O tech/O -/O niques/O ,/O threatened/O to/O disturb/O their/O members/O '/O economic/O status/O ./O ''/O 
6As/O pointed/O out/O by/O Mokyr/PERSON -LRB-/O 1998/DATE ,/O p./O 11/NUMBER -RRB-/O :/O ``/O Unless/O all/O individuals/O accept/O the/O ``/O verdict/O ''/O of/O the/O market/O outcome/O ,/O the/O decision/O whether/O to/O adopt/O an/O innovation/O is/O likely/O to/O be/O resisted/O by/O losers/O through/O non-market/O mechanism/O and/O political/O activism/O ./O ''/O 
Workers/O can/O thus/O be/O expected/O to/O resist/O new/O technologies/O ,/O insofar/O that/O they/O make/O their/O skills/O obso/O -/O lete/O and/O irreversibly/O reduce/O their/O expected/O earnings/O ./O 
The/O balance/O between/O job/O conservation/O and/O technological/O progress/O therefore/O ,/O to/O a/O large/O extent/O ,/O re?ects/O the/O balance/O of/O power/O in/O society/O ,/O and/O how/O gains/O from/O technological/O progress/O are/O being/O distributed/O ./O 
The/O British/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION illustrates/O this/O point/O vividly/O ./O 
While/O still/O widely/O present/DATE on/O the/O Continent/O ,/O the/O craft/O guild/O in/O Britain/LOCATION had/O ,/O by/O the/O time/O of/O the/O Glorious/O Revolution/O of/U_TEMPPRED 1688/DATE ,/O declined/O and/O lost/O most/O of/O its/O political/O clout/O -LRB-/O Nef/PERSON ,/O 1957/DATE ,/O pp./O 26/NUMBER and/O 32/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
With/O Parliamen/PERSON -/O tary/O supremacy/O established/O over/O the/O Crown/O ,/O legislation/O was/O passed/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1769/DATE making/O the/O destruction/O of/O machinery/O punishable/O by/O death/O -LRB-/O Mokyr/PERSON ,/O 1990/DATE ,/O p./O 257/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
To/O be/O sure/O ,/O there/O was/O still/O resistance/O to/O mech/O -/O anisation/O ./O 
The/O ``/O Luddite/O ''/O riots/O between/O 1811/DATE and/O 1816/DATE were/O partly/O a/O manifestation/O of/O the/O fear/O of/O technological/O change/O among/O workers/O as/O Parliament/ORGANIZATION revoked/O a/O 1551/DATE law/O prohibiting/O the/O use/O of/O gig/O mills/O in/O the/O wool-?nishing/O trade/O ./O 
The/O British/O government/O however/O took/O an/O increasingly/O stern/O view/O on/O groups/O attempting/O to/O halt/O technologi/O -/O cal/O progress/O and/O deployed/O 12,000/NUMBER men/O against/O the/O rioters/O -LRB-/O Mantoux/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2006/DATE ,/O p./O 403/NUMBER --/O 408/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O sentiment/O of/O the/O government/O towards/O the/O destruction/O of/O machinery/O was/O explained/O by/O a/O resolution/O passed/O after/O the/O Lancashire/O riots/O of/U_TEMPPRED 1779/DATE ,/O stating/O that/O ``/O The/O sole/O cause/O of/O great/O riots/O was/O the/O new/O machines/O employed/O in/O cotton/O manufacture/O ;/O the/O coun/O -/O try/O notwithstanding/O has/O greatly/O bene?ted/O from/O their/O erection/O -LSB-/O and/O -RSB-/O destroying/O them/O in/O this/O country/O would/O only/O be/O the/O means/O of/O trans/O -/O ferring/O them/O to/O another/O -LSB-/O .../O -RSB-/O to/O the/O detriment/O of/O the/O trade/O of/O Britain/LOCATION ''/O -LRB-/O cited/O in/O Mantoux/LOCATION ,/O 2006/DATE ,/O p./O 403/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
5The/O term/O artisan/O refers/O to/O a/O craftsman/O who/O engages/O in/O the/O entire/O production/O process/O of/O a/O good/O ,/O containing/O almost/O no/O division/O of/O labour/O ./O 
By/O guild/O we/O mean/O an/O association/O of/O artisans/O that/O control/O the/O practice/O of/O their/O craft/O in/O a/O particular/O town/O ./O 
6There/O is/O an/O ongoing/O debate/O about/O the/O technological/O role/O of/O the/O guilds/O ./O 
Epstein/O -LRB-/O 1998/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O has/O argued/O that/O they/O ful?lled/O an/O important/O role/O in/O the/O intergener/O -/O ational/O transmission/O of/O knowledge/O ./O 
Yet/O there/O is/O no/O immediate/O contradiction/O between/O such/O a/O role/O and/O their/O conservative/O stand/O on/O technological/O progress/O :/O there/O are/O clear/O examples/O of/O guilds/O restraining/O the/O diffusion/O of/O inventions/O -LRB-/O see/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O Ogilvie/PERSON ,/O 2004/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
There/O are/O at/O least/O two/NUMBER possible/O explanations/O for/O the/O shift/O in/O attitudes/O towards/O technological/O progress/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O after/O Parliamentary/O supremacy/O was/O established/O over/O the/O Crown/O ,/O the/O property/O owning/O classes/O became/O politically/O dominant/O in/O Britain/LOCATION -LRB-/O North/O and/O Weingast/LOCATION ,/O 1989/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Because/O the/O diffusion/O of/O various/O manufacturing/O technologies/O did/O not/O impose/O a/O risk/O to/O the/O value/O of/O their/O assets/O ,/O and/O some/O property/O owners/O stood/O to/O bene?t/O from/O the/O export/O of/O manufactured/O goods/O ,/O the/O artisans/O simply/O did/O not/O have/O the/O political/O power/O to/O repress/O them/O ./O 
Sec/DURATION -/O ond/O ,/O inventors/O ,/O consumers/O and/O unskilled/O factory/O workers/O largely/O ben/O -/O e?ted/O from/O mechanisation/O -LRB-/O Mokyr/PERSON ,/O 1990/DATE ,/O p./O 256/NUMBER and/O 258/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
It/O has/O even/O been/O argued/O that/O ,/O despite/O the/O employment/O concerns/O over/O mechani/O -/O sation/O ,/O unskilled/O workers/O have/O been/O the/O greatest/O bene?ciaries/O of/O the/O Industrial/O Revolution/O -LRB-/O Clark/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2008/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
7While/O there/O is/O contradictory/O evi/ORGANIZATION -/O dence/O suggesting/O that/O capital/O owners/O initially/O accumulated/O a/O growing/O share/O of/O national/O income/O -LRB-/O Allen/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2009a/O -RRB-/O ,/O there/O is/O equally/O evidence/O of/O growing/O real/O wages/O -LRB-/O Feinstein/PERSON ,/O 1998/DATE ;/O Lindert/PERSON and/O Williamson/PERSON ,/O 1983/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O implies/O that/O although/O manufacturing/O technologies/O made/O the/O skills/O of/O artisans/O obsolete/O ,/O gains/O from/O technological/O progress/O were/O distributed/O in/O a/O manner/O that/O gradually/O bene?ted/O a/O growing/O share/O of/O the/O labour/O force/O ./O 
8/NUMBER An/O important/O feature/O of/O nineteenth/DATE century/DATE manufacturing/O tech/O -/O nologies/O is/O that/O they/O were/O largely/O ``/O deskilling/O ''/O --/O i.e.they/O substituted/O for/O skills/O through/O the/O simpli?cation/O of/O tasks/O -LRB-/O Braverman/PERSON ,/O 1974/DATE ;/O Hounshell/ORGANIZATION ,/O 1985/DATE ;/O James/PERSON and/O Skinner/PERSON ,/O 1985/DATE ;/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 1998/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O deskilling/O process/O occurred/O as/O the/O factory/O system/O began/O to/O dis/O -/O place/O the/O artisan/O shop/O ,/O and/O it/O picked/O up/O pace/O as/O production/O increas/O -/O ingly/O mechanized/O with/O the/O adoption/O of/O steam/O power/O -LRB-/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Sokoloff/PERSON ,/O 1982/DATE ;/O Atack/O et/O al./O ,/O 2008a/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Work/O that/O had/O previously/DATE been/O performed/O by/O artisans/O was/O now/DATE decomposed/O into/O smaller/O ,/O highly/O specialised/O ,/O sequences/O ,/O requiring/O less/O skill/O ,/O but/O more/O workers/O ,/O to/O perform/O ./O 
9Some/O innovations/O were/O even/O designed/O to/O be/O deskilling/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O Eli/PERSON Whitney/PERSON ,/O a/O pioneer/O of/O interchangeable/O parts/O ,/O described/O the/O objective/O of/O this/O technology/O as/O ``/O to/O substitute/O correct/O and/O effective/O operations/O of/O machinery/O for/O the/O skill/O of/O the/O artist/O which/O is/O acquired/O only/O by/O long/O practice/O and/O experience/O ;/O a/O species/O of/O skill/O which/O is/O not/O possessed/O in/O this/O country/O to/O any/O considerable/O extent/O ''/O -LRB-/O Habakkuk/LOCATION ,/O 1962/DATE ,/O p./O 22/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
Together/O with/O developments/O in/O continuous-?ow/O production/O ,/O enabling/O workers/O to/O be/O stationary/O while/O different/O tasks/O were/O moved/O to/O them/O ,/O it/O was/O identical/O interchangeable/O parts/O that/O allowed/O complex/O 7Various/O estimations/O of/O the/O living/O standards/O of/O workers/O in/O Britain/LOCATION during/O the/O indus/O -/O trialisation/O exist/O in/O the/O literature/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O Clark/PERSON -LRB-/O 2008/DATE -RRB-/O ?nds/O that/O real/O wages/O over/O the/O period/O 1760/DATE to/U_TEMPPRED 1860/DATE rose/O faster/O than/O GDP/O per/O capita/O ./O 
Further/O evidence/O provided/O by/O Lindert/PERSON and/O Williamson/PERSON -LRB-/O 1983/DATE -RRB-/O even/O suggests/O that/O real/O wages/O nearly/O doubled/O between/O 1820/DATE and/O 1850/DATE ./O 
Feinstein/O -LRB-/O 1998/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O on/O the/O other/O hand/O ,/O ?nds/O a/O much/O more/O moderate/O increase/O ,/O with/O average/O working-class/O living/O standards/O improving/O by/O less/O than/O 15/PERCENT %/PERCENT between/O 1770/DATE and/O 1870/DATE ./O 
Finally/O ,/O Allen/PERSON -LRB-/O 2009a/O -RRB-/O ?nds/O that/O over/O the/O ?rst/O half/O of/O the/O nine/NUMBER -/O teenth/O century/DURATION ,/O the/O real/O wage/O stagnated/O while/O output/O per/O worker/O expanded/O ./O 
After/O the/DATE mid/DATE nineteenth/DATE century/DATE ,/O however/O ,/O real/O wages/O began/O to/O grow/O in/O line/O with/O productivity/O ./O 
While/O this/O implies/O that/O capital/O owners/O were/O the/O greatest/O bene?ciaries/O of/O the/O Industrial/O Revolution/O ,/O there/O is/O at/O the/O same/O time/O consensus/O that/O average/O living/O standards/O largely/O improved/O ./O 
8The/O term/O skill/O is/O associated/O with/O higher/O levels/O of/O education/O ,/O ability/O ,/O or/O job/O training/O ./O 
Following/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON -LRB-/O 1998/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O we/O refer/O to/O technology-skill/O or/O capital-skill/O com/O -/O plementarity/O when/O a/O new/O technology/O or/O physical/O capital/O complements/O skilled/O labour/O relative/O to/O unskilled/O workers/O ./O 
9The/O production/O of/O plows/O nicely/O illustrates/O the/O differences/O between/O the/O artisan/O shop/O and/O the/O factory/O ./O 
In/O one/NUMBER artisan/O shop/O ,/O two/NUMBER men/O spent/O 118/NUMBER man-hours/O using/O hammers/O ,/O anvils/O ,/O chisels/O ,/O hatchets/O ,/O axes/O ,/O mallets/O ,/O shaves/O and/O augers/O in/O 11/NUMBER distinct/O operations/O to/O produce/O a/O plow/O ./O 
By/O contrast/O ,/O a/O mechanized/O plow/O factory/O employed/O 52/NUMBER workers/O performing/O 97/NUMBER distinct/O tasks/O ,/O of/O which/O 72/NUMBER were/O assisted/O by/O steam/O power/O ,/O to/O produce/O a/O plow/O in/O just/O 3.75/MONEY man-hours/MONEY ./O 
The/O degree/O of/O specialisation/O was/O even/O greater/O in/O the/O production/O of/O men/O 's/O white/O muslin/O shirts/O ./O 
In/O the/O artisan/O shop/O ,/O one/NUMBER worker/O spent/O 1439/DATE hours/TIME performing/O 25/NUMBER different/O tasks/O to/O produce/O 144/NUMBER shirts/O ./O 
In/O the/O factory/O ,/O it/O took/O 188/NUMBER man-hours/O to/O produce/O the/O same/O quantity/O ,/O engaging/O 230/NUMBER different/O work/O -/O ers/O performing/O 39/NUMBER different/O tasks/O ,/O of/O which/O more/O than/O half/O required/O steam/O power/O ./O 
The/O workers/O involved/O included/O cutters/O ,/O turners/O and/O trimmers/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O foremen/O and/O forewomen/O ,/O inspectors/O ,/O errand/O boys/O ,/O an/O engineer/O ,/O a/O ?reman/O ,/O and/O a/O watchman/O -LRB-/O US/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION ,/O 1899/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
C./PERSON Frey/PERSON ,/O M./ORGANIZATION Osborne/ORGANIZATION //ORGANIZATION Technological/ORGANIZATION Forecasting/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Change/ORGANIZATION 114/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2017/DATE -RRB-/O 254/NUMBER --/O 280257/NUMBER products/O to/O be/O assembled/O from/O mass/O produced/O individual/O compo/O -/O nents/O by/O using/O highly/O specialised/O machine/O tools/O to/O a/O sequence/O of/O operations/O ./O 
10/NUMBER Yet/O while/O the/O ?rst/O assembly-line/O was/O documented/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1804/DATE ,/O it/O was/O not/O until/O the/DATE late/DATE nineteenth/DATE century/DATE that/O continuous/O -/O ?ow/O processes/O started/O to/O be/O adopted/O on/O a/O larger/O scale/O ,/O which/O enabled/O corporations/O such/O as/O the/O Ford/ORGANIZATION Motor/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION to/O manufacture/O the/O T/O -/O Ford/ORGANIZATION at/O a/O su?ciently/O low/O price/O for/O it/O to/O become/O the/O people/O 's/O vehicle/O -LRB-/O Mokyr/PERSON ,/O 1990/DATE ,/O p./O 137/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
Crucially/O ,/O the/O new/O assembly/O line/O introduced/O by/O Ford/ORGANIZATION in/U_TEMPPRED 1913/DATE was/O speci?cally/O designed/O for/O machinery/O to/O be/O operated/O by/O unskilled/O workers/O -LRB-/O Hounshell/ORGANIZATION ,/O 1985/DATE ,/O p./O 239/NUMBER -RRB-/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O what/O had/O previously/DATE been/O a/O one-man/O job/O was/O turned/O into/O a/O 29-man/O worker/O operation/O ,/O reducing/O the/O overall/O work/O time/O by/O 34/PERCENT %/PERCENT -LRB-/O Bright/O ,/O 1958/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O example/O of/O the/O Ford/ORGANIZATION Motor/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION thus/O underlines/O the/O general/O pattern/O observed/O in/O the/DATE nineteenth/DATE century/DATE ,/O with/O physical/O capital/O providing/O a/O relative/O complement/O to/O unskilled/O labour/O ,/O while/O substitut/O -/O ing/O for/O relatively/O skilled/O artisans/O -LRB-/O James/PERSON and/O Skinner/PERSON ,/O 1985/DATE ;/O Louis/LOCATION and/O Paterson/PERSON ,/O 1986/DATE ;/O Brown/PERSON and/O Philips/ORGANIZATION ,/O 1986/DATE ;/O Atack/O et/O al./O ,/O 2004/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
11Hence/O ,/O as/O pointed/O out/O by/O Acemoglu/PERSON -LRB-/O 2002/DATE ,/O p./O 7/NUMBER -RRB-/O :/O ``/O the/O idea/O that/O technological/O advances/O favour/O more/O skilled/O workers/O is/O a/O twentieth/DATE century/DATE phe/O -/O nomenon/O ./O ''/O 
The/O conventional/O wisdom/O among/O economic/O historians/O ,/O in/O other/O words/O ,/O suggests/O a/O discontinuity/O between/O the/O nineteenth/ORDINAL and/DATE twentieth/DATE century/DATE in/O the/O impact/O of/O capital/O deepening/O on/O the/O relative/O demand/O for/O skilled/O labour/O ./O 
The/O modern/O pattern/O of/O capital-skill/O complementarity/O gradually/O emerged/O in/O the/DATE late/DATE nineteenth/DATE century/DATE ,/O as/O manufacturing/O produc/O -/O tion/O shifted/O to/O increasingly/O mechanized/O assembly/O lines/O ./O 
This/O shift/O can/O be/O traced/O to/O the/O switch/O to/O electricity/O from/O steam/O and/O water-power/O which/O ,/O in/O combination/O with/O continuous-process/O and/O batch/O produc/O -/O tion/O methods/O ,/O reduced/O the/O demand/O for/O unskilled/O manual/O workers/O in/O many/O hauling/O ,/O conveying/O ,/O and/O assembly/O tasks/O ,/O but/O increased/O the/O demand/O for/O skills/O -LRB-/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 1998/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O short/O ,/O while/O factory/O assembly/O lines/O ,/O with/O their/O extreme/O division/O of/O labour/O ,/O had/O required/O vast/O quantities/O of/O human/O operatives/O ,/O electri?cation/O allowed/O many/O stages/O of/O the/O production/O process/O to/O be/O automated/O ,/O which/O in/O turn/O increased/O the/O demand/O for/O relatively/O skilled/O blue-collar/O production/O workers/O to/O operate/O the/O machinery/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O electri?cation/O con/O -/O tributed/O to/O a/O growing/O share/O of/O white-collar/O nonproduction/O workers/O -LRB-/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 1998/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Over/O the/O course/O of/O the/O nineteenth/ORDINAL cen/O -/O tury/O ,/O establishments/O became/O larger/O in/O size/O as/O steam/O and/O water/O power/O technologies/O improved/O ,/O allowing/O them/O to/O adopt/O powered/O machinery/O to/O realise/O productivity/O gains/O through/O the/O combination/O of/O enhanced/O division/O of/O labour/O and/O higher/O capital/O intensity/O -LRB-/O Atack/ORGANIZATION et/O al./O ,/O 2008a/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O the/O transport/O revolution/O lowered/O costs/O of/O shipping/O goods/O domestically/O and/O internationally/O as/O infrastructure/O spread/O and/O improved/O -LRB-/O Atack/ORGANIZATION et/O al./O ,/O 2008b/O -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O market/O for/O artisan/O goods/O early/O on/O had/O largely/O been/O con?ned/O to/O the/O immediate/O surround/O -/O ing/O area/O because/O transport/O costs/O were/O high/O relative/O to/O the/O value/O of/O 10These/O machines/O were/O sequentially/O implemented/O until/O the/O production/O process/O was/O completed/O ./O 
Over/O time/O ,/O such/O machines/O became/O much/O cheaper/O relative/O to/O skilled/O labour/O ./O 
As/O a/O result/O ,/O production/O became/O much/O more/O capital/O intensive/O -LRB-/O Hounshell/ORGANIZATION ,/O 1985/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
11Williamson/O and/O Lindert/PERSON -LRB-/O 1980/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O on/O the/O other/O hand/O ,/O ?nd/O a/O relative/O rise/O in/O wage/O premium/O of/O skilled/O labour/O over/O the/O period/O 1820/DATE to/O 1860/DATE ,/O which/O they/O partly/O attribute/O to/O capital/O deepening/O ./O 
Their/O claim/O of/O growing/O wage/O inequality/O over/O this/O period/O has/O ,/O however/O ,/O been/O challenged/O -LRB-/O Margo/PERSON ,/O 2000/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Yet/O seen/O over/O the/O long-run/O ,/O a/O more/O re?ned/O explanation/O is/O that/O the/O manufacturing/O share/O of/O the/O labour/O force/O in/O the/DATE nineteenth/DATE century/DATE hollowed/O out/O ./O 
This/O is/O suggested/O by/O recent/O ?ndings/O ,/O revealing/O a/O decline/O of/O middle-skill/O artisan/O jobs/O in/O favour/O of/O both/O high-skill/O white/O collar/O workers/O and/O low/O -/O skill/O operatives/O -LRB-/O Gray/O ,/O 2013/DATE ;/O Katz/PERSON and/O Margo/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O even/O if/O the/O share/O of/O operatives/O was/O increasing/O due/O to/O organizational/O change/O within/O manufacturing/O and/O overall/O manufacturing/O growth/O ,/O it/O does/O not/O follow/O that/O the/O share/O of/O unskilled/O labour/O was/O rising/O in/O the/O aggregate/O economy/O ,/O because/O some/O of/O the/O growth/O in/O the/O share/O of/O oper/O -/O atives/O may/O have/O come/O at/O the/O expense/O of/O a/O decrease/O in/O the/O share/O of/O workers/O employed/O as/O low-skilled/O farm/O workers/O in/O agriculture/O -LRB-/O Katz/PERSON and/O Margo/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Nevertheless/O ,/O this/O evidence/O is/O consistent/O with/O the/O literature/O showing/O that/O relatively/O skilled/O artisans/O were/O replaced/O by/O unskilled/O factory/O workers/O ,/O suggesting/O that/O technological/O change/O in/O manufacturing/O was/O deskilling/O ./O 
the/O goods/O produced/O ./O 
With/O the/O transport/O revolution/O ,/O however/O ,/O mar/DATE -/O ket/O size/O expanded/O ,/O thereby/O eroding/O local/O monopoly/O power/O ,/O which/O in/O turn/O increased/O competition/O and/O compelled/O ?rms/O to/O raise/O produc/O -/O tivity/O through/O mechanisation/O ./O 
As/O establishments/O became/O larger/O and/O served/O geographically/O expended/O markets/O ,/O managerial/O tasks/O increased/O in/O number/O and/O complexity/O ,/O requiring/O more/O managerial/O and/O clerking/O employees/O -LRB-/O Chandler/LOCATION ,/O 1977/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O pattern/O was/O ,/O by/O the/O turn/O of/O the/DATE twentieth/DATE century/DATE ,/O reinforced/O by/O electri?cation/O ,/O which/O not/O only/O con/O -/O tributed/O to/O a/O growing/O share/O of/O relatively/O skilled/O blue-collar/O labour/O ,/O but/O also/O increased/O the/O demand/O for/O white-collar/O workers/O -LRB-/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 1998/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O who/O tended/O to/O have/O higher/O educational/O attainment/O -LRB-/O Allen/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2001/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
12/NUMBER Since/O electri?cation/O ,/O the/O story/O of/O the/DATE twentieth/DATE century/DATE has/O been/O the/O race/O between/O education/O and/O technology/O -LRB-/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O US/O high/O school/O movement/O coincided/O with/O the/O ?rst/O industrial/O revolution/O of/O the/O o?ce/O -LRB-/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 1995/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
While/O the/O type/O -/O writer/O was/O invented/O in/O the/DATE 1860s/DATE ,/O it/O was/O not/O introduced/O in/O the/O o?ce/O until/O the/DATE early/DATE twentieth/DATE century/DATE ,/O when/O it/O entered/O a/O wave/O of/O mech/O -/O anisation/O ,/O with/O dictaphones/O ,/O calculators/O ,/O mimeo/O machines/O ,/O address/O machines/O ,/O and/O the/O predecessor/O of/O the/O computer/O --/O the/O keypunch/O -LRB-/O Beniger/O ,/O 1986/DATE ;/O Cortada/O ,/O 2000/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Importantly/O ,/O these/O o?ce/O machines/O reduced/O the/O cost/O of/O information/O processing/O tasks/O and/O increased/O the/O demand/O for/O the/O complementary/O factor/O --/O i.e.educated/O o?ce/O workers/O ./O 
Yet/O the/O increased/O supply/O of/O educated/O o?ce/O workers/O ,/O following/O the/O high/O school/O movement/O ,/O was/O associated/O with/O a/O sharp/O decline/O in/O the/O wage/O premium/O of/O clerking/O occupations/O relative/O to/O production/O work/O -/O ers/O -LRB-/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 1995/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O was/O ,/O however/O ,/O not/O the/O result/O of/O deskilling/O technological/O change/O ./O 
Clerking/O workers/O were/O indeed/O rela/O -/O tively/O educated/O ./O 
Rather/O ,/O it/O was/O the/O result/O of/O the/O supply/O of/O educated/O workers/O outpacing/O the/O demand/O for/O their/O skills/O ,/O leading/O educational/O wage/O differentials/O to/O compress/O ./O 
While/O educational/O wage/O differentials/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION narrowed/O from/O 1915/DATE to/O 1980/DATE -LRB-/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O both/O educational/O wage/O dif/O -/O ferentials/O and/O overall/O wage/O inequality/O have/O increased/O sharply/O since/O the/DATE 1980s/DATE in/O a/O number/O of/O countries/O -LRB-/O Krueger/PERSON ,/O 1993/DATE ;/O Murphy/PERSON et/O al./O ,/O 1998/DATE ;/O Atkinson/PERSON ,/O 2008/DATE ;/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Although/O there/O are/O clearly/O several/O variables/O at/O work/O ,/O consensus/O is/O broad/O that/O this/O can/O be/O ascribed/O to/O an/O acceleration/O in/O capital-skill/O complementarity/O ,/O driven/O by/O the/O adoption/O of/O computers/O and/O information/O technology/O -LRB-/O Krueger/PERSON ,/O 1993/DATE ;/O Autor/O et/O al./O ,/O 1998/DATE ;/O Bresnahan/PERSON et/O al./O ,/O 2002/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
What/O is/O commonly/O referred/O to/O as/O the/O Computer/O Revolution/O began/O with/O the/O ?rst/O com/O -/O mercial/O uses/O of/O computers/O around/O 1960/DATE and/O continued/O through/O the/O development/O of/O the/O Internet/O and/O e-commerce/O in/O the/DATE 1990s/DATE ./O 
As/O the/O cost/O per/O computation/O declined/O at/O an/O annual/SET average/O of/O 37/PERCENT %/PERCENT between/O 1945/DATE and/O 1980/DATE -LRB-/O Nordhaus/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2007/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O telephone/O operators/O were/O made/O redun/O -/O dant/O ,/O the/O ?rst/O industrial/O robot/O was/O introduced/O by/O General/ORGANIZATION Motors/ORGANIZATION in/O the/DATE 1960s/DATE ,/O and/O in/O the/DATE 1970s/DATE airline/O reservations/O systems/O led/O the/O way/O in/O self-service/O technology/O -LRB-/O Gordon/LOCATION ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
During/O the/DATE 1980s/DATE and/O 1990s/DATE ,/O computing/O costs/O declined/O even/O more/O rapidly/O ,/O on/O average/O by/O 64/PERCENT %/PERCENT per/O year/DURATION ,/O accompanied/O by/O a/O surge/O in/O computational/O power/O -LRB-/O Nordhaus/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2007/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
13At/O the/O same/O time/O ,/O bar-code/O scanners/O and/O cash/O machines/O were/O spreading/O across/O the/O retail/O and/O ?nancial/O industries/O ,/O and/O the/O ?rst/O per/O -/O sonal/O computers/O were/O introduced/O in/O the/DATE early/DATE 1980s/DATE ,/O with/O their/O word/O processing/O and/O spreadsheet/O functions/O eliminating/O copy/O typist/O occupa/O -/O tions/O and/O allowing/O repetitive/O calculations/O to/O be/O automated/O -LRB-/O Gordon/LOCATION ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O substitution/O for/O labour/O marks/O a/O further/O important/O reversal/O ./O 
The/DATE early/DATE twentieth/DATE century/DATE o?ce/O machines/O increased/O the/O demand/O for/O clerking/O workers/O -LRB-/O Chandler/LOCATION ,/O 1977/DATE ;/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 1995/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O a/O 12Most/O likely/O ,/O the/O growing/O share/O of/O white-collar/O workers/O increased/O the/O element/O of/O human/O interaction/O in/O employment/O ./O 
Notably/O ,/O Michaels/PERSON et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ?nd/O that/O the/O increase/O in/O the/O employment/O share/O of/O interactive/O occupations/O ,/O going/O hand/O in/O hand/O with/O an/O increase/O in/O their/O relative/O wage/O bill/O share/O ,/O was/O particularly/O strong/O between/O 1880/DATE and/O 1930/DATE ,/O which/O is/O a/O period/O of/O rapid/O change/O in/O communication/O and/O transport/O technology/O ./O 
13Computer/O power/O even/O increased/O 18/PERCENT %/PERCENT faster/O on/O annual/SET basis/O than/O predicted/O by/O Moore/PERSON 's/O Law/O ,/O implying/O a/O doubling/O every/SET two/SET years/SET -LRB-/O Nordhaus/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2007/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
258C/O ./O 
Frey/O ,/O M./ORGANIZATION Osborne/ORGANIZATION //ORGANIZATION Technological/ORGANIZATION Forecasting/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Change/ORGANIZATION 114/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2017/DATE -RRB-/O 254/NUMBER --/O 280/NUMBER similar/O manner/O ,/O computerisation/O augments/O demand/O for/O such/O tasks/O ,/O but/O it/O also/O permits/O them/O to/O be/O automated/O -LRB-/O Autor/O et/O al./O ,/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O Computer/O Revolution/O can/O go/O some/O way/O in/O explaining/O the/O growing/O wage/O inequality/O of/O the/DATE past/DATE decades/DATE ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O Krueger/PERSON -LRB-/O 1993/DATE -RRB-/O ?nds/O that/O workers/O using/O a/O computer/O earn/O roughly/O earn/O 10/NUMBER to/O 15/PERCENT %/PERCENT more/O than/O others/O ,/O but/O also/O that/O computer/O use/O accounts/O for/O a/O sub/O -/O stantial/O share/O of/O the/O increase/O in/O the/O rate/O of/O return/O to/O education/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O more/O recent/O studies/O ?nd/O that/O computers/O have/O caused/O a/O shift/O in/O the/O occupational/O structure/O of/O the/O labour/O market/O ./O 
Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O show/O that/O as/O computerisation/O erodes/O wages/O for/O labour/O performing/O routine/O tasks/O ,/O workers/O will/O reallocate/O their/O labour/O supply/O to/O relatively/O low-skill/O service/O occupations/O ./O 
More/O speci?cally/O ,/O between/O 1980/DATE and/O 2005/DATE ,/O the/O share/O of/O US/LOCATION labour/O hours/DURATION in/O service/O occu/O -/O pations/O grew/O by/O 30/PERCENT %/PERCENT after/O having/O been/O ?at/O or/O declining/O in/O the/O three/NUMBER prior/O decades/DURATION ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O net/O changes/O in/O US/LOCATION employment/O were/O U/O -/O shaped/O in/O skill/O level/O ,/O meaning/O that/O the/O lowest/O and/O highest/O job-skill/O quartile/O expanded/O sharply/O with/O relative/O employment/O declines/O in/O the/O middle/O of/O the/O distribution/O ./O 
The/O expansion/O in/O high-skill/O employment/O can/O be/O explained/O by/O the/O falling/O price/O of/O carrying/O out/O routine/O tasks/O by/O means/O of/O comput/O -/O ers/O ,/O which/O complements/O more/O abstract/O and/O creative/O services/O ./O 
Seen/O from/O a/O production/O function/O perspective/O ,/O an/O outward/O shift/O in/O the/O supply/O of/O routine/O informational/O inputs/O increases/O the/O marginal/O pro-/O ductivity/O of/O workers/O they/O are/O demanded/O by/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O text/O and/O data/O mining/O has/O improved/O the/O quality/O of/O legal/O research/O as/O constant/O access/O to/O market/O information/O has/O improved/O the/O e?ciency/O of/O man/O -/O agerial/O decision-making/O --/O i.e.tasks/O performed/O by/O skilled/O workers/O at/O the/O higher/O end/O of/O the/O income/O distribution/O ./O 
The/O result/O has/O been/O an/O increasingly/O polarised/O labour/O market/O ,/O with/O growing/O employment/O in/O high-income/O cognitive/O jobs/O and/O low-income/O manual/O occupations/O ,/O accompanied/O by/O a/O hollowing-out/O of/O middle-income/O routine/O jobs/O ./O 
This/O is/O a/O pattern/O that/O is/O not/O unique/O to/O the/O US/LOCATION and/O equally/O applies/O to/O a/O number/O of/O developed/O economies/O -LRB-/O Goos/O et/O al./O ,/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
14/NUMBER How/O technological/O progress/O in/O the/O twenty-?rst/O century/DURATION will/O impact/O on/O labour/O market/O outcomes/O remains/O to/O be/O seen/O ./O 
Throughout/O history/O ,/O technological/O progress/O has/O vastly/O shifted/O the/O composition/O of/O employment/O ,/O from/O agriculture/O and/O the/O artisan/O shop/O ,/O to/O manufactur/O -/O ing/O and/O clerking/O ,/O to/O service/O and/O management/O occupations/O ./O 
Yet/O the/O concern/O over/O technological/O unemployment/O has/O proven/O to/O be/O exag/O -/O gerated/O ./O 
The/O obvious/O reason/O why/O this/O concern/O has/O not/O materialised/O relates/O to/O Ricardo/LOCATION 's/O famous/O chapter/O on/O machinery/O ,/O which/O suggests/O that/O labour-saving/O technology/O reduces/O the/O demand/O for/O undifferenti/O -/O ated/O labour/O ,/O thus/O leading/O to/O technological/O unemployment/O -LRB-/O Ricardo/O ,/O 1819/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
As/O economists/O have/O long/O understood/O ,/O however/O ,/O an/O invention/O that/O replaces/O workers/O by/O machines/O will/O have/O effects/O on/O all/O prod/O -/O uct/O and/O factor/O markets/O ./O 
An/O increase/O in/O the/O e?ciency/O of/O production/O which/O reduces/O the/O price/O of/O one/NUMBER good/O ,/O will/O increase/O real/O income/O and/O thus/O increase/O demand/O for/O other/O goods/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O in/O short/O ,/O technolog/O -/O ical/O progress/O has/O two/NUMBER competing/O effects/O on/O employment/O -LRB-/O Aghion/O and/O Howitt/PERSON ,/O 1994/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O as/O technology/O substitutes/O for/O labour/O ,/O there/O is/O a/O destruction/O effect/O ,/O requiring/O workers/O to/O reallocate/O their/O labour/O supply/O ;/O and/O second/ORDINAL ,/O there/O is/O the/O capitalisation/O effect/O ,/O as/O more/O com/O -/O panies/O enter/O industries/O where/O productivity/O is/O relatively/O high/O ,/O leading/O employment/O in/O those/O industries/O to/O expand/O ./O 
14While/O there/O is/O broad/O consensus/O that/O computers/O substituting/O for/O workers/O in/O routine-intensive/O tasks/O has/O driven/O labour/O market/O polarisation/O over/O the/DATE past/DATE decades/DATE ,/O there/O are/O ,/O indeed/O ,/O alternative/O explanations/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O technological/O advances/O in/O computing/O have/O dramatically/O lowered/O the/O cost/O of/O leaving/O information-based/O tasks/O to/O foreign/O worksites/O -LRB-/O Jensen/PERSON and/O Kletzer/PERSON ,/O 2005/DATE ;/O Blinder/O ,/O 2009/DATE ;/O Jensen/PERSON and/O Kletzer/PERSON ,/O 2010/DATE ;/O Oldenski/PERSON ,/O 2012/DATE ;/O Blinder/O and/O Krueger/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O decline/O in/O the/O routine-intensity/O of/O employment/O is/O thus/O likely/O to/O result/O from/O a/O combination/O of/O offshoring/O and/O automa/O -/O tion/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O there/O is/O evidence/O suggesting/O that/O improvements/O in/O transport/O and/O communication/O technology/O have/O augmented/O occupations/O involving/O human/O interac/O -/O tion/O ,/O spanning/O across/O both/O cognitive/O and/O manual/O tasks/O -LRB-/O Michaels/PERSON et/O al./O ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
These/O explanations/O are/O nevertheless/O equally/O related/O to/O advance/O in/O computing/O and/O communi/O -/O cations/O technology/O ./O 
Although/O the/O capitalisation/O effect/O has/O been/O predominant/O histori/O -/O cally/O ,/O our/O discovery/O of/O means/O of/O economising/O the/O use/O of/O labour/O can/O outrun/O the/O pace/O at/O which/O we/O can/O ?nd/O new/O uses/O for/O labour/O ,/O as/O Keynes/PERSON -LRB-/O 1933/DATE -RRB-/O pointed/O out/O ./O 
The/O reason/O why/O human/O labour/O has/O prevailed/O relates/O to/O its/O ability/O to/O adopt/O and/O acquire/O new/O skills/O by/O means/O of/O edu/O -/O cation/O -LRB-/O Goldin/PERSON and/O Katz/PERSON ,/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Yet/O as/O computerisation/O enters/O more/O cognitive/O domains/O this/O will/O become/O increasingly/O challenging/O -LRB-/O Bryn/O -/O jolfsson/O and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Recent/O empirical/O ?ndings/O are/O therefore/O particularly/O concerning/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O Beaudry/ORGANIZATION et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O docu/O -/O ment/O a/O decline/O in/O the/O demand/O for/O skill/O over/O the/DATE past/DATE decade/DATE ,/O even/O as/O the/O supply/O of/O workers/O with/O higher/O education/O has/O continued/O to/O grow/O ./O 
They/O show/O that/O high-skilled/O workers/O have/O moved/O down/O the/O occupa/O -/O tional/O ladder/O ,/O taking/O on/O jobs/O traditionally/O performed/O by/O low-skilled/O workers/O ,/O pushing/O low-skilled/O workers/O even/O further/O down/O the/O occu/O -/O pational/O ladder/O and/O ,/O to/O some/O extent/O ,/O even/O out/O of/O the/O labour/O force/O ./O 
This/O raises/O questions/O about/O -LRB-/O a/O -RRB-/O the/O ability/O of/O human/O labour/O to/O win/O the/O race/O against/O technology/O by/O means/O of/O education/O ;/O and/O -LRB-/O b/O -RRB-/O the/O poten/O -/O tial/O extent/O of/O technological/O unemployment/O ,/O as/O an/O increasing/O pace/O of/O technological/O progress/O will/O cause/O higher/O job/O turnover/O ,/O resulting/O in/O a/O higher/O natural/O rate/O of/O unemployment/O -LRB-/O Lucas/PERSON and/O Prescott/PERSON ,/O 1974/DATE ;/O Davis/PERSON and/O Haltiwanger/PERSON ,/O 1992/DATE ;/O Pissarides/O ,/O 2000/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
While/O the/O present/DATE study/O is/O limited/O to/O examining/O the/O destruction/O effect/O of/O technology/O ,/O it/O nevertheless/O provides/O a/O useful/O indication/O of/O the/O job/O growth/O required/O to/O counterbalance/O the/O jobs/O at/O risk/O over/O the/DATE next/DATE decades/DATE ./O 
3/NUMBER ./O 
The/O technological/O revolutions/O of/O the/O twenty-?rst/O century/DURATION The/O secular/O price/O decline/O in/O the/O real/O cost/O of/O computing/O has/O cre/O -/O ated/O vast/O economic/O incentives/O for/O employers/O to/O substitute/O labour/O for/O computer/O capital/O ./O 
15Yet/O the/O tasks/O computers/O are/O able/O to/O perform/O ulti/O -/O mately/O depend/O upon/O the/O ability/O of/O a/O programmer/O to/O write/O a/O set/O of/O procedures/O or/O rules/O that/O appropriately/O direct/O the/O technology/O in/O each/O possible/O contingency/O ./O 
Computers/O will/O therefore/O be/O relatively/O pro-/O ductive/O to/O human/O labour/O when/O a/O problem/O can/O be/O speci?ed/O --/O in/O the/O sense/O that/O the/O criteria/O for/O success/O are/O quanti?able/O and/O can/O readily/O be/O evaluated/O -LRB-/O Acemoglu/PERSON and/O Autor/O ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O extent/O of/O job/O com/O -/O puterisation/O will/O thus/O be/O determined/O by/O technological/O advances/O that/O allow/O engineering/O problems/O to/O be/O su?ciently/O speci?ed/O ,/O which/O sets/O the/O boundaries/O for/O the/O scope/O of/O computerisation/O ./O 
In/O this/O section/O ,/O we/O examine/O the/O extent/O of/O tasks/O computer-controlled/O equipment/O can/O be/O expected/O to/O perform/O over/O the/DATE next/DATE decades/DATE ./O 
Doing/O so/O ,/O we/O focus/O on/O advances/O in/O ?elds/O related/O to/O Machine/O Learning/O -LRB-/O ML/O -RRB-/O ,/O including/O Data/O Mining/O ,/O Machine/ORGANIZATION Vision/ORGANIZATION ,/O Computational/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION and/O other/O sub-?elds/O of/O Arti?cial/ORGANIZATION Intelligence/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O AI/O -RRB-/O ,/O in/O which/O efforts/O are/O explic/O -/O itly/O dedicated/O to/O the/O development/O of/O algorithms/O that/O allow/O cognitive/O tasks/O to/O be/O automated/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O we/O examine/O the/O application/O of/O ML/O technologies/O in/O Mobile/ORGANIZATION Robotics/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O MR/O -RRB-/O ,/O and/O thus/O the/O extent/O of/O computerisation/O in/O manual/O tasks/O ./O 
Our/O analysis/O builds/O on/O the/O task/O categorisation/O of/O Autor/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O which/O distinguishes/O between/O workplace/O tasks/O using/O a/O two/NUMBER -/O by-two/O matrix/O ,/O with/O routine/O versus/O non-routine/O tasks/O on/O one/NUMBER axis/O ,/O and/O manual/O versus/O cognitive/O tasks/O on/O the/O other/O ./O 
In/O short/O ,/O routine/O tasks/O are/O de?ned/O as/O tasks/O that/O follow/O explicit/O rules/O that/O can/O be/O accomplished/O by/O machines/O ,/O while/O non-routine/O tasks/O are/O not/O su?/O -/O ciently/O well/O understood/O to/O be/O speci?ed/O in/O computer/O code/O ./O 
Each/O of/O these/O task/O categories/O can/O ,/O in/O turn/O ,/O be/O of/O either/O manual/O or/O cognitive/O nature/O --/O i.e.they/O relate/O to/O physical/O labour/O or/O knowledge/O work/O ./O 
His/O -/O torically/O ,/O computerisation/O has/O largely/O been/O con?ned/O to/O manual/O and/O cognitive/O routine/O tasks/O involving/O explicit/O rule-based/O activities/O -LRB-/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE ;/O Goos/O et/O al./O ,/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Following/O recent/O technological/O advances/O ,/O however/O ,/O computerisation/O is/O now/DATE spreading/O to/O domains/O commonly/O de?ned/O as/O non-routine/O ./O 
The/O rapid/O pace/O at/O which/O tasks/O that/O 15We/O refer/O to/O computer/O capital/O as/O accumulated/O computers/O and/O computer-controlled/O equipment/O by/O means/O of/O capital/O deepening/O ./O 
C./PERSON Frey/PERSON ,/O M./ORGANIZATION Osborne/ORGANIZATION //ORGANIZATION Technological/ORGANIZATION Forecasting/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Change/ORGANIZATION 114/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2017/DATE -RRB-/O 254/NUMBER --/O 280259/NUMBER were/O de?ned/O as/O non-routine/O only/O a/DATE decade/DATE ago/DATE have/O now/DATE become/O computerisable/O is/O illustrated/O byAutor/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O asserting/O that/O ``/O Navigating/O a/O car/O through/O city/O tra?c/O or/O deciphering/O the/O scrawled/O handwriting/O on/O a/O personal/O check/O --/O minor/O undertakings/O for/O most/O adults/O --/O are/O not/O routine/O tasks/O by/O our/O de?nition/O ./O ''/O 
Today/DATE ,/O the/O problems/O of/O navigating/O a/O car/O and/O deciphering/O handwriting/O are/O su?ciently/O well/O understood/O that/O many/O related/O tasks/O can/O be/O speci?ed/O in/O computer/O code/O and/O automated/O -LRB-/O Veres/PERSON et/O al./O ,/O 2011/DATE ;/O Pl?tz/O and/O Fink/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Recent/O technological/O breakthroughs/O are/O ,/O in/O large/O part/O ,/O due/O to/O efforts/O to/O turn/O non-routine/O tasks/O into/O well-de?ned/O problems/O ./O 
De?n/O -/O ing/O such/O problems/O is/O helped/O by/O the/O provision/O of/O relevant/O data/O :/O this/O is/O highlighted/O in/O the/O case/O of/O handwriting/O recognition/O by/O Pl?tz/O and/O Fink/PERSON -LRB-/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O success/O of/O an/O algorithm/O for/O handwriting/O recogni/O -/O tion/O is/O di?cult/O to/O quantify/O without/O data/O to/O test/O on/O --/O in/O particular/O ,/O determining/O whether/O an/O algorithm/O performs/O well/O for/O different/O styles/O of/O writing/O requires/O data/O containing/O a/O variety/O of/O such/O styles/O ./O 
That/O is/O ,/O data/O is/O required/O to/O specify/O the/O many/O contingencies/O a/O technology/O must/O manage/O in/O order/O to/O form/O an/O adequate/O substitute/O for/O human/O labour/O ./O 
With/O data/O ,/O objective/O and/O quanti?able/O measures/O of/O the/O success/O of/O an/O algorithm/O can/O be/O produced/O ,/O which/O aid/O the/O continual/O improvement/O of/O its/O performance/O relative/O to/O humans/O ./O 
As/O such/O ,/O technological/O progress/O has/O been/O aided/O by/O the/O recent/O pro-/O duction/O of/O increasingly/O large/O and/O complex/O datasets/O ,/O known/O as/O big/O data/O ./O 
16For/O instance/O ,/O with/O a/O growing/O corpus/O of/O human-translated/O dig/O -/O italised/O text/O ,/O the/O success/O of/O a/O machine/O translator/O can/O now/DATE be/O judged/O by/O its/O accuracy/O in/O reproducing/O observed/O translations/O ./O 
Data/O from/O United/ORGANIZATION Nations/ORGANIZATION documents/O ,/O which/O are/O translated/O by/O human/O experts/O into/O six/NUMBER languages/O ,/O allow/O Google/ORGANIZATION Translate/ORGANIZATION to/O monitor/O and/O improve/O the/O performance/O of/O different/O machine/O translation/O algorithms/O -LRB-/O Tanner/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2007/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Further/O ,/O ML/O algorithms/O can/O discover/O unexpected/O similarities/O between/O old/O and/O new/O data/O ,/O aiding/O the/O computerisation/O of/O tasks/O for/O which/O big/O data/O has/O newly/O become/O available/O ./O 
As/O a/O result/O ,/O computer/O -/O isation/O is/O no/O longer/O con?ned/O to/O routine/O tasks/O that/O can/O be/O written/O as/O rule-based/O software/O queries/O ,/O but/O is/O spreading/O to/O every/O non-routine/O task/O where/O big/O data/O becomes/O available/O -LRB-/O Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O this/O section/O ,/O we/O examine/O the/O extent/O of/O future/DATE computerisa/O -/O tion/O beyond/O routine/O tasks/O ./O 
3.1/NUMBER ./O 
Computerisation/O in/O non-routine/O cognitive/O tasks/O With/O the/O availability/O of/O big/O data/O ,/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O non-routine/O cognitive/O tasks/O are/O becoming/O computerisable/O ./O 
That/O is/O ,/O further/O to/O the/O general/O improvement/O in/O technological/O progress/O due/O to/O big/O data/O ,/O algorithms/O for/O big/O data/O are/O rapidly/O entering/O domains/O reliant/O upon/O storing/O or/O accessing/O information/O ./O 
The/O use/O of/O big/O data/O is/O afforded/O by/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O chief/O comparative/O advantages/O of/O computers/O relative/O to/O human/O labour/O :/O scalability/O ./O 
Little/O evidence/O is/O required/O to/O demonstrate/O that/O ,/O in/O performing/O the/O task/O of/O labourious/O computation/O ,/O networks/O of/O machines/O scale/O better/O than/O human/O labour/O -LRB-/O Campbell-Kelly/O ,/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
As/O such/O ,/O computers/O can/O better/O manage/O the/O large/O calculations/O required/O in/O using/O large/O datasets/O ./O 
ML/O algorithms/O running/O on/O computers/O are/O now/DATE ,/O in/O many/O cases/O ,/O better/O able/O to/O detect/O patterns/O in/O big/O data/O than/O humans/O ./O 
Computerisation/O of/O cognitive/O tasks/O is/O also/O aided/O by/O another/O core/O comparative/O advantage/O of/O algorithms/O :/O their/O absence/O of/O some/O human/O biases/O ./O 
An/O algorithm/O can/O be/O designed/O to/O ruthlessly/O satisfy/O the/O small/O range/O of/O tasks/O it/O is/O given/O ./O 
Humans/O ,/O in/O contrast/O ,/O must/O ful/O -/O ?ll/O a/O range/O of/O tasks/O unrelated/O to/O their/O occupation/O ,/O such/O as/O sleeping/O ,/O necessitating/O occasional/O sacri?ces/O in/O their/O occupational/O performance/O -LRB-/O Kahneman/PERSON et/O al./O ,/O 1982/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O additional/O constraints/O under/O which/O 16Predictions/O by/O Cisco/ORGANIZATION Systems/ORGANIZATION suggest/O that/O the/O Internet/O tra?c/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2016/DATE will/O be/O around/O 1/NUMBER zettabyte/O -LRB-/O 1/NUMBER ?/O 10/NUMBER 21bytes/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O Cisco/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O comparison/O ,/O the/O information/O contained/O in/O all/O books/O worldwide/O is/O about/O 480/NUMBER terabytes/O -LRB-/O 5/NUMBER ?/O 10/NUMBER 14bytes/O -RRB-/O ,/O and/O a/O text/O transcript/O of/O all/O the/O words/O ever/O spoken/O by/O humans/O would/O represent/O about/O 5/NUMBER exabytes/O -LRB-/O 5/NUMBER ?/O 10/NUMBER 18bytes/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O UC/ORGANIZATION Berkeley/ORGANIZATION School/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Information/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
humans/O must/O operate/O manifest/O themselves/O as/O biases/O ./O 
Consider/O an/O example/O of/O human/O bias/O :/O Danziger/PERSON et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O demonstrate/O that/O expe/O -/O rienced/O Israeli/O judges/O are/O substantially/O more/O generous/O in/O their/O rulings/O following/O a/O lunch/O break/O ./O 
It/O can/O thus/O be/O argued/O that/O many/O roles/O involving/O decision-making/O will/O bene?t/O from/O impartial/O algorithmic/O solutions/O ./O 
Fraud/O detection/O is/O a/O task/O that/O requires/O both/O impartial/O decision/O making/O and/O the/O ability/O to/O detect/O trends/O in/O big/O data/O ./O 
As/O such/O ,/O this/O task/O is/O now/DATE almost/O completely/O automated/O -LRB-/O Phua/PERSON et/O al./O ,/O 2010/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O a/O similar/O manner/O ,/O the/O comparative/O advantages/O of/O computers/O are/O likely/O to/O change/O the/O nature/O of/O work/O across/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O industries/O and/O occupations/O ./O 
In/O health/O care/O ,/O diagnostics/O tasks/O are/O already/O being/O computerised/O ./O 
Oncologists/O at/O Memorial/O Sloan-Kettering/O Cancer/O Center/O are/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O using/O IBM/ORGANIZATION 's/O Watson/PERSON computer/O to/O provide/O chronic/O care/O and/O cancer/O treatment/O diagnostics/O ./O 
Knowledge/O from/O 600,000/NUMBER medical/O evi/ORGANIZATION -/O dence/O reports/O ,/O 1.5/NUMBER million/NUMBER patient/O records/O and/O clinical/O trials/O ,/O and/O two/NUMBER million/NUMBER pages/O of/O text/O from/O medical/O journals/O ,/O are/O used/O for/O benchmark/O -/O ing/O and/O pattern/O recognition/O purposes/O ./O 
This/O allows/O the/O computer/O to/O compare/O each/O patient/O 's/O individual/O symptoms/O ,/O genetics/O ,/O family/O and/O medication/O history/O ,/O etc./O ,/O to/O diagnose/O and/O develop/O a/O treatment/O plan/O with/O the/O highest/O probability/O of/O success/O -LRB-/O Cohn/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O computerisation/O is/O entering/O the/O domains/O of/O legal/O and/O ?nancial/O services/O ./O 
Sophisticated/O algorithms/O are/O gradually/O taking/O on/O a/O number/O of/O tasks/O performed/O by/O paralegals/O ,/O contract/O and/O patent/O lawyers/O -LRB-/O Markoff/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
More/O speci?cally/O ,/O law/O ?rms/O now/DATE rely/O on/O computers/O that/O can/O scan/O thousands/O of/O legal/O briefs/O and/O precedents/O to/O assist/O in/O pre-trial/O research/O ./O 
A/O frequently/O cited/O example/O is/O Syman/PERSON -/O tec/O 's/O Clearwell/O system/O ,/O which/O uses/O language/O analysis/O to/O identify/O general/O concepts/O in/O documents/O ,/O can/O present/DATE the/O results/O graphically/O ,/O and/O proved/O capable/O of/O analysing/O and/O sorting/O more/O than/O 570,000/NUMBER documents/O in/O two/DURATION days/DURATION -LRB-/O Markoff/PERSON ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O the/O improvement/O of/O sensing/O technology/O has/O made/O sensor/O data/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O most/O prominent/O sources/O of/O big/O data/O -LRB-/O Ackerman/PERSON and/O Guizzo/O ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Sensor/O data/O is/O often/O coupled/O with/O new/O ML/O fault/O -/O and/O anomaly-detection/O algorithms/O to/O render/O many/O tasks/O computeris/O -/O able/O ./O 
A/O broad/O class/O of/O examples/O can/O be/O found/O in/O condition/O monitoring/O and/O novelty/O detection/O ,/O with/O technology/O substituting/O for/O closed-circuit/O TV/O -LRB-/O CCTV/ORGANIZATION -RRB-/O operators/O ,/O workers/O examining/O equipment/O defects/O ,/O and/O clin/O -/O ical/O staff/O responsible/O for/O monitoring/O the/O state/O of/O patients/O in/O intensive/O care/O ./O 
Here/O ,/O the/O fact/O that/O computers/O lack/O human/O biases/O is/O of/O great/O value/O :/O algorithms/O are/O free/O of/O irrational/O bias/O ,/O and/O their/O vigilance/O need/O not/O be/O interrupted/O by/O rest/O breaks/O or/O lapses/O of/O concentration/O ./O 
Following/O the/O declining/O costs/O of/O digital/O sensing/O and/O actuation/O ,/O ML/O approaches/O have/O successfully/O addressed/O condition/O monitoring/O applications/O rang/O -/O ing/O from/O batteries/O -LRB-/O Saha/O et/O al./O ,/O 2007/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O to/O aircraft/O engines/O -LRB-/O King/O et/O al./O ,/O 2009/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O water/O quality/O -LRB-/O Osborne/PERSON et/O al./O ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O and/O intensive/O care/O units/O -LRB-/O ICUs/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O Clifford/PERSON and/O Clifton/PERSON ,/O 2012/DATE ;/O Clifton/PERSON et/O al./O ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Sensors/O can/O equally/O be/O placed/O on/O trucks/O and/O pallets/O to/O improve/O companies/O '/O sup/O -/O ply/O chain/O management/O ,/O and/O used/O to/O measure/O the/O moisture/O in/O a/O ?eld/O of/O crops/O to/O track/O the/O ?ow/O of/O water/O through/O utility/O pipes/O ./O 
This/O allows/O for/O automatic/O meter/O reading/O ,/O eliminating/O the/O need/O for/O personnel/O to/O gather/O such/O information/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O the/O cities/O of/O Doha/LOCATION ,/O S?o/LOCATION Paulo/LOCATION ,/O and/O Beijing/LOCATION use/O sensors/O on/O pipes/O ,/O pumps/O ,/O and/O other/O water/O infrastruc/O -/O ture/O to/O monitor/O conditions/O and/O manage/O water/O loss/O ,/O reducing/O leaks/O by/O 40/NUMBER to/O 50/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
In/O the/DATE near/DATE future/DATE ,/O it/O will/O be/O possible/O to/O place/O inexpen/O -/O sive/O sensors/O on/O light/O poles/O ,/O sidewalks/O ,/O and/O other/O public/O property/O to/O capture/O sound/O and/O images/O ,/O likely/O reducing/O the/O number/O of/O workers/O in/O law/O enforcement/O -LRB-/O MGI/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Advances/O in/O user/O interfaces/O also/O enable/O computers/O to/O respond/O directly/O to/O a/O wider/O range/O of/O human/O requests/O ,/O thus/O augmenting/O the/O work/O of/O highly/O skilled/O labour/O ,/O while/O allowing/O some/O types/O of/O jobs/O to/O become/O fully/O automated/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O Apple/ORGANIZATION 's/O Siri/PERSON and/O Google/ORGANIZATION Now/DATE rely/O on/O natural/O user/O interfaces/O to/O recognise/O spoken/O words/O ,/O interpret/O their/O meanings/O ,/O and/O act/O on/O them/O accordingly/O ./O 
Moreover/O ,/O a/O company/O called/O SmartAction/O now/DATE provides/O call/O computerisation/O solutions/O that/O use/O ML/O technology/O and/O advanced/O speech/O recognition/O to/O improve/O upon/O conventional/O interactive/O voice/O response/O systems/O ,/O 260C/O ./O 
Frey/O ,/O M./ORGANIZATION Osborne/ORGANIZATION //ORGANIZATION Technological/ORGANIZATION Forecasting/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Change/ORGANIZATION 114/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2017/DATE -RRB-/O 254/NUMBER --/O 280/NUMBER realising/O cost/O savings/O of/O 60/NUMBER to/O 80/PERCENT %/PERCENT over/O an/O outsourced/O call/O center/O con/O -/O sisting/O of/O human/O labour/O -LRB-/O CAA/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Even/O education/O ,/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O most/O labour/O intensive/O sectors/O ,/O will/O most/O likely/O be/O signi?cantly/O impacted/O by/O improved/O user/O interfaces/O and/O algorithms/O building/O upon/O big/O data/O ./O 
The/O recent/O growth/O in/O MOOCs/O -LRB-/O Massive/O Open/O Online/O Courses/O -RRB-/O has/O begun/O to/O generate/O large/O datasets/O detailing/O how/O students/O interact/O on/O forums/O ,/O their/O diligence/O in/O completing/O assignments/O and/O viewing/O lectures/O ,/O and/O their/O ultimate/O grades/O -LRB-/O Simonite/O ,/O 2013/DATE ;/O Breslow/PERSON et/O al./O ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Such/O information/O ,/O together/O with/O improved/O user/O interfaces/O ,/O will/O allow/O for/O ML/O algorithms/O that/O serve/O as/O interactive/O tutors/O ,/O with/O teaching/O and/O assessment/O strategies/O statistically/O calibrated/O to/O match/O individual/O student/O needs/O -LRB-/O Woolf/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2010/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Big/O data/O analysis/O will/O also/O allow/O for/O more/O effective/O predictions/O of/O student/O performance/O ,/O and/O for/O their/O suitability/O for/O post-graduation/O occupations/O ./O 
These/O technologies/O can/O equally/O be/O implemented/O in/O recruitment/O ,/O most/O likely/O resulting/O in/O the/O streamlining/O of/O human/O resource/O -LRB-/O HR/DURATION -RRB-/O departments/O ./O 
Occupations/O that/O require/O subtle/O judgement/O are/O also/O increasingly/O susceptible/O to/O computerisation/O ./O 
To/O many/O such/O tasks/O ,/O the/O unbiased/O decision/O making/O of/O an/O algorithm/O represents/O a/O comparative/O advantage/O over/O human/O operators/O ./O 
In/O the/O most/O challenging/O or/O critical/O applica/O -/O tions/O ,/O as/O in/O ICUs/O ,/O algorithmic/O recommendations/O may/O serve/O as/O inputs/O to/O human/O operators/O ;/O in/O other/O circumstances/O ,/O algorithms/O will/O them/O -/O selves/O be/O responsible/O for/O appropriate/O decision-making/O ./O 
In/O the/O ?nan/O -/O cial/O sector/O ,/O such/O automated/O decision-making/O has/O played/O a/O role/O for/O quite/O some/O time/O ./O 
AI/O algorithms/O are/O able/O to/O process/O a/O greater/O number/O of/O ?nancial/O announcements/O ,/O press/O releases/O ,/O and/O other/O information/O than/O any/O human/O trader/O ,/O and/O then/O act/O faster/O upon/O them/O -LRB-/O Mims/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2010/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Services/O like/O Future/DATE Advisor/O similarly/O use/O AI/O to/O offer/O personalised/O ?nancial/O advice/O at/O larger/O scale/O and/O lower/O cost/O ./O 
Even/O the/O work/O of/O soft/O -/O ware/O engineers/O may/O soon/O largely/O be/O computerisable/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O advances/O in/O ML/O allow/O a/O programmer/O to/O leave/O complex/O parameter/O and/O design/O choices/O to/O be/O appropriately/O optimised/O by/O an/O algorithm/O -LRB-/O Hoos/PERSON ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Algorithms/O can/O further/O automatically/O detect/O bugs/O in/O software/O -LRB-/O Hangal/O and/O Lam/LOCATION ,/O 2002/DATE ;/O Livshits/O and/O Zimmermann/PERSON ,/O 2005/DATE ;/O Kimetal./O ,2008/O -RRB-/O ,/O with/O a/O reliability/O that/O humans/O are/O unlikely/O to/O match/O ./O 
Big/O databases/O of/O code/O also/O offer/O the/O eventual/O prospect/O of/O algorithms/O that/O learn/O how/O to/O write/O programs/O to/O satisfy/O speci?cations/O provided/O by/O a/O human/O ./O 
Such/O an/O approach/O is/O likely/O to/O eventually/O improve/O upon/O human/O programmers/O ,/O in/O the/O same/O way/O that/O human-written/O compil/O -/O ers/O eventually/O proved/O inferior/O to/O automatically/O optimised/O compilers/O ./O 
An/O algorithm/O can/O better/O keep/O the/O whole/O of/O a/O program/O in/O working/O memory/O ,/O and/O is/O not/O constrained/O to/O human-intelligible/O code/O ,/O allowing/O for/O holistic/O solutions/O that/O might/O never/O occur/O to/O a/O human/O ./O 
Such/O algo/O -/O rithmic/O improvements/O over/O human/O judgement/O are/O likely/O to/O become/O increasingly/O common/O ./O 
Although/O the/O extent/O of/O these/O developments/O remains/O to/O be/O seen/O ,/O estimates/O by/O MGI/ORGANIZATION -LRB-/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O suggests/O that/O sophisticated/O algorithms/O could/O substitute/O for/O approximately/O 140/NUMBER million/NUMBER full-time/O knowledge/O workers/O worldwide/O ./O 
Hence/O ,/O while/O technological/O progress/O through/O -/O out/O economic/O history/O has/O largely/O been/O con?ned/O to/O the/O mechanisation/O of/O manual/O tasks/O ,/O requiring/O physical/O labour/O ,/O technological/O progress/O in/O the/O twenty-?rst/O century/DURATION can/O be/O expected/O to/O contribute/O to/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O cognitive/O tasks/O ,/O which/O ,/O until/O now/DATE ,/O have/O largely/O remained/O a/O human/O domain/O ./O 
Of/O course/O ,/O many/O occupations/O being/O affected/O by/O these/O developments/O are/O still/O far/O from/O fully/O computerisable/O ,/O meaning/O that/O the/O computerisation/O of/O some/O tasks/O will/O simply/O free-up/O time/O for/O human/O labour/O to/O perform/O other/O tasks/O ./O 
Nonetheless/O ,/O the/O trend/O is/O clear/O :/O computers/O increasingly/O challenge/O human/O labour/O in/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O cognitive/O tasks/O -LRB-/O Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
3.2/NUMBER ./O 
Computerisation/O in/O non-routine/O manual/O tasks/O Mobile/ORGANIZATION robotics/ORGANIZATION provides/O a/O means/O of/O directly/O leveraging/O ML/O tech/O -/O nologies/O to/O aid/O the/O computerisation/O of/O a/O growing/O scope/O of/O manual/O tasks/O ./O 
The/O continued/O technological/O development/O of/O robotic/O hardware/O is/O having/O notable/O impact/O upon/O employment/O :/O over/O the/DATE past/DATE decades/DATE ,/O industrial/O robots/O have/O taken/O on/O the/O routine/O tasks/O of/O most/O operatives/O in/O manufacturing/O ./O 
Now/DATE ,/O however/O ,/O more/O advanced/O robots/O are/O gain/O -/O ing/O enhanced/O sensors/O and/O manipulators/O ,/O allowing/O them/O to/O perform/O non-routine/O manual/O tasks/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O General/ORGANIZATION Electric/ORGANIZATION has/O recently/DATE developed/O robots/O to/O climb/O and/O maintain/O wind/O turbines/O ,/O and/O more/O ?exible/O surgical/O robots/O with/O a/O greater/O range/O of/O motion/O will/O soon/O per/O -/O form/O more/O types/O of/O operations/O -LRB-/O Robotics-VO/O ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
In/O a/O similar/O man/O -/O ner/O ,/O the/O computerisation/O of/O logistics/O is/O being/O aided/O by/O the/O increasing/O cost-effectiveness/O of/O highly/O instrumented/O and/O computerised/O cars/O ./O 
Mass-production/O vehicles/O ,/O such/O as/O the/O Nissan/ORGANIZATION LEAF/O ,/O contain/O on-board/O computers/O and/O advanced/O telecommunication/O equipment/O that/O render/O the/O car/O a/O potentially/O ?y-by-wire/O robot/O ./O 
17/NUMBER Advances/O in/O sensor/O tech/O -/O nology/O mean/O that/O vehicles/O are/O likely/O to/O soon/O be/O augmented/O with/O even/O more/O advanced/O suites/O of/O sensors/O ./O 
These/O will/O permit/O an/O algorith/O -/O mic/O vehicle/O controller/O to/O monitor/O its/O environment/O to/O a/O degree/O that/O exceeds/O the/O capabilities/O of/O any/O human/O driver/O :/O they/O have/O the/O ability/O to/O simultaneously/O look/O both/O forwards/O and/O backwards/O ,/O can/O natively/O inte/O -/O grate/O camera/O ,/O GPS/O and/O LIDAR/O data/O ,/O and/O are/O not/O subject/O to/O distraction/O ./O 
Algorithms/O are/O thus/O potentially/O safer/O and/O more/O effective/O drivers/O than/O humans/O ./O 
The/O big/O data/O provided/O by/O these/O improved/O sensors/O are/O offer/O -/O ing/O solutions/O to/O many/O of/O the/O engineering/O problems/O that/O had/O hin/O -/O dered/O robotic/O development/O in/O the/DATE past/DATE ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O the/O creation/O of/O detailed/O three/NUMBER dimensional/O maps/O of/O road/O networks/O has/O enabled/O autonomous/O vehicle/O navigation/O ;/O most/O notably/O illustrated/O by/O Google/ORGANIZATION 's/O use/O of/O large/O ,/O specialised/O datasets/O collected/O by/O its/O driverless/O cars/O -LRB-/O Guizzo/O ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
It/O is/O now/DATE completely/O feasible/O to/O store/O represen/O -/O tations/O of/O the/O entire/O road/O network/O on-board/O a/O car/O ,/O dramatically/O simplifying/O the/O navigation/O problem/O ./O 
Algorithms/O that/O could/O perform/O navigation/O throughout/O the/O changing/O seasons/O ,/O particularly/O after/O snow/O -/O fall/DATE ,/O have/O been/O viewed/O as/O a/O substantial/O challenge/O ./O 
However/O ,/O the/O big/O data/O approach/O can/O answer/O this/O by/O storing/O records/O from/O the/O last/O time/O snow/O fell/O ,/O against/O which/O the/O vehicle/O 's/O current/DATE environment/O can/O be/O compared/O -LRB-/O Churchill/ORGANIZATION and/O Newman/PERSON ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
ML/O approaches/O have/O also/O been/O developed/O to/O identify/O unprecedented/O changes/O to/O a/O par/O -/O ticular/O piece/O of/O the/O road/O network/O ,/O such/O as/O roadworks/O -LRB-/O Mathibela/O et/O al./O ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O emerging/O technology/O will/O affect/O a/O variety/O of/O logis/O -/O tics/O jobs/O ./O 
Agricultural/O vehicles/O ,/O forklifts/O and/O cargo-handling/O vehicles/O are/O imminently/O automatable/O ,/O and/O hospitals/O are/O already/O employing/O autonomous/O robots/O to/O transport/O food/O ,/O prescriptions/O and/O samples/O -LRB-/O Bloss/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O computerisation/O of/O mining/O vehicles/O is/O further/O being/O pursued/O by/O companies/O such/O as/O Rio/LOCATION Tinto/LOCATION ,/O seeking/O to/O replace/O labour/O in/O Australian/O mine-sites/O ./O 
18/NUMBER With/O improved/O sensors/O ,/O robots/O are/O capable/O of/O producing/O goods/O with/O higher/O quality/O and/O reliability/O than/O human/O labour/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O El/ORGANIZATION Dulze/ORGANIZATION ,/O a/O Spanish/O food/O processor/O ,/O now/DATE uses/O robotics/O to/O pick/O up/O heads/O of/O lettuce/O from/O a/O conveyor/O belt/O ,/O rejecting/O heads/O that/O do/O not/O comply/O with/O company/O standards/O ./O 
This/O is/O achieved/O by/O measuring/O their/O density/O and/O replacing/O them/O on/O the/O belt/O -LRB-/O IFR/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2012a/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Advanced/O sen/O -/O sors/O further/O allow/O robots/O to/O recognise/O patterns/O ./O 
Baxter/O ,/O a/O 22,000/NUMBER USD/O general-purpose/O robot/O ,/O provides/O a/O well-known/O example/O ./O 
The/O robot/O features/O an/O LCD/O display/O screen/O displaying/O a/O pair/O of/O eyes/O that/O take/O on/O different/O expressions/O depending/O on/O the/O situation/O ./O 
When/O the/O robot/O is/O ?rst/O installed/O or/O needs/O to/O learn/O a/O new/O pattern/O ,/O no/O programming/O is/O required/O ./O 
A/O human/O worker/O simply/O guides/O the/O robot/O arms/O through/O the/O motions/O that/O will/O be/O needed/O for/O the/O task/O ./O 
Baxter/O then/O memorises/O these/O patterns/O and/O can/O communicate/O that/O it/O has/O understood/O its/O new/O instructions/O ./O 
While/O the/O physical/O ?exibility/O of/O Baxter/LOCATION is/O limited/O to/O per/O -/O forming/O simple/O operations/O such/O as/O picking/O up/O objects/O and/O moving/O them/O ,/O different/O standard/O attachments/O can/O be/O installed/O on/O its/O arms/O ,/O 17A/O ?y-by-wire/O robot/O is/O a/O robot/O that/O is/O controllable/O by/O a/O remote/O computer/O .18/NUMBER Rio/ORGANIZATION Tinto/ORGANIZATION 's/O computerisation/O efforts/O are/O advertised/O at/O http://www.mineofthefuture/O ./O 
com.au/O ./O 
C./PERSON Frey/PERSON ,/O M./ORGANIZATION Osborne/ORGANIZATION //ORGANIZATION Technological/ORGANIZATION Forecasting/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Change/ORGANIZATION 114/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2017/DATE -RRB-/O 254/NUMBER --/O 280261/NUMBER allowing/O Baxter/PERSON to/O perform/O a/O relatively/O broad/O scope/O of/O manual/O tasks/O at/O low/O cost/O -LRB-/O MGI/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Technological/O advances/O are/O contributing/O to/O declining/O costs/O in/O robotics/O ./O 
Over/O the/DATE past/DATE decades/DATE ,/O robot/O prices/O have/O fallen/O about/O 10/PERCENT %/PERCENT annually/SET and/O are/O expected/O to/O decline/O at/O an/O even/O faster/O pace/O in/O the/DATE near/DATE future/DATE -LRB-/O MGI/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Industrial/O robots/O ,/O with/O features/O enabled/O by/O machine/O vision/O and/O high-precision/O dexterity/O ,/O which/O typically/O cost/O 100,000/NUMBER to/O 150,000/NUMBER USD/O ,/O will/O be/O available/O for/O 50,000/NUMBER to/O 75,000/NUMBER USD/O in/O the/DATE next/DATE decade/DATE ,/O with/O higher/O levels/O of/O intelligence/O and/O additional/O capabilities/O -LRB-/O IFR/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2012b/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Declining/O robot/O prices/O will/O inevitably/O place/O them/O within/O reach/O of/O more/O users/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O in/O China/LOCATION ,/O employ/O -/O ers/O are/O increasingly/O incentivised/O to/O substitute/O robots/O for/O labour/O ,/O as/O wages/O and/O living/O standards/O are/O rising/O --/O Foxconn/ORGANIZATION ,/O a/O Chinese/O contract/O manufacturer/O that/O employs/O 1.2/NUMBER million/NUMBER workers/O ,/O is/O now/DATE investing/O in/O robots/O to/O assemble/O products/O such/O as/O the/O Apple/O iPhone/O -LRB-/O Markoff/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
According/O to/O the/O International/ORGANIZATION Federation/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Robotics/ORGANIZATION ,/O robot/O sales/O in/O China/LOCATION grew/O by/O more/O than/O 50/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/U_TEMPPRED 2011/DATE and/O are/O expected/O to/O increase/O further/O ./O 
Globally/O ,/O industrial/O robot/O sales/O reached/O a/O record/O 166,000/NUMBER units/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2011/DATE ,/O a/O 40/PERCENT %/PERCENT year-on-year/O increase/O -LRB-/O IFR/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2012b/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Most/O likely/O ,/O there/O will/O be/O even/O faster/O growth/O ahead/O as/O low-priced/O general-purpose/O models/O ,/O such/O as/O Baxter/LOCATION ,/O are/O adopted/O in/O simple/O man/O -/O ufacturing/O and/O service/O work/O ./O 
Expanding/O technological/O capabilities/O and/O declining/O costs/O will/O make/O entirely/O new/O uses/O for/O robots/O possible/O ./O 
Robots/O will/O likely/O con/O -/O tinue/O to/O take/O on/O an/O increasing/O set/O of/O manual/O tasks/O in/O manufacturing/O ,/O packing/O ,/O construction/O ,/O maintenance/O ,/O and/O agriculture/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O robots/O are/O already/O performing/O many/O simple/O service/O tasks/O such/O as/O vacuuming/O ,/O mopping/O ,/O lawn/O mowing/O ,/O and/O gutter/O cleaning/O --/O the/O mar/DATE -/O ket/O for/O personal/O and/O household/O service/O robots/O is/O growing/O by/O about/O 20/PERCENT %/PERCENT annually/SET -LRB-/O MGI/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
Meanwhile/O ,/O commercial/O service/O robots/O are/O now/DATE able/O to/O perform/O more/O complex/O tasks/O in/O food/O preparation/O ,/O health/O care/O ,/O commercial/O cleaning/O ,/O and/O elderly/O care/O -LRB-/O Robotics-VO/O ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
As/O robot/O costs/O decline/O and/O technological/O capabilities/O expand/O ,/O robots/O can/O thus/O be/O expected/O to/O gradually/O substitute/O for/O labour/O in/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O low-wage/O service/O occupations/O ,/O where/O most/O US/O job/O growth/O has/O occurred/O over/O the/DATE past/DATE decades/DATE -LRB-/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O means/O that/O many/O low-wage/O manual/O jobs/O that/O have/O been/O previ/ORGANIZATION -/O ously/O protected/O from/O computerisation/O could/O diminish/O over/O time/O ./O 
3.3/NUMBER ./O 
The/O task/O model/O revisited/O The/O task/O model/O of/O Autor/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O has/O delivered/O intuitive/O and/O accurate/O predictions/O in/O that/O -LRB-/O a/O -RRB-/O computers/O are/O more/O substitutable/O for/O human/O labour/O in/O routine/O relative/O to/O non-routine/O tasks/O ;/O and/O -LRB-/O b/O -RRB-/O a/O greater/O intensity/O of/O routine/O inputs/O increases/O the/O marginal/O productiv/O -/O ity/O of/O non-routine/O inputs/O ./O 
Accordingly/O ,/O computers/O have/O served/O as/O a/O substitute/O for/O labour/O for/O many/O routine/O tasks/O ,/O while/O exhibiting/O strong/O complementarities/O with/O labour/O performing/O cognitive/O non/routine/O tasks/O ./O 
19/NUMBER Yet/O the/O premises/O about/O what/O computers/O do/O have/O recently/DATE expanded/O ./O 
Computer/O capital/O can/O now/DATE equally/O substitute/O for/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O tasks/O commonly/O de?ned/O as/O non-routine/O -LRB-/O Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O McAfee/ORGANIZATION ,/O 2011/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O meaning/O that/O the/O task/O model/O will/O not/O hold/O in/O predict/O -/O ing/O the/O impact/O of/O computerisation/O on/O the/O task/O content/O of/O employ/O -/O ment/O in/O the/O twenty-?rst/O century/DURATION ./O 
While/O focusing/O on/O the/O substitution/O effects/O of/O recent/O technological/O progress/O ,/O we/O build/O on/O the/O task/O model/O by/O deriving/O several/O factors/O that/O we/O expect/O will/O determine/O the/O extent/O of/O computerisation/O in/O non-routine/O tasks/O ./O 
The/O task/O model/O assumes/O for/O tractability/O an/O aggregate/O ,/O constant/O -/O returns-to-scale/O ,/O Cobb-Douglas/O production/O function/O of/O the/O form/O Q/O =-LRB-/O L/O S+C/O -RRB-/O 1/NUMBER ?/O b/O Lb/O NS/O ,/O b/O ?/O -LSB-/O 0/NUMBER ,/O 1/NUMBER -RSB-/O ,/O -LRB-/O 1/NUMBER -RRB-/O 19The/O model/O does/O not/O predict/O any/O substantial/O substitution/O or/O complementarity/O with/O non-routine/O manual/O tasks/O ./O 
where/O L/O SandL/O NS/O are/O susceptible/O and/O non-susceptible/O labour/O inputs/O and/O Cis/ORGANIZATION computer/O capital/O ./O 
Computer/O capital/O is/O supplied/O perfectly/O elastically/O at/O market/O price/O per/O e?ciency/O unit/O ,/O where/O the/O market/O price/O is/O falling/O exogenously/O with/O time/O due/O to/O technological/O progress/O ./O 
It/O fur/O -/O ther/O assumes/O income-maximising/O workers/O ,/O with/O heterogeneous/O pro-/O ductivity/O endowments/O in/O both/O susceptible/O and/O non-susceptible/O tasks/O ./O 
Their/O task/O supply/O will/O respond/O elastically/O to/O relative/O wage/O levels/O ,/O meaning/O that/O workers/O will/O reallocate/O their/O labour/O supply/O according/O to/O their/O comparative/O advantage/O as/O in/O Roy/O -LRB-/O 1951/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
With/O expanding/O com/O -/O putational/O capabilities/O ,/O resulting/O from/O technological/O advances/O ,/O and/O a/O falling/O market/O price/O of/O computing/O ,/O workers/O in/O susceptible/O tasks/O will/O thus/O reallocate/O to/O non-susceptible/O tasks/O ./O 
The/O above/O described/O simple/O model/O differs/O from/O the/O task/O model/O of/O Autor/O et/O al./O -LRB-/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O inthatL/O NS/O is/O not/O con?ned/O to/O routine/O labour/O inputs/O ./O 
This/O is/O because/O recent/O developments/O in/O ML/O and/O MR/O ,/O build/O -/O ing/O upon/O big/O data/O ,/O allow/O for/O pattern/O recognition/O ,/O and/O thus/O enable/O computer/O capital/O to/O rapidly/O substitute/O for/O labour/O across/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O non-routine/O tasks/O ./O 
Yet/O some/O inhibiting/O engineering/O bottlenecks/O to/O computerisation/O persist/O ./O 
Beyond/O these/O bottlenecks/O ,/O however/O ,/O we/O argue/O that/O it/O is/O largely/O already/O technologically/O possible/O to/O automate/O almost/O any/O task/O ,/O provided/O that/O su?cient/O amounts/O of/O data/O are/O gath/O -/O ered/O for/O pattern/O recognition/O ./O 
Our/O model/O thus/O predicts/O that/O the/O pace/O at/O which/O these/O bottlenecks/O can/O be/O overcome/O will/O determine/O the/O extent/O of/O computerisation/O in/O the/O twenty-?rst/O century/DURATION ./O 
Hence/O ,/O in/O short/O ,/O while/O the/O task/O model/O predicts/O that/O comput/O -/O ers/O for/O labour/O substitution/O will/O be/O con?ned/O to/O routine/O tasks/O ,/O our/O model/O predicts/O that/O computerisation/O can/O be/O extended/O to/O any/O non/O -/O routine/O task/O that/O is/O not/O subject/O to/O any/O engineering/O bottlenecks/O to/O computerisation/O ./O 
These/O bottlenecks/O thus/O set/O the/O boundaries/O for/O the/O computerisation/O of/O non-routine/O tasks/O ./O 
Drawing/O upon/O the/O ML/O and/O MR/O literature/O ,/O and/O a/O workshop/O held/O at/O the/O Oxford/ORGANIZATION University/ORGANIZATION Engineering/ORGANIZATION Sciences/ORGANIZATION Department/ORGANIZATION ,/O we/O identify/O several/O engineering/O bottlenecks/O ,/O corresponding/O to/O three/NUMBER task/O categories/O ./O 
According/O to/O these/O ?ndings/O ,/O non-susceptible/O labour/O inputs/O can/O be/O described/O as/O ,/O L/O NS/O =/O n/O i/O =/O 1/NUMBER -LRB-/O LPM/O ,/O i/O +/O L/O C/O ,/O i/O +/O L/O SI/O ,/O i/O -RRB-/O -LRB-/O 2/NUMBER -RRB-/O where/O L/O PM/O ,/O LCand/O L/O SIare/O labour/O inputs/O into/O perception/O and/O manipu/O -/O lation/O tasks/O ,/O creative/O intelligence/O tasks/O ,/O and/O social/O intelligence/O tasks/O ./O 
We/O note/O that/O some/O related/O engineering/O bottlenecks/O can/O be/O par/O -/O tially/O alleviated/O by/O the/O simpli?cation/O of/O tasks/O ./O 
One/NUMBER generic/O way/O of/O achieving/O this/O is/O to/O reduce/O the/O variation/O between/O task/O iterations/O ./O 
As/O a/O prototypical/O example/O ,/O consider/O the/O factory/O assembly/O line/O ,/O turning/O the/O non-routine/O tasks/O of/O the/O artisan/O shop/O into/O repetitive/O routine/O tasks/O performed/O by/O unskilled/O factory/O workers/O ./O 
A/O more/O recent/O example/O is/O the/O computerisation/O of/O non-routine/O manual/O tasks/O in/O construction/O ./O 
On-site/O construction/O tasks/O typically/O demand/O a/O high/O degree/O of/O adapt/O -/O ability/O ,/O so/O as/O to/O accommodate/O work/O environments/O that/O are/O typically/O irregularly/O laid/O out/O ,/O and/O vary/O according/O to/O weather/O ./O 
Prefabrication/O ,/O in/O which/O the/O construction/O object/O is/O partially/O assembled/O in/O a/O fac/O -/O tory/O before/O being/O transported/O to/O the/O construction/O site/O ,/O provides/O a/O way/O of/O largely/O removing/O the/O requirement/O for/O adaptability/O ./O 
It/O allows/O many/O construction/O tasks/O to/O be/O performed/O by/O robots/O under/O con/O -/O trolled/O conditions/O that/O eliminate/O task/O variability/O --/O a/O method/O that/O is/O becoming/O increasingly/O widespread/O ,/O particularly/O in/O Japan/LOCATION -LRB-/O Barlow/PERSON and/O Ozaki/PERSON ,/O 2005/DATE ;/O Linner/PERSON and/O Bock/PERSON ,/O 2012/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O extent/O of/O computerisation/O in/O the/O twenty-?rst/O century/DURATION will/O thus/O partly/O depend/O on/O innovative/O approaches/O to/O task/O restructuring/O ./O 
In/O the/O remainder/O of/O this/O section/O we/O examine/O the/O engineering/O bottlenecks/O related/O to/O the/O above/O mentioned/O task/O categories/O ,/O each/O in/O turn/O ./O 
262C/O ./O 
Frey/O ,/O M./ORGANIZATION Osborne/ORGANIZATION //ORGANIZATION Technological/ORGANIZATION Forecasting/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION Social/ORGANIZATION Change/ORGANIZATION 114/NUMBER -LRB-/O 2017/DATE -RRB-/O 254/NUMBER --/O 280/NUMBER 3.3.1/O ./O 
Perception/O and/O manipulation/O tasks/O Robots/O are/O still/O unable/O to/O match/O the/O depth/O and/O breadth/O of/O human/O perception/O ./O 
While/O basic/O geometric/O identi?cation/O is/O reason/O -/O ably/O mature/O ,/O enabled/O by/O the/O rapid/O development/O of/O sophisticated/O sensors/O and/O lasers/O ,/O signi?cant/O challenges/O remain/O for/O more/O complex/O perception/O tasks/O ,/O such/O as/O identifying/O objects/O and/O their/O properties/O in/O a/O cluttered/O ?eld/O of/O view/O ./O 
As/O such/O ,/O tasks/O that/O relate/O to/O an/O unstructured/O work/O environment/O can/O make/O jobs/O less/O susceptible/O to/O computeri/O -/O sation/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O most/O homes/O are/O unstructured/O ,/O requiring/O the/O identi?cation/O of/O a/O plurality/O of/O irregular/O objects/O and/O containing/O many/O cluttered/O spaces/O which/O inhibit/O the/O mobility/O of/O wheeled/O objects/O ./O 
Con/O -/O versely/O ,/O supermarkets/O ,/O factories/O ,/O warehouses/O ,/O airports/O and/O hospitals/O have/O been/O designed/O for/O large/O wheeled/O objects/O ,/O making/O it/O easier/O for/O robots/O to/O navigate/O in/O performing/O non-routine/O manual/O tasks/O ./O 
Percep/O -/O tion/O problems/O can/O ,/O however/O ,/O sometimes/O be/O sidestepped/O by/O clever/O task/O design/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O Kiva/ORGANIZATION Systems/ORGANIZATION ,/O acquired/O by/O Amazon.com/ORGANIZATION in/U_TEMPPRED 2012/DATE ,/O solved/O the/O problem/O of/O warehouse/O navigation/O by/O simply/O plac/O -/O ing/O bar-code/O stickers/O on/O the/O ?oor/O ,/O informing/O robots/O of/O their/O precise/O location/O -LRB-/O Guizzo/O ,/O 2008/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O di?culty/O of/O perception/O has/O rami?cations/O for/O manipulation/O tasks/O ,/O and/O ,/O in/O particular/O ,/O the/O handling/O of/O irregular/O objects/O ,/O for/O which/O robots/O are/O yet/O to/O reach/O human/O levels/O of/O aptitude/O ./O 
This/O has/O been/O evidenced/O in/O the/O development/O of/O robots/O that/O interact/O with/O human/O objects/O and/O environments/O ./O 
While/O advances/O have/O been/O made/O ,/O solu/O -/O tions/O tend/O to/O be/O unreliable/O over/O the/O myriad/O small/O variations/O on/O a/O single/O task/O ,/O repeated/O thousands/O of/O times/O a/DURATION day/DURATION ,/O that/O many/O applica/O -/O tions/O require/O ./O 
A/O related/O challenge/O is/O failure/O recovery/O --/O i.e.identifying/O and/O rectifying/O the/O mistakes/O of/O the/O robot/O when/O it/O has/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O dropped/O an/O object/O ./O 
Manipulation/O is/O also/O limited/O by/O the/O di?culties/O of/O planning/O out/O the/O sequence/O of/O actions/O required/O to/O move/O an/O object/O from/O one/NUMBER place/O to/O another/O ./O 
There/O are/O yet/O further/O problems/O in/O design/O -/O ing/O manipulators/O that/O ,/O like/O human/O limbs/O ,/O are/O soft/O ,/O have/O compliant/O dynamics/O and/O provide/O useful/O tactile/O feedback/O ./O 
Most/O industrial/O manip/O -/O ulation/O makes/O uses/O of/O workarounds/O to/O these/O challenges/O -LRB-/O Brown/PERSON et/O al./O ,/O 2010/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O but/O these/O approaches/O are/O nonetheless/O limited/O to/O a/O narrow/O range/O of/O tasks/O ./O 
The/O main/O challenges/O to/O robotic/O computerisation/O ,/O per/O -/O ception/O and/O manipulation/O ,/O thus/O largely/O remain/O and/O are/O unlikely/O to/O be/O fully/O resolved/O in/O the/DATE next/DATE decade/DATE or/O two/NUMBER -LRB-/O Robotics-VO/O ,/O 2013/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
3.3.2/O ./O 
Creative/O intelligence/O tasks/O The/O psychological/O processes/O underlying/O human/O creativity/O are/O dif/O -/O ?cult/O to/O specify/O ./O 
According/O to/O Boden/PERSON -LRB-/O 2003/DATE -RRB-/O ,/O creativity/O is/O the/O ability/O to/O come/O up/O with/O ideas/O or/O artifacts/O that/O are/O novel/O and/O valuable/O ./O 
