Extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O :/O The/O global/O ,/O regional/O ,/O and/O investment/O implications/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORDINAL Industrial/O Revolution/O January/DATE 2016/DATE UBS/O White/O Paper/O for/O the/ORGANIZATION World/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Forum/ORGANIZATION Annual/ORGANIZATION Meeting/ORGANIZATION 2016/ORGANIZATION World/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Forum/ORGANIZATION 3/ORGANIZATION Foreword/ORGANIZATION The/O global/O economy/O is/O on/O the/O cusp/O of/O profound/O changes/O that/O are/O com/O -/O parable/O in/O magnitude/O to/O the/O advent/O of/O the/O first/ORDINAL industrial/O revolution/O ,/O the/O development/O of/O assembly/O line/O production/O ,/O or/O the/O invention/O of/O the/O micro-chip/O ./O 
Technological/O advances/O are/O permitting/O ever/O greater/O levels/O of/O automation/O ./O 
Meanwhile/O ,/O the/O near/O universal/O ownership/O of/O smart/O devices/O in/O many/O parts/O of/O the/O world/O is/O leading/O to/O a/O degree/O of/O interconnectedness/O that/O was/O previously/DATE unimaginable/O ./O 
These/O developments/O ,/O which/O we/O believe/O are/O part/O of/O a/O technology-driven/O Fourth/ORDINAL Industrial/O Revolution/O ,/O have/O significant/O implications/O for/O investors/O ,/O the/O global/O economy/O and/O the/O relative/O competitiveness/O of/O developed/O and/O emerging/O nations/O ./O 
Thus/O ,/O these/O changes/O are/O an/O interesting/O and/O impor/O -/O tant/O topic/O for/O discussion/O at/O the/ORGANIZATION World/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Forum/ORGANIZATION ./O 
In/O this/O White/ORGANIZATION Paper/ORGANIZATION ,/O we/O have/O tried/O to/O put/O recent/O technological/O shifts/O in/O a/O broader/O historical/O context/O ./O 
Previous/O industrial/O revolutions/O have/O been/O driven/O by/O rapid/O advances/O in/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ,/O starting/O with/O the/O technologies/O that/O launched/O the/O First/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION in/O 18th/DATE century/DATE England/DATE through/O to/O the/O exponential/O increases/O in/O computing/O power/O of/O recent/DURATION decades/DURATION ./O 
The/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION is/O based/O on/O the/O same/O two/NUMBER forces/O ./O 
The/O first/ORDINAL is/O extreme/O automation/O ,/O the/O product/O of/O a/O growing/O role/O for/O robotics/O and/O artificial/O intelligence/O in/O business/O ,/O government/O and/O private/O life/O ./O 
The/O second/ORDINAL ,/O extreme/O connectivity/O ,/O annihilates/O distance/O and/O time/O as/O obstacles/O to/O ever/O deeper/O ,/O faster/O communication/O between/O and/O among/O humans/O and/O machines/O ./O 
These/O changes/O will/O have/O very/O different/O effects/O on/O nations/O ,/O businesses/O and/O individuals/O ./O 
Automation/O will/O continue/O to/O put/O downward/O pressure/O on/O the/O wages/O of/O the/O low/O skilled/O and/O is/O starting/O to/O impinge/O on/O the/O employment/O prospects/O of/O middle/O skilled/O workers/O ./O 
By/O contrast/O the/O potential/O returns/O to/O highly/O skilled/O and/O more/O adaptable/O workers/O are/O increasing/O ./O 
Among/O corpo/O rations/O ,/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O traditional/O businesses/O --/O especially/O those/O that/O act/O as/O intermediaries/O --/O can/O be/O expected/O to/O suffer/O ./O 
Many/O labor/O intensive/O firms/O should/O be/O able/O to/O boost/O profit/O margins/O as/O they/O substitute/O costly/O workers/O for/O cheaper/O robots/O or/O intelligent/O software/O ./O 
And/O a/O range/O of/O entirely/O new/O companies/O and/O sectors/O will/O spring/DATE into/O existence/O ./O 
For/O nations/O ,/O the/O largest/O gains/O from/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION are/O likely/O to/O be/O captured/O by/O those/O with/O the/O most/O flexible/O economies/O ,/O adding/O a/O further/O incentive/O for/O governments/O to/O trim/O red/O tape/O and/O barriers/O to/O business/O ./O 
4/NUMBER At/O UBS/ORGANIZATION we/O believe/O in/O embracing/O change/O ,/O rather/O than/O fighting/O it/O ./O 
Our/O technol/O ogy/O lab/O in/O London/LOCATION ,/O established/O in/O early/DATE 2015/DATE ,/O is/O already/O exploring/O a/O range/O of/O innovations/O ./O 
These/O include/O blockchain/O ,/O the/O shared/O ledger/O system/O that/O under/O -/O pins/O Bitcoin/O and/O offers/O the/O potential/O to/O enhance/O transparency/O and/O trust/O ,/O while/O reducing/O transaction/O costs/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O the/O UBS/ORGANIZATION Future/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Finance/ORGANIZATION Chal/ORGANIZATION -/O lenge/O aims/O to/O identify/O disruptive/O ideas/O and/O support/O their/O commercialization/O ./O 
Last/DATE year/DATE 's/O competition/O drew/O 600/NUMBER participants/O from/O 52/NUMBER countries/O ./O 
In/O the/O same/O vein/O ,/O we/O hope/O this/O White/ORGANIZATION Paper/ORGANIZATION will/O stimulate/O debate/O as/O well/O as/O offering/O useful/O insights/O into/O the/O forces/O that/O are/O reshaping/O global/O business/O ./O 
Your/O sincerely/O ,/O Axel/PERSON A./PERSON Weber/PERSON Sergio/PERSON P./PERSON Ermotti/PERSON Chairman/O of/O the/O Group/ORGANIZATION Chief/ORGANIZATION Board/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Directors/ORGANIZATION Executive/ORGANIZATION Officer/ORGANIZATION World/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Forum/ORGANIZATION 5/ORGANIZATION Authors/ORGANIZATION Bhanu/ORGANIZATION Baweja/ORGANIZATION ,/O Head/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Emerging/ORGANIZATION Market/ORGANIZATION CrossAsset/ORGANIZATION Strategy/ORGANIZATION ,/O UBS/ORGANIZATION Investment/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION Paul/ORGANIZATION Donovan/ORGANIZATION ,/ORGANIZATION Deputy/ORGANIZATION Head/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Global/ORGANIZATION Economics/ORGANIZATION ,/O UBS/ORGANIZATION Investment/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION Mark/ORGANIZATION Haefele/ORGANIZATION ,/O Global/O Chief/O Investment/O Officer/O ,/O UBS/ORGANIZATION Wealth/ORGANIZATION Management/ORGANIZATION &/ORGANIZATION UBS/ORGANIZATION Wealth/ORGANIZATION Management/ORGANIZATION Americas/ORGANIZATION Lutfey/ORGANIZATION Siddiqi/ORGANIZATION ,/O Global/O Head/O ,/O Emerging/O Markets/O FX/O ,/O Rates/O ,/O and/O Credit/O ,/O UBS/ORGANIZATION Investment/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION Simon/ORGANIZATION Smiles/ORGANIZATION ,/O Chief/O Investment/O Officer/O --/O UHNW/O ,/O UBS/ORGANIZATION Wealth/ORGANIZATION Management/ORGANIZATION With/ORGANIZATION thanks/O to/O Matthew/PERSON Carter/PERSON Kiran/PERSON Ganesh/PERSON Josh/PERSON Holcroft/PERSON Marco/PERSON Spinelli/PERSON Christopher/PERSON Swann/PERSON 6/NUMBER Contents/O //O Executive/O Summary/O P./O 10/NUMBER 1/NUMBER ./O 
A/O brief/O history/O of/O industrial/O revolutions/O ?/O Prior/O industrial/O revolutions/O have/O centered/O around/O improvements/O in/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
?/O The/O First/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION introduced/O early/O automation/O through/O machinery/O ,/O and/O boosted/O intra-national/O connections/O through/O the/O building/O of/O bridges/O and/O railways/O ./O 
?/O The/O Second/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION began/O when/O automation/O enabled/O mass/O production/O and/O fostered/O more/O efficient/O ,/O productive/O connectivity/O via/O the/O division/O of/O labor/O ./O 
?/O The/ORGANIZATION Third/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION was/O propelled/O by/O the/O rise/O of/O the/O digital/O age/O ,/O of/O more/O sophisticated/O automation/O ,/O and/O of/O increasing/O connectivity/O between/O and/O within/O humanity/O and/O the/O natural/O world/O ./O 
?/O The/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION is/O being/O driven/O by/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
A/O special/O feature/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION will/O be/O the/O wider/O implementation/O of/O artificial/O intelligence/O ./O 
P./O 14/NUMBER 2/NUMBER ./O 
What/O are/O the/O potential/O global/O economic/O consequences/O ?/O 
?/O Polarization/O of/O the/O labor/O force/O as/O low/O skill/O jobs/O continue/O to/O be/O automated/O an/O this/O trend/O increasingly/O spreads/O to/O middle/O skill/O jobs/O ./O 
This/O implies/O higher/O potential/O levels/O of/O inequality/O in/O the/O short/O run/O ,/O and/O a/O need/O for/O labor/O market/O flexibility/O to/O harness/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION benefits/O in/O the/O long/O run/O ./O 
?/O Greater/O returns/O accruing/O to/O those/O with/O already/O high/O savings/O rates/O ./O 
In/O the/O short/O run/O ,/O this/O could/O exacerbate/O inequality/O via/O relatively/O lower/O borrowing/O costs/O and/O higher/O asset/O valuations/O ./O 
?/O As/O the/O issuer/O of/O the/O world/O 's/O reserve/O currency/O ,/O the/O US/LOCATION '/O competitive/O advantages/O ,/O sitting/O at/O the/O heart/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ,/O could/O tighten/O effective/O monetary/O conditions/O among/O US/LOCATION dollar/O linked/O economies/O ./O 
?/O The/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION increases/O the/O magnitude/O and/O probability/O of/O tail/O risks/O related/O to/O cybersecurity/O and/O geopolitics/O ,/O but/O may/O spur/O regional/O action/O to/O invest/O and/O embrace/ORGANIZATION Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION benefits/O ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O P./O 21/NUMBER 3/NUMBER ./O 
Who/O will/O be/O the/O regional/O winners/O and/O losers/O ?/O 
?/O ``/O Flexibility/O ''/O will/O be/O key/O to/O success/O in/O the/O Fourth/ORDINAL Industrial/O Revolution/O ;/O economies/O with/O the/O most/O flexible/O labor/O markets/O ,/O educational/O systems/O ,/O infrastructure/O ,/O and/O legal/O systems/O are/O likely/O to/O be/O relative/O beneficiaries/O ./O 
?/O Developed/O economies/O are/O likely/O to/O be/O relative/O winners/O at/O this/O stage/O ,/O whereas/O developing/O economies/O face/O greater/O challenges/O as/O their/O abundance/O of/O low/O skill/O labor/O ceases/O to/O be/O an/O advantage/O and/O becomes/O more/O of/O a/O headwind/O ./O 
?/O Emerging/O markets/O in/O their/O demographic/O prime/O may/O find/O that/O extreme/O automation/O displaces/O low/O skill/O workers/O ,/O but/O that/O their/O limited/O technology/O infrastructures/O do/O not/O allow/O them/O to/O reap/O the/O full/O benefits/O of/O extreme/O connectivity/O ./O 
P./O 28/NUMBER 4/NUMBER ./O 
What/O are/O the/O investment/O consequences/O ?/O 
?/O Given/O current/DATE assessments/O of/O relative/O competitiveness/O ,/O emerging/O markets/O may/O be/O less/O well/O placed/O to/O profit/O from/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION benefits/O ,/O relative/O to/O developed/O markets/O ./O 
?/O We/O expect/O further/O disruption/O to/O traditional/O industries/O from/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
?/O Big/O data/O beneficiaries/O include/O firms/O that/O harness/O big/O data/O to/O cut/O costs/O or/O target/O sales/O ;/O firms/O that/O automate/O big/O data/O analysis/O ,/O and/O firms/O that/O keep/O big/O data/O secure/O ./O 
?/O Blockchain/O applications/O could/O benefit/O firms/O that/O use/O them/O to/O automate/O processes/O securely/O ,/O to/O cut/O out/O costly/O intermediaries/O ,/O and/O to/O protect/O intellectual/O property/O ./O 
7/NUMBER 8/NUMBER Automation/O and/O Connectivity/O Industrial/O Revolutions/O mechanical/O production/O mass/O production/O steam/O power/O energy/O electrical/O energy/O 2/NUMBER nd/O 1/DATE st/DATE 1870/DATE 17/DATE 8/DATE 4/DATE World/O Economic/O Forum/O 9/NUMBER electronics/O artificial/O intelligence/O IT/O big/O data/O 3/NUMBER rd/O 4/NUMBER th/O 19/NUMBER 69/NUMBER To/O d/O a/O y/O 10/NUMBER 1/NUMBER ./O 
A/O brief/O history/O of/O industrial/O revolutions/O We/O have/O characterized/O the/O prior/O three/NUMBER industrial/O revolutions/O using/O the/O timeline/O proposed/O by/O Nicholas/PERSON Davis/PERSON ,/O the/ORGANIZATION World/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Forum/ORGANIZATION 's/ORGANIZATION Head/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Society/ORGANIZATION and/O Innovation/O ./O 
Our/O cen/O -/O tral/O view/O is/O that/O all/O industrial/O revolutions/O involve/O advances/O in/O two/NUMBER fields/O --/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
The/O First/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION The/ORGANIZATION First/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ushered/O in/O early/O automation/O via/O machinery/O ,/O in/O lieu/O of/O agricultural/O inputs/O ./O 
1784/DATE saw/O Henry/PERSON Cort/PERSON 's/O invention/O in/O England/LOCATION of/O the/O ``/O puddling/O ''/O process/O that/O turned/O pig/O iron/O into/O wrought/O iron/O ./O 
This/O was/O seen/O by/O economic/O historians/O as/O a/O key/O inflexion/O point/O of/O the/O First/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ,/O marking/O the/O beginnings/O of/O automation/O ./O 
Mechanization/O became/O a/O key/O element/O of/O economic/O devel/O -/O opment/O ,/O leading/O to/O a/O profound/O split/O between/O the/O East/LOCATION and/O West/O that/O has/O only/O recently/DATE started/O to/O converge/O ./O 
Manufacturing/O progress/O and/O the/O nascent/O use/O of/O higher/O energy-intensive/O fuels/O such/O as/O coal/O and/O petrol/O followed/O ,/O paving/O the/O way/O for/O steam/O power/O and/O locomotives/O ./O 
This/O in/O turn/O spurred/O both/O a/O connectivity/O revolution/O via/O wider/O travel/O ,/O and/O a/O surge/O in/O the/O construction/O of/O infrastructure/O projects/O ,/O including/O bridges/O ,/O tunnels/O ,/O aqueducts/O ,/O and/O ports/O ./O 
We/O also/O note/O that/O an/O agricultural/O revolution/O supported/O by/O the/O inclu/O -/O sion/O of/O crop/O rotation/O and/O selective/O breeding/O boosted/O farm/O productivity/O and/O helped/O contain/O the/O costs/O of/O labor-intensive/O foodstuffs/O ./O 
The/O Second/ORDINAL Industrial/O Revolution/O The/O Second/ORDINAL Industrial/O Revolution/O -LRB-/O typically/O seen/O by/O historians/O as/O beginning/O around/O 1870/DATE ,/DATE the/DATE second/DATE half/DATE of/DATE the/DATE ``/DATE long/DATE 19th/DATE century/DATE ''/O -RRB-/O was/O characterized/O by/O three/NUMBER factors/O :/O higher/O levels/O of/O automation/O via/O the/O development/O of/O mass/O produc/O -/O tion/O ;/O more/O efficient/O connectivity/O in/O production/O via/O the/O divi/O -/O sion/O of/O labor/O ;/O and/O further/O progress/O in/O the/O use/O of/O energy/O sources/O such/O as/O electricity/O and/O petroleum/O ./O 
While/O at/O first/ORDINAL the/O Second/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION was/O limited/O to/O ``/O within/O company/O ''/O supply/O chains/O ,/O automation/O and/O connec/O -/O tivity/O gains/O allowed/O supply/O chains/O to/O evolve/O into/O the/O complex/O systems/O we/O know/O today/DATE ./O 
These/O supply/O chains/O rapidly/O expanded/O across/O different/O firms/O and/O ,/O increasingly/O ,/O between/O different/O nations/O ./O 
Automation/O also/O contributed/O to/O a/DURATION second/DURATION agricultural/O revolution/O by/O boosting/O agricultural/O yields/O via/O industrial/O fertilizer/O production/O ,/O and/O by/O introducing/O more/O productive/O food/O storage/O methods/O through/O refrigeration/O ./O 
Standardization/O was/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O key/O drivers/O of/O these/O achieve/O ments/O ,/O including/O of/O quality/O standards/O -LRB-/O for/O example/O ,/O within/O trade/O blocks/O -RRB-/O and/O transportation/O systems/O -LRB-/O for/O instance/O ,/O the/O shipping/O container/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Legal/O and/O trade/O protections/O were/O also/O needed/O to/O assure/O innovators/O that/O they/O would/O be/O able/O to/O enjoy/O the/O financial/O rewards/O of/O their/O creativity/O ,/O without/O being/O exposed/O to/O early/O competition/O from/O rivals/O copying/O their/O tech/O -/O nologies/O ./O 
Prior/O industrial/O revolutions/O have/O centered/O around/O improvements/O in/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
The/O First/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION introduced/O early/O automation/O through/O machinery/O and/O boosted/O intra-national/O connections/O through/O the/O building/O of/O bridges/O and/O railways/O ./O 
The/O Second/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION began/O when/O automation/O enabled/O mass/O production/O and/O fostered/O more/O efficient/O ,/O productive/O connectivity/O via/O the/O division/O of/O labor/O ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O The/O concept/O of/O the/O corporation/O was/O key/O to/O this/O ./O 
In/O the/O absence/O of/O this/O integrated/O entity/O ,/O the/O high/O transaction/O costs/O involved/O in/O individuals/O contracting/O every/O single/O economic/O interaction/O would/O have/O restrained/O profit/O growth/O ,/O and/O heavy/O capital/O goods/O could/O never/O have/O achieved/O economies/O of/O scale/O ./O 
The/O Third/ORDINAL Industrial/O Revolution/O The/O rise/O of/O the/O digital/O age/O characterized/O the/O Third/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
1969/DATE was/O the/DATE year/DATE in/O which/O connectivity/O took/O a/O leap/O forward/O ,/O with/O the/O first/ORDINAL message/O sent/O over/O ARPANET/LOCATION ,/O the/O forebear/O of/O today/DATE 's/O Internet/O ./O 
Equally/O ,/O the/O scope/O for/O automation/O was/O vastly/O enhanced/O by/O the/O implications/O of/O Moore/ORGANIZATION 's/O Law/O --/O the/O observation/O that/O the/O number/O of/O transistors/O on/O an/O integrated/O circuit/O has/O doubled/O approximately/O every/SET two/SET years/SET ./O 
This/O advancing/O automation/O coupled/O with/O the/O growing/O appreciation/O of/O the/O environmental/O damage/O caused/O by/O more/O intensive/O farming/O led/O ,/O from/O an/O agricultural/O revolu/O -/O tion/O perspective/O ,/O to/O the/O rise/O of/O a/O ``/O green/O revolution/O ./O ''/O 
Moore/O 's/O Law/O generally/O refers/O directly/O to/O electronic/O circuitry/O ,/O the/O foundational/O technology/O of/O this/O era/O ./O 
It/O captures/O the/O wider/O phenomenon/O of/O output/O growing/O as/O an/O exponential/O function/O of/O input/O ./O 
Moore/PERSON 's/O Law/O resulted/O in/O greater/O comput/O -/O ing/O power/O and/O the/O ability/O to/O automate/O ever/O more/O complex/O tasks/O ./O 
In/O some/O areas/O ,/O such/O as/O biotechnology/O ,/O the/O pace/O of/O progress/O has/O even/O exceeded/O Moore/PERSON 's/O Law/O ./O 
The/O Third/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION was/O propelled/O by/O the/O rise/O of/O the/O digital/O age/O ,/O of/O more/O sophisticated/O automation/O ,/O and/O of/O increasing/O connectivity/O between/O and/O within/O humanity/O and/O the/O natural/O world/O ./O 
12/NUMBER The/ORGANIZATION Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION is/O being/O driven/O by/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
A/O special/O feature/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION will/O be/O the/O wider/O implementation/O of/O artificial/O intelligence/O ./O 
1/NUMBER We/O note/O that/O the/O need/O for/O lower-skilled/O ,/O relatively/O lower-paid/O labor/O to/O provide/O sufficient/O affordable/O food/O may/O intensify/O ./O 
Coupled/O with/O growing/O environmental/O concerns/O ,/O this/O factor/O may/O spur/O a/O fourth/ORDINAL agricultural/O revolution/O ,/O in/O line/O with/O historical/O experience/O ./O 
Take/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O the/O cost/O of/O sequencing/O a/O genome/O ,/O which/O has/O fallen/O from/O as/O high/O as/O USD/ORGANIZATION 100,000/NUMBER in/U_TEMPPRED 2001/DATE to/O USD/O 5,000/NUMBER last/DATE year/DATE to/O USD/ORGANIZATION 1,400/NUMBER today/DATE ./O 
The/O concept/O of/O crossing/O the/O chasm/O recognizes/O the/O gap/O between/O the/O early/O adopters/O of/O new/O technology/O and/O an/O early/O majority/O who/O play/O ``/O c/O a/O t/O c/O h/O -/O u/O p/O ''/O as/O later/O adopters/O ./O 
This/O chasm/O is/O most/O easily/O bridged/O by/O continuous/O innovation/O ,/O allowing/O minimal/O disrup/O -/O tion/O to/O the/O consumer/O ./O 
Advances/O in/O computing/O set/O the/O stage/O f/O or/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION in/O three/NUMBER broad/O areas/O ,/O according/O to/O the/O WEF/ORGANIZATION 's/O Davis/PERSON :/O the/O ``/O technosphere/O ''/O or/O digital/O world/O ;/O the/O natural/O world/O that/O technology/O now/DATE allows/O us/O to/O monitor/O ,/O analyze/O and/O digitize/O ;/O and/O the/O human/O world/O ,/O as/O technology/O impacts/O the/O way/O in/O which/O we/O connect/O and/O with/O whom/O we/O connect/O -LRB-/O human/O &/O machine/O ,/O human/O &/O human/O ,/O machine/O &/O machine/O -RRB-/O ./O 
The/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION The/ORGANIZATION Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION is/O being/O driven/O by/O extreme/O automation/O and/O extreme/O connectivity/O ./O 
Extreme/O automation/O will/O ,/O as/O a/O first/ORDINAL step/O ,/O expand/O the/O range/O of/O jobs/O it/O is/O possible/O to/O automate/O ,/O to/O include/O not/O only/O highly/O repetitive/O low-skill/O jobs/O ,/O but/O also/O highly/O routine/O medium-skill/O jobs/O ./O 
As/O we/O out/O -/O line/O in/O the/O next/O section/O ,/O the/O relative/O impact/O of/O this/O extreme/O automation/O on/O income/O inequality/O between/O low-skill/O and/O high-skill/O labor/O looks/O set/O to/O intensify/O 1/NUMBER ./O 
We/O expect/O artificial/O intelligence/O -LRB-/O AI/O -RRB-/O to/O be/O a/O pervasive/O f/O eature/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Extreme/O auto/O -/O mation/O via/O AI/O will/O increasingly/O automate/O some/O of/O the/O skills/O that/O formerly/O only/O humans/O possessed/O ./O 
Where/O AI/O could/O be/O poised/O to/O make/O the/O biggest/O gains/O is/O in/O big/O data/O processing/O ,/O World/O Economic/O Forum/O 13/NUMBER potentially/O including/O the/O processing/O of/O language/O and/O images/O ,/O which/O have/O thus/O far/O been/O off-limits/O for/O computers/O to/O under/O -/O stand/O ./O 
Extreme/O automation/O could/O allow/O more/O robots/O and/O AI/O to/O produce/O output/O ,/O analyze/O results/O ,/O make/O complex/O deci/O -/O sions/O ,/O and/O adapt/O conclusions/O to/O environmental/O factors/O ./O 
Extreme/O connectivity/O enables/O more/O universal/O ,/O global/O and/O close-to-instant/O communication/O ./O 
It/O is/O giving/O rise/O to/O new/O business/O models/O and/O is/O opening/O up/O economic/O supply/O in/O ways/O previously/DATE not/O possible/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O the/O creation/O of/O Uber/O ,/O the/O taxi-hailing/O smartphone/O app/O ,/O was/O only/O made/O possible/O by/O the/O explosive/O increase/O in/O portable/O Internet-enabled/O devises/O ./O 
Supply/O effectively/O created/O its/O own/O demand/O ./O 
Services/O like/O Facebook/O ,/O WhatsApp/O ,/O Pinterest/LOCATION ,/O Snapchat/O ,/O Twitter/O ,/O and/O Instagram/PERSON have/O come/O to/O play/O a/O pivotal/O role/O in/O the/O social/O interaction/O of/O citizens/O around/O the/O world/O ./O 
Extreme/O automation/O can/O also/O be/O coupled/O with/O extreme/O connectivity/O ,/O allowing/O computing/O systems/O to/O control/O and/O manage/O physical/O processes/O and/O respond/O in/O ever/O more/O ``/O human/O ''/O ways/O ./O 
This/O represents/O a/O democratization/O of/O the/O ability/O to/O communicate/O between/O and/O among/O governments/O ,/O corporates/O ,/O humans/O ,/O and/O machines/O ./O 
The/O advent/O of/O ``/O cyber-physical/O systems/O ''/O may/O allow/O robots/O and/O AI/O ,/O via/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ,/O to/O ``/O cross/O the/O chasm/O ''/O between/O the/O technosphere/O ,/O the/O natural/O world/O ,/O and/O the/O human/O world/O ./O 
A/O number/O of/O radical/O implications/O may/O arise/O from/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
We/O shall/O now/DATE look/O at/O how/O extreme/O automation/O and/O extreme/O connectivity/O may/O impact/O the/O global/O macroeconomy/O ,/O regional/O economies/O ,/O and/O investment/O opportunities/O ./O 
2/NUMBER ./O 
What/O are/O the/O potential/O global/O consequences/O ?/O 
Polarization/O of/O the/O labor/O force/O as/O lowskill/O jobs/O continue/O to/O be/O automated/O ,/O and/O this/O trend/O increasingly/O spreads/O to/O middle/O skill/O jobs/O ./O 
This/O implies/O higher/O potential/O levels/O of/O inequality/O in/O the/O short/O run/O ,/O and/O a/O need/O for/O labor/O market/O flexibility/O to/O harness/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION benefits/O in/O the/O long/O run/O ./O 
Greater/O returns/O accruing/O to/O those/O with/O already/O high/O savings/O rates/O ./O 
In/O the/O short-run/O ,/O this/O could/O exacerbate/O inequality/O via/O relatively/O lower/O borrowing/O costs/O and/O higher/O asset/O valuations/O ./O 
A/O polarized/O labor/O force/O While/O technological/O revolutions/O often/O stoke/O fears/O of/O declin/O -/O ing/O employment/O as/O ``/O robots/O do/O all/O the/O work/O ,/O ''/O we/O believe/O a/O decline/O in/O aggregate/O employment/O is/O unlikely/O ./O 
As/O we/O discuss/O in/O our/O assessment/O of/O regional/O winners/O and/O losers/O ,/O the/O attri/O -/O butes/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORDINAL Industrial/O Revolution/O --/O extreme/O auto/O -/O mation/O and/O particularly/O extreme/O connectivity/O --/O could/O improve/O the/O productivity/O of/O existing/O jobs/O or/O create/O demand/O for/O entirely/O new/O jobs/O ./O 
It/O is/O usually/O difficult/O to/O envision/O today/DATE what/O the/O jobs/O of/O the/DATE future/DATE might/O be/O ./O 
But/O we/O believe/O that/O extreme/O automation/O and/O extreme/O connectivity/O could/O actually/O increase/O demand/O for/O customized/O ``/O human/O ''/O work/O ./O 
That/O is/O not/O to/O say/O we/O will/O not/O see/O an/O impact/O on/O relative/O dif/O -/O ferences/O in/O regional/O labor/O forces/O in/O the/O short/O run/O ./O 
Low/O skill/O employment/O will/O likely/O continue/O to/O contract/O ,/O and/O an/O increas/O -/O ing/O range/O of/O middle/O skill/O jobs/O will/O become/O vulnerable/O as/O extreme/O automation/O is/O rolled/O out/O ./O 
While/O aggregate/O employ/O -/O ment/O is/O unlikely/O to/O fall/O in/O the/O long/O run/O ,/O we/O could/O start/O to/O see/O polarization/O in/O the/O labor/O force/O and/O frictional/O unemployment/O until/O workers/O reskill/O ,/O relocate/O or/O alternatively/O adapt/O ./O 
Addi/O -/O tionally/O ,/O labor-intensive/O goods/O could/O see/O their/O prices/O fall/O relative/O to/O more/O capital-intensive/O goods/O ./O 
Some/O of/O the/O low/O skilled/O parts/O of/O the/O labor/O force/O -LRB-/O for/O instance/O ,/O assembly/O line/O work/O -RRB-/O that/O have/O already/O been/O heavily/O affected/O by/O basic/O automation/O could/O be/O further/O impacted/O ./O 
The/O advent/O of/O ``/O cobots/O ,/O ''/O or/O collaborative/O robots/O ,/O which/O are/O able/O to/O ``/O move/O around/O ''/O and/O interact/O without/O the/O need/O for/O fixed/O positions/O ,/O have/O the/O potential/O to/O work/O at/O a/O higher/O rate/O of/O production/O relative/O to/O that/O of/O lower/O skilled/O human/O workers/O ./O 
The/O greatest/O disruption/O ,/O however/O ,/O could/O be/O experienced/O by/O workers/O who/O have/O so/O far/O felt/O immune/O to/O robotic/O competition/O ,/O namely/O those/O in/O middle/O skill/O professions/O ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O 15/NUMBER As/O the/O issuer/O of/O the/O world/O 's/O reserve/O currency/O ,/O the/O US/LOCATION '/O competitive/O advantages/O ,/O sitting/O at/O the/O heart/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ,/O could/O tighten/O effective/O monetary/O conditions/O among/O US/LOCATION dollarlinked/O economies/O ./O 
We/O expect/O developments/O in/O extreme/O automation/O and/O extreme/O connectivity/O ,/O blended/O in/O AI/O solutions/O ,/O to/O have/O a/O significant/O impact/O on/O the/O nature/O of/O knowledge/O work/O ./O 
Automation/O will/O initially/O affect/O clerical/O work/O ,/O sales/O ,/O cus/O -/O tomer/O service/O ,/O and/O support/O functions/O ./O 
Robotic/O process/O automation/O ,/O automatic/O reporting/O ,/O and/O virtual/O assistants/O will/O become/O common/O ./O 
Minor/O claims/O in/O insurance/O could/O be/O processed/O without/O human/O intervention/O ,/O most/O incoming/O customer/O queries/O answered/O automatically/O ,/O and/O many/O customer/O calls/O deflected/O ./O 
In/O finance/O ,/O ``/O robo/O advisors/O ''/O are/O already/O available/O in/O the/O market/O ./O 
In/O the/O legal/O world/O ,/O computers/O can/O quickly/O go/O through/O millions/O of/O emails/O and/O dramatically/O cut/O the/O cost/O of/O investigations/O ./O 
And/O if/O fewer/O people/O are/O employed/O in/O a/O sector/O ,/O fewer/O managers/O will/O likely/O be/O needed/O in/O that/O sector/O ./O 
This/O combination/O could/O force/O a/O broad/O swath/O of/O workers/O to/O adapt/O ./O 
Lower/O skilled/O and/O middle/O skilled/O workers/O may/O face/O greater/O unemployment/O in/O the/O near/O term/O unless/O a/O number/O of/O criteria/O are/O met/O ,/O allowing/O them/O to/O reskill/O into/O tasks/O that/O extreme/O automation/O can/O not/O perform/O ,/O or/O move/O into/O industries/O where/O extreme/O connectivity/O permits/O them/O to/O work/O outside/O of/O traditional/O global/O or/O regional/O boundaries/O ./O 
Equally/O ,/O higher/O -/O skilled/O workers/O ,/O particularly/O those/O who/O do/O routine/O tasks/O ,/O may/O face/O future/DATE threats/O from/O the/O developments/O in/O advanced/O artificial/O intelligence/O such/O as/O natural/O language/O processing/O ./O 
Once/DATE again/O ,/O we/O do/O not/O expect/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION to/O result/O in/O an/O aggregate/O increase/O in/O global/O unemployment/O ;/O however/O we/O do/O examine/O ,/O in/O our/O regional/O section/O below/O ,/O which/O countries/O may/O be/O best/O placed/O shor/O t-term/O to/O harness/O fully/O extreme/O automation/O and/O con/O -/O nectivity/O benefits/O ./O 
Higher/O savings/O at/O the/O top/O Near/O term/O polarization/O in/O the/O labor/O force/O and/O greater/O income/O inequality/O imply/O larger/O gains/O for/O those/O at/O the/O top/O of/O the/O income/O ,/O skills/O and/O wealth/O spectrums/O ./O 
These/O individuals/O are/O likely/O to/O be/O best/O placed/O from/O a/O skills/O perspective/O to/O harness/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ;/O they/O typically/O already/O have/O high/O savings/O rates/O and/O will/O benefit/O from/O holding/O more/O of/O the/O assets/O whose/O value/O will/O be/O boosted/O by/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
And/O the/O pattern/O may/O not/O be/O limited/O to/O individuals/O ./O 
The/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION can/O be/O characterized/O by/O relatively/O low/O capital/O intensity/O via/O deployment/O of/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
Put/O another/O way/O ,/O the/O prototype/O company/O in/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION may/O enjoy/O a/O small/O human/O capital/O pool/O ,/O but/O a/O large/O economic/O value/O ,/O either/O private/O or/O in/O equity/O market/O capitalization/O ./O 
An/O example/O from/O our/O 2015/DATE whitepaper/O on/O ``/O The/O New/O Global/O Context/O ''/O :/O WhatsApp/O generated/O impressive/O returns/O for/O a/O small/O group/O of/O founders/O and/O investors/O when/O Facebook/O agreed/O to/O pay/O what/O ended/O up/O being/O USD/MONEY 22/MONEY billion/MONEY for/O the/O company/O in/O February/DATE 2014/DATE ,/O despite/O the/O fact/O that/O the/O firm/O had/O only/O 55/NUMBER employees/O ./O 
By/O contrast/O ,/O US/LOCATION airline/O United/ORGANIZATION Continental/ORGANIZATION has/O a/O similar/O market/O capitalization/O as/O of/O midDecember/O 2015/DATE of/O around/O USD/O 22/NUMBER billion/NUMBER ,/O but/O around/O 82,300/NUMBER employees/O ./O 
The/O USD/O 400/NUMBER mil/O -/O lion/O of/O enterprise/O value/O per/O person/O garnered/O by/O WhatsApp/O is/O an/O extreme/O example/O ,/O but/O it/O highlights/O the/O possible/O outsized/O gains/O and/O inequality/O that/O may/O arise/O from/O low/O capital-inten/O -/O sity/O business/O models/O of/O the/DATE future/DATE ./O 
Even/O in/O low/O capital-intensity/O businesses/O ,/O the/O capital/O goods/O that/O are/O employed/O --/O that/O perhaps/O used/O to/O suffer/O from/O ``/O asset/O specificity/O ''/O --/O are/O now/DATE divisible/O into/O smaller/O and/O more/O accessible/O units/O of/O usage/O ,/O as/O exemplified/O by/O AirBnB/O and/O Uber/O ./O 
The/O growing/O use/O of/O the/O Internet/O of/O Things/O and/O extreme/O connectivity/O allows/O these/O more/O accessible/O units/O to/O be/O monitored/O and/O their/O efficiency/O evaluated/O in/O real/O time/O ./O 
-LRB-/O The/O October/DATE release/O from/O AirDNA/O ,/O a/O data/O analytics/O com/O -/O pany/O that/O aggregates/O AirBnB/O listing/O data/O ,/O may/O be/O one/NUMBER example/O ./O -RRB-/O 
As/O such/O ,/O investments/O by/O firms/O benefiting/O from/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION may/O become/O more/O efficient/O and/O ,/O over/O time/O ,/O less/O burdensome/O in/O terms/O of/O capital/O deployed/O ./O 
Con/O sequently/O ,/O even/O companies/O who/O invest/O heavily/O may/O often/O be/O able/O to/O fund/O these/O investments/O out/O of/O earnings/O ,/O without/O the/O need/O to/O borrow/O ./O 
In/O this/O regard/O ,/O it/O perhaps/O should/O not/O be/O regarded/O as/O a/O coincidence/O that/O many/O tech/O giants/O run/O such/O large/O cash/O surpluses/O ,/O in/O sharp/O contrast/O to/O the/O capital-in/O -/O tensive/O investment/O cycle/O of/O many/O basic/O resources/O funds/O ./O 
Eventually/O ,/O as/O we/O highlight/O later/O on/O ,/O flexibility/O of/O capital/O and/O infrastructure/O may/O balance/O out/O some/O of/O this/O capital/O inequal/O -/O ity/O ./O 
Yet/O early/O adopters/O of/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connec/O -/O tivity/O may/O enjoy/O lower/O borrowing/O costs/O in/O the/O short/O run/O ,/O and/O put/O downward/O pressure/O on/O interest/O rates/O in/O parts/O of/O the/O economy/O where/O they/O operate/O ./O 
This/O is/O likely/O to/O drive/O up/O asset/O valuations/O of/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION beneficiaries/O and/O further/O widen/O inequality/O levels/O ./O 
The/O dollar/O dilemma/O As/O we/O highlight/O in/O the/O regional/O analysis/O of/O this/O paper/O ,/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION possesses/O many/O of/O the/O key/O attributes/O neces/O -/O sary/O for/O success/O in/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
While/O technology/O is/O ultimately/O universal/O ,/O economic/O structures/O tend/O to/O exacerbate/O differences/O between/O regions/O in/O the/O short/O run/O ./O 
While/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION faces/O a/O variety/O of/O structural/O issues/O ,/O including/O falling/O high/O school/O education/O rankings/O ,/O increasing/O income/O and/O wealth/O inequality/O ,/O and/O a/O problematic/O health/O -/O care/O system/O ,/O it/O remains/O an/O attractive/O destination/O for/O invest/O -/O ment/O ,/O company/O establishment/O and/O headquartering/O ./O 
This/O creates/O a/O plausible/O scenario/O where/O the/O USD/ORGANIZATION maintains/O its/O structural/O strength/O ./O 
This/O trend/O has/O been/O in/O evidence/O during/O 2015/DATE ,/O as/O the/O US/LOCATION business/O and/O credit/O cycle/O looks/O to/O be/O more/O advanced/O than/O those/O of/O other/O regions/O ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O 17/NUMBER Further/O dollar/O strength/O would/O add/O to/O the/O difficulties/O of/O emerging/O market/O economies/O whose/O struggles/O are/O currently/DATE garnering/O headlines/O ./O 
Countries/O maintaining/O dollar/O pegs/O would/O face/O extra/O competitive/O pressures/O ./O 
And/O the/O cost/O of/O debt/O servicing/O would/O also/O rise/O for/O emerging/O countries/O and/O com/O -/O panies/O that/O have/O used/O the/O period/O of/O low/O US/LOCATION interest/O rates/O and/O broad/O USD/O weakness/O since/O the/O financial/O crisis/O to/O increase/O significantly/O their/O USD/O denominated/O borrowing/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O we/O noted/O in/O a/O previous/O UBS/O whitepaper/O ,/O ``/O Macro/O problems/O ,/O micro/O solutions/O ,/O ''/O that/O shifts/O in/O technology/O may/O prove/O disruptive/O for/O other/O economies/O and/O sectors/O ./O 
The/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION increases/O the/O magnitude/O and/O probability/O of/O tail/O risks/O related/O to/O cybersecurity/O and/O geopolitics/O ,/O but/O may/O spur/O regional/O action/O to/O invest/O and/O embrace/ORGANIZATION Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION benefits/O ./O 
Labor/O markets/O in/O manufacturing/O could/O be/O materially/O affect/O ed/O as/O capital/O such/O as/O robotics/O and/O 3D/O printing/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O displace/O low/O and/O middle/O skill/O jobs/O ./O 
For/O some/O economies/O on/O the/O cusp/O of/O joining/O the/O global/O manufactur/O -/O ing/O and/O trading/O system/O -LRB-/O for/O example/O in/O South/LOCATION Asia/LOCATION ,/O the/O Middle/LOCATION East/LOCATION ,/O Africa/LOCATION ,/O and/O parts/O of/O Latin/LOCATION America/LOCATION -RRB-/O ,/O extreme/O automation/O of/O capital/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION could/O have/O short/O run/O negative/O demographic/O and/O employment/O effects/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O the/O ``/O onshoring/O ''/O of/O work/O back/O to/O the/O US/LOCATION -LRB-/O and/O shortening/O of/O global/O supply/O chains/O -RRB-/O from/O areas/O with/O a/O former/O comparative/O advantage/O of/O labor/O could/O be/O seen/O as/O a/O risk/O to/O developing/O nations/O ./O 
In/O particular/O ,/O the/O rise/O of/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connec/O -/O tivity/O via/O ``/O smart/O grid/O ''/O systems/O ,/O while/O improving/O energy/O efficiency/O and/O helping/O match/O supply/O with/O demand/O more/O effectively/O ,/O may/O be/O vulnerable/O to/O hacks/O which/O shut/O down/O electricity/O transmission/O or/O generation/O systems/O entirely/O ./O 
According/O to/O Symantec/ORGANIZATION ,/O the/O energy/O sector/O is/O now/DATE one/NUMBER of/O the/O five/NUMBER most/O targeted/O sectors/O for/O hackers/O globally/O ,/O and/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2012/DATE Saudi/O Aramco/O spent/O weeks/DURATION repairing/O its/O computer/O systems/O after/O a/O virus/O attack/O ./O 
In/U_TEMPPRED 2013/DATE ,/O parts/O of/O the/O Austrian/O and/O German/O power/O grids/O were/O threatened/O after/O an/O IT/O acci/O -/O dent/O led/O to/O the/O network/O being/O flooded/O with/O data/O ./O 
Similarly/O ,/O cloud/O computing/O allows/O companies/O to/O outsource/O a/O host/O of/O IT/O tasks/O via/O extreme/O connectivity/O ,/O including/O soft/O -/O ware/O installation/O and/O server/O maintenance/O ./O 
This/O gives/O them/O more/O flexibility/O and/O allows/O them/O to/O better/O deploy/O capital/O to/O their/O core/O business/O ./O 
But/O if/O the/O IT/O infrastructure/O of/O a/O large/O number/O of/O companies/O is/O being/O managed/O and/O distributed/O As/O highlighted/O in/O more/O detail/O in/O a/O later/O section/O of/O this/O paper/O ,/O however/O ,/O extreme/O connectivity/O may/O allow/O a/O shortening/O in/O the/O length/O of/O global/O supply/O chains/O ./O 
One/NUMBER particular/O impli/O -/O cation/O of/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O in/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION will/O be/O the/O role/O of/O ``/O virtual/O ''/O trade/O in/O ideas/O and/O intellectual/O property/O versus/O ``/O traditional/O ''/O trade/O in/O physical/O goods/O ./O 
Relative/O advantages/O in/O developed/O market/O legal/O protections/O of/O intangible/O ideas/O may/O lead/O to/O ``/O onshoring/O ''/O from/O emerging/O markets/O to/O the/O developed/O world/O initially/O ,/O but/O this/O trend/O may/O reverse/O over/O the/O longer/O term/O as/O emerging/O nations/O grow/O and/O develop/O their/O infrastructure/O to/O embrace/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
2/NUMBER Rising/O risks/O relating/O to/O cyber/O warfare/O and/O geopolitics/O Extreme/O connectivity/O also/O increases/O the/O risks/O posed/O by/O cyber/O security/O breaches/O ,/O as/O we/O have/O highlighted/O in/O previous/O White/O Papers/O ,/O including/O ``/O The/O New/O Global/O Context/O :/O Could/O economic/O transformations/O threaten/O stability/O ?/O ''/O 
2/NUMBER We/O also/O acknowledge/O that/O Leontief/PERSON 's/O Paradox/O may/O arise/O ,/O whereby/O the/O US/LOCATION could/O end/O up/O importing/O capital/O intensive/O products/O while/O exporting/O labor/O intensive/O products/O ,/O albeit/O where/O the/O labor/O intensity/O used/O to/O produce/O US/LOCATION exports/O is/O highly/O skilled/O ,/O relative/O to/O other/O nations/O ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O 19/NUMBER by/O a/O single/O cloud/O computing/O provider/O ,/O the/O damage/O inflicted/O by/O hackers/O could/O be/O significantly/O greater/O than/O an/O attack/O on/O a/O single/O company/O ./O 
Cyber/O security/O dangers/O vary/O significantly/O between/O nations/O ,/O with/O many/O emerging/O markets/O more/O exposed/O ./O 
Eurasia/ORGANIZATION Group/ORGANIZATION 's/O cyber/O risk/O index/O ,/O which/O rates/O the/O threat/O to/O busi/O -/O nesses/O from/O 1/NUMBER to/O 100/NUMBER ,/O indicates/O a/O relatively/O elevated/O risk/O reading/O of/O 88/NUMBER for/O Chinese/O firms/O ,/O versus/O a/O safe/O score/O of/O just/O 14/NUMBER for/O Swiss/O firms/O ./O 
The/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ,/O despite/O its/O relatively/O robust/O cyber/O environ/O ment/O ,/O is/O considered/O a/O prestige/O target/O by/O foreign/O states/O and/O dissidents/O and/O as/O a/O result/O Eurasia/ORGANIZATION Group/ORGANIZATION gives/O it/O a/O rating/O of/O 77/NUMBER ,/O putting/O it/O at/O far/O greater/O risk/O than/O most/O rich/O nations/O ./O 
The/O potential/O magnitude/O of/O such/O impacts/O could/O increase/O as/O connected/O networks/O grow/O larger/O due/O to/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Without/O strong/O international/O and/O institutional/O frameworks/O governing/O the/O protection/O of/O data/O ,/O cyber/O security/O ,/O and/O Internet/O privacy/O ,/O access/O to/O the/O full/O benefits/O of/O extreme/O connectivity/O may/O be/O stymied/O ./O 
In/O January/DATE of/DATE last/DATE year/DATE ,/O UBS/ORGANIZATION '/O whitepaper/O ``/O The/O New/O Global/O Context/O ''/O called/O for/O greater/O global/O coordination/O on/O cyber-security/O ./O 
We/O expect/O these/O calls/O to/O continue/O and/O intensify/O ./O 
Extreme/O connectivity/O is/O also/O fostering/O geopolitical/O tensions/O in/O several/O ways/O ./O 
It/O increases/O the/O ability/O of/O diverse/O groups/O to/O organize/O protests/O and/O offers/O the/O potential/O for/O greater/O publicity/O to/O violent/O extremists/O ./O 
Recent/O examples/O have/O high/O -/O lighted/O the/O convening/O power/O of/O social/O media/O across/O the/O world/O ./O 
Widely/O distributed/O images/O of/O Mohamed/PERSON Bouazizi/PERSON ,/O and/O his/O self-immolation/O in/O protest/O over/O police/O corruption/O ,/O helped/O give/O rise/O to/O a/O mass/O movement/O that/O displaced/O the/O Tunisian/O government/O and/O triggered/O the/O broader/O Arab/ORGANIZATION Spring/ORGANIZATION in/O the/O Middle/LOCATION East/LOCATION ./O 
Extreme/O connectivity/O has/O also/O proved/O a/O threat/O to/O mainstream/O political/O parties/O across/O the/O globe/O ./O 
The/O 2015/DATE mass/O protests/O in/O Brazil/LOCATION drew/O millions/O to/O the/O street/O ,/O with/O social/O media/O again/O proving/O a/O driving/O force/O ./O 
In/O Western/LOCATION Europe/LOCATION too/O ,/O mainstream/O political/O parties/O have/O been/O threatened/O by/O the/O rapid/O rise/O of/O protest/O movements/O that/O have/O exploited/O social/O media/O to/O galvanize/O their/O followers/O ./O 
Extreme/O connectivity/O has/O the/O potential/O to/O aid/O violent/O extre/O m/O -/O ists/O --/O both/O in/O recruitment/O and/O in/O generating/O publicity/O ./O 
A/O large/O quantity/O of/O online/O propaganda/O material/O is/O now/DATE being/O posted/O on/O social/O media/O platforms/O ./O 
The/O Islamic/ORGANIZATION State/ORGANIZATION has/O been/O deploying/O the/O Internet/O to/O win/O supporters/O throughout/O the/O world/O ,/O managing/O to/O recruit/O citizens/O from/O the/O US/LOCATION and/O Europe/LOCATION to/O their/O cause/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O social/O media/O has/O tended/O to/O magnify/O the/O impact/O of/O violent/O events/O --/O such/O as/O the/O tragic/O terrorist/O attacks/O in/O Paris/LOCATION ./O 
The/O photographs/O and/O videos/O taken/O by/O witnesses/O can/O now/DATE be/O broadcast/O worldwide/O ,/O providing/O the/O kind/O of/O mass/O publicity/O that/O terrorists/O are/O eager/O to/O gener/O -/O ate/O ./O 
The/O possibility/O of/O global/O coverage/O increases/O the/O incen/O -/O tive/O for/O extremist/O groups/O to/O perpetrate/O further/O assaults/O ./O 
Technology/O also/O has/O the/O potential/O to/O heighten/O political/O ten/NUMBER -/O sions/O by/O increasing/O economic/O inequality/O ./O 
The/O returns/O to/O technology/O have/O been/O uneven/O ,/O with/O automation/O threatening/O the/O job/O security/O of/O lower/O -/O skilled/O workers/O and/O helping/O boost/O the/O pay/O and/O investment/O returns/O of/O their/O highly/O skilled/O coun/O -/O terparts/O ./O 
This/O economic/O inequality/O may/O be/O exacerbated/O fur/O -/O ther/O if/O higher/O income/O ,/O higher/O skilled/O workers/O consume/O more/O low/O capital/O intensity/O goods/O and/O services/O -LRB-/O facing/O disinflationary/O pressures/O -RRB-/O relative/O to/O lower/O income/O ,/O lower/O skill/O labor/O ./O 
This/DATE may/DATE further/O contribute/O to/O the/O appeal/O of/O more/O populist/O political/O parties/O ,/O but/O should/O also/O incentivize/O governments/O to/O bridge/O inequality/O gaps/O by/O investing/O regionally/O in/O technol/O -/O ogies/O that/O allow/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O to/O thrive/O ./O 
We/O focus/O on/O regional/O impacts/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION in/O the/O next/O section/O ./O 
Internet/O network/O cyberstalking/O confidential/O information/O confidential/O information/O copyright/O infringement/O copyright/O infringement/O copyright/O infringement/O denialofservice/O attack/O denialofservice/O attack/O copyright/O infringement/O cyberwarfare/O cyberwarfare/O cyberwarfare/O cyberwarfare/O cyberwarfare/O spam/O spam/O spam/O spam/O threats/O law/O law/O victim/O victim/O law/O virus/O virus/O cyber/O defamation/O law/O financial/O theft/O financial/O theft/O phishing/O scams/O phishing/O scams/O hate/O crime/O hate/O crimeinternet/O crime/O internet/O crime/O threats/O hate/O crime/O threats/O cyberterrorism/O cyberwarare/O cracking/O phishing/O scams/O cyberterrorism/O cyberstalking/O network/O cracking/O phishing/O scams/O phishing/O scams/O financial/O theft/O malware/O malware/O malware/O fraud/O offense/O offense/O offense/O network/O espionage/O crime/O IT/O Hacking/O cyber/O defamation/O law/O cyberstalking/O hacking/O hacking/O cracking/O ITIT/O victim/O victim/O virus/O cyberheist/O cyberheist/O cyberheist/O child/O groomingchild/O grooming/O chat/O rooms/O chat/O rooms/O chat/O rooms/O fraud/O denialofservice/O attack/O confidential/O information/O espionage/O copyright/O infringement/O cyberwarfare/O cyber/O defamation/O law/O cyberterrorism/O espionage/O fraud/O W/O 21/NUMBER 3/NUMBER ./O 
Who/O will/O be/O the/O regional/O winners/O and/O losers/O ?/O 
``/O Flexibility/O ''/O will/O be/O key/O to/O success/O in/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION --/O economies/O with/O the/O most/O flexible/O labor/O markets/O ,/O educational/O systems/O ,/O infrastructure/O ,/O and/O legal/O systems/O are/O likely/O to/O be/O relative/O beneficiaries/O ./O 
Developed/O economies/O are/O likely/O to/O be/O relative/O winners/O at/O this/O stage/O ,/O whereas/O developing/O economies/O face/O greater/O challenges/O as/O their/O abundance/O of/O lowskill/O labor/O ceases/O to/O be/O an/O advan/O -/O tage/O and/O becomes/O more/O of/O a/O headwind/O ./O 
Emerging/O markets/O in/O their/O demographic/O prime/O may/O find/O that/O extreme/O automation/O displaces/O low/O skill/O workers/O ,/O but/O that/O their/O limited/O technology/O infrastructures/O do/O not/O allow/O them/O to/O reap/O the/O full/O benefits/O of/O extreme/O connectivity/O ./O 
An/O industrial/O revolution/O leads/O to/O significant/O changes/O in/O how/O economies/O work/O ./O 
Traditional/O economic/O structures/O change/O or/O become/O obsolete/O ,/O and/O new/O economic/O structures/O establish/O themselves/O ./O 
Through/O this/O process/O ,/O an/O industrial/O revolution/O can/O also/O become/O a/O significant/O force/O for/O specific/O disruption/O to/O the/O structures/O of/O the/O labor/O market/O ./O 
How/O an/O economy/O and/O its/O labor/O force/O adapt/O to/O changing/O economic/O structures/O will/O determine/O how/O successful/O a/O nation/O is/O in/O responding/O to/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
By/O and/O large/O ,/O the/O nature/O of/O the/O technological/O change/O is/O not/O that/O relevant/O to/O the/O relative/O economic/O performance/O of/O different/O sectors/O and/O economies/O in/O the/O wake/O of/O an/O industrial/O revo/O lution/O ./O 
There/O may/O be/O peculiar/O instances/O where/O extreme/O auto/O -/O mation/O and/O connectivity/O can/O overcome/O problems/O that/O are/O specific/O to/O an/O economy/O --/O capital/O that/O helps/O an/O ageing/O work/O -/O force/O remain/O productive/O or/O overcomes/O an/O environmental/O challenge/O ,/O for/O instance/O ./O 
As/O a/O general/O rule/O ,/O however/O ,/O it/O is/O an/O economy/O 's/O ability/O to/O adapt/O to/O the/O changes/O associated/O with/O new/O technology/O that/O matters/O ./O 
22/NUMBER 1/NUMBER ./O 
Capital/O for/O labor/O substitution/O Past/DATE industrial/O revolutions/O have/O been/O about/O substituting/O capital/O for/O some/O forms/O of/O labor/O ./O 
This/O often/O leads/O to/O what/O has/O been/O described/O as/O the/O ``/O lump/O of/O labor/O ''/O fallacy/O --/O the/O false/O idea/O that/O there/O is/O a/O finite/O amount/O of/O work/O to/O go/O around/O ./O 
Some/O jobs/O will/O be/O replaced/O by/O capital/O following/O extreme/O automation/O ./O 
Yet/O because/O people/O tend/O to/O extrapolate/O from/O current/DATE circumstances/O ,/O the/O idea/O that/O we/O will/O all/O be/O replaced/O by/O AI/O often/O causes/O concern/O in/O the/O population/O at/O large/O ./O 
In/O fact/O ,/O some/O existing/O jobs/O are/O likely/O to/O be/O replaced/O by/O ma/O chines/O ,/O and/O new/O jobs/O in/O hitherto/O unimagined/O professions/O will/O emerge/O ./O 
However/O ,/O if/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION is/O to/O be/O a/O net/O benefit/O to/O an/O economy/O ,/O then/O it/O is/O vital/O that/O the/O jobs/O market/O is/O flexible/O enough/O to/O adapt/O ./O 
All/O too/O often/O the/O reaction/O to/O structural/O change/O and/O associated/O selective/O job/O losses/O is/O to/O throw/O up/O barriers/O to/O labor/O flexibility/O and/O labor/O mobility/O ./O 
If/O the/O market/O starts/O to/O resemble/O medieval/DATE guilds/O with/O arcane/O qualifications/O or/O other/O barriers/O to/O entry/O ,/O then/O either/O the/O economy/O will/O be/O unable/O to/O adapt/O to/O new/O technology/O ,/O or/O it/O will/O be/O left/O behind/O in/O comparison/O to/O other/O economies/O ./O 
2/NUMBER ./O 
Skills/O and/O inequality/O Related/O to/O the/O importance/O of/O the/O flexibility/O of/O labor/O is/O the/O importance/O of/O the/O nature/O of/O skills/O in/O the/O labor/O force/O ./O 
This/O comes/O about/O in/O two/NUMBER ways/O ./O 
The/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION should/O value/O high/O skilled/O groups/O of/O workers/O more/O than/O low/O skill/O labor/O ./O 
High/O skill/O labor/O is/O likely/O to/O be/O able/O to/O under/O -/O stand/O the/O new/O technology/O more/O effectively/O and/O to/O adapt/O and/O maximize/O subsequent/O economic/O returns/O ./O 
Perhaps/O more/O importantly/O ,/O however/O ,/O the/O skills/O that/O are/O required/O need/O to/O be/O flexible/O in/O themselves/O ./O 
An/O engineer/O ,/O educated/O in/O a/O traditional/O system/O of/O rote/O learning/O ,/O may/O be/O well/O equipped/O for/O the/O standards/O and/O economic/O structures/O of/O today/DATE ./O 
But/O they/O are/O likely/O to/O find/O it/O harder/O ,/O at/O least/O in/O the/O short/O run/O ,/O to/O adapt/O their/O skills/O to/O a/O world/O of/O extreme/O auto/O -/O mation/O and/O connectivity/O that/O will/O shape/O future/DATE economic/O structures/O ./O 
The/O issue/O of/O flexibility/O in/O learning/O skills/O can/O work/O against/O an/O economy/O that/O has/O a/O high/O education/O level/O ./O 
Being/O skilled/O in/O change/O ,/O as/O well/O as/O being/O skilled/O in/O one/NUMBER 's/O profession/O ,/O is/O crucial/O ./O 
This/O issue/O also/O highlights/O the/O risk/O that/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION will/O raise/O income/O inequality/O ./O 
The/O monetary/O return/O to/O skills/O is/O likely/O to/O benefit/O those/O who/O are/O already/O on/O high/O incomes/O ./O 
Lower/O -/O skilled/O ,/O lowerpaid/O workers/O will/O suffer/O from/O relative/O income/O underperformance/O ./O 
But/O middle/O income/O workers/O who/O face/O declining/O barriers/O to/O entry/O due/O to/O extreme/O automation/O ,/O or/O who/O lack/O the/O flexibility/O to/O be/O able/O to/O change/O their/O skills/O to/O meet/O the/O requirements/O of/O extreme/O connectivity/O ,/O could/O face/O a/O decline/O in/O relative/O standard/O of/O living/O ./O 
The/O result/O -/O ing/O increase/O in/O inequality/O risks/O slowing/O the/O progress/O of/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
A/O threatened/O middle/O class/O may/O press/O for/O restrictive/O or/O repressive/O policies/O in/O a/O futile/O attempt/O to/O hold/O back/O the/O tide/O of/O technological/O change/O ./O 
This/O would/O damage/O the/O ability/O of/O an/O economy/O to/O benefit/O ,/O as/O an/O early/O adopter/O ,/O from/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
3/NUMBER ./O 
Infrastructure/O and/O inertia/O Infrastructure/O is/O generally/O thought/O of/O in/O its/O physical/O mani/O -/O festation/O ,/O but/O from/O an/O economic/O perspective/O it/O is/O the/O behavior/O that/O infrastructure/O helps/O to/O shape/O that/O is/O impor/O -/O tant/O ./O 
For/O instance/O ,/O an/O economy/O can/O not/O easily/O move/O to/O a/O car/O free/O transport/O system/O if/O the/O existing/O transport/O infra/O -/O structure/O is/O centered/O around/O an/O extensive/O road/O network/O ./O 
The/O cost/O of/O scrapping/O the/O sunk/O costs/O of/O existing/O infra/O -/O structure/O may/O ossify/O economic/O behavior/O ,/O in/O spite/O of/O the/O advantages/O of/O adapting/O to/O a/O post/O industrial/O revolution/O environment/O ./O 
A/O framework/O for/O determining/O regional/O winners/O and/O losers/O There/O are/O four/NUMBER areas/O where/O flexibility/O and/O the/O ability/O to/O adapt/O are/O likely/O to/O determine/O economic/O success/O in/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O 23/NUMBER Economies/O that/O have/O built/O an/O infrastructure/O designed/O for/O the/O economic/O status/O quo/O ,/O which/O is/O not/O readily/O adapted/O ,/O will/O therefore/O be/O at/O a/O potential/O standard/O of/O living/O disadvantage/O in/O the/DATE future/DATE ./O 
This/O does/O not/O necessarily/O have/O to/O be/O a/O growth/O disadvantage/O ;/O rebuilding/O existing/O infrastructure/O that/O has/O become/O obsolete/O can/O be/O growth-positive/O ./O 
The/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION is/O likely/O to/O change/O the/O physical/O location/O of/O human/O economic/O activity/O --/O localized/O production/O ,/O home/O working/O and/O the/O idea/O of/O the/O factory/O complex/O or/O the/O urban/O central/O business/O district/O ./O 
Having/O a/O phys/O -/O ical/O infrastructure/O that/O is/O adaptable/O will/O speed/O the/O pace/O of/O adjustment/O for/O an/O economy/O ./O 
4/NUMBER ./O 
Robustness/O and/O flexibility/O of/O legal/O system/O The/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION will/O likely/O emphasize/O intel/O -/O lectual/O property/O ./O 
Trade/O in/O ideas/O that/O can/O be/O converted/O into/O a/O product/O at/O a/O local/O level/O -LRB-/O close/O to/O the/O demand/O -RRB-/O will/O become/O more/O economically/O attractive/O as/O a/O business/O model/O ./O 
As/O already/O highlighted/O in/O the/O previous/O section/O ,/O global/O trade/O could/O become/O more/O ``/O virtual/O ''/O than/O physical/O -LRB-/O aside/O from/O basic/O materials/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Extreme/O connectivity/O raises/O the/O imperative/O of/O protecting/O intellectual/O property/O ,/O where/O practical/O ./O 
An/O economy/O that/O offers/O robust/O protection/O is/O more/O likely/O to/O have/O a/O relative/O advan/O -/O tage/O ,/O in/O the/O sense/O that/O the/O legal/O structures/O offer/O innovators/O the/O ability/O to/O capitalize/O on/O their/O ideas/O ,/O and/O foreign/O innovators/O will/O be/O happy/O to/O sell/O their/O ideas/O into/O that/O economy/O ./O 
The/O legal/O approach/O also/O needs/O to/O be/O flexible/O to/O deal/O with/O any/O new/O legal/O challenges/O that/O may/O arise/O ./O 
If/O a/O person/O 's/O DNA/O contains/O a/O cure/O for/O a/O disease/O ,/O who/O owns/O the/O rights/O to/O that/O DNA/O ?/O 
There/O are/O questions/O as/O to/O how/O such/O a/O product/O should/O be/O developed/O ,/O and/O indeed/O whether/O it/O should/O be/O legally/O protected/O at/O all/O ./O 
Revolutions/O are/O not/O linear/O -LRB-/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O reasons/O that/O they/O are/O called/O what/O they/O are/O -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O means/O that/O assessing/O beneficiaries/O in/O advance/O is/O always/O subjective/O and/O fraught/O with/O difficulty/O ./O 
However/O ,/O using/O the/O framework/O outlined/O above/O ,/O it/O is/O possible/O to/O take/O a/O systematic/O approach/O to/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revo/ORGANIZATION lution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
The/O following/O table/O examines/O the/O relative/O strengths/O of/O differ/O -/O ent/O economies/O using/O rankings/O from/O the/O World/O Economic/O Forum/O -LRB-/O WEF/O -RRB-/O Global/O Competitiveness/O Report/O ./O 
Given/O the/O impor/O tance/O of/O responsive/O human/O capital/O to/O the/O success/O of/O any/O industrial/O revolution/O ,/O the/O labor/O market/O element/O is/O covered/O by/O a/O skills/O level/O and/O a/O proxy/O for/O skills/O adaptability/O -LRB-/O in/O the/O form/O of/O its/O output/O ,/O innovation/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Each/O figure/O represents/O either/O a/O rank/O or/O an/O average/O of/O ranks/O in/O specific/O WEF/ORGANIZATION categories/O ./O 
The/O WEF/ORGANIZATION Global/O Competitiveness/O Report/O does/O provide/O specific/O scores/O as/O well/O as/O ranks/O ./O 
However/O ,/O Country/O assessment/O the/O purpose/O of/O this/O table/O is/O to/O judge/O the/O relative/O readiness/O of/O different/O economies/O to/O take/O advantage/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
A/O lower/O score/O implies/O a/O better/O relative/O readiness/O ./O 
The/O ``/O overall/O impact/O ''/O ranking/O in/O this/O table/O should/O therefore/O be/O treated/O as/O a/O means/O of/O obtaining/O a/O relative/O positioning/O ,/O and/O not/O as/O a/O statement/O about/O the/O degree/O of/O an/O economy/O 's/O absolute/O suitability/O for/O dealing/O with/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
It/O should/O not/O come/O as/O a/O major/O surprise/O that/O developed/O economies/O cluster/O towards/O the/O top/O of/O this/O list/O currently/DATE ,/O and/O developing/O economies/O cluster/O towards/O the/O bottom/O ./O 
The/O competitive/O disadvantages/O of/O a/O developed/O economy/O -LRB-/O lower/O availability/O of/O low-cost/O labor/O -RRB-/O are/O in/O some/O way/O mitigated/O by/O the/O consequences/O of/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
Yet/O the/O competitive/O advantages/O of/O developing/O economies/O -LRB-/O abundance/O of/O low/O skill/O labor/O -RRB-/O become/O more/O of/O a/O relative/O liability/O in/O the/O context/O of/O the/O changes/O that/O the/O Fourth/LOCATION Indus/LOCATION -/O trial/O Revolution/O is/O expected/O to/O bring/O about/O ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O 25/NUMBER Adapted/O relative/O rankings/O from/O World/O Economic/O Forum/O Global/O Competitiveness/O Report/O ,/O using/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION categories/O 3/NUMBER ./O 
Labour/O structures/O flexible/O ?/O 
Skill/O level/O high/O ?/O 
Education/O allos/O adapti/O -/O ve/O skills/O ?/O 
Infrascructure/O suitable/O ?/O 
Legal/O protections/O ?/O 
Overall/O impact/O Developed/O -LRB-/O DM/O -RRB-/O ,/O emer/O -/O ging/O market/O -LRB-/O EM/O -RRB-/O or/O frontier/O market/O -LRB-/O FM/O -RRB-/O ?/O 
Switzerland/LOCATION 1414.0/NUMBER 6.75/NUMBER 3.4/NUMBER DM/O Singapore/LOCATION 2193.5/NUMBER 9.00/NUMBER 4.9/NUMBER DM/O Netherlands/O 17386.512.50/O 9.4/NUMBER DM/O Finland/LOCATION 262219.0/NUMBER 1.2510.1/O DM/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION 46414.0/NUMBER 23.00/NUMBER 10.2/NUMBER DM/ORGANIZATION United/ORGANIZATION Kingdom/ORGANIZATION 518/NUMBER 126.010.00/O 10.2/NUMBER DM/O Hong/LOCATION Kong/LOCATION 313/NUMBER 274.510.00/O 11.5/NUMBER DM/O Norway/LOCATION 971319.0/NUMBER 11.50/NUMBER 11.9/NUMBER DM/O Denmark/LOCATION 1091015.5/NUMBER 17.75/NUMBER 12.5/NUMBER DM/O New/LOCATION Zealand/LOCATION 610/NUMBER 2421.5/NUMBER 6.2513.6/O DM/O Sweden/LOCATION 2012/DATE 712.0/NUMBER 19.75/NUMBER 14.2/NUMBER DM/O Japan/LOCATION 2121/DATE 512.0/NUMBER 18.00/NUMBER 15.4/NUMBER DM/O Germany/LOCATION 2817/DATE 69.518.75/O 15.9/NUMBER DM/O Ireland/LOCATION 13152119.0/NUMBER 11.50/NUMBER 15.9/NUMBER DM/O Canada/LOCATION 719/NUMBER 2216.0/NUMBER 20.50/NUMBER 16.9/NUMBER DM/O Taiwan/LOCATION 22141120.0/NUMBER 31.25/NUMBER 19.7/NUMBER EM/O Australia/LOCATION 3682318.5/NUMBER 17.75/NUMBER 20.7/NUMBER DM/O Austria/LOCATION 40161719.5/NUMBER 17.25/NUMBER 22.0/NUMBER DM/O Belgium/LOCATION 5451617.5/NUMBER 21.522.8/O DM/O France/LOCATION 51251812.0/NUMBER 31.00/NUMBER 27.4/NUMBER DM/O Israel/LOCATION 4528/NUMBER 326.0/NUMBER 38.50/NUMBER 28.1/NUMBER DM/O Malaysia/LOCATION 19362035.5/NUMBER 34.50/NUMBER 29.0/NUMBER EM/O Portugal/LOCATION 66262824.5/NUMBER 32.25/NUMBER 35.4/NUMBER DM/O Czech/O Republic/O 47293535.0/NUMBER 44.75/NUMBER 38.2/NUMBER EM/O South/LOCATION Korea/LOCATION 83231920.0/NUMBER 62.25/NUMBER 41.5/NUMBER EM/O Chile/LOCATION 63335042.0/NUMBER 39.25/NUMBER 45.5/NUMBER EM/O Spain/LOCATION 92303717.5/NUMBER 61.25/NUMBER 47.6/NUMBER DM/O China/LOCATION 37683156.5/NUMBER 64.25/NUMBER 51.4/NUMBER EM/O Kazakhstan/LOCATION 18607259.5/NUMBER 68.25/NUMBER 55.6/NUMBER FM/O Poland/LOCATION 81316448.5/NUMBER 58.00/NUMBER 56.5/NUMBER EM/O Russia/LOCATION 50386847.5114.00/O 63.5/NUMBER EM/O Thailand/LOCATION 67565751.0/NUMBER 88.00/NUMBER 63.8/NUMBER EM/O Italy/LOCATION 126453231.5/NUMBER 87.75/NUMBER 64.5/NUMBER DM/O Hungary/LOCATION 77575148.0/NUMBER 90.25/NUMBER 64.7/NUMBER EM/O South/LOCATION Africa/LOCATION 107833859.0/NUMBER 42.75/NUMBER 66.0/NUMBER EM/O Greece/LOCATION 116437735.0/NUMBER 67.00/NUMBER 67.6/NUMBER EM/LOCATION Philippines/LOCATION 82634879.0/NUMBER 78.00/NUMBER 70.0/NUMBER EM/O Indonesia/LOCATION 11565360/NUMBER 73.570.25/O 70.8/NUMBER EM/O Turkey/LOCATION 127556058.5/NUMBER 77.75/NUMBER 75.7/NUMBER EM/O Colombia/LOCATION 86707677.0102.75/O 82.4/NUMBER EM/O India/LOCATION 1039042100.5/NUMBER 81.50/NUMBER 83.4/NUMBER EM/O Mexico/LOCATION 114865966.0100.00/O 85.0/NUMBER EM/O Brazil/LOCATION 122938464.0/NUMBER 97.75/NUMBER 92.2/NUMBER EM/O Peru/LOCATION 6482116/NUMBER 88.5113.25/O 92.8/NUMBER EM/O Argentina/LOCATION 139399378.0125.75/O 95.0/NUMBER FM/O 4/NUMBER Labor/O market/O flexibility/O takes/O the/O ranking/O for/O the/O seventh/ORDINAL WEF/ORGANIZATION pillar/O ``/O Labor/O market/O efficiency/O ./O ''/O 
Skills/O level/O uses/O the/O fifth/ORDINAL pillar/O ``/O Higher/O education/O and/O training/O ./O ''/O 
The/O question/O as/O to/O whether/O education/O allows/O adaptive/O skills/O takes/O the/O ranking/O for/O the/O twelfth/ORDINAL pillar/O ,/O ``/O Innovation/O ,/O ''/O as/O innovation/O can/O be/O thought/O of/O as/O a/O benchmark/O of/O the/O output/O of/O adaptive/O skills/O ./O 
Infrastructure/O suitable/O is/O an/O average/O of/O the/O rankings/O in/O the/O ninth/ORDINAL and/ORDINAL second/ORDINAL pillars/O ``/O Technological/O readiness/O ''/O and/O ``/O Infrastructure/O ./O ''/O 
Legal/O protections/O is/O an/O average/O of/O the/O rankings/O for/O ``/O property/O rights/O ''/O -LRB-/O 1.01/NUMBER -RRB-/O ,/O ``/O intel/O -/O lectual/O property/O protection/O ''/O -LRB-/O 1.02/NUMBER -RRB-/O ,/O ``/O judicial/O independence/O ''/O -LRB-/O 1.06/NUMBER -RRB-/O and/O ``/O ethical/O behaviour/O of/O firms/O ''/O -LRB-/O 1.17/NUMBER -RRB-/O --/O this/O last/O category/O being/O included/O as/O trade/O in/O intellectual/O property/O necessitates/O a/O degree/O of/O confidence/O in/O the/O honor/O of/O one/NUMBER 's/O trading/O partners/O ./O 
Market/O description/O in/O the/O last/O column/O is/O based/O upon/O MSCI/O country/O classification/O methodology/O ./O 
26/NUMBER However/O ,/O it/O does/O highlight/O that/O EM/O economies/O are/O at/O risk/O of/O squandering/O their/O demographic/O prime/O ,/O if/O they/O are/O yet/O to/O move/O from/O lowincome/O to/O middle/O income/O ./O 
Many/O of/O these/O economies/O have/O still/O not/O dealt/O with/O the/O challenge/O of/O previ/ORGANIZATION -/O ous/O industrial/O revolutions/O ./O 
Their/O output/O and/O employment/O are/O still/O largely/O driven/O by/O agriculture/O ,/O small-scale/O manufac/O -/O turing/O and/O low/O skilled/O services/O ,/O large/O parts/O of/O which/O are/O in/O the/O informal/O economy/O ./O 
These/O are/O economies/O with/O low/O capi/O -/O tal/O stock/O and/O high/O population/O growth/O rates/O ./O 
They/O will/O face/O the/O threat/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION compromising/O low/O skilled/O jobs/O via/O extreme/O automation/O ,/O but/O may/O not/O have/O the/O technological/O ability/O to/O enjoy/O the/O relative/O gains/O that/O could/O be/O re-distributed/O via/O extreme/O connectivity/O ./O 
When/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION arrives/O ,/O a/O country/O 's/O present/DATE state/O of/O industrial/O technology/O and/O demographic/O patterns/O will/O together/O determine/O how/O successfully/O it/O adapts/O ,/O economically/O and/O politically/O ,/O to/O extreme/O automation/O and/O extreme/O connectivity/O ./O 
The/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION will/O take/O the/O emphasis/O away/O from/O demographic/O quantity/O to/O demographic/O quality/O ./O 
4/NUMBER The/DURATION years/DURATION for/O the/O various/O economies/O we/O studied/O are/O as/O follows/O ./O 
India/LOCATION :/O 1996/DATE ;/O China/LOCATION :/O 1981/DATE ;/O Korea/LOCATION :/O 1977/DATE ;/O Thailand/LOCATION :/O 1984/DATE ;/O Indonesia/LOCATION :/O 1991/DATE ;/O Brazil/LOCATION :/O 1990/DATE ;/O South/LOCATION Africa/LOCATION :/O 1995/DATE ;/O Mexico/LOCATION :/O 1997/DATE ;/O Turkey/LOCATION :/O 1992/DATE ;/O Malaysia/LOCATION :/O 1993/DATE ;/O Vietnam/LOCATION :/O 1998/DATE ;/O Bangladesh/LOCATION :/O 2003/DATE ;/O Egypt/LOCATION :/O 2002/DATE ./O 
Historically/O ,/O there/O has/O been/O a/O quite/O consistent/O pattern/O among/O economies/O that/O have/O been/O able/O to/O benefit/O from/O their/O demo/O -/O graphic/O dividend/O -LRB-/O through/O their/O demographic/O prime/O ,/O they/O galvanized/O serious/O increases/O in/O productivity/O by/O shifting/O labor/O from/O agriculture/O to/O manufacturing/O through/O education/O and/O by/O promoting/O more/O flexible/O skills/O -RRB-/O ./O 
This/O in/O turn/O substantially/O raised/O manufacturing/O 's/O share/O of/O GDP/O ./O 
This/O is/O the/O same/O pattern/O seen/O earlier/O in/O many/O developed/O markets/O such/O as/O Germany/LOCATION ,/O US/LOCATION and/O Japan/LOCATION ./O 
In/O Figure/O 1/NUMBER and/O Figure/O 2/NUMBER we/O attempt/O to/O show/O how/O manu/O -/O facturing/O has/O evolved/O along/O with/O demographics/O in/O various/O economies/O ./O 
We/O define/O t0/O as/O the/DATE year/DATE when/O the/O working/O age/O population/O as/O a/O proportion/O of/O the/O total/O population/O of/O an/O economy/O rose/O above/O 60/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
This/O is/O the/O time/O we/O use/O as/O a/O proxy/O for/O the/O point/O of/O inflexion/O ,/O the/DATE year/DATE we/O subjectively/O define/O as/O the/O beginning/O of/O an/O economy/O 's/O demographic/O bulge/O 4/NUMBER ./O 
We/O track/O how/O manufacturing/O as/O a/O percentage/O of/O GDP/O evolved/O just/O before/O and/O well/O after/O this/O inflexion/O point/O ./O 
0.50/NUMBER 0.75/NUMBER 1.00/NUMBER 1.25/NUMBER 1.50/NUMBER 1.50/NUMBER 1.25/NUMBER 1.00/NUMBER 0.75/NUMBER 0.50/NUMBER t-5/O t-4/O t-3/O t-2/O t-1/O t0/O t/O +1/NUMBER t/O +2/NUMBER t/O +3/NUMBER t/O +4/NUMBER t/O +5/NUMBER t/O +6/NUMBER t/O +7/NUMBER t/O +8/NUMBER t/O +9/NUMBER t/O +10/NUMBER t/O +11/NUMBER t/O +1/NUMBER \/O 2/NUMBER t/O +13/NUMBER t/O +14/NUMBER t/O +15/NUMBER t/O +16/NUMBER t/O +17/NUMBER t/O +18/NUMBER t/O +19/NUMBER t/O +20/NUMBER !/O ''/O 
#/O !/O 
``/O $/O !/O ''/O 
%/O !/O ''/O 
&/O !/O ''/O '/O 
!/O 
-LRB-/O !/O -RRB-/O '/O 
!/O -RRB-/O 
&/O !/O -RRB-/O 
%/O !/O -RRB-/O 
$/O !/O -RRB-/O 
#/O t/O --/O 4t/O --/O 3t/O --/O 2t/O --/O 1t/O --/O 0t0t/O +1/NUMBER t/O +2/NUMBER t/O +3/NUMBER t/O +4/NUMBER t/O +5/NUMBER t/O +6/NUMBER t/O +7/NUMBER t/O +8/NUMBER t/O +9/NUMBER t/O +10/NUMBER t/O +11/NUMBER t/O +12/NUMBER t/O +13/NUMBER t/O +14/NUMBER t/O +15/NUMBER t/O +16/NUMBER t/O +17/NUMBER t/O +18/NUMBER t/O +19/NUMBER t/O +20/NUMBER Figure/O 1/NUMBER :/O Path/O of/O Manufacturing/O to/O GDP/O --/O demographic/O successes/O Vietnam/LOCATION Thailand/LOCATION Bangladesh/LOCATION Indonesia/LOCATION Korea/LOCATION Malaysia/LOCATION Demographic/O in?exion/O year/DURATION -LRB-/O t0/O -RRB-/O de?ned/O as/O one/NUMBER when/O working/O age/O population/O as/O %/O of/O total/O population/O rises/O above/O 60/PERCENT %/PERCENT ;/O Manufacturing/O to/O GDP/O ratio/O is/O set/O at/O 1/NUMBER at/O t0/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Indexed/O ,/O t0/O =/O 1/NUMBER t/O --/O 5/NUMBER Source/O :/O Haver/O ,/O UBS/ORGANIZATION World/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Forum/ORGANIZATION 27/NUMBER Figure/O 1/NUMBER :/O shows/O the/O success/O stories/O ./O 
It/O is/O well/O known/O that/O China/LOCATION ,/O Korea/LOCATION ,/O and/O Thailand/LOCATION are/O past/DATE their/O demographic/O prime/O ./O 
But/O they/O did/O make/O the/O moment/O of/O demographic/O bulge/O count/O ./O 
Correlation/O does/O not/O imply/O causation/O ,/O yet/O it/O is/O telling/O that/O in/O these/O countries/O manufacturing/O as/O a/O percentage/O of/O GDP/O rose/O significantly/O once/DATE the/O working/O age/O population/O rose/O above/O 60/PERCENT %/PERCENT ./O 
This/O coincided/O with/O a/O big/O upswing/O in/O higher/O per/O capita/O incomes/O ,/O savings/O ,/O and/O typically/O also/O in/O export/O shares/O ./O 
In/O Figure/O 2/NUMBER we/O show/O the/O countries/O --/O some/O of/O which/O ,/O like/O India/LOCATION ,/O are/O current/DATE market/O darlings/O --/O which/O do/O not/O really/O dis/O -/O play/O the/O historical/O pattern/O -LRB-/O evident/O in/O demographic/O success/O stories/O -RRB-/O of/O a/O big/O boost/O to/O manufacturing/O when/O their/O demo/O -/O graphic/O prime/O began/O ./O 
In/O a/O sense/O ,/O this/O latter/O group/O of/O countries/O has/O not/O yet/O adapted/O even/O to/O the/O Second/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Third/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolutions/ORGANIZATION ./O 
As/O we/O will/O show/O in/O our/O final/O section/O on/O investment/O conclu/O -/O sions/O ,/O the/O power/O of/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O to/O change/O global/O manufacturing/O may/O pose/O nearer-term/O challenges/O for/O emerging/O market/O -LRB-/O EM/O -RRB-/O lower/O skill/O labor/O and/O EM/O assets/O ,/O relative/O to/O developed/O market/O peers/O ./O 
We/O reem/O phasize/O the/O need/O ,/O in/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ,/O for/O ``/O flexibility/O ''/O as/O the/O key/O to/O relative/O competitiveness/O ./O 
0.50/NUMBER 0.75/NUMBER 1.00/NUMBER 1.25/NUMBER 1.50/NUMBER 1.50/NUMBER 1.25/NUMBER 1.00/NUMBER 0.75/NUMBER 0.50/NUMBER t-5/O t-4/O t-3/O t-2/O t-1/O t0/O t/O +1/NUMBER t/O +2/NUMBER t/O +3/NUMBER t/O +4/NUMBER t/O +5/NUMBER t/O +6/NUMBER t/O +7/NUMBER t/O +8/NUMBER t/O +9/NUMBER t/O +10/NUMBER t/O +11/NUMBER t/O +1/NUMBER \/O 2/NUMBER t/O +13/NUMBER t/O +14/NUMBER t/O +15/NUMBER t/O +16/NUMBER t/O +17/NUMBER t/O +18/NUMBER t/O +19/NUMBER t/O +20/NUMBER !/O ''/O 
#/O !/O 
``/O $/O !/O ''/O 
%/O !/O ''/O 
&/O !/O ''/O '/O 
!/O 
-LRB-/O !/O -RRB-/O '/O 
!/O -RRB-/O 
&/O !/O -RRB-/O 
%/O !/O -RRB-/O 
$/O !/O -RRB-/O 
#/O t/O --/O 5t/O --/O 4t/O --/O 3t/O --/O 2t/O --/O 1t/O --/O 0t0t/O +1/NUMBER t/O +2/NUMBER t/O +3/NUMBER t/O +4/NUMBER t/O +5/NUMBER t/O +6/NUMBER t/O +7/NUMBER t/O +8/NUMBER t/O +9/NUMBER t/O +10/NUMBER t/O +11/NUMBER t/O +12/NUMBER t/O +13/NUMBER t/O +14/NUMBER t/O +15/NUMBER t/O +16/NUMBER t/O +17/NUMBER t/O +18/NUMBER t/O +19/NUMBER t/O +20/NUMBER Figure/O 2/NUMBER :/O Path/O of/O Manufacturing/O to/O GDP/O --/O demographic/O question/O marks/O Mexico/LOCATION Turkey/LOCATION Egypt/LOCATION India/LOCATION South/LOCATION Africa/LOCATION Brazil/LOCATION Source/O :/O Haver/O ,/O UBS/ORGANIZATION Demographic/O in?exion/O year/DURATION -LRB-/O t0/O -RRB-/O de?ned/O as/O one/NUMBER when/O working/O age/O population/O as/O %/O of/O total/O population/O rises/O above/O 60/PERCENT %/PERCENT ;/O Manufacturing/O to/O GDP/O ratio/O is/O set/O at/O 1/NUMBER at/O t0/O -RRB-/O ./O 
Indexed/O ,/O t0/O =/O 1/NUMBER Like/O prior/O industrial/O revolutions/O ,/O the/O Fourth/ORDINAL Industrial/O Revo/O -/O lution/O will/O likely/O have/O major/O repercussions/O across/O geogra/O -/O phies/O and/O industries/O ./O 
Extreme/O automation/O is/O likely/O to/O gener/O -/O ate/O substantial/O productivity/O gains/O for/O incumbents/O ./O 
But/O extreme/O automation/O using/O AI/O could/O also/O disrupt/O traditional/O business/O models/O ./O 
While/O there/O is/O a/O lot/O of/O hype/O surrounding/O the/O theme/O ,/O we/O believe/O some/O of/O the/O long-term/O investment/O implications/O are/O under-appreciated/O ./O 
We/O highlight/O below/O some/O likely/O implications/O and/O how/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O are/O starting/O to/O shape/O investment/O debates/O ./O 
4/NUMBER ./O 
What/O are/O the/O investment/O consequences/O ?/O 
Given/O current/DATE assessments/O of/O relative/O competitiveness/O ,/O emerging/O markets/O may/O be/O less/O well/O placed/O to/O profit/O from/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION benefits/O ,/O relative/O to/O developed/O markets/O ./O 
Four/NUMBER investment/O implications/O from/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION are/O outlined/O below/O :/O 1/NUMBER ./O 
Emerging/O market/O assets/O relative/O to/O developed/O market/O assets/O Based/O on/O the/O economic/O and/O regional/O assessments/O outlined/O earlier/O in/O this/O Whitepaper/PERSON ,/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION is/O expected/O disproportionally/O to/O benefit/O developed/O markets/O at/O the/O expense/O of/O emerging/O markets/O ,/O at/O least/O given/O current/DATE infrastructures/O ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O 29/NUMBER We/O expect/O further/O disruption/O to/O traditional/O industries/O from/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
We/O have/O noted/O how/O current/DATE labor/O market/O composition/O means/O emerging/O markets/O have/O more/O lowerskilled/O workers/O and/O less/O flexibility/O to/O raise/O skills/O than/O developed/O markets/O ./O 
We/O have/O also/O noted/O the/O nearer/O term/O risks/O of/O a/O higher/O US/LOCATION dollar/O due/O to/O the/O US/LOCATION '/O current/DATE advantage/O in/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION technologies/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O we/O have/O noted/O that/O the/O shift/O from/O physical/O to/O ''/O virtual/O ''/O trade/O may/O impact/O emerging/O market/O growth/O drivers/O and/O large/O proportions/O of/O the/O emerging/O market/O labor/O demo/O -/O graphic/O ,/O at/O least/O until/O investments/O in/O infrastructures/O are/O made/O and/O bear/O fruit/O ./O 
The/O beta/O of/O global/O trade/O to/O global/O growth/O already/O seems/O to/O have/O declined/O since/O the/O global/O financial/O crisis/O ,/O and/O this/O is/O one/NUMBER of/O the/O key/O reasons/O EM/O growth/O rates/O have/O been/O so/O weak/O in/O recent/O times/O ./O 
A/O further/O decline/O in/O import/O propen/O -/O sity/O of/O advanced/O economies/O ,/O along/O with/O the/O risk/O of/O a/O struc/O -/O turally/O stronger/O US/LOCATION dollar/O ,/O has/O the/O potential/O to/O hit/O emerging/O markets/O '/O earnings/O and/O cost/O of/O equity/O at/O the/O same/O time/O ./O 
However/O ,/O this/DATE may/DATE also/O be/O a/O catalyst/O for/O emerging/O markets/O to/O invest/O in/O labor/O markets/O ,/O transferable/O skills/O ,/O and/O infrastruc/O -/O ture/O over/O time/O to/O counteract/O this/O relative/O disadvantage/O ./O 
2/NUMBER ./O 
Traditional/O industries/O disrupted/O A/O number/O of/O traditional/O industries/O will/O likely/O be/O disrupted/O by/O the/O advances/O that/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION will/O bring/O to/O market/O ./O 
Investors/O may/O be/O tempted/O to/O pursue/O disruptive/O trends/O by/O investing/O in/O the/O early/O beneficiaries/O of/O extreme/O automation/O and/O connectivity/O ,/O including/O robotics/O ,/O artificial/O intelligence/O ,/O or/O social/O media/O firms/O ./O 
However/O ,/O directly/O picking/O winners/O from/O the/O new/O crop/O of/O technology/O firms/O may/O not/O be/O straightforward/O ./O 
This/O proved/O to/O be/O the/O case/O during/O the/O Dotcom/O boom/O of/O the/DATE late/DATE 1990s/DATE and/O ,/O recently/DATE ,/O the/O aggressive/O valuations/O granted/O to/O several/O tech/O ``/O unicorns/O ''/O --/O a/O term/O for/O a/O start/O up/O worth/O USD/O 1/MONEY billion/MONEY or/O more/O --/O have/O come/O under/O pressure/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O payment/O provider/O Square/O was/O valued/O at/O USD/ORGANIZATION 6/MONEY billion/MONEY in/O a/O round/O of/O private/O financing/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2014/DATE ./O 
But/O an/O initial/O public/O offering/O in/O late/DATE 2015/DATE gave/O the/O firm/O a/O value/O of/O closer/O to/O USD/ORGANIZATION 4/MONEY billion/MONEY ./O 
That/O has/O raised/O worries/O about/O the/O prospects/O for/O other/O leaders/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolu/ORGANIZATION -/O tion/O which/O may/O also/O go/O public/O over/O the/DATE coming/DATE year/DATE ./O 
It/O may/O be/O more/O prudent/O for/O investors/O not/O to/O invest/O in/O richly/O valued/O disruptor/O firms/O ,/O but/O rather/O to/O avoid/O traditional/O indus/O -/O tries/O that/O have/O been/O disrupted/O ./O 
In/O retail/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O auto/O -/O mation/O seems/O to/O be/O mainly/O a/O threat/O ,/O as/O it/O could/O have/O an/O indi/O -/O rect/O negative/O impact/O on/O traditional/O retailers/O by/O fostering/O online/O competition/O ./O 
Particularly/O in/O food/O ,/O the/O online/O business/O is/O growing/O quickly/O but/O still/O represents/O less/O than/O 1/PERCENT %/PERCENT in/O most/O markets/O ./O 
UBS/O summarizes/O the/O possible/O disruption/O threats/O and/O produc/O -/O tivity/O benefits/O ,/O by/O sector/O ,/O in/O the/O below/O table/O :/O Assessment/O relative/O to/O the/O plan/O Medium/O High/O Productivity/O benefits/O High/O UtilitiesAutos/O ,/O IT/O services/O Medium/O Insurance/O ,/O banks/O ,/O travel/O and/O leisure/O ,/O medtech/O Construction/O Low/O Food/O retail/O ,/O general/O retail/O Source/O :/O UBS/ORGANIZATION ,/O as/O of/O November/DATE 15/DATE ,/DATE 2015/DATE ./O 
For/O more/O detail/O please/O see/O the/O UBS/ORGANIZATION Research/ORGANIZATION Q-Series/O report/O entitled/O ``/O How/O disruptive/O will/O the/O new/O dawn/O of/O artificial/O intelligence/O be/O ?/O ''/O 
,/O published/O on/O 15/DATE November/DATE 2015/DATE ./O 
Figure/O 3/NUMBER :/O Which/O sectors/O are/O at/O risk/O from/O disruption/O by/O artificial/O intelligence/O ?/O 
3/NUMBER ./O 
Big/O data/O beneficiaries/O Big/O data/O is/O arguably/O a/O result/O of/O both/O extreme/O automation/O -LRB-/O in/O data/O analysis/O -RRB-/O and/O extreme/O connectivity/O -LRB-/O in/O terms/O of/O data/O collection/O -RRB-/O ./O 
One/NUMBER could/O argue/O that/O big/O data/O is/O a/O ``/O child/O ''/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
As/O explored/O in/O our/O historical/O analysis/O of/O industrial/O revolutions/O ,/O big/O data/O may/O be/O another/O example/O of/O how/O extreme/O connectivity/O is/O giving/O rise/O to/O new/O business/O models/O and/O expanding/O economic/O supply/O in/O ways/O previously/DATE not/O possible/O ./O 
Among/O the/O most/O prominent/O poten/O -/O tial/O beneficiaries/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION are/O firms/O that/O are/O able/O to/O harness/O big/O data/O effectively/O ,/O provide/O data/O analysis/O ,/O and/O offer/O protection/O from/O the/O threat/O of/O cyber/O attacks/O ./O 
Digital/O data/O usage/O globally/O is/O doubling/O every/SET two/SET years/SET ./O 
The/O size/O of/O the/O digital/O universe/O is/O on/O track/O to/O reach/O 44/NUMBER zettabytes/O -LRB-/O ZB/O -RRB-/O by/U_TEMPPRED 2020/DATE ,/O a/O 50/NUMBER fold/O increase/O over/O 2010/DATE ,/O according/O to/O IDC/ORGANIZATION and/O IMC/ORGANIZATION ./O 
That/O is/O equivalent/O to/O 318/NUMBER iPhones/O -LRB-/O 32/NUMBER GB/O -RRB-/O per/O household/O ./O 
This/O surge/O reflects/O both/O the/O expanding/O use/O of/O Internet-enabled/O devises/O in/O rich/O nations/O ,/O embodied/O by/O the/O trend/O toward/O extreme/O connectivity/O via/O the/O Internet/O of/O Things/O ,/O by/O which/O household/O appliances/O are/O linked/O to/O the/O Internet/O ./O 
Big/O data/O beneficiaries/O include/O firms/O that/O harness/O big/O data/O to/O cut/O costs/O or/O target/O sales/O ,/O firms/O that/O automate/O big/O data/O analysis/O ,/O and/O firms/O that/O keep/O big/O data/O secure/O ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O 31/NUMBER First/ORDINAL ,/O there/O are/O several/O industries/O with/O the/O potential/O to/O har/O -/O ness/O big/O data/O and/O cut/O costs/O ,/O increase/O efficiency/O ,/O and/O boost/O profits/O :/O ?/O Within/O retail/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O large/O supermarkets/O have/O long/O been/O analyzing/O big/O data/O sets/O collected/O through/O store/O card/O use/O to/O understand/O customer/O behavior/O ./O 
But/O improve/O -/O ments/O in/O AI/O are/O now/DATE enabling/O extreme/O automation/O in/O the/O data/O analysis/O process/O ./O 
Customer/O data/O on/O physical/O in/O store/O movements/O ,/O collected/O by/O tracking/O smartphone/O data/O ,/O may/O allow/O more/O targeted/O sales/O strategies/O ./O 
When/O linked/O to/O existing/O AI/O infrastructure/O in/O supply/O chains/O ,/O it/O implies/O an/O almost/O total/O ,/O highly/O intelligent/O and/O demand/O flexible/O auto/O -/O mation/O of/O retail/O supply/O chains/O ,/O with/O potentially/O significant/O cost/O savings/O ./O 
?/O Within/O utilities/O ,/O a/O combination/O of/O automated/O big/O data/O analytics/O and/O extreme/O connectivity/O should/O have/O effi/O -/O ciency/O and/O profit/O boosting/O impacts/O over/O time/O ./O 
By/U_TEMPPRED 2014/DATE ,/O General/ORGANIZATION Electric/ORGANIZATION 's/O big/O data/O product/O Predix/O had/O been/O installed/O in/O 23,000/NUMBER wind/O turbines/O and/O close/O to/O 4,000/NUMBER gas/O turbines/O ,/O according/O to/O a/O New/ORGANIZATION York/ORGANIZATION Times/ORGANIZATION article/O ./O 
?/O Applications/O of/O big/O data/O in/O healthcare/O also/O offer/O possible/O investment/O opportunities/O ./O 
Recently/DATE ,/O medtech/O firm/O Medtronic/ORGANIZATION announced/O US/ORGANIZATION Food/ORGANIZATION and/ORGANIZATION Drug/ORGANIZATION Administration/ORGANIZATION approval/O of/O the/O first/ORDINAL app/O based/O remote/O monitoring/O sys/O -/O tem/O for/O pacemaker/O users/O ./O 
Extreme/O connectivity/O now/DATE allows/O pacemaker/O patients/O to/O send/O diagnostic/O data/O from/O their/O device/O ,/O via/O smartphone/O or/O tablet/O ,/O directly/O to/O their/O doctor/O ,/O who/O can/O assess/O patient/O health/O and/O suggest/O any/O changes/O to/O the/O course/O of/O treatment/O ./O 
?/O Increasing/O computing/O power/O has/O also/O been/O driving/O down/O the/O cost/O of/O analyzing/O the/O genome/O and/O the/O pro/O -/O teome/O ,/O the/O sequence/O of/O proteins/O expressed/O by/O genes/O ./O 
An/O increasing/O understanding/O of/O the/O genome/O is/O leading/O to/O medical/O breakthroughs/O in/O fields/O such/O as/O oncology/O ./O 
The/O impact/O of/O big/O data/O ,/O however/O ,/O extends/O beyond/O the/O treatment/O of/O a/O single/O class/O of/O diseases/O ./O 
The/O falling/O cost/O of/O sequencing/O could/O make/O it/O possible/O to/O tailor/O treat/O -/O ments/O to/O best/O suit/O each/O individual/O ,/O which/O could/O reduce/O waste/O and/O in/O turn/O boost/O medical/O outcomes/O and/O the/O profitability/O of/O hospitals/O ./O 
Second/ORDINAL ,/O software/O firms/O that/O provide/O tools/O to/O analyze/O large/O untapped/O pools/O of/O data/O ,/O too/O complex/O to/O manipulate/O with/O standard/O methods/O available/O until/O now/DATE ,/O will/O continue/O to/O ben/O -/O efit/O ./O 
The/O analytics/O software/O market/O alone/O is/O expected/O to/O reach/O USD/O 75/NUMBER billion/NUMBER by/U_TEMPPRED 2020/DATE ,/O with/O solid/O mid/O teens/O growth/O ,/O according/O to/O UBS/ORGANIZATION estimates/O ./O 
Lastly/O ,/O firms/O that/O can/O protect/O big/O data/O should/O thrive/O in/O a/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Already/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2014/DATE ,/O more/O than/O 348/NUMBER million/NUMBER identities/O of/O customers/O or/O employees/O were/O exposed/O to/O cybercrime/O ,/O with/O an/O average/O 21/DURATION hours/DURATION and/O USD/ORGANIZATION 358/NUMBER per/O person/O wasted/O on/O resolving/O online/O crime/O ,/O according/O to/O Symantec/ORGANIZATION 's/O Norton/O Cybersecurity/O Insights/O Report/O ./O 
UBS/O research/O predicts/O that/O by/U_TEMPPRED 2020/DATE the/O projected/O market/O size/O for/O security/O and/O safety/O -LRB-/O including/O measures/O to/O prevent/O cyber/O warfare/O -RRB-/O will/O have/O grown/O to/O around/O USD/MONEY 700/MONEY billion/MONEY -LRB-/O from/O USD/ORGANIZATION 500/NUMBER billion/NUMBER in/U_TEMPPRED 2014/DATE -RRB-/O ./O 
4/NUMBER ./O 
Blockchain/O applications/O Blockchain/PERSON ,/O a/O shared/O digital/O ledger/O system/O that/O underpins/O Bitcoin/O ,/O is/O the/O ultimate/O product/O of/O extreme/O connectivity/O since/O it/O relies/O for/O its/O existence/O on/O the/O interconnection/O of/O a/O large/O number/O of/O computers/O ./O 
The/O technology/O works/O by/O producing/O a/O record/O of/O ownership/O on/O a/O shared/O database/O that/O should/O be/O impossible/O to/O edit/O or/O forge/O ./O 
It/O is/O a/O system/O that/O could/O have/O significant/O investment/O implications/O ./O 
Though/O Bitcoin/O gave/O rise/O to/O blockchain/O ,/O it/O is/O not/O clear/O whether/O the/O original/O crypto/O currency/O will/O survive/O and/O flour/O -/O ish/O ./O 
It/O is/O already/O facing/O competition/O from/O online/O monetary/O units/O that/O are/O more/O secure/O and/O easier/O to/O transact/O ./O 
The/O first/ORDINAL mover/O advantage/O may/O not/O be/O sufficient/O to/O ensure/O the/DATE future/DATE of/O Bitcoin/O ./O 
The/O outlook/O for/O its/O technological/O under/O -/O pinning/O ,/O blockchain/O ,/O looks/O more/O secure/O ,/O given/O possible/O applications/O in/O other/O industries/O :/O Financial/O services/O In/O the/O financial/O services/O sector/O ,/O the/O potential/O effects/O are/O mixed/O ,/O with/O widely/O different/O implications/O for/O bulge/O brackets/O to/O retail/O banks/O and/O from/O money/O transfer/O firms/O to/O insurers/O ./O 
Although/O the/O technology/O remains/O immature/O ,/O a/O host/O of/O mainstream/O financial/O institutions/O are/O expressing/O interest/O in/O developing/O it/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O UBS/ORGANIZATION is/O also/O one/NUMBER of/O 30/NUMBER banks/O to/O have/O joined/O R3/O ,/O a/O global/O consortium/O working/O on/O ways/O to/O use/O blockchain/O in/O financial/O markets/O ./O 
Exchanges/O like/O NASDAQ/O have/O said/O they/O plan/O on/O using/O a/O blockchain/O system/O to/O track/O deals/O in/O pri/ORGANIZATION -/O vate/O company/O shares/O ./O 
Furthermore/O ,/O the/O Lloyd/LOCATION 's/O insurance/O market/O has/O expressed/O interest/O in/O the/O system/O as/O part/O of/O a/O modernization/O initiative/O ./O 
Blockchain/O could/O prove/O a/O double/O edged/O sword/O for/O the/O banking/O industry/O ./O 
On/O the/O one/NUMBER hand/O ,/O it/O has/O the/O potential/O to/O boost/O profitability/O in/O several/O ways/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O when/O money/O is/O transferred/O between/O banks/O ,/O each/O institution/O needs/O to/O engage/O in/O a/O labor-intensive/O process/O of/O ledger/O reconciliation/O to/O confirm/O that/O the/O correct/O sums/O have/O been/O processed/O ./O 
A/O blockchain/O system/O ,/O by/O eliminating/O the/O need/O for/O such/O a/O pro-/O cess/O ,/O could/O allow/O banks/O to/O cut/O middle/O skill/O administrative/O labor/O ,/O a/O point/O cited/O in/O our/O assessment/O of/O the/O economic/O impacts/O of/O the/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION ./O 
According/O to/O Santander/O ,/O more/O efficient/O digital/O ledgers/O could/O cut/O costs/O in/O the/O banking/O industry/O by/O up/O to/O USD/MONEY 20/MONEY billion/MONEY a/DURATION year/DURATION ./O 
On/O the/O other/O hand/O ,/O the/O ability/O to/O process/O transactions/O directly/O between/O parties/O without/O the/O need/O for/O the/O trusted/O central/O utilities/O that/O currently/DATE serve/O the/O function/O of/O reducing/O counterparty/O risk/O poses/O a/O risk/O to/O traditional/O banking/O ./O 
Extreme/O connectivity/O could/O therefore/O lead/O to/O further/O disinter/O -/O mediation/O ,/O a/O theme/O we/O touched/O upon/O first/ORDINAL in/O our/O 2014/DATE Whitepaper/O ,/O ``/O Macro/O problems/O ,/O micro/O solutions/O :/O How/O trade/O ,/O technology/O and/O finance/O can/O help/O keep/O the/O recovery/O going/O ./O ''/O 
For/O international/O transfers/O ,/O especially/O those/O involving/O small/O institutions/O and/O correspondent/O banks/O ,/O payments/O can/O take/O Blockchain/O applications/O could/O benefit/O firms/O that/O use/O them/O to/O automate/O processes/O securely/O ,/O to/O cut/O out/O costly/O intermediaries/O ,/O and/O to/O protect/O intellectual/O property/O ./O 
World/O Economic/O Forum/O 33/NUMBER three/DURATION to/DURATION four/DURATION days/DURATION before/O they/O are/O settled/O ./O 
Since/O blockchain/O transactions/O can/O be/O processed/O in/O as/O little/O as/O 15/DURATION seconds/DURATION ,/O extreme/O connectivity/O shortens/O this/O process/O ,/O freeing/O up/O capi/O -/O tal/O for/O trading/O ,/O investment/O ,/O and/O other/O purposes/O ./O 
While/O near/O realtime/O settlement/O would/O be/O good/O for/O bank/O clients/O ,/O it/O could/O possibly/O reduce/O intra/O day/DURATION liquidity/O for/O banks/O since/O end-of-day/O settlement/O gives/O them/O access/O to/O capital/O for/O longer/O ./O 
Insurance/O could/O also/O be/O transformed/O ./O 
It/O is/O possible/O to/O envision/O insurance/O processing/O using/O extreme/O automation/O ,/O with/O blockchain/O policies/O that/O instantly/O pay/O claims/O based/O on/O preset/O information/O from/O a/O trusted/O third/ORDINAL party/O ./O 
Lloyd/O 's/O of/O London/LOCATION has/O been/O looking/O into/O ways/O to/O use/O blockchains/O to/O improve/O access/O to/O information/O and/O cut/O administrative/O costs/O ./O 
Retail/O banking/O operations/O and/O money/O transfer/O businesses/O also/O face/O a/O clear/O risk/O ./O 
Blockchain/O could/O theoretically/O allow/O individuals/O to/O store/O money/O ,/O bypassing/O the/O need/O for/O banks/O ./O 
Money/O transfer/O operators/O would/O also/O face/O a/O gradual/O erosion/O of/O their/O market/O share/O under/O such/O conditions/O ./O 
Outside/O financial/O services/O In/O branded/O goods/O or/O indeed/O any/O business/O that/O faces/O threats/O to/O intellectual/O property/O ,/O blockchain/O as/O a/O reliable/O method/O of/O verification/O is/O a/O potential/O boon/O ./O 
The/O global/O trade/O in/O counter/O -/O feit/O goods/O and/O pirated/O products/O ,/O estimated/O by/O the/O ICC/ORGANIZATION to/O be/O worth/O as/O much/O as/O USD/O 1.77/NUMBER trillion/NUMBER in/U_TEMPPRED 2015/DATE ,/O stretches/O beyond/O faux-designer/O handbags/O and/O counterfeit/O medicines/O ./O 
``/O Tagging/O ''/O the/O authentic/O goods/O with/O blockchain/O enabled/O digital/O fingerprints/O will/O make/O a/O life/O saving/O difference/O to/O those/O in/O need/O ,/O --/O those/O who/O are/O often/O the/O most/O exposed/O to/O the/O dangers/O wrought/O by/O adulterated/O medicines/O ,/O drugs/O ,/O or/O baby/O food/O ./O 
The/O WHO/O estimates/O that/O more/O than/O 50/PERCENT %/PERCENT of/O medications/O purchased/O from/O online/O vendors/O where/O the/O doctor/O 's/O name/O is/O concealed/O are/O counterfeit/O ./O 
Blockchain/O appli/O -/O cations/O ,/O such/O as/O BlockVerify/O used/O to/O track/O pharmaceuticals/O throughout/O the/O supply/O chain/O ,/O improve/O the/O likelihood/O that/O consumers/O receive/O authentic/O products/O ./O 
A/O demand/O for/O transparency/O was/O borne/O in/O part/O by/O a/O crisis/O of/O brand/O trust/O ./O 
Access/O to/O more/O information/O at/O rapid/O speed/O across/O the/O globe/O is/O a/O result/O of/O extreme/O connectivity/O ./O 
Using/O this/O extreme/O connectivity/O ,/O consumers/O insist/O on/O knowing/O the/O origins/O of/O their/O staple/O goods/O --/O the/O coffee/O they/O drink/O -LRB-/O which/O farm/O did/O it/O come/O from/O ?/O -RRB-/O 
,/O the/O jeans/O they/O wear/O -LRB-/O is/O there/O chemical/O residue/O leftover/O from/O dyeing/O ?/O -RRB-/O 
,/O or/O the/O steak/O they/O eat/O -LRB-/O truly/O hormone/O free/O ?/O -RRB-/O 
./O 
Companies/O like/O Provenance/O are/O the/O first/ORDINAL to/O tackle/O these/O issues/O by/O creating/O transparent/O supply/O chains/O for/O all/O types/O of/O products/O ,/O versus/O those/O specialized/O in/O specific/O products/O like/O diamond/O and/O digital/O artwork/O in/O the/O cases/O of/O Everledger/O and/O Ascribe/O ./O 
Provenance/O was/O designed/O to/O track/O any/O type/O of/O product/O ,/O throughout/O every/O part/O of/O its/O lifecycle/O --/O an/O example/O of/O key/O Fourth/ORGANIZATION Industrial/ORGANIZATION Revolution/ORGANIZATION trends/O of/O extreme/O auto/O -/O mation/O and/O connectivity/O ./O 
www.ubs.com/O ?/O UBS/O 2016/DATE ./O 
The/O key/O symbol/O and/O UBS/ORGANIZATION are/O among/O the/O registered/O and/O unregistered/O trademarks/O of/O UBS/ORGANIZATION ./O 
All/O rights/O reserved/O ./O 
