American/ORGANIZATION Economic/ORGANIZATION Association/ORGANIZATION Why/O Are/O There/O Still/O So/O Many/O Jobs/O ?/O 
The/O History/O and/O Future/DATE of/O Workplace/O Automation/O Author/O -LRB-/O syf/O '/O D/O Y/O L/O G/O +/O $/MONEY X/MONEY W/O R/O r/O Source/O :/O The/O Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O ,/O Vol/O ./O 
The/O History/O and/O Future/DATE of/O Workplace/O Automation1/O David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON There/O jobs/O ./O 
and/O new/O have/O The/O technology/O best-known/O been/O periodic/O were/O early/O warnings/O going/O example/O to/O in/O wipe/O is/O the/O the/O out/O last/O Luddite/O large/O two/DURATION centuries/DURATION numbers/O movement/O that/O of/O middle/O automation/O of/O the/O early/O class/O and/O new/O technology/O were/O going/O to/O wipe/O out/O large/O numbers/O of/O middle/O class/O jobs/O ./O 
The/O best-known/O early/O example/O is/O the/O Luddite/O movement/O of/O the/DATE early/DATE 19th/DATE century/DATE ,/O in/O which/O a/O group/O of/O English/O textile/O artisans/O protested/O the/O automation/O of/O textile/O production/O by/O seeking/O to/O destroy/O some/O of/O the/O machines/O ./O 
A/O lesser-known/O but/O more/O recent/O example/O is/O the/O concern/O over/O &#34;/O The/O Automation/O Jobless/O ,/O &#34;/O as/O they/O were/O called/O in/O the/O title/O of/O a/O TIME/O magazine/O story/O of/O February/DATE 24/DATE ,/DATE 1961/DATE :/O The/O number/O of/O jobs/O lost/O to/O more/O efficient/O machines/O is/O only/O part/O of/O the/O prob/O -/O lem/O ./O 
What/O worries/O many/O job/O experts/O more/O is/O that/O automation/O may/O prevent/O the/O economy/O from/O creating/O enough/O new/O jobs/O .../O ./O 
Throughout/O industry/O ,/O the/O trend/O has/O been/O to/O bigger/O production/O with/O a/O smaller/O work/O force/O .../O ./O 
Many/O of/O the/O losses/O in/O factory/O jobs/O have/O been/O countered/O by/O an/O increase/O in/O the/O service/O industries/O or/O in/O office/O jobs/O ./O 
But/O automation/O is/O beginning/O to/O move/O in/O and/O elimi/O -/O nate/O office/O jobs/O too/O ./O 
.../O In/O ithe/O past/DATE ,/O new/O industries/O hired/O far/O more/O people/O than/O those/O they/O put/O out/O of/O business/O ./O 
But/O this/O is/O not/O true/O of/O many/O of/O today/DATE &#39;/O s/O new/O industries/O .../O ./O 
Today/DATE &#39;/O s/O new/O industries/O have/O comparatively/O few/O jobs/O for/O the/O unskilled/O or/O semiskilled/O ,/O just/O the/O class/O of/O workers/O whose/O jobs/O are/O being/O eliminated/O by/O automation/O ./O 
Concerns/O over/O automation/O and/O joblessness/O during/O the/DATE 1950s/DATE and/O early/DATE 1960s/DATE were/O strong/O enough/O that/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1964/DATE ,/O President/O Lyndon/PERSON B./PERSON Johnson/PERSON empaneled/O a/O ?/O David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON is/O Professor/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Economics/ORGANIZATION ,/O Massachusetts/ORGANIZATION Institute/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION ,/O Cambridge/LOCATION ,/O Massachusetts/LOCATION ./O 
From/O 2009/DATE to/U_TEMPPRED 2014/DATE ,/O he/O was/O Editor/O of/O the/O Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O ./O 
*/O To/O access/O the/O Data/O Appendix/O and/O disclosure/O statement/O ,/O visit/O http://dx.doi.Org/10.1257/jep.29.3.3/O doi/O =/O 10.1257/NUMBER //O jep/O .29.3.3/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 4/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O &#34;/O Blue-Ribbon/ORGANIZATION National/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION on/ORGANIZATION Technology/ORGANIZATION ,/O Automation/O ,/O and/O Economic/O Progress/O &#34;/O to/O confront/O the/O productivity/O problem/O of/O that/O period/O -/O specifically/O ,/O the/O problem/O that/O productivity/O was/O rising/O so/O fast/O it/O might/O outstrip/O demand/O for/O labor/O ./O 
The/O commission/O ultimately/O concluded/O that/O automation/O did/O not/O threaten/O employ/O -/O ment/O :/O &#34;/O Thus/O technological/O change/O -LRB-/O along/O with/O other/O forms/O of/O economic/O changeyf/O L/O s/O an/O important/O determinant/O of/O the/O precise/O places/O ,/O industries/O ,/O and/O people/O affected/O by/O unemployment/O ./O 
But/O the/O general/O level/O of/O demand/O for/O goods/O and/O services/O is/O by/O far/O the/O most/O important/O factor/O determining/O how/O many/O are/O affected/O ,/O how/O long/O they/O stay/O unem/O -/O ployed/O ,/O and/O how/O hard/O it/O is/O for/O new/O entrants/O to/O the/O labor/O market/O to/O find/O jobs/O ./O 
The/O basic/O fact/O is/O that/O technology/O eliminates/O jobs/O ,/O not/O work/O &#34;/O -LRB-/O Bowen/ORGANIZATION 1966/DATE ,/O p./O 9yf/O +/O R/O Z/O H/O Y/O H/O U/O ,/O the/O Commission/ORGANIZATION took/O the/O reality/O of/O technological/O disruption/O as/O severe/O enough/O that/O it/O recommended/O ,/O as/O one/NUMBER newspaper/O -LRB-/O The/O Herald/ORGANIZATION Post/ORGANIZATION 1966yf/O U/O H/O S/O R/O U/O W/O H/O G/O D/O J/O X/O D/O U/O D/O Q/O W/O H/O H/O d/O minimum/O income/O for/O each/O family/O ;/O using/O the/O government/O as/O the/O employer/O of/O last/O resort/O for/O the/O hard/O core/O jobless/O ;/O two/DURATION years/DURATION of/O free/O education/O in/O either/O community/O or/O vocational/O colleges/O ;/O a/O fully/O administered/O federal/O employment/O service/O ,/O and/O indi/O -/O vidual/ORGANIZATION Federal/ORGANIZATION Reserve/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION sponsorship/O in/O area/O economic/O development/O free/O from/O the/O Fed/ORGANIZATION &#39;/O s/O national/O headquarters/O ./O 
&#34;/O Such/O concerns/O have/O recently/DATE regained/O prominence/O ./O 
In/O their/O widely/O discussed/O book/O The/O Second/ORDINAL Machine/O Age/O ,/O MIT/ORGANIZATION scholars/O Erik/PERSON Brynjolfsson/PERSON and/O Andrew/PERSON McAfee/PERSON -LRB-/O 2014/DATE ,/O p./O 11yf/O R/O I/O I/O H/O U/O D/O Q/O X/O Q/O V/O H/O W/O W/O O/O L/O Q/O J/O S/O L/O F/O W/O X/O U/O H/O R/O I/O W/O K/O H/O O/O L/O N/O H/O O/O \/O H/O I/O I/O H/O F/O W/O V/O R/O I/O D/O X/O W/O R/O P/O D/O W/O L/O R/O Q/O R/O Q/O H/O P/O S/O O/O R/O \/O P/O H/O Q/O W/O :/O Rapid/O and/O accelerating/O digitization/O is/O likely/O to/O bring/O economic/O rather/O than/O environmental/O disruption/O ,/O stemming/O from/O the/O fact/O that/O as/O computers/O get/O more/O powerful/O ,/O companies/O have/O less/O need/O for/O some/O kinds/O of/O workers/O ./O 
Technological/O progress/O is/O going/O to/O leave/O behind/O some/O people/O ,/O perhaps/O even/O a/O lot/O of/O people/O ,/O as/O it/O races/O ahead/O ./O 
As/O we/O &#39;/O ll/O demonstrate/O ,/O there/O &#39;/O s/O never/O been/O a/O better/O time/O to/O be/O a/O worker/O with/O special/O skills/O or/O the/O right/O education/O ,/O because/O these/O people/O can/O use/O technology/O to/O create/O and/O capture/O value/O ./O 
However/O ,/O there/O &#39;/O s/O never/O been/O a/O worse/O time/O to/O be/O a/O worker/O with/O only/O &#39;/O ordinary/O &#39;/O skills/O and/O abilities/O to/O offer/O ,/O because/O computers/O ,/O robots/O ,/O and/O other/O digital/O technologies/O are/O acquiring/O these/O skills/O and/O abilities/O at/O an/O extraordinary/O rate/O ./O 
Clearly/O ,/O the/DURATION past/DURATION two/DURATION centuries/DURATION of/O automation/O and/O technological/O progress/O have/O not/O made/O human/O labor/O obsolete/O :/O the/O employment-to-population/O ratio/O rose/O during/O the/DATE 20th/DATE century/DATE even/O as/O women/O moved/O from/O home/O to/O market/O ;/O and/O although/O the/O unemployment/O rate/O fluctuates/O cyclically/O ,/O there/O is/O no/O apparent/O long-run/O increase/O ./O 
But/O those/O concerned/O about/O automation/O and/O employment/O are/O quick/O to/O point/O out/O that/O past/DATE interactions/O between/O automation/O and/O employment/O can/O not/O settle/O arguments/O about/O how/O these/O elements/O might/O interact/O in/O the/DATE future/DATE :/O in/O particular/O ,/O the/O emergence/O of/O greatly/O improved/O computing/O power/O ,/O artificial/O intelligence/O ,/O and/O robotics/O raises/O the/O possibility/O of/O replacing/O labor/O on/O a/O scale/O not/O previously/DATE observed/O ./O 
There/O is/O no/O funda/O -/O mental/O economic/O law/O that/O guarantees/O every/O adult/O will/O be/O able/O to/O earn/O a/O living/O solely/O on/O the/O basis/O of/O sound/O mind/O and/O good/O character/O ./O 
Whatever/O the/DATE future/DATE holds/O ,/O the/O present/DATE clearly/O offers/O a/O resurgence/O of/O automation/O anxiety/O -LRB-/O Akst/ORGANIZATION 2013yf/ORGANIZATION ./O 
This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON 5/NUMBER In/O this/O essay/O ,/O I/O begin/O by/O identifying/O the/O reasons/O that/O automation/O has/O not/O wiped/O out/O a/O majority/O of/O jobs/O over/O the/DURATION decades/DURATION and/O centuries/DURATION ./O 
Automation/O does/O indeed/O substitute/O for/O labor/O -/O as/O it/O is/O typically/O intended/O to/O do/O ./O 
However/O ,/O automation/O also/O complements/O labor/O ,/O raises/O output/O in/O ways/O that/O lead/O to/O higher/O demand/O for/O labor/O ,/O and/O interacts/O with/O adjustments/O in/O labor/O supply/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O a/O key/O observation/O of/O the/O paper/O is/O that/O journalists/O and/O even/O expert/O commentators/O tend/O to/O overstate/O the/O extent/O of/O machine/O substitution/O for/O human/O labor/O and/O ignore/O the/O strong/O complementarities/O between/O automation/O and/O labor/O that/O increase/O productivity/O ,/O raise/O earnings/O ,/O and/O augment/O demand/O for/O labor/O ./O 
Changes/O in/O technology/O do/O alter/O the/O types/O of/O jobs/O available/O and/O what/O those/O jobs/O pay/O ./O 
In/O the/DURATION last/DATE few/DATE decades/DATE ,/O one/NUMBER noticeable/O change/O has/O been/O &#34;/O polarization/O &#34;/O of/O the/O labor/O market/O ,/O in/O which/O wage/O gains/O went/O disproportionately/O to/O those/O at/O the/O top/O and/O at/O the/O bottom/O of/O the/O income/O and/O skill/O distribution/O ,/O not/O to/O those/O in/O the/O middle/O ./O 
I/O will/O offer/O some/O evidence/O on/O this/O phenomenon/O ./O 
However/O ,/O I/O will/O also/O argue/O that/O this/O polar/O -/O ization/O is/O unlikely/O to/O continue/O very/O far/O into/O the/O foreseeable/O future/DATE ./O 
The/O final/O section/O of/O this/O paper/O reflects/O on/O how/O recent/O and/O future/DATE advances/O in/O arti/O -/O ficial/O intelligence/O and/O robotics/O should/O shape/O our/O thinking/O about/O the/O likely/O trajectory/O of/O occupational/O change/O and/O employment/O growth/O ./O 
I/O argue/O that/O the/O interplay/O between/O machine/O and/O human/O comparative/O advantage/O allows/O computers/O to/O substitute/O for/O workers/O in/O performing/O routine/O ,/O codifiable/O tasks/O while/O amplifying/O the/O comparative/O advantage/O of/O workers/O in/O supplying/O problem-solving/O skills/O ,/O adaptability/O ,/O and/O creativity/O ./O 
The/O frontier/O of/O automation/O is/O rapidly/O advancing/O ,/O and/O the/O challenges/O to/O substituting/O machines/O for/O workers/O in/O tasks/O requiring/O flexibility/O ,/O judgment/O ,/O and/O common/O sense/O remain/O immense/O ./O 
In/O many/O cases/O ,/O machines/O both/O substitute/O for/O and/O complement/O human/O labor/O ./O 
Focusing/O only/O on/O what/O is/O lost/O misses/O a/O central/O economic/O mechanism/O by/O which/O automation/O affects/O the/O demand/O for/O labor/O :/O raising/O the/O value/O of/O the/O tasks/O that/O workers/O uniquely/O supply/O ./O 
How/O Automation/O and/O Employment/O Interact/O In/U_TEMPPRED 1900/DATE ,/O 41/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O the/O US/LOCATION workforce/O was/O employed/O in/O agriculture/O ;/O by/U_TEMPPRED 2000/DATE ,/O that/O share/O had/O fallen/O to/O 2/PERCENT percent/PERCENT -LRB-/O Autor/O 2014yf/O P/O R/O V/O W/O O/O \/O G/O X/O H/O W/O R/O D/O Z/O L/O G/O H/O U/O D/O Q/O J/O e/O of/O technologies/O including/O automated/O machinery/O ./O 
The/O mass-produced/O automo/O -/O bile/O drastically/O reduced/O demand/O for/O many/O equestrian/O occupations/O ,/O including/O blacksmiths/O and/O stable/O hands/O ./O 
Successive/O waves/O of/O earth-moving/O equipment/O and/O powered/O tools/O displaced/O manual/O labor/O from/O construction/O ./O 
In/O more/O recent/DURATION years/DURATION ,/O when/O a/O computer/O processes/O a/O company/O &#39;/O s/O payroll/O ,/O alphabetizes/O a/O list/O of/O names/O ,/O or/O tabulates/O the/O age/O distribution/O of/O residents/O in/O each/O Census/O enumeration/O district/O ,/O it/O is/O replacing/O a/O task/O that/O a/O human/O would/O have/O done/O in/O a/O previous/O era/O ./O 
Broadly/O speaking/O ,/O many/O -/O perhaps/O most/O -/O workplace/O technologies/O are/O designed/O to/O save/O labor/O ./O 
Whether/O the/O technology/O is/O tractors/O ,/O assembly/O lines/O ,/O or/O spreadsheets/O ,/O the/O first-order/O goal/O is/O to/O substitute/O mechanical/O power/O for/O human/O musculature/O ,/O machine-consistency/O for/O human/O handiwork/O ,/O and/O digital/O calculation/O for/O slow/O and/O error-prone/O &#34;/O wetware/O ./O 
&#34;/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 6/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O Given/O that/O these/O technologies/O demonstrably/O succeed/O in/O their/O labor/O saving/O objective/O and/O ,/O moreover/O ,/O that/O we/O invent/O many/O more/O labor-saving/O technologies/O all/O the/O time/O ,/O should/O we/O not/O be/O somewhat/O surprised/O that/O technological/O change/O hasn/O &#39;/O t/O already/O wiped/O out/O employment/O for/O the/O vast/O majority/O of/O workers/O ?/O 
Why/O doesn/O &#39;/O t/O auto/O -/O mation/O necessarily/O reduce/O aggregate/O employment/O ,/O even/O as/O it/O demonstrably/O reduces/O labor/O requirements/O per/O unit/O of/O output/O produced/O ?/O 
These/O questions/O underline/O an/O economic/O reality/O that/O is/O as/O fundamental/O as/O it/O is/O over/O -/O looked/O :/O tasks/O that/O can/O not/O be/O substituted/O by/O automation/O are/O generally/O complemented/O by/O it/O ./O 
Most/O work/O processes/O draw/O upon/O a/O multifaceted/O set/O of/O inputs/O :/O labor/O and/O capital/O ;/O brains/O and/O brawn/O ;/O creativity/O and/O rote/O repetition/O ;/O technical/O mastery/O and/O intuitive/O judg/O -/O ment/O ;/O perspiration/O and/O inspiration/O ;/O adherence/O to/O rules/O and/O judicious/O application/O of/O discretion/O ./O 
Typically/O ,/O these/O inputs/O each/O play/O essential/O roles/O ;/O that/O is/O ,/O improvements/O in/O one/NUMBER do/O not/O obviate/O the/O need/O for/O the/O other/O ./O 
If/O so/O ,/O productivity/O improvements/O in/O one/NUMBER set/O of/O tasks/O almost/O necessarily/O increase/O the/O economic/O value/O of/O the/O remaining/O tasks/O ./O 
An/O iconic/O representation/O of/O this/O idea/O is/O found/O in/O the/O O-ring/O production/O function/O studied/O by/O Kremer/PERSON -LRB-/O 1993yf/O `/O ,/O Q/O W/O K/O H/O 2/NUMBER U/O L/O Q/O J/O P/O R/O G/O H/O O/O I/O D/O L/O O/O X/O U/O H/O R/O I/O D/O Q/O \/O R/O Q/O H/O V/O W/O H/O S/O L/O Q/O W/O K/O H/O F/O K/O D/O L/O n/O of/O production/O leads/O the/O entire/O production/O process/O to/O fail/O ./O 
Conversely/O ,/O improvements/O in/O the/O reliability/O of/O any/O given/O link/O increase/O the/O value/O of/O improvements/O in/O all/O of/O the/O others/O ./O 
Intuitively/O ,/O if/O n/O -/O 1/NUMBER links/O in/O the/O chain/O are/O reasonably/O likely/O to/O fail/O ,/O the/O fact/O that/O link/O n/O is/O somewhat/O unreliable/O is/O of/O little/O consequence/O ./O 
If/O the/O other/O n/O -/O 1/NUMBER links/O are/O made/O reliable/O ,/O then/O the/O value/O of/O making/O link/O n/O more/O reliable/O as/O well/O rises/O ./O 
Analo/O -/O gously/O ,/O when/O automation/O or/O computerization/O makes/O some/O steps/O in/O a/O work/O process/O more/O reliable/O ,/O cheaper/O ,/O or/O faster/O ,/O this/O increases/O the/O value/O of/O the/O remaining/O human/O links/O in/O the/O production/O chain/O ./O 
As/O a/O contemporary/O example/O ,/O consider/O the/O surprising/O complementarities/O between/O information/O technology/O and/O employment/O in/O banking/O ,/O specifically/O the/O experience/O with/O automated/O teller/O machines/O -LRB-/O ATMsyf/O D/O Q/O G/O E/O D/O Q/O N/O W/O H/O O/O O/O H/O U/O V/O G/O R/O F/O X/O P/O H/O Q/O W/O H/O G/O E/O \/PERCENT %/PERCENT H/O V/O V/O H/O Q/O \/O f./O ATMs/O were/O introduced/O in/O the/DATE 1970s/DATE ,/O and/O their/O numbers/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION economy/O quadrupled/O from/O approximately/O 100,000/NUMBER to/O 400,000/NUMBER between/O 1995/DATE and/O 2010/DATE ./O 
One/NUMBER might/O naturally/O assume/O that/O these/O machines/O had/O all/O but/O eliminated/O bank/O tellers/O in/O that/O interval/O ./O 
But/O US/LOCATION bank/O teller/O employment/O actually/O rose/O modestly/O from/O 500,000/NUMBER to/O approximately/O 550,000/NUMBER over/O the/O 30-year/DURATION period/O from/O 1980/DATE to/O 2010/DATE -LRB-/O although/O given/O the/O growth/O in/O the/O labor/O force/O in/O this/O time/O interval/O ,/O these/O numbers/O do/O imply/O that/O bank/O tellers/O declined/O as/O a/O share/O of/O overall/O US/O employmentyf/O :/O L/O W/O K/O W/O K/O H/O J/O U/O R/O Z/O W/O K/O R/O I/O $/MONEY 7/MONEY 0/MONEY V/O Z/O K/O D/O W/O D/O U/O H/O D/O O/O O/O R/O I/O W/O K/O H/O V/O e/O tellers/O doing/O ?/O 
Bessen/PERSON observes/O that/O two/NUMBER forces/O worked/O in/O opposite/O directions/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O by/O reducing/O the/O cost/O of/O operating/O a/O bank/O branch/O ,/O ATMs/O indirectly/O increased/O the/O demand/O for/O tellers/O :/O the/O number/O of/O tellers/O per/O branch/O fell/O by/O more/O than/O a/O third/ORDINAL between/O 1988/DATE and/O 2004/DATE ,/O but/O the/O number/O of/O urban/O bank/O branches/O -LRB-/O also/O encouraged/O by/O a/O wave/O of/O 1/NUMBER The/O name/O of/O the/O O-ring/O production/O function/O refers/O to/O the/O 1986/DATE accident/O of/O Space/O Shuttle/O Challenger/O ,/O which/O exploded/O and/O crashed/O back/O to/O earth/O less/DURATION than/DURATION two/DURATION minutes/DURATION after/O takeoff/O ,/O killing/O its/O seven/NUMBER crew/O members/O ./O 
The/O proximate/O cause/O of/O the/O Challenger/O crash/O was/O an/O inexpensive/O and/O seemingly/O inconsequen/O -/O tial/O rubber/O O-ring/O seal/O in/O one/NUMBER of/O its/O booster/O rockets/O that/O failed/O after/O hardening/O and/O cracking/O during/O the/O icy/O Florida/LOCATION weather/O on/O the/O night/TIME before/TIME takeoff/O ./O 
This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O Why/O Are/O There/O Still/O So/O Many/O Jobs/O ?/O 
7/NUMBER bank/O deregulation/O allowing/O more/O branchesyf/O U/O R/O V/O H/O E/O \/O P/O R/O U/O H/O W/O K/O D/O Q/O S/O H/O U/O F/O H/O Q/O W/O 6/NUMBER H/O F/O R/O Q/O G/O ,/O as/O the/O routine/O cash-handling/O tasks/O of/O bank/O tellers/O receded/O ,/O information/O technology/O also/O enabled/O a/O broader/O range/O of/O bank/O personnel/O to/O become/O involved/O in/O &#34;/O relationship/O banking/O ./O 
&#34;/O Increasingly/O ,/O banks/O recognized/O the/O value/O of/O tellers/O enabled/O by/O information/O technology/O ,/O not/O primarily/O as/O checkout/O clerks/O ,/O but/O as/O salespersons/O ,/O forging/O relation/O -/O ships/O with/O customers/O and/O introducing/O them/O to/O additional/O bank/O services/O like/O credit/O cards/O ,/O loans/O ,/O and/O investment/O products/O ./O 
This/O example/O should/O not/O be/O taken/O as/O paradigmatic/O ;/O technological/O change/O is/O not/O necessarily/O employment-increasing/O or/O Pareto-improving/O ./O 
Three/NUMBER main/O factors/O can/O mitigate/O or/O augment/O its/O impacts/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O workers/O are/O more/O likely/O to/O benefit/O directly/O from/O automation/O if/O they/O supply/O tasks/O that/O are/O complemented/O by/O automation/O ,/O but/O not/O if/O they/O primarily/O -LRB-/O or/O exclusivelyyf/O V/O X/O S/O S/O O/O \/O W/O D/O V/O N/O V/O W/O K/O D/O W/O D/O U/O H/O V/O X/O E/O V/O W/O L/O W/O X/O W/O H/O G/O $/MONEY F/MONEY R/O Q/O V/O W/O U/O X/O F/O -/O tion/O worker/O who/O is/O expert/O with/O a/O shovel/O but/O can/O not/O drive/O an/O excavator/O will/O generally/O experience/O falling/O wages/O as/O automation/O advances/O ./O 
Similarly/O ,/O a/O bank/O teller/O who/O can/O tally/O currency/O but/O can/O not/O provide/O &#34;/O relationship/O banking/O &#34;/O is/O unlikely/O to/O fare/O well/O at/O a/O modern/O bank/O ./O 
Second/ORDINAL ,/O the/O elasticity/O of/O labor/O supply/O can/O mitigate/O wage/O gains/O ./O 
If/O the/O complemen/O -/O tary/O tasks/O that/O construction/O workers/O or/O relationship/O bankers/O supply/O are/O abundantly/O available/O elsewhere/O in/O the/O economy/O ,/O then/O it/O is/O plausible/O that/O a/O flood/O of/O new/O workers/O will/O temper/O any/O wage/O gains/O that/O would/O emanate/O from/O complementarities/O between/O automation/O and/O human/O labor/O input/O ./O 
While/O these/O kinds/O of/O supply/O effects/O will/O prob/O -/O ably/O not/O offset/O productivity-driven/O wage/O gains/O fully/O ,/O one/NUMBER can/O find/O extreme/O examples/O :/O Hsieh/O and/O Moretti/PERSON -LRB-/O 2003yf/O G/O R/O F/O X/O P/O H/O Q/O W/O W/O K/O D/O W/O Q/O H/O Z/O H/O Q/O W/O U/O \/O L/O Q/O W/O R/O W/O K/O H/O U/O H/O D/O O/O H/O V/O W/O D/O W/O H/O E/O U/O R/O N/O H/O U/O R/O F/O F/O X/O -/O pation/O in/O response/O to/O rising/O house/O prices/O fully/O offsets/O average/O wage/O gains/O that/O would/O otherwise/O have/O occurred/O ./O 
Third/ORDINAL ,/O the/O output/O elasticity/O of/O demand/O combined/O with/O income/O elasticity/O of/O demand/O can/O either/O dampen/O or/O amplify/O the/O gains/O from/O automation/O ./O 
In/O the/O case/O of/O agricultural/O products/O over/O the/O long/O run/O ,/O spectacular/O productivity/O improvements/O have/O been/O accompanied/O by/O declines/O in/O the/O share/O of/O household/O income/O spent/O on/O food/O ./O 
In/O other/O cases/O ,/O such/O as/O the/O health/O care/O sector/O ,/O improvements/O in/O technology/O have/O led/O to/O ever-larger/O shares/O of/O income/O being/O spent/O on/O health/O ./O 
Even/O if/O the/O elasticity/O of/O final/O demand/O for/O a/O given/O sector/O is/O below/O unity/O -/O meaning/O that/O the/O sector/O shrinks/O as/O produc/O -/O tivity/O rises/O -/O this/O does/O not/O imply/O that/O aggregate/O demand/O falls/O as/O technology/O advances/O ;/O clearly/O ,/O the/O surplus/O income/O can/O be/O spent/O elsewhere/O ./O 
As/O passenger/O cars/O displaced/O eques/O -/O trian/O travel/O and/O the/O myriad/O occupations/O that/O supported/O it/O in/O the/DATE 1920s/DATE ,/O the/O roadside/O motel/O and/O fast/O food/O industries/O rose/O up/O to/O serve/O the/O &#34;/O motoring/O public/O &#34;/O -LRB-/O Jackson/ORGANIZATION 1993yf/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Rising/O income/O may/O also/O spur/O demand/O for/O activities/O that/O have/O nothing/O to/O do/O with/O the/O technological/O vanguard/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Production/O of/O restaurant/O meals/O ,/O cleaning/O services/O ,/O haircare/O ,/O and/O personal/O fitness/O is/O neither/O strongly/O complemented/O nor/O substituted/O by/O current/DATE technologies/O ;/O these/O sectors/O are/O &#34;/O technologically/O lagging/O &#34;/O in/O Baumol/O &#39;/O s/O -LRB-/O 1967yf/O S/O K/O U/O D/O V/O H/O ./O 
But/O demand/O for/O these/O goods/O appears/O strongly/O income-elastic/O ,/O so/O that/O rising/O produc/O -/O tivity/O in/O technologically/O leading/O sectors/O may/O boost/O employment/O nevertheless/O in/O these/O activities/O ./O 
Ultimately/O ,/O this/O outcome/O requires/O that/O the/O elasticity/O of/O substitution/O between/O leading/O and/O lagging/O sectors/O is/O less/O than/O or/O equal/O to/O unity/O -LRB-/O Autor/O and/O Dora/PERSON 2013yf/PERSON ./O 
This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 8/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O Over/O the/O very/O long/O run/O ,/O gains/O in/O productivity/O have/O not/O led/O to/O a/O shortfall/O of/O demand/O for/O goods/O and/O services/O :/O instead/O ,/O household/O consumption/O has/O largely/O kept/O pace/O with/O household/O incomes/O ./O 
We/O know/O this/O because/O the/O share/O of/O the/O population/O engaged/O in/O paid/O employment/O has/O generally/O risen/O over/O -LRB-/O at/O leastyf/O W/O K/O H/O S/O D/O V/O W/O F/O H/O Q/O W/O X/O U/O y/O despite/O vast/O improvements/O in/O material/O standards/O of/O living/O ./O 
An/O average/O US/LOCATION worker/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2015/DATE wishing/O to/O live/O at/O the/O income/O level/O of/O an/O average/O worker/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1915/DATE could/O roughly/O achieve/O this/O goal/O by/O working/O about/DURATION 17/DURATION weeks/DURATION per/O year/DURATION .2/NUMBER Most/O citizens/O would/O not/O consider/O this/O tradeoff/O between/O hours/DURATION and/O income/O desirable/O ,/O however/O ,/O suggesting/O that/O consumption/O demands/O have/O risen/O along/O with/O productivity/O ./O 
Of/O course/O ,/O citizens/O in/O high-income/O countries/O work/O fewer/O annual/SET hours/DURATION ,/O take/O more/O vacations/O ,/O and/O retire/O earlier/O -LRB-/O relative/O to/O deathyf/O W/O K/O D/O Q/O D/O F/O H/O Q/O W/O X/O U/O \/O D/O J/O R/O L/O P/O S/O O/O \/O L/O Q/O J/O W/O K/O D/O W/O W/O K/O H/O \/O F/O K/O R/O R/O V/O H/O W/O R/O V/O S/O H/O Q/O d/O part/O of/O their/O rising/O incomes/O on/O increased/O leisure/O ./O 
This/O is/O clearly/O good/O news/O on/O many/O fronts/O ,/O but/O does/O it/O also/O imply/O that/O consumption/O demands/O are/O approaching/O satia/O -/O tion/O ?/O 
I/O think/O not/O ./O 
In/O high-income/O countries/O ,/O consumption/O and/O leisure/O appear/O to/O be/O complements/O ;/O citizens/O spend/O much/O of/O their/O leisure/O time/O consuming/O -/O shopping/O ,/O traveling/O ,/O dining/O ,/O and/O ,/O less/O pleasantly/O ,/O obtaining/O medical/O care/O .3/NUMBER What/O about/O the/O Marxian/O concern/O that/O automation/O will/O immiserate/O workers/O by/O obviating/O the/O demand/O for/O labor/O ?/O 
In/O simple/O economic/O models/O ,/O this/O outcome/O can/O not/O really/O occur/O because/O capital/O is/O owned/O by/O the/O economic/O agents/O who/O are/O presumably/O also/O the/O workers/O ;/O but/O ,/O alternatively/O ,/O the/O returns/O could/O accrue/O to/O a/O narrow/O subset/O of/O agents/O ./O 
Sachs/O and/O Kotlikoff/PERSON -LRB-/O 2012yf/O D/O Q/O G/O 6/NUMBER D/O F/O K/O V/PERCENT %/PERCENT H/O Q/O -RSB-/O H/O O/O O/O D/O Q/O G/O //O D/O */O D/O U/O G/O D/O \/O f/O explore/O multigenerational/O economic/O environments/O in/O which/O a/O burst/O of/O robotic/O productivity/O can/O enrich/O one/NUMBER generation/O of/O capital/O owners/O at/O the/O expense/O of/O future/DATE generations/O ./O 
These/O later/O generations/O suffer/O because/O the/O fruits/O of/O the/O productivity/O surge/O are/O consumed/O by/O the/O old/O ,/O while/O the/O young/O face/O diminished/O demand/O for/O their/O labor/O and/O ,/O in/O some/O cases/O ,/O also/O experience/O credit/O constraints/O that/O inhibit/O their/O human/O capital/O investments/O ./O 
In/O these/O models/O ,/O the/O fundamental/O threat/O is/O not/O technology/O per/O se/O but/O misgovernance/O ;/O an/O appropriate/O capital/O tax/O will/O render/O the/O technological/O advance/O broadly/O welfare-improving/O ,/O as/O these/O papers/O stress/O ./O 
Thus/O ,/O a/O key/O takeaway/O is/O that/O rapid/O automation/O may/O create/O distributional/O challenges/O that/O invite/O a/O broad/O policy/O response/O ,/O a/O point/O to/O which/O I/O will/O return/O ./O 
2/NUMBER Douglas/PERSON -LRB-/O 1930/DATE ;/O reproduced/O in/O US/LOCATION Bureau/LOCATION of/O the/O Census/O 1949yf/O U/O H/O S/O R/O U/O W/O V/O D/O Y/O H/O U/O D/O J/O H/O D/O Q/O Q/O X/O D/O O/O H/O D/O U/O Q/O L/O Q/O J/O V/O D/O F/O U/O R/O V/O s/O all/O sectors/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1915/DATE at/O $/MONEY 633/MONEY ./O 
Inflating/O this/O to/O 2015/MONEY dollars/MONEY using/O the/O US/ORGANIZATION Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION historical/O Consumer/O Price/O Index/O calculator/O yields/O a/O current/DATE dollar/O equivalent/O of/O $/MONEY 14,711/MONEY ./O 
The/O BLS/ORGANIZATION employment/O report/O from/O April/DATE 2015/DATE reports/O mean/O weekly/SET private/O nonfarm/O earnings/O of/O $/MONEY 858/MONEY ./O 
Thus/O ,/O it/O would/O take/O 17/DURATION weeks/DURATION of/O work/O at/O the/O average/O US/LOCATION weekly/SET wage/O to/O earn/O a/O full-time/O annual/SET 1915/DATE income/O ./O 
3/NUMBER This/O outcome/O is/O a/O modern/O version/O of/O the/O &#34;/O coal/O paradox/O &#34;/O posed/O by/O William/PERSON Stanley/PERSON Jevons/PERSON in/O his/O 1865/DATE book/O The/O Coal/O Question/O ./O 
Jevons/O argued/O that/O as/O we/O became/O more/O efficient/O in/O mining/O coal/O ,/O we/O would/O use/O more/O of/O it/O ,/O not/O less/O ./O 
Modern/O environmental/O economists/O term/O this/O idea/O the/O &#34;/O rebound/O effect/O ./O 
&#34;/O In/O this/O discus/O -/O sion/O ,/O the/O broad/O parallel/O is/O that/O greater/O efficiency/O of/O production/O of/O all/O goods/O and/O services/O means/O that/O we/O consume/O more/O of/O them/O ,/O not/O the/O same/O or/O less/O ./O 
This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON 9/NUMBER Figure/O 1/NUMBER Average/O Change/O per/O Decade/DURATION in/O US/LOCATION Occupational/O Employment/O Shares/O for/O Two/NUMBER Periods/O :/O 1940-1980/DURATION and/O 1980-2010/DURATION Source/O :/O Based/O on/O Katz/PERSON and/O Margo/PERSON -LRB-/O 2014/DATE ;/O ,/O table/O 1.6/NUMBER ,/O panel/O A/O ,/O which/O is/O based/O upon/O the/O 1920/DATE through/O 2000/DATE Census/O of/O population/O IPUMS/O and/O 2010/DATE American/ORGANIZATION Community/ORGANIZATION Survey/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Notes/O :/O Observed/O long/O changes/O in/O US/LOCATION occupational/O employment/O shares/O over/O 1940-1980/DURATION and/O 1980-2010/DURATION are/O scaled/O by/O the/O number/O of/O intervening/O decades/DURATION to/O yield/O average/O change/O per/O decade/DURATION ./O 
Occupations/O are/O classified/O into/O occupational/O groups/O based/O on/U_TEMPPRED 1950/DATE occupation/O codes/O using/O the/O consistent/O coding/O of/O occupations/O in/O all/O years/DURATION into/O 1950/DATE codes/O -LRB-/O the/O OCC1950/O variableyf/O L/O Q/O W/O K/O H/O ,/O 3/MONEY 8/MONEY 0/MONEY 6/MONEY $/MONEY G/MONEY G/O L/O W/O L/O R/O Q/O D/O O/O G/O H/O W/O D/O L/O O/O V/O D/O U/O e/O found/O in/O Katz/PERSON and/O Margo/PERSON -LRB-/O 2014/DATE ,/O p./O 46yf/O ./O 
Polarization/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION Labor/O Market/O Even/O if/O automation/O does/O not/O reduce/O the/O quantity/O of/O jobs/O ,/O it/O may/O greatly/O affect/O the/O qualities/O of/O jobs/O available/O ./O 
For/O the/DURATION three/DURATION decades/DURATION or/O so/O from/O the/O end/O of/O World/O War/O II/O and/O up/O through/O the/DATE late/DATE 1970s/DATE ,/O the/O US/LOCATION experienced/O rapid/O automation/O and/O tech/O -/O nological/O change/O -/O inspiring/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O the/O TIME/O magazine/O story/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1961/DATE and/O Lyndon/PERSON Johnson/PERSON &#39;/O s/O 1964/DATE National/ORGANIZATION Commission/ORGANIZATION mentioned/O earlier/O ./O 
While/O it/O &#39;/O s/O diffi/O -/O cult/O to/O paint/O an/O accurate/O picture/O of/O occupational/O change/O over/O a/O large/O time/O interval/O ,/O Figure/O 1/NUMBER ,/O which/O draws/O from/O Katz/PERSON and/O Margo/PERSON -LRB-/O 2014yf/O S/O U/O R/O Y/O L/O G/O H/O V/O D/O K/O L/O J/O K/O O/O H/O Y/O H/O O/O R/O Y/O H/O U/O Y/O L/O H/O w/O by/O depicting/O the/O average/O change/O per/O decade/DURATION in/O employment/O for/O seven/NUMBER broad/O occu/O -/O pational/O categories/O ,/O ranked/O from/O lowest/O to/O highest/O paid/O ,/O for/O two/NUMBER periods/O :/O 1940-1980/DURATION and/O 1980-2010/DURATION ./O 
In/O the/DURATION first/DURATION four/DURATION decades/DURATION after/O World/O War/O II/O ,/O the/O thrust/O of/O occupa/O -/O tional/O change/O skewed/O strongly/O away/O from/O physically/O demanding/O ,/O dangerous/O ,/O and/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 1/NUMBER 0/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O menial/O work/O and/O towards/O skilled/O blue/O -/O and/O white-collar/O work/O ./O 
Agricultural/O employ/O -/O ment/O declined/O by/O almost/O 4/NUMBER percentage/O points/O per/O decade/DURATION ./O 
Professional/O ,/O technical/O ,/O and/O managerial/O employment/O -/O the/O highest/O skill/O categories/O -/O grew/O by/O 3/NUMBER percentage/O points/O per/O decade/DURATION -LRB-/O 2.5/NUMBER for/O the/O professionals/O and/O technicians/O plus/O 0.5/NUMBER for/O the/O managersyf/O $/MONEY Q/MONEY G/O D/O P/O R/O Q/O J/O W/O K/O H/O Y/O D/O V/O W/O P/O L/O G/O G/O O/O H/O J/O U/O R/O X/O S/O R/O I/O Z/O R/O U/O N/O H/O U/O V/O E/O H/O W/O Z/O H/O H/O Q/O D/O J/O U/O L/O F/O X/O O/O W/O X/O U/O H/O D/O t/O the/O bottomyf/O D/O Q/O G/O S/O U/O R/O I/O H/O V/O V/O L/O R/O Q/O D/O O/O W/O H/O F/O K/O Q/O L/O F/O D/O O/O D/O Q/O G/O P/O D/O Q/O D/O J/O H/O U/O L/O D/O O/O W/O K/O H/O W/O K/O U/O H/O H/O J/O U/O R/O X/O S/O V/O D/O W/O W/O K/O e/O topyf/O V/O H/O U/O Y/O L/O F/O H/O D/O Q/O G/O V/O N/O L/O O/O O/O H/O G/O E/O O/O X/O H/O F/O R/O O/O O/O D/O U/O R/O F/O F/O X/O S/O D/O W/O L/O R/O Q/O V/O Z/O H/O U/O H/O V/O W/O D/O E/O O/O H/O F/O O/O H/O U/O L/O F/O D/O O/O V/O D/O O/O H/O V/O R/O F/O F/O X/O S/O D/O -/O tions/O rose/O ,/O and/O operative/O and/O laborer/O occupations/O fell/O sharply/O ./O 
Thus/O ,/O physically/O demanding/O ,/O repetitive/O ,/O dangerous/O ,/O and/O cognitively/O monot/O -/O onous/O work/O was/O receding/O ,/O ushered/O out/O by/O extraordinary/O productivity/O gains/O in/O agriculture/O ./O 
Rising/O consumer/O affluence/O spurred/O demand/O for/O manufactured/O goods/O and/O leisure/O complements/O ./O 
Growth/O of/O technologically/O intensive/O corporations/O ,/O health/O care/O services/O ,/O and/O higher/O education/O created/O employment/O for/O credentialed/O professionals/O and/O a/O cadre/O of/O supporting/O clerical/O ,/O administrative/O ,/O and/O sales/O workers/O ./O 
Though/O automation/O was/O clearly/O reducing/O labor/O demand/O across/O a/O large/O swath/O of/O occupations/O ,/O it/O is/O easy/O to/O see/O why/O overall/O job/O prospects/O appeared/O broadly/O favorable/O during/O this/O period/O ./O 
But/O after/O the/DATE late/DATE 1970s/DATE ,/O these/O favorable/O winds/O slowed/O and/O in/O some/O cases/O reversed/O ./O 
While/O jobs/O at/O the/O top/O of/O the/O skill/O ladder/O -/O professional/O ,/O technical/O ,/O and/O managerial/O occupations/O -/O grew/O even/O more/O rapidly/O between/O 1980/DATE and/O 2010/DATE than/O in/O the/DURATION four/DURATION decades/DURATION prior/O ,/O positive/O occupational/O shifts/O outside/O of/O these/O catego/O -/O ries/O mostly/O halted/O ./O 
Skilled/O blue-collar/O occupations/O shrank/O rapidly/O and/O clerical/O and/O sales/O occupations/O -/O the/O vulnerable/O &#34;/O production/O jobs/O &#34;/O of/O the/O information/O age/O -/O sharply/O reversed/O course/O ./O 
While/O physically/O demanding/O operative/O and/O laborer/O jobs/O continued/O to/O atrophy/O ,/O low-paid/O personal/O services/O began/O absorbing/O an/O increasing/O share/O of/O noncollege/O labor/O ./O 
By/O this/O time/O ,/O the/O vast/O movement/O away/O from/O agricultural/O work/O had/O already/O played/O out/O ./O 
Many/O forces/O distinguish/O the/O labor/O markets/O of/O these/O two/NUMBER epochs/O of/O 1940-1980/DURATION and/O 1980-2010/DURATION :/O a/O partial/O list/O would/O include/O changes/O in/O the/O relative/O supply/O of/O college/O and/O noncollege/O labor/O ,/O rising/O trade/O penetration/O ,/O offshoring/O ,/O and/O globalization/O of/O production/O chains/O ,/O declines/O in/O labor/O union/O penetration/O ,/O the/O changing/O &#34;/O bite/O &#34;/O of/O the/O minimum/O wage/O ,/O and/O certain/O shifts/O in/O tax/O policy/O ./O 
Of/O course/O ,/O many/O of/O these/O factors/O combine/O and/O interact/O as/O well/O such/O that/O attributing/O changes/O to/O a/O single/O cause/O would/O be/O foolish/O ./O 
However/O ,/O my/O focus/O here/O is/O on/O the/O effects/O of/O technological/O change/O ,/O and/O espe/PERSON -/O cially/O information/O technology/O ,/O on/O employment/O and/O occupations/O -LRB-/O and/O later/O wagesyf/O ./O 
To/O understand/O the/O role/O that/O information/O technology/O has/O played/O -LRB-/O and/O may/O playyf/O L/O t/O is/O useful/O to/O start/O from/O first/ORDINAL principles/O :/O What/O do/O computers/O do/O ?/O 
And/O how/O does/O their/O widespread/O adoption/O change/O what/O workers/O do/O ?/O 
Fundamentally/O ,/O computers/O follow/O procedures/O meticulously/O laid/O out/O by/O program/O -/O mers/O ./O 
The/O typical/O pattern/O has/O been/O that/O for/O a/O computer/O to/O accomplish/O a/O task/O ,/O a/O programmer/O must/O first/ORDINAL fully/O understand/O the/O sequence/O of/O steps/O required/O to/O perform/O that/O task/O ,/O and/O then/O must/O write/O a/O program/O that/O ,/O in/O effect/O ,/O causes/O the/O machine/O to/O simu/O -/O late/O these/O steps/O precisely/O ./O 
-LRB-/O The/O field/O of/O machine/O learning/O ,/O discussed/O below/O ,/O provides/O an/O interesting/O exception/O to/O this/O process.yf/O :/O K/O H/O Q/O D/O F/O R/O P/O S/O X/O W/O H/O U/O S/O U/O R/O F/O H/O V/O V/O H/O V/O D/O F/O R/O P/O S/O D/O Q/O \/O s/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O Why/O Are/O There/O Still/O So/O Many/O Jobs/O f/O 11/NUMBER payroll/O ,/O alphabetizes/O a/O list/O of/O names/O ,/O or/O tabulates/O the/O age/O distribution/O of/O residents/O in/O each/O Census/O enumeration/O district/O ,/O it/O is/O &#34;/O simulating/O &#34;/O a/O work/O process/O that/O would/O ,/O in/O a/O previous/O era/O ,/O have/O been/O done/O by/O humans/O using/O nearly/O identical/O procedures/O ./O 
The/O principle/O of/O computer/O simulation/O of/O workplace/O tasks/O has/O not/O fundamentally/O changed/O since/O the/O dawn/O of/O the/O computer/O era/O -/O but/O its/O cost/O has/O ./O 
An/O ingenious/O 2007/DATE paper/O by/O William/PERSON Nordhaus/PERSON estimates/O that/O the/O cost/O of/O performing/O a/O standardized/O set/O of/O computations/O has/O fallen/O by/O at/O least/O 1.7/NUMBER trillion-fold/O since/O the/O manual/O computing/O era/O ,/O with/O most/O of/O that/O decline/O occurring/O since/O 1980/DATE ./O 
Thus/O ,/O firms/O have/O strong/O economic/O incentives/O to/O substitute/O ever-cheaper/O computing/O power/O for/O relatively/O expensive/O human/O labor/O ./O 
What/O are/O the/O effects/O ?/O 
One/NUMBER first-order/O effect/O is/O ,/O of/O course/O ,/O substitution/O ./O 
As/O the/O price/O of/O computing/O power/O has/O fallen/O ,/O computers/O and/O their/O robot/O cousins/O have/O increasingly/O displaced/O workers/O in/O accomplishing/O explicit/O ,/O codifiable/O tasks/O ./O 
In/O Autor/O ,/O Levy/PERSON ,/O and/O Murnane/PERSON -LRB-/O 2003yf/O P/O \/O F/O R/O D/O X/O W/O K/O R/O U/O V/O D/O Q/O G/O ,/O O/O D/O E/O H/O O/O W/O K/O H/O V/O H/O D/O F/O W/O L/O Y/O L/O W/O L/O H/O V/O D/O V/O U/O R/O X/O W/O L/O Q/O H/O W/O D/O V/O N/O V/O Q/O R/O W/O E/O H/O F/O D/O X/O V/O e/O they/O are/O mundane/O ,/O but/O because/O they/O can/O be/O fully/O codified/O and/O hence/O automated/O -LRB-/O see/O Levy/ORGANIZATION and/O Murnane/O 2004/DATE for/O many/O examplesyf/O 5/NUMBER R/O X/O W/O L/O Q/O H/O W/O D/O V/O N/O V/O D/O U/O H/O F/O K/O D/O U/O D/O F/O W/O H/O U/O L/O V/O W/O L/O c/O of/O many/O middle-skilled/O cognitive/O and/O manual/O activities/O :/O for/O example/O ,/O the/O math/O -/O ematical/O calculations/O involved/O in/O simple/O bookkeeping/O ;/O the/O retrieving/O ,/O sorting/O ,/O and/O storing/O of/O structured/O information/O typical/O of/O clerical/O work/O ;/O and/O the/O precise/O executing/O of/O a/O repetitive/O physical/O operation/O in/O an/O unchanging/O environment/O as/O in/O repetitive/O production/O tasks/O ./O 
Because/O core/O tasks/O of/O these/O occupations/O follow/O precise/O ,/O well-understood/O procedures/O ,/O they/O are/O increasingly/O codified/O in/O computer/O software/O and/O performed/O by/O machines/O ./O 
This/O force/O has/O led/O to/O a/O substantial/O decline/O in/O employ/O -/O ment/O in/O clerical/O ,/O administrative/O support/O ,/O and/O to/O a/O lesser/O degree/O ,/O in/O production/O and/O operative/O employment/O ./O 
But/O the/O scope/O for/O this/O kind/O of/O substitution/O is/O bounded/O because/O there/O are/O many/O tasks/O that/O people/O understand/O tacitly/O and/O accomplish/O effortlessly/O but/O for/O which/O neither/O computer/O programmers/O nor/O anyone/O else/O can/O enunciate/O the/O explicit/O &#34;/O rules/O &#34;/O or/O procedures/O ./O 
I/O have/O referred/O to/O this/O constraint/O as/O Polanyi/PERSON &#39;/O s/O paradox/O ,/O named/O after/O the/O economist/O ,/O philosopher/O ,/O and/O chemist/O who/O observed/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1966/DATE ,/O &#34;/O We/O know/O more/O than/O we/O can/O tell/O &#34;/O -LRB-/O Polanyi/LOCATION 1966/DATE ;/O Autor/O 2015yf/O :/O K/O H/O Q/O Z/O H/O E/O U/O H/O D/O N/O D/O Q/O H/O J/O J/O R/O Y/O H/O U/O W/O K/O e/O edge/O of/O a/O mixing/O bowl/O ,/O identify/O a/O distinct/O species/O of/O birds/O based/O on/O a/O fleeting/O glimpse/O ,/O write/O a/O persuasive/O paragraph/O ,/O or/O develop/O a/O hypothesis/O to/O explain/O a/O poorly/O understood/O phenomenon/O ,/O we/O are/O engaging/O in/O tasks/O that/O we/O only/O tacitly/O under/O -/O stand/O how/O to/O perform/O ./O 
Following/O Polanyi/PERSON &#39;/O s/O observation/O ,/O the/O tasks/O that/O have/O proved/O most/O vexing/O to/O automate/O are/O those/O demanding/O flexibility/O ,/O judgment/O ,/O and/O common/O sense/O -/O skills/O that/O we/O understand/O only/O tacitly/O .4/NUMBER Polanyi/PERSON &#39;/O s/O paradox/O also/O suggests/O why/O high-level/O reasoning/O is/O straightforward/O to/O computerize/O and/O certain/O sensorimotor/O skills/O are/O not/O ./O 
High-level/O reasoning/O uses/O a/O set/O 4/NUMBER Computer/O scientists/O often/O refer/O to/O this/O phenomenon/O as/O Moravec/PERSON &#39;/O s/O paradox/O ,/O after/O Moravec/PERSON -LRB-/O 1988yf/O Z/O K/O o/O wrote/O ,/O &#34;/O -LSB-/O I/O -RSB-/O t/O is/O comparatively/O easy/O to/O make/O computers/O exhibit/O adult/O level/O performance/O on/O intelligence/O tests/O or/O playing/O checkers/O ,/O and/O difficult/O or/O impossible/O to/O give/O them/O the/O skills/O of/O a/O one-year-old/DURATION when/O it/O comes/O to/O perception/O and/O mobility/O ./O 
&#34;/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 1/NUMBER 2/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O of/O formal/O logical/O tools/O that/O were/O developed/O specifically/O to/O address/O formal/O problems/O :/O for/O example/O ,/O counting/O ,/O mathematics/O ,/O logical/O deduction/O ,/O and/O encoding/O quantita/O -/O tive/O relationships/O ./O 
In/O contrast/O ,/O sensorimotor/O skills/O ,/O physical/O flexibility/O ,/O common/O sense/O ,/O judgment/O ,/O intuition/O ,/O creativity/O ,/O and/O spoken/O language/O are/O capabilities/O that/O the/O human/O species/O evolved/O ,/O rather/O than/O developed/O ./O 
Formalizing/O these/O skills/O requires/O reverse-engineering/O a/O set/O of/O activities/O that/O we/O normally/O accomplish/O using/O only/O tacit/O understanding/O ./O 
Hoffman/O and/O Furcht/O -LRB-/O 2014yf/O G/O L/O V/O F/O X/O V/O V/O W/O K/O H/O F/O K/O D/O O/O O/O H/O Q/O J/O H/O W/O K/O D/O W/O 3/NUMBER R/O O/O D/O Q/O \/O '/O s/O paradox/O poses/O for/O scientific/O innovation/O more/O broadly/O ./O 
If/O computers/O largely/O substitute/O for/O routine/O tasks/O ,/O how/O do/O we/O characterize/O the/O nonroutine/O tasks/O for/O which/O they/O do/O not/O substitute/O ?/O 
In/O Autor/O ,/O Levy/PERSON ,/O and/O Murnane/PERSON -LRB-/O 2003yf/O Z/O H/O G/O L/O V/O W/O L/O Q/O J/O X/O L/O V/O K/O W/O Z/O R/O E/O U/O R/O D/O G/O V/O H/O W/O V/O R/O I/O W/O D/O V/O N/O V/O W/O K/O D/O W/O K/O D/O Y/O H/O S/O U/O R/O Y/O H/O Q/O V/O W/O X/O E/O E/O R/O U/O Q/O O/O \/O F/O K/O D/O O/O O/O H/O Q/O J/O L/O Q/O g/O to/O computerize/O ./O 
One/NUMBER category/O includes/O tasks/O that/O require/O problem-solving/O capabili/O -/O ties/O ,/O intuition/O ,/O creativity/O ,/O and/O persuasion/O ./O 
These/O tasks/O ,/O which/O we/O term/O &#34;/O abstract/O ,/O &#34;/O are/O characteristic/O of/O professional/O ,/O technical/O ,/O and/O managerial/O occupations/O ./O 
They/O employ/O workers/O with/O high/O levels/O of/O education/O and/O analytical/O capability/O ,/O and/O they/O place/O a/O premium/O on/O inductive/O reasoning/O ,/O communications/O ability/O ,/O and/O expert/O mastery/O ./O 
The/O second/ORDINAL broad/O category/O includes/O tasks/O requiring/O situational/O adaptability/O ,/O visual/O and/O language/O recognition/O ,/O and/O in-person/O interactions/O -/O which/O we/O call/O &#34;/O manual/O &#34;/O tasks/O ./O 
Manual/O tasks/O are/O characteristic/O of/O food/O preparation/O and/O serving/O jobs/O ,/O cleaning/O and/O janitorial/O work/O ,/O grounds/O cleaning/O and/O maintenance/O ,/O in-person/O health/O assistance/O by/O home/O health/O aides/O ,/O and/O numerous/O jobs/O in/O security/O and/O protective/O services/O ./O 
These/O jobs/O tend/O to/O employ/O workers/O who/O are/O physically/O adept/O and/O ,/O in/O some/O cases/O ,/O able/O to/O communicate/O fluendy/O in/O spoken/O language/O ./O 
While/O these/O activities/O are/O not/O highly/O skilled/O by/O the/O standards/O of/O the/O US/LOCATION labor/O market/O ,/O they/O present/DATE daunting/O challenges/O for/O automation/O ./O 
Equally/O noteworthy/O ,/O many/O outputs/O of/O these/O manual/O task/O jobs/O -LRB-/O hair/O -/O cuts/O ,/O fresh/O meals/O ,/O housecleaningyf/O P/O X/O V/O W/O E/O H/O S/O U/O R/O G/O X/O F/O H/O G/O D/O Q/O G/O S/O H/O U/O I/O R/O U/O P/O H/O G/O O/O D/O U/O J/O H/O O/O \/O R/O Q/O V/O L/O W/O e/O or/O in/O person/O -LRB-/O at/O least/O for/O nowyf/O D/O Q/O G/O K/O H/O Q/O F/O H/O W/O K/O H/O V/O H/O W/O D/O V/O N/O V/O D/O U/O H/O Q/O R/O W/O V/O X/O E/O M/O H/O F/O W/O W/O R/O R/O X/O W/O V/O R/O X/O U/O F/O L/O Q/O J/O ./O 
The/O potential/O supply/O of/O workers/O who/O can/O perform/O these/O jobs/O is/O very/O large/O ./O 
Because/O jobs/O that/O are/O intensive/O in/O either/O abstract/O or/O manual/O tasks/O are/O gener/O -/O ally/O found/O at/O opposite/O ends/O of/O the/O occupational/O skill/O spectrum/O -/O in/O professional/O ,/O managerial/O ,/O and/O technical/O occupations/O on/O the/O one/NUMBER hand/O ,/O and/O in/O service/O and/O laborer/O occupations/O on/O the/O other/O -/O this/O reasoning/O implies/O that/O computerization/O of/O &#34;/O routine/O &#34;/O job/O tasks/O may/O lead/O to/O the/O simultaneous/O growth/O of/O high-education/O ,/O high-wage/O jobs/O at/O one/NUMBER end/O and/O low-education/O ,/O low-wage/O jobs/O at/O the/O other/O end/O ,/O both/O at/O the/O expense/O of/O middle-wage/O ,/O middle/O education/O jobs/O -/O a/O phenomenon/O that/O Goos/O and/O Manning/PERSON -LRB-/O 2003yf/O F/O D/O O/O O/O H/O G/O M/O R/O E/O S/O R/O O/O D/O U/O L/O -RSB-/O D/O W/O L/O R/O Q/O $/MONEY O/MONEY D/O U/O J/O H/O E/O R/O G/O \/O R/O I/O 8/NUMBER 6/NUMBER D/O Q/O G/O L/O Q/O W/O H/O U/O Q/O D/O W/O L/O R/O Q/O D/O O/O H/O Y/O L/O G/O H/O Q/O F/O e/O confirms/O the/O presence/O of/O employment/O polarization/O at/O the/O level/O of/O industries/O ,/O locali/O -/O ties/O ,/O and/O national/O labor/O markets/O -LRB-/O Autor/O ,/O Katz/PERSON ,/O and/O Kearney/PERSON 2006/DATE ,/O 2008/DATE ;/O Goos/O and/O Manning/PERSON 2007/DATE ;/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON 2013/DATE ;/O Michaels/PERSON ,/O Natraj/ORGANIZATION ,/O and/O Van/O Reenen/O 2014/DATE ;/O Goos/O ,/O Manning/PERSON ,/O and/O Salomons/PERSON 2014/DATE ;/O Graetz/PERSON and/O Michaels/PERSON 2015/DATE ;/O Autor/O ,/O Dorn/PERSON ,/O and/O Hanson/PERSON 2015yf/O 5/NUMBER 5/NUMBER Mishel/PERSON ,/O Shierholz/O ,/O and/O Schmitt/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013yf/O R/O I/O I/O H/O U/O D/O Q/O H/O -LSB-/O W/O H/O Q/O G/O H/O G/O D/O Q/O G/O I/O R/O U/O W/O K/O H/O P/O R/O V/O W/O S/O D/O U/O W/O H/O -LSB-/O W/O U/O H/O P/O H/O O/O \/O F/O D/O U/O H/O I/O X/O O/O ,/O critique/O of/O the/O literature/O on/O technological/O change/O ,/O employment/O ,/O and/O wage/O inequality/O ./O 
Their/O paper/O argues/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON 13/NUMBER Figure/O 2/NUMBER Change/O in/O Employment/O by/O Major/O Occupational/O Category/O ,/O 1979-2012/DURATION -LRB-/O the/O y-axis/O plots/O 100/NUMBER times/O log/O changes/O in/O employment/O ,/O which/O is/O nearly/O equivalent/O to/O percentage/O points/O for/O small/O changesyf/O Sources/O :/O Author/O using/O data/O from/O the/O 1980/DATE ,/O 1990/DATE ,/O and/DATE 2000/DATE Census/O IPUMS/O files/O ,/O American/ORGANIZATION Community/ORGANIZATION Survey/ORGANIZATION combined/O file/O 2006-2008/DURATION ,/O and/O American/ORGANIZATION Community/ORGANIZATION Survey/ORGANIZATION 2012/ORGANIZATION ./O 
The/O sample/O includes/O the/O working-age/O -LRB-/O 16-64yf/O F/O L/O Y/O L/O O/O L/O D/O Q/O Q/O R/O Q/O L/O Q/O V/O W/O L/O W/O X/O W/O L/O R/O Q/O D/O O/O L/O -RSB-/O H/O G/O S/O R/O S/O X/O O/O D/O W/O L/O R/O Q/O -LRB-/O P/O S/O O/O R/O \/O P/O H/O Q/O W/O L/O V/O P/O H/O D/O V/O X/O U/O H/O G/O D/O V/O I/O X/O O/O O/O W/O L/O P/O H/O H/O T/O X/O L/O Y/O D/O O/O H/O Q/O W/O Z/O R/O U/O N/O H/O U/O V/O ./O 
Notes/O :/O Figure/O 2/NUMBER plots/O percentage/O point/O changes/O in/O employment/O -LRB-/O more/O precisely/O ,/O the/O figure/O plots/O 100/NUMBER times/O log/O changes/O in/O employment/O ,/O which/O is/O close/O to/O equivalent/O to/O percentage/O points/O for/O small/O changesyf/O E/O \/O G/O H/O F/O D/O G/O e/O for/O the/DURATION years/DURATION 1979-2012/DURATION for/O ten/NUMBER major/O occupational/O groups/O encompassing/O all/O of/O US/LOCATION nonagricultural/O employment/O ./O 
Agricultural/O occupations/O comprise/O no/O more/O than/O 2.2/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O employment/O in/O this/O time/O interval/O ,/O so/O this/O omission/O has/O a/O negligible/O effect/O ./O 
Figure/O 2/NUMBER illustrates/O this/O pattern/O for/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION by/O plotting/O percentage/O point/O changes/O in/O employment/O by/O decade/DURATION for/O the/DURATION years/DURATION 1979-2012/DURATION for/O ten/NUMBER major/O occupational/O groups/O encompassing/O all/O of/O US/LOCATION nonagricultural/O employment/O ./O 
-LRB-/O More/O that/O the/O growth/O of/O low-wage/O service/O employment/O does/O not/O commence/O in/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION until/O the/DATE 2000s/DATE ,/O a/O finding/O that/O is/O at/O odds/O with/O all/O other/O work/O using/O contemporary/O occupation/O codes/O of/O which/O I/O am/O aware/O -LRB-/O including/O the/O Bureau/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Labor/ORGANIZATION Statistici/ORGANIZATION own/O tabulations/O of/O Occupational/ORGANIZATION Employment/ORGANIZATION Statistics/ORGANIZATION data/O for/O this/O time/O period/O provided/O in/O Alpert/PERSON and/O Auyer/O 2003/DATE ,/O table/O 1yf/O $/MONEY W/MONEY D/O P/O H/O W/O K/O R/O G/O R/O O/O R/O J/O L/O F/O D/O O/O O/O H/O Y/O H/O O/O Z/O R/O U/O N/O L/O n/O this/O area/O always/O requires/O adjustments/O and/O judgment/O calls/O in/O comparing/O occupational/O data/O across/O Census/O years/DURATION ,/O but/O the/O adjustments/O that/O Mishel/PERSON et/O al./O apply/O to/O the/O data/O generate/O occupational/O patterns/O that/O appear/O anomalous/O ./O 
Substantively/O ,/O I/O believe/O the/O main/O issue/O is/O not/O whether/O employment/O polarization/O has/O occurred/O -/O on/O this/O ,/O the/O evidence/O appears/O unambiguous/O -/O but/O the/O extent/O to/O which/O these/O occupational/O employment/O shifts/O are/O helpful/O for/O understanding/O wage/O polarization/O or/O wage/O inequality/O more/O broadly/O ./O 
This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 1/NUMBER 4/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O precisely/O ,/O the/O figure/O plots/O 100/NUMBER times/O log/O changes/O in/O employment/O ,/O which/O are/O close/O to/O equivalent/O to/O percentage/O points/O for/O small/O changes/O ./O 
Agricultural/O occupations/O comprise/O no/O more/O than/O 2.2/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O employment/O in/O this/O time/O interval/O ,/O so/O this/O omission/O has/O a/O negligible/O effect.yf/O 7/NUMBER K/O H/O V/O H/O W/O H/O Q/O R/O F/O F/O X/O S/O D/O W/O L/O R/O Q/O V/O F/O D/O Q/O E/O H/O G/O L/O Y/O L/O G/O H/O G/O L/O Q/O W/O o/O three/NUMBER groups/O ./O 
On/O the/O right-hand/O side/O of/O the/O figure/O are/O managerial/O ,/O professional/O ,/O and/O technical/O occupations/O ,/O which/O are/O highly/O educated/O and/O highly/O paid/O ./O 
Moving/O leftward/O ,/O the/O next/O four/NUMBER columns/O display/O employment/O growth/O in/O middle-skill/O occu/O -/O pations/O ,/O comprising/O sales/O ;/O office/O and/O administrative/O support/O ;/O production/O ,/O craft/O and/O repair/O ;/O and/O operator/O ,/O fabricator/O ,/O and/O laborer/O ./O 
The/O leftmost/O three/NUMBER columns/O of/O Figure/O 2/NUMBER depict/O employment/O trends/O in/O service/O occupations/O ,/O defined/O by/O the/O Census/ORGANIZATION Bureau/ORGANIZATION as/O jobs/O that/O involve/O helping/O ,/O caring/O for/O ,/O or/O assisting/O others/O ./O 
The/O majority/O of/O workers/O in/O service/O occupations/O have/O no/O post-secondary/O education/O ,/O and/O average/O hourly/SET wages/O in/O service/O occupations/O are/O in/O most/O cases/O below/O the/O other/O seven/NUMBER occu/O -/O pational/O categories/O ./O 
As/O Figure/O 2/NUMBER illustrates/O ,/O the/O rapid/O employment/O growth/O in/O both/O high/O -/O and/O low-education/O jobs/O has/O substantially/O reduced/O the/O share/O of/O employment/O accounted/O for/O by/O &#34;/O middle-skill/O &#34;/O jobs/O ./O 
In/U_TEMPPRED 1979/DATE ,/O the/O four/NUMBER middle-skill/O occupations/O -LRB-/O sales/O ;/O office/O and/O administrative/O workers/O ;/O production/O workers/O ;/O and/O operativesyf/O D/O F/O F/O R/O X/O Q/O W/O H/O G/O I/O R/O r/O 60/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O employment/O ./O 
In/U_TEMPPRED 2007/DATE ,/O this/O number/O was/O 49/PERCENT percent/PERCENT ,/O and/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2012/DATE ,/O it/O was/O 46/PERCENT percent/PERCENT ./O 
The/O employment/O share/O of/O service/O occupations/O was/O essentially/O flat/O between/O 1959/DATE and/O 1979/DATE ,/O and/O so/O their/O rapid/O growth/O since/O 1980/DATE marks/O a/O sharp/O trend/O reversal/O -LRB-/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON 2013yf/O ./O 
The/O polarization/O of/O employment/O across/O occupations/O is/O not/O unique/O to/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION ./O 
Figure/O 3/NUMBER plots/O changes/O in/O the/O share/O of/O employment/O between/O 1993/DATE and/O 2010/DATE within/O three/NUMBER broad/O sets/O of/O occupations/O -/O low/O -/O ,/O middle/O -/O ,/O and/O high-wage/O -/O covering/O all/O nonagricultural/O employment/O in/O 16/NUMBER European/LOCATION Union/LOCATION economies/O ./O 
In/O all/O countries/O ,/O middle-wage/O occupations/O declined/O as/O a/O share/O of/O employment/O while/O both/O high-wage/O and/O low-wage/O occupations/O increased/O their/O shares/O of/O employment/O over/O this/DATE 17-year/DATE period/O ./O 
While/O the/O US/LOCATION and/O EU/ORGANIZATION data/O are/O not/O precisely/O comparable/O ,/O the/O US/LOCATION economy/O would/O fall/O roughly/O in/O the/O middle/O of/O the/O pack/O of/O this/O set/O of/O countries/O in/O terms/O of/O its/O employment/O polarization/O ./O 
The/O comparability/O of/O these/O occupational/O shifts/O across/O a/O large/O set/O of/O developed/O countries/O makes/O it/O likely/O that/O a/O common/O set/O of/O forces/O contributes/O to/O these/O shared/O labor-market/O developments/O ./O 
Simultaneously/O ,/O the/O substantial/O differences/O among/O countries/O underscores/O that/O no/O single/O factor/O or/O common/O cause/O explains/O the/O diversity/O of/O experiences/O across/O the/O United/LOCATION States/LOCATION and/O the/O European/LOCATION Union/LOCATION ./O 
Does/O Employment/O Polarization/O Lead/O to/O Wage/O Polarization/O ?/O 
From/O the/O barbell/O shape/O of/O occupational/O employment/O growth/O depicted/O in/O Figures/O 2/NUMBER and/O 3/DATE ,/O one/NUMBER might/O surmise/O that/O occupational/O polarization/O would/O also/O cata/O -/O lyze/O wage/O polarization/O -/O that/O is/O ,/O rising/O relative/O wages/O in/O both/O high-education/O ,/O abstract/O task-intensive/O jobs/O and/O in/O low-education/O ,/O manual/O task-intensive/O jobs/O ./O 
However/O ,/O this/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O Why/O Are/O There/O Still/O So/O Many/O Jobs/O ?/O 
15/NUMBER Figure/O 3/NUMBER Change/O in/O Occupational/O Employment/O Shares/O in/O Low/O ,/O Middle/LOCATION ,/O and/O High-Wage/O Occupations/O in/O 16/NUMBER EU/ORGANIZATION Countries/O ,/O 1993-2010/DURATION Source/O :/O Goos/O ,/O Manning/PERSON ,/O and/O Salomons/PERSON -LRB-/O 2014/DATE ,/O table/O 2yf/O ./O 
Notes/O :/O High-paying/O occupations/O are/O corporate/O managers/O ;/O physical/O ,/O mathematical/O ,/O and/O engineering/O professionals/O ;/O life/O science/O and/O health/O professionals/O ;/O other/O professionals/O ;/O managers/O of/O small/O enterprises/O ;/O physical/O ,/O mathematical/O ,/O and/O engineering/O associate/O professionals/O ;/O other/O associate/O professionals/O ;/O life/O science/O and/O health/O associate/O professionals/O ./O 
Middle-paying/O occupations/O are/O stationary/O plant/O and/O related/O operators/O ;/O metal/O ,/O machinery/O ,/O and/O related/O trade/O work/O ;/O drivers/O and/O mobile/O plant/O operators/O ;/O office/O clerks/O ;/O precision/O ,/O handicraft/O ,/O craft/O printing/O ,/O and/O related/O trade/O workers/O ;/O extraction/O and/O building/O trades/O workers/O ;/O customer/O service/O clerks/O ;/O machine/O operators/O and/O assemblers/O ;/O and/O other/O craft/O and/O related/O trade/O workers/O ./O 
Low-paying/O occupations/O are/O laborers/O in/O mining/O ,/O construction/O ,/O manufacturing/O ,/O and/O transport/O ;/O personal/O and/O protective/O service/O workers/O ;/O models/O ,/O salespersons/O ,/O and/O demonstrators/O ;/O and/O sales/O and/O service/O elementary/O occupations/O ./O 
reasoning/O does/O not/O take/O into/O account/O the/O role/O played/O by/O the/O three/NUMBER mitigating/O forces/O discussed/O above/O :/O complementarity/O ,/O demand/O elasticity/O ,/O and/O labor/O supply/O ./O 
Let/O &#39;/O s/O first/ORDINAL consider/O the/O effect/O of/O computerization/O on/O wages/O in/O abstract/O task-intensive/O occupations/O such/O as/O managerial/O ,/O professional/O ,/O and/O technical/O occupations/O ./O 
These/O occu/O -/O pations/O all/O draw/O upon/O large/O bodies/O of/O constantly/O evolving/O expertise/O :/O for/O example/O ,/O medical/O knowledge/O ,/O legal/O precedents/O ,/O sales/O data/O ,/O financial/O analysis/O ,/O programming/O languages/O ,/O and/O economic/O statistics/O ./O 
Information/O technology/O and/O computerization/O should/O strongly/O complement/O workers/O performing/O abstract/O task-intensive/O jobs/O ./O 
By/O dramatically/O lowering/O the/O cost/O and/O increasing/O the/O scope/O of/O information/O and/O analysis/O available/O to/O them/O ,/O computerization/O enables/O workers/O performing/O abstract/O tasks/O to/O further/O specialize/O in/O their/O area/O of/O comparative/O advantage/O ,/O with/O less/O time/O spent/O on/O acquiring/O and/O crunching/O information/O ,/O and/O more/O time/O spent/O on/O interpreting/O and/O applying/O it/O ./O 
By/O the/O same/O token/O ,/O information/O technology/O substitutes/O for/O many/O of/O the/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 1/NUMBER 6/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O support/O occupations/O that/O these/O professions/O employ/O ,/O including/O medical/O secretaries/O ,/O para/O -/O legals/O ,/O and/O research/O assistants/O ./O 
Similarly/O ,/O computerization/O and/O information/O technology/O appears/O to/O allow/O &#34;/O delayering/O &#34;/O of/O management/O structures/O -LRB-/O Caroli/ORGANIZATION and/O Van/ORGANIZATION Reenen/ORGANIZATION 2001yf/O $/MONEY U/MONEY J/O X/O D/O E/O O/O \/O P/O D/O Q/O \/O R/O I/O W/O K/O H/O P/O L/O G/O G/O O/O H/O P/O D/O Q/O D/O J/O H/O U/O V/O G/O L/O V/O S/O O/O D/O F/O H/O G/O E/O \/O G/O H/O O/O D/O \/O H/O U/O L/O Q/O J/O S/O H/O U/O I/O R/O U/O P/O H/O d/O routine/O information-processing/O tasks/O ./O 
If/O demand/O for/O the/O output/O of/O abstract/O task-intensive/O activities/O is/O inelastic/O ,/O these/O productivity/O gains/O might/O work/O to/O lower/O expenditure/O on/O these/O outputs/O ,/O which/O could/O mitigate/O wage/O gains/O ./O 
However/O ,/O all/O outward/O evidence/O suggests/O that/O as/O technology/O has/O boosted/O the/O output/O of/O the/O professions/O ,/O demand/O for/O their/O services/O has/O more/O than/O kept/O pace/O ./O 
Health/O care/O is/O an/O obvious/O example/O ,/O but/O one/NUMBER can/O readily/O make/O similar/O argu/O -/O ments/O about/O finance/O ,/O law/O ,/O engineering/O ,/O research/O ,/O and/O design/O ./O 
What/O about/O reactions/O from/O labor/O supply/O ?/O 
If/O workers/O could/O quickly/O move/O into/O the/O highly/O educated/O professions/O ,/O such/O a/O shift/O would/O mute/O earnings/O gains/O ./O 
But/O of/O course/O ,/O many/O professions/O require/O both/O college/O and/O graduate/O degrees/O ,/O so/O the/O produc/O -/O tion/O pipeline/O for/O new/O entrants/O is/O at/DURATION least/DURATION five/DURATION to/DURATION ten/DURATION years/DURATION in/O length/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O young/O US/LOCATION adults/O ,/O particularly/O US/LOCATION males/O ,/O have/O responded/O with/O remarkable/O sluggishness/O to/O the/O rising/O educational/O premium/O over/O the/DURATION last/DATE 30/DATE years/DATE -LRB-/O Autor/O 2014yf/O -RRB-/O R/O U/O H/O -LSB-/O D/O P/O S/O O/O H/O L/O n/O 1975/DATE ,/O approximately/O 40/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O hours/DURATION worked/O by/O males/O with/O fewer/O than/O ten/DURATION years/DURATION of/O experience/O -LRB-/O a/O group/O that/O has/O made/O the/O more/O recent/O choices/O about/O collegeyf/O Z/O H/O U/O e/O supplied/O by/O those/O with/O a/O college/O education/O ./O 
Forty/DATE years/DATE later/DATE in/U_TEMPPRED 2005/DATE ,/O this/O share/O was/O almost/O unchanged/O ./O 
For/O women/O workers/O with/O less/DURATION than/DURATION ten/DURATION years/DURATION of/O experience/O ,/O the/O share/O of/O total/O hours/DURATION worked/O by/O those/O with/O a/O college/O education/O was/O 42/PERCENT percent/PERCENT in/U_TEMPPRED 1982/DATE but/O had/O risen/O to/O 53/PERCENT percent/PERCENT by/U_TEMPPRED 2005/DATE ./O 
In/O the/DATE last/DATE decade/DATE ,/O the/O share/O of/O hours/DURATION worked/O by/O those/O with/O less/DURATION than/DURATION ten/DURATION years/DURATION of/O experience/O and/O a/O college/O degree/O has/O increased/O for/O both/O men/O and/O women/O :/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2012/DATE ,/O it/O was/O 52/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O hours/DURATION for/O men/O in/O this/O group/O and/O 62/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O the/DURATION hours/DURATION for/O women/O ./O 
Thus/O ,/O while/O the/O stock/O of/O workers/O with/O college/O and/O graduate/O degrees/O has/O certainly/O grown/O ,/O the/O supply/O response/O has/O not/O been/O nearly/O large/O enough/O to/O swamp/O the/O contemporaneous/O movements/O in/O labor/O demand/O ./O 
Workers/O in/O abstract/O task-intensive/O occupations/O therefore/O benefit/O from/O informa/O -/O tion/O technology/O via/O a/O virtuous/O combination/O of/O strong/O complementarities/O between/O routine/O and/O abstract/O tasks/O ,/O elastic/O demand/O for/O services/O provided/O by/O abstract/O task-intensive/O occupations/O ,/O and/O inelastic/O labor/O supply/O to/O these/O occupations/O over/O the/O short/O and/O medium/O term/O ./O 
In/O combination/O ,/O these/O forces/O mean/O that/O information/O tech/O -/O nology/O should/O raise/O earnings/O in/O occupations/O that/O make/O intensive/O use/O of/O abstract/O tasks/O and/O among/O workers/O who/O intensively/O supply/O them/O ./O 
These/O same/O synergies/O do/O not/O apply/O to/O jobs/O that/O are/O intensive/O in/O manual/O tasks/O ,/O such/O as/O janitors/O and/O cleaners/O ,/O vehicle/O drivers/O ,/O security/O guards/O ,/O flight/O attendants/O ,/O food/O service/O workers/O ,/O and/O home/O health/O aides/O ./O 
Most/O manual/O task-intensive/O occupa/O -/O tions/O are/O only/O minimally/O reliant/O on/O information/O or/O data/O processing/O for/O their/O core/O tasks/O ,/O and/O involve/O only/O limited/O opportunities/O for/O either/O direct/O complementarity/O or/O substitution/O .6/NUMBER 6/NUMBER There/O are/O partial/O exceptions/O to/O this/O generalization/O :/O global/O positioning/O system/O satellites/O and/O scheduling/O software/O allows/O truckers/O and/O delivery/O services/O to/O minimize/O wasted/O mileage/O ;/O calendar/O ,/O contact/O ,/O and/O billing/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O David/PERSON H./PERSON Autor/PERSON 1/NUMBER 7/NUMBER Aggregate/O evidence/O suggests/O that/O final/O demand/O for/O manual/O task-intensive/O work/O -/O services/O in/O particular/O -/O is/O relatively/O price/O inelastic/O -LRB-/O Baumol/O 1967/DATE ;/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON 2013yf/PERSON ,/O I/O V/O R/O S/O U/O R/O G/O X/O F/O W/O L/O Y/O L/O W/O \/O J/O D/O L/O Q/O V/O L/O Q/O P/O D/O Q/O X/O D/O O/O W/O D/O V/O N/O L/O Q/O W/O H/O Q/O V/O L/O Y/O H/O R/O F/O F/O X/O S/O D/O W/O L/O R/O Q/O V/O W/O K/O D/O W/O W/O H/O Q/O d/O to/O reduce/O their/O price/O per/O unit/O of/O service/O provided/O will/O not/O necessarily/O raise/O expendi/O -/O ture/O on/O their/O outputs/O ./O 
On/O the/O other/O hand/O ,/O demand/O for/O manual/O task-intensive/O work/O appears/O to/O be/O relatively/O income/O elastic/O -LRB-/O Clark/PERSON 1951/DATE ;/O Mazzorali/PERSON and/O Ragusa/PERSON 2013yf/PERSON ,/O so/O that/O rising/O aggregate/O incomes/O will/O tend/O to/O increase/O demand/O for/O these/O activities/O ./O 
New/O technology/O and/O productivity/O growth/O in/O other/O areas/O may/O therefore/O indirectly/O raise/O demand/O for/O manual/O task-intensive/O occupations/O by/O increasing/O societal/O income/O ./O 
Labor/O supply/O to/O manual/O task-intensive/O occupations/O is/O intrinsically/O elastic/O ,/O due/O to/O their/O generally/O low/O education/O and/O training/O requirements/O ./O 
This/O insight/O does/O not/O preclude/O the/O possibility/O that/O wages/O in/O manual/O tasks/O will/O rise/O ,/O at/O least/O to/O some/O extent/O ./O 
As/O Baumol/PERSON -LRB-/O 1967yf/O R/O E/O V/O H/O U/O Y/O H/O G/O H/O Y/O H/O Q/O D/O E/O V/O H/O Q/O W/O S/O U/O R/O G/O X/O F/O W/O L/O Y/O L/O W/O \/O J/O U/O R/O Z/O W/O K/O L/O Q/O W/O H/O F/O K/O Q/O R/O O/O R/O J/O L/O F/O D/O O/O O/O \/O O/O D/O J/O J/O L/O Q/O g/O occupations/O ,/O wages/O in/O these/O occupations/O must/O rise/O over/O time/O with/O societal/O income/O to/O compensate/O workers/O for/O not/O entering/O other/O sectors/O -LRB-/O again/O ,/O assuming/O that/O demand/O for/O these/O activities/O is/O relatively/O inelasticyf/PERCENT %/PERCENT X/O W/O L/O W/O G/O R/O H/O V/O V/O X/O J/O J/O H/O V/O W/O W/O K/O D/O W/O Z/O D/O J/O H/O L/O Q/O F/O U/O H/O D/O V/O H/O V/O L/O n/O these/O jobs/O will/O be/O restrained/O to/O some/O extent/O by/O the/O labor/O supply/O response/O ,/O including/O from/O workers/O displaced/O in/O other/O sectors/O of/O the/O economy/O ./O 
Overall/O ,/O manual/O task-intensive/O activities/O are/O at/O best/O weakly/O complemented/O by/O computerization/O ,/O do/O not/O benefit/O from/O elastic/O final/O demand/O ,/O and/O face/O elastic/O labor/O supply/O that/O tempers/O demand-induced/O wage/O increases/O ./O 
Thus/O ,/O while/O information/O tech/O -/O nology/O has/O strongly/O contributed/O to/O employment/O polarization/O measured/O in/O quantity/O of/O jobs/O ,/O we/O would/O not/O generally/O expect/O these/O employment/O changes/O to/O culminate/O in/O a/O corresponding/O wage/O polarization/O except/O perhaps/O at/O certain/O times/O or/O in/O certain/O labor/O markets/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O in/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013yf/O Z/O H/O S/O U/O H/O V/O H/O Q/O W/O H/O Y/O L/O G/O H/O Q/O F/O H/O W/O K/O D/O W/O Z/O D/O J/O H/O V/O I/O R/O r/O manual-task/O occupations/O rose/O during/O the/DATE 1990s/DATE when/O labor/O markets/O were/O extremely/O tight/O ,/O but/O after/O 2000/DATE ,/O the/O expansion/O of/O manual/O task-intensive/O service/O occupations/O accelerated/O while/O wages/O in/O these/O occupations/O fell/O ./O 
For/O insight/O about/O the/O evolution/O of/O wage/O patterns/O ,/O consider/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER ./O 
The/O hori/PERSON -/O zontal/O axis/O of/O this/O figure/O is/O based/O on/O a/O ranking/O of/O all/O 318/NUMBER detailed/O occupations/O from/O lowest/O to/O highest/O by/O their/O initial/O skill/O level/O ,/O as/O measured/O by/O its/O 1979/DATE mean/O hourly/SET occupational/O wage/O ./O 
These/O categories/O are/O weighted/O by/O their/O initial/O size/O ,/O and/O then/O grouped/O into/O 100/NUMBER bins/O of/O equal/O size/O ./O 
The/O vertical/O axis/O of/O the/O figure/O then/O shows/O the/O percentage/O change/O in/O wages/O over/O each/O of/O four/NUMBER periods/O across/O the/O skill/O distribution/O -/O with/O the/O line/O smoothed/O for/O clarity/O ./O 
-LRB-/O Again/O ,/O more/O precisely/O ,/O the/O figure/O plots/O 100/NUMBER times/O log/O changes/O in/O employment/O ,/O which/O is/O nearly/O equivalent/O to/O percentage/O points/O for/O small/O changes.yf/O The/O right-hand/O two-thirds/O of/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER look/O like/O the/O plots/O of/O employment/O polariza/O -/O tion/O ./O 
From/O 1979/DATE through/O 2007/DATE ,/O wages/O rose/O consistently/O across/O the/O high-skill/O portion/O software/O assists/O home/O health/O workers/O to/O manage/O data/O more/O effectively/O ;/O and/O computerized/O ordering/O systems/O enable/O food/O service/O workers/O to/O rapidly/O tally/O customer/O tabs/O ./O 
In/O a/DURATION few/DURATION years/DURATION time/O ,/O many/O retailers/O may/O employ/O RFID/O &#34;/O chip/O &#34;/O technology/O that/O will/O scan/O purchases/O without/O needing/O a/O human/O checkout/O cashier/O at/O all/O ./O 
This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 1/NUMBER 8/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER Changes/O in/O Mean/O Wages/O by/O Occupational/ORGANIZATION Skill/ORGANIZATION Percentile/ORGANIZATION among/O Full-Time/O ,/O Full-Year/O -LRB-/O FTFYyf/O :/O R/O U/O N/O H/O U/O V/O 2/NUMBER -LRB-/O the/O y-axis/O plots/O 100/NUMBER times/O log/O changes/O in/O employment/O ,/O which/O is/O nearly/O equivalent/O to/O percentage/O points/O for/O small/O changesyf/O Sources/O :/O Author/O ,/O calculated/O using/O 1980/DATE ,/O 1990/DATE ,/O and/DATE 2000/DATE Census/O IPUMS/O files/O ;/O American/ORGANIZATION Community/ORGANIZATION Survey/ORGANIZATION combined/O file/O 2006-2008/DURATION ,/O American/ORGANIZATION Community/ORGANIZATION Survey/ORGANIZATION 2012/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Notes/O :/O The/O figure/O plots/O changes/O in/O mean/O log/O wages/O over/O each/O period/O ,/O by/U_TEMPPRED 1979/DATE occupational/O skill/O percentile/O rank/O using/O a/O locally/O weighted/O smoothing/O regression/O -LRB-/O bandwidth/O 0.8/NUMBER with/O 100/NUMBER observationsyf/O Z/O K/O H/O U/O H/O V/O N/O L/O O/O l/O percentiles/O are/O measured/O as/O the/O employment-weighted/O percentile/O rank/O of/O an/O occupation/O &#39;/O s/O mean/O log/O wage/O in/O the/O Census/O IPUMS/O 1980/DATE 5/DATE percent/PERCENT extract/O ./O 
The/O sample/O includes/O the/O working-age/O -LRB-/O 1-64yf/O F/O L/O Y/O L/O O/O L/O D/O n/O non-institutionalized/O population/O with/O 48/NUMBER +/O annual/SET weeks/DURATION worked/O and/O 35/NUMBER +/O usual/O weekly/SET hours/DURATION ./O 
Weekly/SET wages/O are/O calculated/O as/O annual/SET earnings/O divided/O by/O weeks/DURATION worked/O ./O 
of/O the/O figure/O ,/O which/O is/O disproportionately/O made/O up/O of/O the/O abstract/O task-intensive/O categories/O of/O professional/O ,/O technical/O ,/O and/O managerial/O occupations/O ./O 
By/O contrast/O ,/O wage/O growth/O in/O the/O middle-skill/O ,/O typically/O routine/O task-intensive/O occupations/O was/O less/O rapid/O and/O generally/O decelerated/O over/O time/O ./O 
For/O the/O low-education/O ,/O manual/O task-intensive/O occupations/O heavily/O represented/O on/O the/O left-hand/O side/O of/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER ,/O in/O the/DATE 1980s/DATE ,/O wage/O growth/O was/O a/O little/O more/O rapid/O than/O in/O the/O middle-skill/O occupations/O -/O and/O in/O the/DATE 1990s/DATE ,/O it/O was/O much/O more/O rapid/O ./O 
However/O ,/O that/O changed/O in/O the/DATE 2000s/DATE :/O while/O Figure/O 2/NUMBER showed/O that/O employment/O growth/O in/O these/O occupations/O exceeded/O that/O in/O all/O other/O categories/O between/O 1999/DATE and/O 2007/DATE ,/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER shows/O wage/O growth/O was/O gener/O -/O ally/O negative/O in/O the/O low-skill/O percentiles/O ,/O lower/O than/O in/O all/O other/O categories/O -LRB-/O Mishel/LOCATION ,/O Shierholz/O ,/O and/O Schmitt/PERSON 2013yf/O '/O X/O U/O L/O Q/O J/O W/O K/O L/O V/O W/O L/O P/O H/O S/O H/O U/O L/O R/O G/O P/O \/O V/O W/O U/O R/O Q/O J/O K/O X/O Q/O F/O K/O L/O V/O W/O K/O D/O t/O the/O explanation/O is/O that/O declining/O employment/O in/O middle-skill/O routine/O task-intensive/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O Why/O Are/O There/O Still/O So/O Many/O Jobs/O ?/O 
19/NUMBER jobs/O led/O middle-skill/O workers/O -/O including/O new/O entrants/O ,/O those/O displaced/O from/O routine/O task-intensive/O jobs/O ,/O and/O those/O who/O lost/O jobs/O during/O recession/O -/O to/O enter/O manual/O task-intensive/O occupations/O instead/O -LRB-/O Smith/ORGANIZATION 2013/ORGANIZATION ;/O Cortes/O ,/O Jaimovich/PERSON ,/O Nekarda/LOCATION ,/O and/O Siu/O 2014/DATE ;/O Foote/PERSON and/O Ryan/PERSON 2014yf/PERSON ./O 
A/O final/O set/O of/O facts/O illustrated/O by/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER is/O that/O overall/O wage/O growth/O was/O anemic/O throughout/O the/DATE 2000s/DATE ,/O even/O prior/O to/O the/O Great/O Recession/O ./O 
Between/O 1999/DATE and/O 2007/DATE ,/O real/O wage/O changes/O were/O negative/O below/O approximately/O the/O 15th/DATE percentile/DATE ,/O and/O were/O below/O 5/PERCENT percentage/PERCENT points/PERCENT up/O to/O the/O 70th/ORDINAL percentile/O of/O the/O distribution/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O wage/O growth/O was/O greater/O at/O all/O percentiles/O during/O both/O the/DATE 1980s/DATE and/O 1990s/DATE than/O in/O the/O pre-recession/O 2000s/DATE .7/NUMBER Of/O course/O ,/O wage/O growth/O was/O essentially/O zero/NUMBER at/O all/O percentiles/O from/O 2007/DATE to/U_TEMPPRED 2012/DATE ./O 
Why/O are/O the/O rapidly/O rising/O earnings/O of/O the/O top/O 1/PERCENT percent/PERCENT -LRB-/O as/O discussed/O in/O Atkinson/LOCATION ,/O Piketty/LOCATION ,/O and/O Saez/PERSON 2011/DATE ,/O for/O exampleyf/O Q/O R/O W/O V/O W/O U/O R/O Q/O J/O O/O \/O H/O Y/O L/O G/O H/O Q/O W/O L/O Q/O -RRB-/O L/O J/O X/O U/O H/O ?/O 
One/NUMBER reason/O reflects/O substance/O ;/O another/O is/O an/O artifact/O of/O the/O data/O ./O 
Substantively/O ,/O the/O plot/O depicts/O changes/O in/O earnings/O by/O occupational/O percentile/O rather/O than/O wage/O percen/O -/O tile/O ./O 
Wage/O growth/O by/O occupational/O percentile/O is/O less/O concentrated/O than/O wage/O growth/O across/O wage/O percentiles/O because/O the/O highest/O earners/O are/O found/O across/O a/O variety/O of/O occupations/O ./O 
In/O addition/O ,/O the/O very/O highest/O percentiles/O of/O earnings/O are/O censored/O in/O public/O use/O Census/O and/O American/ORGANIZATION Community/ORGANIZATION Survey/ORGANIZATION data/O files/O ,/O which/O further/O masks/O earnings/O gains/O at/O extreme/O quantiles/O ./O 
The/O Recent/O Slowdown/O in/O the/O Growth/O of/O High-Skill/O Occupations/O The/O hypothesis/O that/O automation/O and/O information/O technology/O has/O led/O to/O occu/O -/O pational/O and/O ,/O to/O a/O lesser/O degree/O ,/O wage/O polarization/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION labor/O force/O can/O explain/O some/O key/O features/O of/O the/O US/LOCATION and/O the/O cross-national/O data/O ./O 
But/O reality/O invariably/O proves/O more/O complicated/O than/O any/O single/O theory/O anticipates/O ./O 
For/O my/O thesis/O linking/O technological/O change/O to/O occupational/O change/O ,/O one/NUMBER concern/O is/O the/O unexplained/O deceleration/O of/O employment/O growth/O in/O abstract/O task-intensive/O occupations/O after/O 2000/DATE -LRB-/O Beaudry/LOCATION ,/O Green/ORGANIZATION ,/O and/O Sand/O 2014/DATE ,/O forth/O -/O coming/O ;/O Mishel/PERSON ,/O Shierholz/O ,/O and/O Schmitt/PERSON 2013yf/O -RRB-/O L/O J/O X/O U/O H/O I/O R/O O/O O/O R/O Z/O V/O W/O K/O H/O I/O R/O U/O P/O D/O W/O R/O f/O Figure/O 4/NUMBER but/O instead/O of/O showing/O -LRB-/O approximateyf/O S/O H/O U/O F/O H/O Q/O W/O D/O J/O H/O F/O K/O D/O Q/O J/O H/O V/O L/O Q/O Z/O D/O J/O H/O V/O R/O n/O the/O vertical/O axis/O ,/O it/O shows/O percentage/O changes/O in/O the/O employment/O share/O of/O the/O jobs/O ranked/O by/O their/O skill/O level/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1979/DATE ./O 
Since/O the/O sum/O of/O shares/O must/O equal/O one/NUMBER at/O any/O time/O period/O ,/O the/O changes/O in/O these/O shares/O across/O the/DURATION decades/DURATION must/O total/O zero/NUMBER ,/O and/O thus/O ,/O the/O height/O at/O each/O skill/O percentile/O measures/O the/O growth/O in/O each/O occupation/O &#39;/O s/O employment/O relative/O to/O the/O whole/O ./O 
7/NUMBER Because/O the/O 2000-2007/DURATION interval/O is/O two/DURATION years/DURATION shorter/O than/O the/O 1979-1989/DURATION period/O ,/O one/NUMBER should/O multiply/O the/O later/O changes/O by/O 1.25/NUMBER to/O put/O them/O on/O the/O same/O temporal/O footing/O ./O 
But/O even/O after/O making/O such/O an/O adjustment/O ,/O wage/O growth/O was/O still/O considerably/O weaker/O at/O all/O percentiles/O from/O 2000-2007/DURATION than/O in/O the/O earlier/DATE two/DATE decades/DATE ./O 
This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 20/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O Figure/O 5/NUMBER Smoothed/O Employment/O Changes/O by/O Occupational/ORGANIZATION Skill/ORGANIZATION Percentile/ORGANIZATION ,/O 1979-2012/DURATION Sources/O :/O Author/O ,/O calculated/O using/O 1980/DATE ,/O 1990/DATE ,/O and/DATE 2000/DATE Census/O Integrated/O Public/O Use/O Microdata/O Series/O -LRB-/O IPUMSyf/O I/O L/O O/O H/O V/O $/MONEY P/MONEY H/O U/O L/O F/O D/O Q/O &/O R/O P/O P/O X/O Q/O L/O W/O \/O 6/NUMBER X/O U/O Y/O H/O \/O F/O R/O P/O E/O L/O Q/O H/O G/O I/O L/O O/O H/O $/MONEY P/MONEY H/O U/O L/O F/O D/O Q/O &/O R/O P/O P/O X/O Q/O L/O W/O \/O 6/NUMBER X/O U/O Y/O H/O \/O ./O 
Notes/O :/O The/O figure/O plots/O changes/O in/O employment/O shares/O by/U_TEMPPRED 1980/DATE occupational/O skill/O percentile/O rank/O using/O a/O locally/O weighted/O smoothing/O regression/O -LRB-/O bandwidth/O 0.8/NUMBER with/O 100/NUMBER observationsyf/O Z/O K/O H/O U/O H/O V/O N/O L/O O/O O/O S/O H/O U/O F/O H/O Q/O W/O L/O O/O H/O V/O D/O U/O e/O measured/O as/O the/O employment-weighted/O percentile/O rank/O of/O an/O occupation/O &#39;/O s/O mean/O log/O wage/O in/O the/O Census/O IPUMS/O 1980/DATE 5/DATE percent/PERCENT extract/O ./O 
Employment/O in/O each/O occupation/O is/O calculated/O using/O workers/O &#39;/O hours/DURATION of/O annual/SET labor/O supply/O times/O the/O Census/O sampling/O weights/O ./O 
Consistent/O occupation/O codes/O for/O Census/O years/DATE 1980/DATE ,/DATE 1990/DATE ,/DATE and/DATE 2000/DATE ,/O and/O 2008/DATE are/O from/O Autor/O and/O Dorn/PERSON -LRB-/O 2013yf/O ./O 
Figure/O 5/NUMBER contributes/O three/NUMBER nuances/O to/O the/O occupational/O polarization/O story/O above/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O the/O pace/O of/O employment/O gains/O in/O low-wage/O ,/O manual/O task-intensive/O jobs/O has/O risen/O successively/O across/O periods/O ,/O as/O shown/O at/O the/O left-hand/O side/O of/O the/O figure/O ./O 
Second/ORDINAL ,/O the/O occupations/O that/O are/O losing/O employment/O share/O appear/O to/O be/O increas/O -/O ingly/O drawn/O from/O higher/O ranks/O of/O the/O occupational/O distribution/O ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O the/O highest/O ranked/O occupation/O to/O lose/O employment/O share/O during/O the/DATE 1980s/DATE lay/O at/O approx/O -/O imately/O the/O 45th/ORDINAL percentile/O of/O the/O skill/O distribution/O ./O 
In/O the/O final/O two/NUMBER subperiods/O ,/O this/O rank/O rose/O still/O further/O to/O above/O the/O 75th/DATE percentile/DATE -/O suggesting/O that/O the/O locus/O of/O displaced/O middle-skill/O employment/O is/O moving/O into/O higher-skilled/O territories/O ./O 
Third/ORDINAL ,/O growth/O of/O high-skill/O ,/O high-wage/O occupations/O -LRB-/O those/O associated/O with/O abstract/O workyf/O decelerated/O markedly/O in/O the/DATE 2000s/DATE ,/O with/O no/O relative/O growth/O in/O the/O top/O two/NUMBER deciles/O of/O the/O occupational/O skill/O distribution/O during/O 1999/DATE through/O 2007/DATE ,/O and/O only/O a/O modest/O recovery/O between/O 2007/DATE and/O 2012/DATE ./O 
Stated/O plainly/O ,/O the/O growth/O of/O occupational/O employ/O -/O ment/O across/O skill/O levels/O looks/O U-shaped/O earlier/O in/O the/O period/O ,/O with/O gains/O at/O low-skill/O and/O high-skill/O levels/O ./O 
By/O the/DATE 2000s/DATE ,/O the/O pattern/O of/O occupational/O employment/O across/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O David/PERSON H/PERSON ./O 
Autor/O 21/NUMBER Figure/O 6/NUMBER Private/ORGANIZATION Fixed/ORGANIZATION Investment/ORGANIZATION in/ORGANIZATION Information/ORGANIZATION Processing/ORGANIZATION Equipment/ORGANIZATION and/O Software/O as/O a/O Percentage/O of/O Gross/O Domestic/O Product/O ,/O 1949-2014/DURATION Source/O :/O FRED/O ,/O Federal/ORGANIZATION Bank/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION St./ORGANIZATION Louis/ORGANIZATION ./O 
http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/graph/?g=GXc/O -LRB-/O accessed/O 8/3/2014yf/O ./O 
skill/O levels/O began/O to/O resemble/O a/O downward/O ramp/O ./O 
In/O Autor/O -LRB-/O 2015yf/O ,/O S/O U/O H/O V/O H/O Q/O W/O D/O P/O R/O U/O e/O detailed/O breakdown/O of/O these/O patterns/O ,/O and/O in/O particular/O suggest/O that/O the/O set/O of/O abstract/O task-intensive/O jobs/O is/O not/O growing/O as/O rapidly/O as/O the/O potential/O supply/O of/O highly/O educated/O workers/O ./O 
What/O explains/O the/O slowing/O growth/O of/O abstract/O task-intensive/O employment/O ?/O 
One/NUMBER interpretation/O is/O that/O automation/O ,/O information/O technology/O ,/O and/O technological/O progress/O in/O general/O are/O encroaching/O upward/O in/O the/O task/O domain/O and/O beginning/O to/O substitute/O strongly/O for/O the/O work/O done/O by/O professional/O ,/O technical/O ,/O and/O managerial/O occupations/O ./O 
While/O one/NUMBER should/O not/O dismiss/O this/O possibility/O out/O of/O hand/O ,/O it/O doesn/O &#39;/O t/O fit/O well/O with/O the/O pattern/O of/O computer/O and/O software/O investment/O ./O 
If/O information/O tech/O -/O nology/O is/O increasingly/O replacing/O workers/O high/O in/O the/O skill/O distribution/O ,/O one/NUMBER would/O expect/O a/O surge/O of/O corporate/O investment/O in/O computer/O hardware/O and/O software/O ./O 
Instead/O ,/O Figure/O 6/NUMBER shows/O that/O in/O early/DATE 2014/DATE ,/O information/O processing/O equipment/O and/O software/O investment/O was/O only/O 3.5/PERCENT percent/PERCENT of/O GDP/O ,/O a/O level/O last/O seen/O in/U_TEMPPRED 1995/DATE at/O the/O outset/O of/O the/O &#34;/O dot-com/O &#34;/O era/O ./O 
To/O me/O ,/O the/O evidence/O in/O Figure/O 6/NUMBER suggests/O a/O temporary/O disloca/O -/O tion/O of/O demand/O for/O information/O technology/O capital/O during/O the/DATE latter/DATE half/DATE of/DATE the/DATE 1990s/DATE ,/O followed/O by/O a/O sharp/O correction/O after/O 2000/DATE ./O 
I/O suspect/O that/O the/O huge/O falloff/O in/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 22/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O information/O investment/O may/O have/O dampened/O innovative/O activity/O and/O demand/O for/O high-skilled/O workers/O more/O broadly/O ./O 
As/O noted/O earlier/O ,/O technological/O change/O is/O far/O from/O the/O only/O factor/O affecting/O US/LOCATION labor/O markets/O in/O the/DURATION last/DATE 15/DATE years/DATE ./O 
For/O example/O ,/O the/O deceleration/O of/O wage/O growth/O and/O changes/O in/O occupational/O patterns/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION labor/O market/O after/O 2000/DATE ,/O and/O further/O after/O 2007/DATE ,/O is/O surely/O associated/O to/O some/O extent/O with/O two/NUMBER types/O of/O macro/O -/O economic/O events/O ./O 
First/ORDINAL ,/O there/O are/O the/O business/O cycle/O effects/O -/O the/O bursting/O of/O the/O &#34;/O dot-com/O &#34;/O bubble/O in/U_TEMPPRED 2000/DATE ,/O and/O the/O collapse/O of/O the/O housing/O market/O and/O the/O ensuing/O financial/O crisis/O in/O 2007-2008/DURATION -/O both/O of/O which/O curtailed/O investment/O and/O innovative/O activity/O ./O 
Second/ORDINAL ,/O there/O are/O the/O employment/O dislocations/O in/O the/O US/LOCATION labor/O market/O brought/O about/O by/O rapid/O globalization/O ,/O particularly/O the/O sharp/O rise/O of/O import/O pene/O -/O tration/O from/O China/LOCATION following/O its/O accession/O to/O the/O World/ORGANIZATION Trade/ORGANIZATION Organization/ORGANIZATION in/U_TEMPPRED 2001/DATE -LRB-/O Autor/O ,/O Dorn/PERSON ,/O and/O Hanson/PERSON 2013/DATE ;/O Pierce/PERSON and/O Schott/PERSON 2012/DATE ;/O Acemoglu/PERSON ,/O Autor/LOCATION ,/O Dorn/PERSON ,/O Hanson/LOCATION ,/O and/O Price/O forthcomingyf/O &/O K/O L/O Q/O D/O V/O U/O D/O S/O L/O G/O U/O L/O V/O H/O W/O R/O D/O S/O U/O H/O P/O L/O H/O U/O P/O D/O Q/O X/O I/O D/O F/O -/O turing/O exporter/O had/O far-reaching/O impacts/O on/O US/LOCATION workers/O ,/O reducing/O employment/O in/O directly/O import-competing/O US/LOCATION manufacturing/O industries/O and/O depressing/O labor/O demand/O in/O both/O manufacturing/O and/O nonmanufacturing/O sectors/O that/O served/O as/O upstream/O suppliers/O to/O these/O industries/O ./O 
Of/O course/O ,/O these/O forces/O are/O in/O various/O ways/O linked/O with/O the/O spread/O of/O automa/O -/O tion/O and/O technology/O ./O 
Advances/O in/O information/O and/O communications/O technologies/O have/O changed/O job/O demands/O in/O US/LOCATION workplaces/O directly/O and/O also/O indirectly/O ,/O by/O making/O it/O increasingly/O feasible/O and/O cost-effective/O for/O firms/O to/O source/O ,/O monitor/O ,/O and/O coordi/O -/O nate/O complex/O production/O processes/O at/O disparate/O locations/O worldwide/O and/O altering/O competitive/O conditions/O for/O US/LOCATION manufacturers/O and/O workers/O ./O 
This/O multidimensional/O complementarity/O among/O causal/O factors/O makes/O it/O both/O conceptually/O and/O empirically/O difficult/O to/O isolate/O the/O &#34;/O pure/O &#34;/O effect/O of/O any/O one/NUMBER factor/O ./O 
Polanyi/O &#39;/O s/O Paradox/O :/O Will/O It/O Be/O Overcome/O ?/O 
Automation/O ,/O complemented/O in/O recent/DURATION decades/DURATION by/O the/O exponentially/O increasing/O power/O of/O information/O technology/O ,/O has/O driven/O changes/O in/O productivity/O that/O have/O disrupted/O labor/O markets/O ./O 
This/O essay/O has/O emphasized/O that/O jobs/O are/O made/O up/O of/O many/O tasks/O and/O that/O while/O automation/O and/O computerization/O can/O substitute/O for/O some/O of/O them/O ,/O understanding/O the/O interaction/O between/O technology/O and/O employment/O requires/O thinking/O about/O more/O than/O just/O substitution/O ./O 
It/O requires/O thinking/O about/O the/O range/O of/O tasks/O involved/O in/O jobs/O ,/O and/O how/O human/O labor/O can/O often/O complement/O new/O tech/O -/O nology/O ./O 
It/O also/O requires/O thinking/O about/O price/O and/O income/O elasticities/O for/O different/O kinds/O of/O output/O ,/O and/O about/O labor/O supply/O responses/O ./O 
The/O tasks/O that/O have/O proved/O most/O vexing/O to/O automate/O are/O those/O demanding/O flexi/O -/O bility/O ,/O judgment/O ,/O and/O common/O sense/O -/O skills/O that/O we/O understand/O only/O tacitly/O ./O 
I/O referred/O to/O this/O constraint/O above/O as/O Polanyi/PERSON &#39;/O s/O paradox/O ./O 
In/O the/DATE past/DATE decade/DATE ,/O computerization/O and/O robotics/O have/O progressed/O into/O spheres/O of/O human/O activity/O that/O were/O considered/O off/O */O limits/O only/O a/DATE few/DATE years/DATE earlier/DATE -/O driving/O vehicles/O ,/O parsing/O legal/O documents/O ,/O even/O This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O Why/O Are/O There/O Still/O So/O Many/O Jobs/O f/O 23/NUMBER performing/O agricultural/O field/O labor/O ./O 
Is/O Polanyi/PERSON &#39;/O s/O paradox/O soon/O to/O be/O at/O least/O mostly/O overcome/O ,/O in/O the/O sense/O that/O the/O vast/O majority/O of/O tasks/O will/O soon/O be/O automated/O ?/O 
8/NUMBER My/O reading/O of/O the/O evidence/O suggests/O otherwise/O ./O 
Indeed/O ,/O Polanyi/PERSON &#39;/O s/O paradox/O helps/O to/O explain/O what/O has/O not/O yet/O been/O accomplished/O ,/O and/O further/O illuminates/O the/O paths/O by/O which/O more/O will/O ultimately/O be/O accomplished/O ./O 
Specifically/O ,/O I/O see/O two/NUMBER distinct/O paths/O that/O engineering/O and/O computer/O science/O can/O seek/O to/O traverse/O to/O automate/O tasks/O for/O which/O we/O &#34;/O do/O not/O know/O the/O rules/O &#34;/O :/O environmental/O control/O and/O machine/O learning/O ./O 
The/O first/ORDINAL path/O circumvents/O Polanyi/PERSON &#39;/O s/O paradox/O by/O regularizing/O the/O environment/O ,/O so/O that/O comparatively/O inflexible/O machines/O can/O function/O semi-autonomously/O ./O 
The/O second/ORDINAL approach/O inverts/O Polanyi/PERSON &#39;/O s/O paradox/O :/O rather/O than/O teach/O machines/O rules/O that/O we/O do/O not/O understand/O ,/O engi/O -/O neers/O develop/O machines/O that/O attempt/O to/O infer/O tacit/O rules/O from/O context/O ,/O abundant/O data/O ,/O and/O applied/O statistics/O ./O 
Environmental/O Control/O Most/O automated/O systems/O lack/O flexibility/O -/O they/O are/O brittle/O ./O 
Modern/O automobile/O plants/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O employ/O industrial/O robots/O to/O install/O windshields/O on/O new/O vehicles/O as/O they/O move/O through/O the/O assembly/O line/O ./O 
But/O aftermarket/O windshield/O replacement/O companies/O employ/O technicians/O ,/O not/O robots/O ,/O to/O install/O replacement/O windshields/O ./O 
Evidendy/O ,/O the/O tasks/O of/O removing/O a/O broken/O windshield/O ,/O preparing/O the/O windshield/O frame/O to/O accept/O a/O replacement/O ,/O and/O fitting/O a/O replacement/O into/O that/O frame/O demand/O more/O real-time/O adaptability/O than/O any/O contemporary/O robot/O can/O cost-effectively/O approach/O ./O 
The/O distinction/O between/O assembly/O line/O production/O and/O the/O in-situ/O repair/O highlights/O the/O role/O of/O environmental/O control/O in/O enabling/O automation/O ./O 
Engineers/O can/O in/O some/O cases/O radically/O simplify/O the/O environment/O in/O which/O machines/O work/O to/O enable/O autonomous/O operation/O ,/O as/O in/O the/O familiar/O example/O of/O a/O factory/O assembly/O line/O ./O 
Numerous/O examples/O of/O this/O approach/O to/O environmental/O regularization/O are/O so/O ingrained/O in/O daily/SET technology/O that/O they/O escape/O notice/O ,/O however/O ./O 
To/O enable/O the/O operation/O of/O present-day/O automobiles/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O humanity/O has/O adapted/O the/O natu/O -/O rally/O occurring/O environment/O by/O leveling/O ,/O re-grading/O ,/O and/O covering/O with/O asphalt/O a/O nontrivial/O percentage/O of/O the/O earth/O &#39;/O s/O land/O surface/O .9/NUMBER The/O ongoing/O automation/O of/O warehouses/O provides/O another/O example/O ./O 
Large/O online/O retailers/O ,/O such/O as/O Amazon.com/ORGANIZATION ,/O Zappos.com/LOCATION ,/O and/O Staples/LOCATION ,/O operate/O systems/O of/O warehouses/O that/O have/O traditionally/O employed/O legions/O of/O dexterous/O ,/O athletic/O &#34;/O pickers/O ,/O &#34;/O who/O run/O and/O climb/O through/O shelves/O of/O typically/O non-air-conditioned/O warehouses/O to/O locate/O ,/O collect/O ,/O box/O ,/O label/O ,/O and/O ship/O goods/O ./O 
There/O is/O at/O present/DATE no/O cost-effective/O robotic/O 8/NUMBER For/O a/O glimpse/O of/O the/O view/O that/O just/O about/O anything/O can/O now/DATE be/O computerized/O ,/O see/O the/O widely/O cited/O -LRB-/O albeit/O unpublishedyf/O D/O U/O W/O L/O F/O O/O H/O E/O \/O W/O K/O H/O H/O F/O R/O Q/O R/O P/O L/O V/O W/O V/O &/O D/O U/O O/O -RRB-/O U/O H/O \/O D/O Q/O G/O 0/NUMBER L/O F/O K/O D/O H/O O/O 2/NUMBER V/O E/O R/O U/O Q/O H/O Z/O K/O R/O Z/O U/O L/O W/O H/O S/O \/O f/O that/O ,/O &#34;/O recent/O developments/O in/O ML/O -LSB-/O machine/O learning/O -RSB-/O and/O MR/O -LSB-/O mobile/O robotics/O -RSB-/O ,/O building/O upon/O big/O data/O ,/O allow/O for/O pattern/O recognition/O ,/O and/O thus/O enable/O computer/O capital/O to/O rapidly/O substitute/O for/O labour/O across/O a/O wide/O range/O of/O non-routine/O tasks/O ./O 
Yet/O some/O inhibiting/O engineering/O bottlenecks/O to/O computerization/O persist/O ./O 
Beyond/O these/O bottlenecks/O ,/O however/O ,/O we/O argue/O that/O it/O is/O largely/O already/O technologically/O possible/O to/O automate/O almost/O any/O task/O ,/O provided/O that/O sufficient/O amounts/O of/O data/O are/O gathered/O for/O pattern/O recognition/O ./O 
&#34;/O According/O to/O Wikipedia/LOCATION ,/O so-called/O impervious/O surfaces/O -LRB-/O mostly/O roads/O and/O parking/O lotsyf/O F/O R/O Y/O H/O U/O 0/NUMBER square/O miles/O of/O land/O in/O the/O lower/O 48/NUMBER United/LOCATION States/LOCATION -/O roughly/O equal/O to/O the/O land/O area/O of/O the/O state/O of/O Ohio/LOCATION -LRB-/O http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impervious_surface/O ,/O accessed/O 8/4/2014yf/O ./O 
This/O content/O downloaded/O from/O 200.130.19.157/O on/O Sat/TIME ,/TIME 15/TIME Apr/DATE 2017/DATE 01:24:43/TIME UTC/ORGANIZATION All/O use/O subject/O to/O http://about.jstor.org/terms/O 24/NUMBER Journal/O of/O Economic/O Perspectives/O facsimile/O for/O these/O human/O pickers/O ./O 
The/O job/O &#39;/O s/O steep/O requirements/O for/O flexibility/O ,/O object/O recognition/O ,/O physical/O dexterity/O ,/O and/O fine/O motor/O coordination/O are/O too/O formidable/O ./O 
But/O large/O components/O of/O warehousing/O can/O be/O automated/O ,/O as/O demonstrated/O by/O Kiva/ORGANIZATION Systems/ORGANIZATION ,/O a/O robotic/O warehousing/O startup/O that/O was/O purchased/O by/O Amazon/LOCATION in/U_TEMPPRED 2012/DATE ./O 
